<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-11">Sept. 11, 1906.</date><title level="a">Banker Stensland Arrested in Morocco</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_4_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_4_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-11">Sept. 11, 1906.</date><title level="a">BANKER STENSLAND ARRESTED IN MOROCCO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fugitive banker, Paul O. Stensland, was arrested last week by Harry Olson and James Kecley, representative of the Chicago Tribune. Stensland had fled to Tangier, Morocco and that is where he was caught and arrested.</p>
   <p>The truth of the old saying: "hell hath no fury like a woman scorned" was exemplified in Stensland's case. One of this libertine's lady friends considered herself unfairly treated by Stensland and she gave the Chicago Tribune a strong suggestion as to where the fugitive could be found. The Tribune followed up the clew and on August 13, received the information that their man was staying at Tangier, Morocco. The route he had taken was from Chicago to New York on July 12, and he sailed on the first available steamer for Liverpool. Here he stayed two days, then continued his journey to Tangier.</p>
   <p>Instead of publicizing the sensational flight and announcing the whereabouts <pb facs="5423969_4_0298.jpg" n="2"/>of the wanted absconder the Tribune decided to keep their knowledge secret and capture him first, and then print the story. State's Attorney Healy and his assistant, Harry Olson, were taken into the secret and the arrangement was made for Olson and James Keeley, representing the Tribune, to go to Tangier, or wherever necessary, and arrest Stensland.</p>
   <p>Olson and Keeley sailed from New York on August 20, and reached Paris on August 27. They traveled via Madrid and Gibraltar to Tangier, reaching their goal on the evening of September 1. All evening and all of the following day they hunted their quarry. They finally located Stensland in a small hotel where he had registered as P. Olsen from Norway. Stensland seemed to feel perfectly safe in Morocco as he was traced from one to another of the finest cafes. One day he had created a lot of excitement by showing twelve thousand dollars in American, English, and French currency. This money "P. Olsen" later deposited in a local bank for safety.</p>
   <p>Before being seen by Olson and Keeley, Stensland had gone to Gibraltar and the two followed him there only to learn that he had just returned <pb facs="5423969_4_0299.jpg" n="3"/>to Tangier, reaching there before the slower boat on which Stensland sailed reached the port. Tangier spies were engaged to watch Stensland carefully and prevent him from leaving the city whenever he wanted to. Immediately upon landing in the morning, Stensland went to the British Postal Station and instructed the postmaster to forward his mail to Mogador, a small town to the south, one seldom visited by a European.</p>
   <p>Just as he was about to fill the change of address blank Harry Olson stepped up to him and said: "Write your right name, Stensland, and Chicago instead of Mogador. The State of Illinois wants you and we are detailed to bring you back."</p>
   <p>Stensland tried to bluff his way out but soon he humbly accompanied Olson to the American Embassy in the Bristol hotel where he was placed under guard.</p>
   <p>It is reported that Stensland has made a confession regarding forgeries amounting to $500,000. He claims, however, that every dollar he took <pb facs="5423969_4_0300.jpg" n="4"/>was invested in real estate and stocks. His career started in 1896 when he helped himself to a loan secured by absolutely worthless security. His transactions grew steadily and he states that he had forgeries committed by Hering. He declares that Theodore Stensland is innocent of taking any part.</p>
   <p>On Friday last, Harry Olson and Keeley were authorized by President Roosevelt to represent the government and bring Stensland back to the United States and Chicago. Stensland was placed under a guard of six native soldiers in a private home pending the sailing date.</p>
   <p>A cablegram from Tangier announces that Stensland had given Harry Olson a memorandum book showing which deals cashier Hering had taken part in.</p>
   <p>Names of a number of other participants also appear in the book and its effect on the trial of Stensland and all others will be surprising.</p>
   <p>Upon opening and going through Stensland's trunks it was found that they <pb facs="5423969_4_0301.jpg" n="5"/>contained clothes only; the natives thought the man they were guarding had bought clothing for nearly all the money he had stolen.</p>
   <p>Stensland now plans to serve his time and then start life anew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
