<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-01">Oct. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">S. P. Norman Is Seventy Years Old</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fourth of a page, picture of S. P. Norman]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-01">Oct. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">S. P. NORMAN IS SEVENTY YEARS OLD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fourth of a page, picture of S. P. Norman]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>S. P. Norman, real-estate man and former building contractor, and for years a well-known figure among Chicago's Swedes, observed his seventieth birthday last week. On that occasion a banquet was given in his honor, at the Swedish Club. Attorney Carl O. Beroth presided, and among the speakers were City Treasurer Charles S. Peterson, County Assessor Charles Krutzkoff, Assistant Corporation Counsel Gotthard Dahlberg and August West, building contractor. Mr. Norman received an expensive watch as a birthday gift.</p>
   <p>Norman was born in Kristianstad, Sweden, in 1860, and came to America and to Chicago in 1880. During the first fifteen years he engaged in building construction, and erected several large buildings here. In 1891 he planned and built the Zion Swedish Lutheran Church, at 22nd Place and Irving Avenue. The congregation was so pleased with his work that it presented him with a gold <pb facs="5423404_5_0406.jpg" n="2"/>watch as a token of gratitude.</p>
   <p>He has been very active in local politics, and belongs to the Hamilton Club, and to several Free Mason organizations, as well as to the Svithiod Singing Club and the Swedish Club.</p>
   <p>In 1916, he served as president of the Swedish Old People's Home Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
