<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-16">Oct. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">"Kurre-Johnson" Retires</title>
[Half-tone one column, fifth of a page, picture of Alexander J. Johnson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-16">Oct. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">"KURRE-JOHNSON" RETIRES</title>
[Half-tone one column, fifth of a page, picture of Alexander J. Johnson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspaper Svenska Kuriren merged with Svenska Amerikanaren last October 10, and its independent existence has thus come to an end. The merger was decided on because Kuriren's owner, Alexander J. Johnson, has reached his eighieth year, and feels that he deserves a rest.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson is a native of Stockholm, Sweden and was born in 1850. When he, as a young man, set his course for the far west he probably did not intend to come here looking for trouble but, nevertheless, fate would have it that he choose the thorny road of a Swedish-American newspaperman.</p>
   <p>After having worked for various business houses here for a number of years, he bought the publication Kurre, which specialized in humor and satire.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0419.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He had, from time to time, contributed to newspapers and had developed an interest in that kind of work. He changed the name Kurre to Svenska-Kuriren, but many readers had formed a sentimental attachment to the former name, and transferred it to Johnson himself, who soon became known as Kurre-Johnson, a name to which he never had any objection.</p>
   <p>During its more than forty years of existence, Svenska Kuriren had many good men on its staff, among whom may be mentioned Johan Persson, who passed away many years ago. But Johnson himself wrote most of the editorials, and they were always read with interest, even by people who disagreed with him.</p>
   <p>As Johnson retires to private life, his colleagues join in wishing that the evening of his life may be peaceful and happy. He deserves it after the long workday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
