<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">Apr. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Real-Estate Broker of Swedish Birth</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Axel Lonnquist]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">Apr. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Real-Estate Broker of Swedish Birth</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Axel Lonnquist]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are a great number of Swedish builders and contractors in Chicago, and they have contributed a great deal to the development and progress of the city. From time to time, we have presented on this page some of the outstanding members of the group. Today we shall introduce to our readers a representative of another group which, as it were, prepares the way for the builders: namely, the real-estate dealers. The man is Axel Lonnquist, well-known real-estate broker with offices in the Conway Building.</p>
   <p>Lonnquist was born in Stockholm, Sweden, August 16, 1881. As early as 1893 he decided to see the New World. He first went to Canada, where he remained until 1901, when he moved to the States and came to Chicago. Soon after <pb facs="5423404_5_0503.jpg" n="2"/>his arrival here, he took out his first citizenship papers, which shows that he intended to stay put in this country.</p>
   <p>Lonnquist had not been here long, before he realized that the real-estate business offered tempting opportunities for a young, ambitious man, and about eighteen years ago he decided to establish himself in that field. It seems that he was particularly well adapted for the business, and when the automobile king, Henry Ford, decided to subdivide some of the land which he owned near Detroit into building lots for his workers, Lonnquist was selected to take charge of the extensive project. He came to be considered an expert on subdividing and planning, and his experience has, of course, increased with the years.</p>
   <p>A couple of years ago, a firm headed by him undertook the subdivision of a residential district on Chicago's North Side, and a short time ago he supervised a similar project in the Calumet district, near the Ford Company's <pb facs="5423404_5_0504.jpg" n="3"/>new plant, not far from 130th Street. At the present time, Lonnquist's firm has at its disposal building lots covering an area of five hundred acres within the city limits.</p>
   <p>He is married. Mrs. Lonnquist was born in St. Louis, Missouri. They have two children, a boy and a girl. The former is now attending Princeton University. The family home is in Wilmette.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
