<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1903-01-14">Jan. 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Portrait Gallery Alfred Stromberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1903-01-14">Jan. 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">PORTRAIT GALLERY ALFRED STROMBERG</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alfred Stromberg was born in the vicinity of Stockholm in 1861. At the age of 15 years he began his career as an electrician. In 1879, at 18 years of age, he was a foreman for a telephone company in Stockholm. In 1885, Stromberg was working for the Bell Telephone Company, in Chicago. It did not take long before the officials of the company realized that Stromberg had an inventive mind. He was then employed in the instrument construction department where he initiated several improvements, which are in constant use today. In 1890, he became the head of the burglar alarm system for the Chicago Protective Company. In this capacity he invented and improved much equipment for the company. These inventions were known as the Stromberg System. When the Bell Telephone Company's original patents expired in 1894, Stromberg started his own company for the manufacture of telephone instruments. The company was incorporated in 1895 under the name of the Stromberg Carlson Telephone Manufacturing Company. His partner was Anders Carlson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0783.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1895, this company had only five employees, and they worked in a small building. Today the Stromberg Carlson Company is known throughout the entire world, and their equipment and telephone devices are sold everywhere.</p>
   <p>Their building, owned by the company,is located at Jackson Blvd. and Clinton Street, Chicago. This building soon proved inadequate so five stories were added to it in order to carry on the ever-increasing business. Besides the telephone equipment of all kinds, which this company manufactures, they also make various electrical apparatus.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thomas, W. Finnucoue, and Mr. Eugene H. Satterlee, capitalists from New York City, who amassed millions in the manufacture of kodaks, became interested in the Stromberg Carlson Company and in May,1902, they invested three million dollars. There are a great many small stockholders also, who <pb facs="5423404_5_0784.jpg" n="3"/>have invested much of their savings in this company, which in the past has paid unusually large dividends to them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stromberg left Stockholm at the age of 24 as a poor workman and came to Chicago.</p>
   <p>After being in the city three days and having failed to find employment he sought a loan of twenty-five cents which was refused him. Since that experience, he has never attempted to secure a loan. He is now taking a much needed rest and vacation, visiting his native land. He has returned to his native land at the age of forty-one, a multi-millionaire. Should our nation not feel justly proud of the record of such a man?</p>
   <p>He who sees this little, unassuming man with sharp features and intelligent eyes, can hardly imagine that he stands before a man with great will power, <pb facs="5423404_5_0785.jpg" n="4"/>with nerves and muscles of steel. He seemed somewhat tired when he left for Sweden, but he returned as fresh as a winter morning.</p>
   <p>Alfred Stromberg has been married since 1886 to Ella Johnson, also from Stockholm. They have four children, one boy and three girls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
