<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">America in Sweden</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA IN SWEDEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago, the Svenska Morgonbladet published an article under the heading "America in Sweden" in which the paper warmly advocates the use of a fund of 100,000,000 crowns for the bringing about of a return to Sweden of Swedes who had emigrated to America. The article seems to have made an impression in some quarters, and we have seen newspapers which, after presenting an epitome of the article, have expressed the opinion that the matter deserves consideration. We are, however, of a different opinion and shall, therefore, try to determine the possibilities of the plan. It did not originate with the Svenska Morgonbladet, but is taken from a book, "Swedish Problems and Their Solution."</p>
   <p>To start with, the paper refers to Count L. Akerhjelm's statement in the <pb facs="5423404_5_0108.jpg" n="2"/>Swedish parliament during the debate about the Karlstad agreement. He said among other things that "through united cooperation regarding our internal problems, we must try to win back what we have lost through the dissolution of the union." To accomplish this, we suppose is what the Svenska Morgonbladet is aiming at when proposing the use of the fund of 100,000,000 crowns. Sweden is a rich country, the article insists, with great natural resources; vast stretches of land waiting to be tilled; great forests; inexhaustible water power; mountains containing riches which are yet for the most part unexplored; all of this in Norrland, our America in Sweden. To this province, then, the stream of returning Swedes should be directed, according to the dream of the paper. Well, we do not object. The plan for this undertaking is simple enough, and may be outlined as follows: A systematic re-immigration to their homeland of Swedes is to be organized, <pb facs="5423404_5_0109.jpg" n="3"/>this being at the same time the most effective means of checking emigration from Sweden. This must be done through the action of the government. The means is to consist of practically organized bureaus in the larger cities in Sweden, as well as in the more important Swedish centers in America, for the procurement of positions, the placing of capital, the acquisition of property, etc. In addition, direct steamship connection between Sweden and America with low priced fares, in some cases even free tickets home for Swedes who desire to return for the purpose of settling in their home district. The most important factor in this plan are the bureaus. Through them, the Swedish industry would be able to obtain engineers and workers from America, and Swedes in the United States, thinking of returning to Sweden, would receive from the bureaus information about conditions in Sweden, that is of the arrangement for government loans for those wanting to acquire their <pb facs="5423404_5_0110.jpg" n="4"/>own homes; of properties for sale; of new business undertakings; of possibilities for investments in Sweden, etc.</p>
   <p>It would be interesting to know who has conceived this plan. Certainly, the person who did possesses a fantasy far livelier than that of the ordinary individual, a fantasy, moreover, which does not stop at the border of the naive, but seems to lie entirely within its field. At the same time, the author of the plan seems to be entirely lacking in that knowledge of conditions in America, which is a prime requirement for a reasonably common sense treatment of the subject. From his reasonings, one can only conclude that he has never been in America, or, at best, that he is one of the many Swedes who of late years has visited America <pb facs="5423404_5_0111.jpg" n="5"/>for a year or so, "for the sake of studying Swedish-American conditions." Anyone who has been in a position to get close to the emigrants under their varying exigencies must recoil before a plan as the one described above. The intention is to prevail upon Swedish-Americans who have acquired experience in American ways of production to return to Sweden, and especially such as would be able to give a push ahead to the Swedish industry and agriculture, in other words, Swedish-Americans who possess some capital. We repeat that one must be entirely ignorant of Swedes in America to imagine even for a moment the possibility of persuading such among them who have succeeded to return to Sweden in order to resume there, in Norrland, a new and perhaps a harder struggle for existence. To turn, first, to the matter of industry, one finds at the start that the worker under American industrial conditions receives higher wages than in Sweden, <pb facs="5423404_5_0112.jpg" n="6"/>and also that it is easier for him to gain promotion in America. As a result of this, the Swedish-American industrial worker has developed demands of which the average Swedish worker knows nothing. Frequently, also, the Swedish-American industrial worker possesses his own home, a condition which binds him to his new country still more strongly. In brief, the economic conditions in America, compared with those in Sweden, are such that an exchange of the former for the latter would be unthinkable. If in addition one considers that the Swedes in America possess a sense of freedom that is simply unfathomable to those in Sweden, and that this sense of freedom probably contributes more than anything else to bind them to their new country, also that there are many things, political and social, which add to the score for America, then it will be evident that the "plan" is, quite simply, an utopia, a product of fantasy. Those Swedish-Americans <pb facs="5423404_5_0113.jpg" n="7"/>who have their own factories, etc., would hardly be tempted to go back to Sweden, especially since they in most cases have become so Americanized that Sweden to them is but little more than an old memory. It remains, then, to interest the Swedish-American farmers for Swedish agriculture. In many respects the same difficulties will here be encountered as we have mentioned above. As an additional and very important factor comes the matter of climatic conditions. To expect the Swedish-Americans, accustomed to the fertile fields of the prairie or the no less fertile forest land to start farming in the Swedish Norrland may well be considered as rather naive. It would be wise to speak in whispers of the agricultural possibilities of Norrland, especially to people who have been accustomed to the very best in farming lands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0114.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>But why "carry coal to Newcastle"? Why not start right and in the right place. In the middle and southern part of Sweden there is a great deal of fertile land that might be portioned out to the sons of Sweden who are staying at home and who wish to have homes of their own. Why not employ the 100,000,000 crowns for the purchase of large estates, frequently but poorly cared for, the estates to be divided into farms suitable for home owners? Why not split up the many large crown estates which, in their present condition, produce but little; why not give the thousands of sharecroppers, day workers, hired men, a chance to become farmers in their own right? If the 100,000,000 crowns were employed for such purpose, the fund would be of real benefit to the country.</p>
   <p>The basic evil in these matters needs to be rooted out. The high ciphers <pb facs="5423404_5_0115.jpg" n="9"/>of the emigration lists must strike terror in the breast of those in Sweden who really love their country.... yet there are those.... who insist that the country holds too many people, and who gleefully rub their hands when the young and unruly element leave for abroad. Sweden has become a land of old people, and as long as present conditions prevail there, it is idle to talk about regaining what has been lost.</p>
   <p>Sweden is in need of a thorough revival such as will overturn the view which clings to old ways, a revival which will take care of the young forces in the country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
