<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-11-29">Nov. 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Johan Peterson Passes Away</title>
[Half-tone, two column-third of a page, full face picture of Johan Peterson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-11-29">Nov. 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">JOHAN PETERSON PASSES AWAY</title>
[Half-tone, two column-third of a page, full face picture of Johan Peterson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Johan Peterson, associate editor of Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter, died in the Chicago Union Hospital last Tuesday after a few days of illness, at the age of thirty-nine.</p>
   <p>Peterson was born in 1871 in Ronneby, Sweden, where his father owned a flour mill. At the age of two he became fatherless and went to live in the home of a well-to-do uncle, who later paid for his education. In 1890 he graduated from college in Karlskrona.</p>
   <p>He was very studious and his ambition was to become a doctor, but due to financial difficulties he had to give up the idea and instead entered the customs service. He was stationed for some time in Karlshamn and later in <pb facs="5423404_5_0705.jpg" n="2"/>Ostersund and Falun. During this time he became more and more interested in newspaper work, and contributed regularly to the newspapers in the cities where he lived.</p>
   <p>In the fall of 1907 he came to Chicago in the hope of joining the staff of some Swedish-American publication here, and within a few days he was working on the Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter.</p>
   <p>From the very beginning he has done fine work and earned the respect and confidence of his employers as well as the friendship of his colleagues. He was always willing to give a hand, and had no difficulties in adjusting himself to American working methods and conditions in general.</p>
   <p>Johan Peterson always preferred to speak and write kindly of his fellow men but, if necessary, he could be rough. He had a solid educational background, and was widely read. Fundamentally he was of the serious type, but <pb facs="5423404_5_0706.jpg" n="3"/>this did not prevent him from enjoying good company and the lighter side of life. He was much in demand as an after-dinner speaker.</p>
   <p>Besides his many friends he is mourned by two half brothers, Fred and Oscar Lindell of this city, a mother and stepfather and two sisters who are living in Sweden.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
