<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-01-30">Jan. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Architect Sandegren Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of architect Andrew Sandegren]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-01-30">Jan. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ARCHITECT SANDEGREN IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of architect Andrew Sandegren]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The noted Swedish architect, Andrew Sandegren, was found dead last Wednesday morning in a gas-filled room in his home at 116 East Oak Street. He was sitting on a chair next to a gas stove from which gas was escaping, and it is believed that he had turned on the gas in order to warm up the room, and that the flame had gone out without his noticing it.</p>
   <p>The deceased enjoyed an enviable reputation as an architect, and was also known as an art patron. He was born in Halmstad, Sweden, June 25, 1867, the son of a school teacher of the old type. At the age of ten, he entered the Cathedral School of Lund, where he received an excellent education. When he had finished his studies, he found employment in the shops of the Halmstad-Nassjo railroad, and later he worked in the mapmaking and architecture departments of the road. Architecture was his chief interest, but he did not <pb facs="5423404_5_0515.jpg" n="2"/>get a real opportunity to develop his talents in that direction until he came to America in the spring of 1888. He worked for some time for several of the leading architects here in Chicago, and then moved to the East. But in 1892 he returned to this city, opened an office of his own, and remained here.</p>
   <p>He specialized in large apartment buildings, and was recognized as a leader in that field. It is estimated that during his thirty years as an architect here he planned and made the drawings for at least one thousand such structures.</p>
   <p>Sandegren belonged to many organizations, among which were the St. Bernard Commandery No. 35, of the K. T., Lodge Covenant No. 526 of the A. F. &amp; A. M., the Medinah Temple, the Architectural Club, the Illinois Society of Architects, the Hamilton Club, the Swedish Club, the Svithiod Singing Club, the Swedish Engineering Society, and the John Ericsson Lodge, No. 361, of I. O. O. F.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0516.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Close relatives who survive Mr. Sandegren are his brother and sister, Tobias and Marie Sandegren, of Tacoma, Washington, and a nephew, Andrew Sandegren, of this city. The burial took place yesterday in Graceland Cemetary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
