<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Fifty Years Old</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Gustaf Holmquist]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTY YEARS OLD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Gustaf Holmquist]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebrated singer, Gustaf Holmquist, rounded the half-century mark on February 14. The majority of his friends and admirers were unaware of the fact, as he would have been flooded with a wave of felicitations on the occasion. Only his closest friends knew about it, however, and they had arranged a festive party in the Swedish Club. As might be guessed, it was a very successful and memorable affair.</p>
   <p>Frank Gustafson acted as master of ceremonies and discharged his duties in a creditable manner. Speeches were so numerous that we will not attempt to enumerate them. Suffice it to say that Mr. Holmquist was feted in prose as well as in rhyme, and as a fitting climax, the master of ceremonies presented him with a beautiful gold watch, a birthday present from the guests. A program of songs and music was given between speeches.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0584.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Holmquist was born in the city of Nora, Sweden and came to America at the age of thirteen. Shortly after his arrival here, he began to sing in a mixed chorus, but it was not until he was twenty years old that he began to attract attention because of his unusual voice. Arrangements were made by interested people to enable him to obtain professional instruction, and he began to study voice in Minneapolis. In 1898, he came to Chicago, where he studied under such masters as W. N. Burritt, W. L. Hubbard, and others. We cannot here give a detailed review of his career as a singer during the last twenty years. He has been associated with several musical organizations and has participated in the presentation of many great musical works, especially oratorios, besides having distinguished himself as a concert singer. Among the organizations which have engaged him as a soloist may be mentioned the Apollo Musical Club of Chicago, the Evanston Musical Club, the Philharmonic Club of Minneapolis, the Handel Oratorio Society of Augustana College, the Swedish Singers' League of America, and the Norwegian Singer's League of America. He was a soloist with the Swedish Choral Club when it toured Sweden in 1920, and as early as 1910 he visited the old country as a soloist with the Swedish-American Elite Choir. After the <pb facs="5423404_5_0585.jpg" n="3"/>conclusion of this latter tour, he studied for some time in Paris and in England. In recent years, Mr. Holmquist has been a teacher in conservatories. He is now with the Bush Conservatory here. At one time he taught at the Chicago Musical College.</p>
   <p>Few Swedish-American musicians and singers have become so popular among native Americans as Mr. Holmquist. They, as well as his own countrymen, look up to him not only because of his magnificent voice, but also because of his friendly and unaffected personality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
