<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Remember the Poor in Sweden</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter, signed, Homo Sapiens)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">REMEMBER THE POOR IN SWEDEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter, signed, Homo Sapiens)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago, the writer received a letter from Sweden in which was related the story of four aged men and women, all of them past eighty, one nearly ninety years, who found themselves placed in a little poor-house situated in the parish within which they had passed most of their lives, that part of their lives, at least, which we call the productive period. They had given their labor within the parish. Now they were without work, unable to work, and, consequently, useless. Two of the four, of opposite sex, were lodged in the same room against their will and especially the old woman, who complained bitterly about this. The reading of this letter recalled to my thoughts the hard and bitter lot <pb facs="5423404_5_0311.jpg" n="2"/>which, frequently, is the only reward of the worn-out workers in Sweden. No lot can be worse than that of a poorhouse inmate in Sweden. Helpless, idle, ill, and without defense, the decrepit worker, formerly so agile and energetic, is placed in the poorhouse, over the portals of which hovers the words of Dante's Inferno, "Ye who enter here, leave hope behind."</p>
   <p>The lot of the poor is hard even when still he harbors the hope that he may overcome his state of poverty. But the hopeless poverty often follows its victim even to the grave.... this poverty is hellish.</p>
   <p>Swedes in America, living here under easy conditions, safe from the hideous spectre of this kind of poverty; remember those unhappy inmates of cheerless poorhouses in Sweden. Spread some light on their dark way by sending some <pb facs="5423404_5_0312.jpg" n="3"/>gift to these poor souls..... One dollar will not make you poor, but one dollar is nearly four crowns in Swedish money, and if sent to the poorhouse in your home community will bring more joy than you can possibly imagine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
