<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-01-19">Jan. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Swedish-American Insurance Man</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-01-19">Jan. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Swedish-American Insurance Man</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among those of our countrymen who are proud of their nationality, and who at every opportunity do all they can to promote the interests of their fellow Swedes in business and politics as well as in church and welfare work, N.A. Nelson, president of the Scandia Life Insurance Company, occupies a prominent place.</p>
   <p>Nels Anton Nelson was born on a farm near Varberg, in Holland, Sweden. The family ranked high in the community, and had been on that farm for many generations. Nelson went through the public school near his home, and then immigrated to America.</p>
   <p>He came first to Batavia, Illinois, where he worked on a farm, and at the same time attended night school and learned the machinist's trade, thus preparing himself for the opportunities which were waiting for him in <pb facs="5423404_5_0730.jpg" n="2"/>his adopted country.</p>
   <p>In 1885 he came to Chicago, where he finished up his schooling with an eighteen month course at the Metropolitan Business College, following which he obtained a job of considerable responsibility with a stock exchange firm, where he remained until 1896. In that year he took over the management of the Svea Building and Loan Association, and at the same time established a real-estate and insurance brokerage business. The Building and Loan Association was founded in 1892 with Mr. Nelson as its president, but he now became its secretary and managing director. Under his leadership Svea has prospered, and is now one of the biggest and most secure Scandinavian organizations of its kind in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nelson is also secretary of the Oak Hill Cemetery Association, 119 Street and Kedzie Avenue, an undertaking which he was instrumental in organizing, and which was incorporated in 1902. Its property is now valued at $135,000, and $40,000 has been expended in its improvements.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0731.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Scandia Life Insurance Company of Chicago was established in 1904, and Mr. Nelson, convinced that it had great possibilities, took an active part in its organization. The new company took over the assets and liabilities of the old Scandia Mutual Life Insurance Company, and he was first elected its treasurer and later on its president, in which capacity he still serves. The company now has some ten thousand policy holders, whose combined policies amount to about ten million dollars.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nelson is also a director of the Insurance Company of Rockford, Rockford, Illinois, which handles fire insurance and is capitalized at one million dollars.</p>
   <p>Politically, he is a Republican, and he belongs to the Lutheran Church. For more than twenty years he has been a member of the Bethlehem Church of Englewood, and during most of that time he has served as a deacon and assisted in the Sunday School work. At the same time he has also supported other churches and various welfare organizations. He is a <pb facs="5423404_5_0732.jpg" n="4"/>trustee of the Englewood Hospital at 60th and Green Streets.</p>
   <p>In 1895 he married Adelia H.M. Olson, daughter of the Wentworth Avenue merchant, Herman Olson, and they have three children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
