<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-03-14">Mar. 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Captain Lofstrom on His Way to Sweden</title>
(2" X 3" Halftone of Mr. Lofstrom)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0761</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0761.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-03-14">Mar. 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CAPTAIN LOFSTROM ON HIS WAY TO SWEDEN</title>
(2" X 3" Halftone of Mr. Lofstrom)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's largest Swedish book dealer, both as to length of time in the business and as to size of stock, Captain And. Lofstrom, whose business is located at 113 Oak Street, left the city last Sunday for a two months' visit to Sweden. It was not nostalgia which caused him to leave the splendid Chicago. Captain Lofstrom is too practical for that sort of emotion; he is a businessman to the very tips of his fingers, and it is in his capacity as such that he now is about to visit Old Sweden. The Swedes in Chicago, as well as Swedes elsewhere in this country, know Lofstrom through his calendar, the "Dalkullan" which he publishes once a year. But he is also known to many by his rich supply of Swedish books, imported by him from Sweden for sale in <pb facs="5423404_5_0762.jpg" n="2"/>America. Only a couple of years have elapsed since his last visit to Sweden, at which time he brought back loads of interesting books, many of these books being literary rarities. The works of our most noted Swedish authors line his shelves, but preferably he seeks books which are all but unobtainable in the average bookstore, antique volumes. His stack of books, already well assorted, will be added to very significantly after he returns from his round of Stockholm's bookstores in a couple of months. He is especially interested in the distribution of Swedish novels in this country, but he does not turn away from Swedish poetical works, and also the comics in Swedish literature find a friend in him. The religious literature, on the other hand, he leaves to other book dealers to import and distribute.</p>
   <p>During Mr. Lofstrom's absence, his business will be conducted by well qualified <pb facs="5423404_5_0763.jpg" n="3"/>persons, and buyers of books may safely send in their order to the bookstore, now as before.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter wishes Captain Lofstrom a very happy voyage, and shall be eager to welcome him back to Chicago on his return.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
