<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1914-06-25">June 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish-American Line</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0281</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0281.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1914-06-25">June 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH-AMERICAN LINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Be a partner in a profitable undertaking. Over three hundred prominent Swedish citizens invite you to become a partner with them as stockholders in the new Swedish-American Line, and to promote a direct, modern, and speedy mail, passenger, and freight route between Gothenburg and New York or Boston. We will start with two steamships, 19,000 tons each, capable of making a speed of 19 1/2 knots, completing the trip across the ocean in seven days.</p>
   <p>We need thirteen million kroner to start this business. Six millions will be signed up for in Sweden, four millions will be obtained in America, and the balance, three millions, will be borrowed from the Swedish government. Shares for more than five million kroner have been signed up for in Sweden to date. This gives you an opportunity to be partner in this national enterprise, which, no doubt, will be a <pb facs="5423404_5_0282.jpg" n="2"/>A committee of about two hundred prominent countrymen has undertaken the task here in Chicago to encourage and put forward the sale of stocks in the new line. Why is a direct line between Sweden and North America necessary? Because there are over two million Swedish-Americans in the United States, and thousands of them visit their old homeland every year, and in some cases, are forced to make the trip on strange ships. Over 19,000 persons made trips during 1913 to and from America, according to statistics. Over fifteen million kroner are paid yearly for passenger tickets and freight between Sweden and America. Sweden's exchange in goods with North America amounts now to 700,000 tons yearly. All of this money goes to foreign steamship companies now. Why should not the profit of these sums fall to the Swedes on both sides of the Atlantic when we ourselves can feed our own line? The price of the shares is very low, 100 Swedish Kroner each, or $27 in American money. The owner of the ship Mr. Wilhelm R. Lundgren, of Gothenburg, who <pb facs="5423404_5_0283.jpg" n="3"/>initiated this enterprise started the first ocean line from Sweden to South Africa and Australia with much success, and his successful action in this case is a security that even this new enterprise is laid in right hands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
