<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-05-30">May 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">John E. Ericsson</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-05-30">May 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN E. ERICSSON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most popular Swede in Chicago is John E. Ericsson, building contractor, who last week celebrated his fiftieth birthday. He was honored with many banquets. After the banquet mentioned in our last issue, given by the Swedish Engineers' Club, another banquet was held Thursday in the same quarters, given by Svithiod Singing Society. A more elaborate homage was paid Mr. Ericsson on that occasion. Nearly three hundred of Mr. Ericsson's closest friends and representatives from the thirty-nine different organizations, to which he belongs, had gathered for a splendid "Supe", to which he was invited as guest of honor. Edwin A. Olson acquitted himself as master of ceremonies in the usual able manner. He presented the different speakers, who all praised Mr. Ericsson and John F. Friedlund for their work within Svithiod Singing Society; he also praised George E. Q. Johnson for his activities within Monitor Council, Royal Arcanum. The Swedish Club was <pb facs="5423404_5_0655.jpg" n="2"/>represented by its president, Charles S. Peterson. Svithiod members sang two numbers.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the "Nestor" of the Swedish-American Press, Editor Alex J. Johnson, who was greeted with a powerful "salvo" of applause. He spoke on the important work that the guest of honor in particular, and the Swedes in America in general, have done in this country in the years that have passed. The speaker concluded with wishing John E. Ericsson the best of health and enjoyment of life in the years to come, whereupon all present sang "Ja ma han lefva." After Mr. Johnson's speech the master of ceremonies called upon another editor - Frithiof Malmquist. He responded by reading a poem written by himself in honor of the birthday. Joel Mossberg sang "Per Svineherde."</p>
   <p>Carl R. Chindblom spoke on Mr. Ericsson's unselfish and widespread work, and <pb facs="5423404_5_0656.jpg" n="3"/>particularly of his work within the Swedish Old People's Home Society. His speech was followed by two of his favorite songs by Gustof Holmquist, accompanied by Edgar A. Nelson.</p>
   <p>Dr. John A. Christenson spoke on the importance of the occasion, and concluded his speech by presenting Mr. Ericsson, in behalf of those present, with a beautiful silver cup. Mr. Alfred A. Norton spoke for Mrs. Ericsson, who was not present, and presented her sponsor with a beautiful bouquet of flowers. Peter Parker spoke in behalf of the Engineers' Society. Mr. Ericsson himself was now given an opportunity to express in words his feelings at the honor bestowed upon him. This highly successful evening was rounded off with "The Star-Spangled Banner."</p>
   <p>John E. Ericsson, was born May 23, 1868, in Torp, near Moheda in Smaland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0657.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He came to America with his parents and brothers and sisters in 1884, after having studied in his parish school and technical school in Stockholm. Here he learned the bricklaying trade. At 19 years of age he was a foreman; at 22, a superintendent on building works. After having occupied responsible positions for twelve years, he joined with his older brother, Henry, in 1902, and under the name Henry and John Ericsson, engaged in the building line for four years, when the partnership was dissolved, and John E. became a member of the firm, Lanquist &amp; Illsley Co.</p>
   <p>In 1895 he married Celia Peterson, daughter of the late merchant, Swan Peterson, and lives at present with his wife, her mother, and their two daughters, in his magnificent home at 4530 Beacon Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
