<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-10-15">Oct. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Victor Tessing Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Victor Tessing]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-10-15">Oct. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">VICTOR TESSING IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Victor Tessing]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known builder and contractor, Victor Tessing, president of the firm Tessing &amp; Peterson, suffered a stroke last Saturday as he was on his way to the firm's offices at 329 Plymouth Court. He was taken to a near-by hospital, where he passed away last Monday.</p>
   <p>Tessing was born in Slaka, Ostergotland, Sweden, September 15, 1864, and observed his sixtieth birthday last month, on which occasion he was heartily feted by his many friends. He attended the public school near his home and afterwards entered a private school. Later, he went to Stockholm, where he attended a technical school for three years, and obtained the training which fitted him for a career as a builder. When in 1890 he decided to go to America, he chose Chicago as the place which offered him the best <pb facs="5423404_5_0494.jpg" n="2"/>opportunities, and gradually he won a prominent place among Swedish contractors here.</p>
   <p>For many years he belonged to the Swedish Baptist organization, and was a member of the First Swedish Baptist Church here, in which he held many positions of trust. When the congregation built its new church, he was very helpful; his firm did the interior work. The Baptist organizations as a whole profited by his business experience, and he was made treasurer of the mission department.</p>
   <p>Tessing was a lover of song and music, and belonged to the Arion Male Chorus, which has often been heard at concerts and festivals. For many years he served as its president.</p>
   <p>In 1894 he married May Kallbom. She and four children survive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
