<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-02-09">Feb. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Swedish-American Literary Woman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-02-09">Feb. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Swedish-American Literary Woman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Velma Swanston Howard is undoubtedly one of our finest Swedish-American writers at the present time, even thought she has not won great acclaim among her own countrymen here. Her excellent translation of Selma Lagerlof's Nels Holgerson's Journey, which was published here in 1907 and later in England, and of Legends of Christ by the same author, would alone be enough to endear her to lovers of fine literature.</p>
   <p>Velma Swanston Howard was born in Ostergotland, Sweden, in 1867, and came to America at the age of five with her parents who made their home in Chicago. Two years later she lost her mother, and she was very young when it became necessary for her to make her own living. Her mind was set on a stage career, and at the age of eighteen she went to the School of Oratory at Boston on a scholarship, for the particular purpose of fitting herself for classical dramatic roles.</p>
   <p>After two years of study she graduated with honors, and after another year <pb facs="5423404_5_0727.jpg" n="2"/>of training in New York her theatrical engagements took her all over America.</p>
   <p>But after some time her literary interests began to overshadow all others, and she devoted considerable time to writing. She finally gave up her stage work and began to travel as a lecturer, and it soon became evident that she had the remarkable ability of holding the attention of her audiences.</p>
   <p>In 1903 she made a journey to Sweden, and during her stay there she became very interested in the famous author, Selma Lagerlof, and her works. She translated two of her books into English, as already mentioned, and her literary style as well as the faithfulness with which she preserved the original author's ideas, were highly praised by critics.</p>
   <p>She has also translated some of Strindberg's dramas, and cherishes the hope of some day being able to present his most important works to the American reading public.</p>
   <p>Judging by the articles which she has contributed to American periodicals <pb facs="5423404_5_0728.jpg" n="3"/>she has all that is required to become a successful author in her own right. We should, therefore, be particularly grateful to her because she makes such a sacrifice in order to make modern Swedish writers known in this country.</p>
   <p>What kind of a person Mrs. Howard is may be easier to understand when we consider that, according to her own statement, her dearest hope is to spend the evening of her life in Sweden, in a cottage at the edge of a fir forest, close to the ocean, and in the company of laughing and playing children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
