<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-05-14">May 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Our District Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0836</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0836.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-05-14">May 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DISTRICT SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: A Swedish-American district society is an organization of people who hail from the same district (province or county) in Sweden].</p>
   <p>During the last few years reports have, from time to time, appeared in the Swedish-American press, of people from certain districts in Sweden having met and formed district societies. Some of these organizations have already been in existence for several years, and hold conventions which attract much interest. They resemble somewhat the home town societies in Sweden.</p>
   <p>In the larger Swedish cities organizations of people who are natives of the same country districts have existed for many years now, and hold regular social gatherings where old friends meet and old memories and old acquaintances are revived. Our district societies here have been formed for the purpose of bringing <pb facs="5423404_5_0837.jpg" n="2"/>together people whose childhood homes were located in the same village or country district, so that they may renew old friendships and make new friends among people with whom they have so many memories and interests in common. Like their counterparts in Sweden, they try to strengthen the ties between the old home and those who went away. In Sweden these societies have been the originators of a great popular movement, which has had a far-reaching and beneficial effect on the entire nation. It has created a deeper appreciation of the ancestral inheritance, and revived in people, no matter where they happen to be living their love for the old home and the land on which it stands.</p>
   <p>For us Swedish-Americans our district societies serve as a link between members, and as a medium through which we are better enabled to preserve our language, our Swedish customs and traditions, and our appreciation of the cultural and material achievements of our forefathers, not only in the old country but also in our adopted land. That is the only mission of these organizations. They have no other purpose, and do not, therefore, in any way, compete with existing <pb facs="5423404_5_0838.jpg" n="3"/>Swedish-American orders, benefit societies, or other organizations.</p>
   <p>We think the time has come for a new step in the development of these district societies. A closer co-operation among the various units is desirable. The leaders might get together and discuss questions of mutual interest, such as joint meetings, and an occasional pooling of resources and entertainment talent, exchange of speakers and so on. The next step might well be the formation of a league, for the purpose of presenting a united front and promoting certain joint undertakings without infringing on the special interests and efforts of the individual societies.</p>
   <p>Many small streams make a big river, and if these district societies can manage to avoid becoming the tools of private ambitions and political intrigues they may well turn out to be the forerunners of a great Swedish-American movement; links in a strong chain, which tie all Swedish-Americans together, thus enabling them to form a unit strong enough to preserve Swedish-American tradition, protect Swedish-American interests, and build an unbreakable ring around our Swedish <pb facs="5423404_5_0839.jpg" n="4"/>language and around the Swedish spirit, which has been transplanted into American soil.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
