<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1903-03-04">Mar. 4, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Gustaf H. Carlson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1903-03-04">Mar. 4, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">GUSTAF H. CARLSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gustaf H. Carlson was born in Sweden in 1848. At the age of twelve he went to Germany, where he received his first training in the art of surveying. He returned to his home town in 1869, but during his stay in Germany he had discovered that the world was a little greater than the city of his birth. Consequently, in 1870 he emigrated to America, going to the state of Kansas, where he remained for three years. In 1873 he came to Chicago to practice his profession.</p>
   <p>His successful career as civil engineer began in Hyde Park. His work made Carlson an important figure in engineering circles, and in 1878 he was appointed County Surveyor by the Democrats. In 1880 Carlson entered into a partnership with Samuel S. Greeley to publish an atlas covering Hyde Park. Similar atlases were published for the Town of Lake, Lake View and other places. This huge task was under Mr. Carlson's <pb facs="5423404_5_0776.jpg" n="2"/>supervision. His maps are now in use by all departments of the municipal government of Chicago, by real-estate promoters, and by law firms. In 1887 the Greeley-Carlson Company was incorporated, with Mr. Carlson acting as manager. Town sites were laid out under his supervision, as well as subdivisions, cemeteries, etc. The firm has surveyed the following: Hegewisch, Pullman, Normal Park, Auburn Park, Chicago Heights, Edgebrook Cemetery in Joliet. Other surveys were made in St. Joseph, Missouri, and in the Dupont Powder Company's plants in Keokuk, Iowa. Carlson laid the lines for the Auditorium, the Leiter Bldg, and many others. He was frequently employed by the railroads as an expert wherever a dispute arose in regard to the rights of way.</p>
   <p>In the famous case of Santa Fe Railway vs International Bank, Mr. Carson was the Chief expert.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0777.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1878 Carlson married Miss Julie Vodoz from Switzerland. The couple have two children, a son and a daughter.</p>
   <p>The family belongs to the Christian Science Church - and lives at 3746 Lake Avenue, Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Carlson does not take any active interest in politics, but continues with his work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
