<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-30">June 30, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Jews and Negroes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-30">June 30, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS AND NEGROES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Are there any two racial groups in the world that are being more brutally treated than the Russian Jews and the American Negroes? If there are, then we would wish to be informed on the point. The Russians believe themselves fully justified in murdering Jews en masse. The Americans believe that they may, with an easy conscience, burn Negroes one by one. The Russians condemn our treatment of the Negroes. The Americans condemn the slaughter of Jews by the Russians. But neither party takes the trouble to sweep in front of the home door before starting to find fault with the other's place..... When a number of Jews were murdered at Kishinev, there were cries of angry protests in America against the Russian people, and against the Russian rulers. It was demanded by some that the United States should step in and act, not merely protest against the brutalities. The critics did not then see, or did not want to see the "beam in their own eye." Of course, it was known that in the <pb facs="5423404_5_0333.jpg" n="2"/>South our black brothers were hanged or burned to death for crimes of which they were accused without investigation or trial, but, of course, they were merely "black devils" who had to die at the hands of white gentlemen. These murders of Negroes did not affect our nerves as strongly as the murder of the Jews. Why? Because there were always those who knew how to place upon the murdered Negro some offense of such an unsavory character which the average individual came to think the punishment was deserved, or else the reason was that only one Negro was murdered at a time, and such an occurence would only get a space of a couple of inches in the papers.</p>
   <p>The blame for the cruel massacre at Kishinev is placed on a fanatical clergy, and this class of the clergy is being condemned both by laymen and the better class of clergy in America. But what attitude did some of the clergymen in our <pb facs="5423404_5_0334.jpg" n="3"/>country take in regard to the murder of George White, the Negro, who was burned to death over a show fire last week in Delaware? Shortly after White had been put in jail, and while he was yet under the supervision of the guardians of law, the Reverend Robert Elwood of the Olivet Presbyterian Church in Wilmington, Delaware, delivered a sermon in which he.... directly exhorted his listeners to kill the Negro, advising them, however, to wait until it had been shown whether the grand jury had been called to sentence the accused Negro to death. The words of the clergyman added fuel to the flame, and the following day a "black spot" was put upon the escutcheon of the State of Delaware. Whether any of the murderers in the case will be punished, we do not know, though we hope it will be done. But this we do know that the clergyman mentioned deserves the greater punishment, for it was he who awakened the spirit of hatred and vengeance in the mob which caused the murder.</p>
   <p>Before we demand protest and action against the officials in Russia who permitted <pb facs="5423404_5_0335.jpg" n="4"/>the murder of the Jews...let us sweep before our own door.... As long as our governments in Illinois, Delaware, Indiana, Kansas, Tennessee, Kentucky, Missouri, Mississippi, and other states close their eyes to the crimes of the white population against the Negroes, and as long as that part of the clergy in our country which exhorts to violence and murder, prevails over the calmly thinking, law-abiding group within the same class, we have but little reason to blame the adherents of the Greek-Catholic doctrine for murdering Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
