<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Poet and Literary Critic</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Carl Sandburg]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Poet and Literary Critic</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Carl Sandburg]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among contemporary American poets few have attracted more attention than Carl Sandburg, who is of Swedish ancestry and who has been living in Chicago for several years.</p>
   <p>Sandburg has not been exceptionally productive; in that respect he is probably surpassed by many others. But what he has written has been characterized by critics as typical of modern American poetry, and his work is being pointed to as a model for those who try to depict the beauty in commonplace everyday things and happenings. For Sandburg has studied life and people at close range; and instead of becoming a pessimist and an egotist as a result of that study, he has been drawn closer to his fellow men, especially to those who <pb facs="5423404_5_0543.jpg" n="2"/>labor and to the mass of humanity, who, in the opinion of some observers, seem to be oppressed. He is at his greatest as the poet of labor and the laborer.</p>
   <p>Sandburg was born in Galesburg, Illinois in 1878, the son of August and Clara (Anderson) Sandburg. His father came to America from Sweden as an ordinary laborer. It is said that back home he went under the name of Jonsson.</p>
   <p>In his younger years, Sandburg followed in the footsteps of his father. He had excellent opportunity to observe life in the raw in the great variety of jobs he held. He was everything from hotel dishwasher to quarry worker and stagehand. Then came the Spanish-American War, and, like so many other American youngsters, Sandburg enlisted in the army. When he returned from the war, he did not go back to the old life; instead, he entered Lombard College in Galesburg, from which he graduated in 1902. Some years later from 1910-1912, we find him working as secretary to the mayor of Milwaukee, Wisconsin. Later, he became associate editor of the periodical, System Magazine, published in Chicago. He also began at this time to contribute <pb facs="5423404_5_0544.jpg" n="3"/>articles to The Chicago Daily News and other newspapers. He is now a book reviewer on The Daily News staff.</p>
   <p>His best-known works of poetry are Cornhuskers and Chicago Poems. Columbia University awarded him a prize of $250 in 1919 for the former.</p>
   <p>A couple of years ago, he made a trip to Sweden and visited his father's birthplace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
