<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-23">Apr. 23, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">John E. Norling Taken by Death</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of John E. Norling]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-23">Apr. 23, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN E. NORLING TAKEN BY DEATH</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of John E. Norling]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John E. Norling, owner of the Svenska Tribunen and Fosterlandet from 1901 to 1905, died April 16 in his home at 2838 Burling Street. He had been in poor health for some time.</p>
   <p>Norling was born in Bishop Hill, Illinois, January 13, 1859. His parents were Anders and Elizabeth Norling, natives of Nora, Sweden, who came to America in 1858. As a boy, Norling received a very good education, and when only twenty years of age became manager of a drugstore in Galva, Illinois. A year later, he and his two brothers bought the business, and he remained part owner until 1889, when he organized the Mulford Stearn Company in Streator. Its offices were later moved to Galva.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0500.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far back as the early eighties, Norling began to interest himself in the lumber and land business, and became more actively engaged in those fields when he moved to Chicago in 1891. In the year 1900, he and his brother, P. O. Norling, and S. E. Carlson bought the Svenska Tribunen and Fosterlandet, and in 1901 he became the sole owner of these two Swedish-American publications. In 1905, he sold them to C. F. Erikson.</p>
   <p>Norling became interested in the automatic telephone invented by F. A. Lundquist, and, in 1901, founded the Globe Automatic Telephone Company, which was taken over in 1911 by the Western Electric Company.</p>
   <p>In 1907, when the automobile industry was still in its infancy, Norling founded the Monitor Automobile Works, which manufactured automobiles of various kinds. He served as secretary and treasurer of that concern until 1914, when he resigned to devote his time to his lumber and real-estate interests. He is survived by his wife, who was Christine Ericson, two daughters, Lillian and Ruth, two brothers, and two sisters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0501.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The burial took place last Saturday in the cemetery at Bishop Hill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
