<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-12-27">Dec. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Noted Swedish-American Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Neander N. Cronholm]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-12-27">Dec. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NOTED SWEDISH-AMERICAN IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Neander N. Cronholm]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The noted jurist and historian, Neander N. Cronholm, died last Tuesday at his home, 631 Greenleaf Avenue, Wilmette.</p>
   <p>He was born near Kristianstad, Sweden on November 19, 1843. He belonged to an old and illustrious family which owned great estates in Finland and the Baltic provinces. These, however, were lost during the great war in the beginning of the nineteenth century. Young Cronholm received an excellent education, and, even as a youth, showed unusual ability.</p>
   <p>When the American Civil War broke out, he planned to join the army of the North, but the press of personal business prevented him from enlisting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0562.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some years later, in 1867, he immigrated to an eastern city, and from there he came to Illinois.</p>
   <p>After remaining in Illinois and in Iowa for some time, he returned to the East and entered Pennsylvania College, at Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, from which he graduated. He later spent some time at Yale University, where he wrote a widely acclaimed thesis on the Swedish constitution. He then made an extended study trip to Europe, and upon his return to America, he entered New York University and graduated from its law school. He established himself as an attorney in New York City, but in 1877 he moved to Chicago, which he has since made his home. In the eighties, he was one of the most prominent Swedish attorneys of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Later, however, he became even better known as an historian and as a linguist. His book, Cronholm's History of Sweden, is still considered the best work <pb facs="5423404_5_0563.jpg" n="3"/>of its kind in the English language. It was published in 1902. He continued his linguistic studies almost up to the time of his death. Sanskrit was his specialty. He was the owner of a well-selected and valuable library.</p>
   <p>In 1878 Cronholm married Guilaelma P. Frazee, a member of one of America's oldest families. They had one son, who died in 1883.</p>
   <p>Cronholm's body was taken to its last resting place in Oakwood Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
