<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1902-08-20">Aug. 20, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Emigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1902-08-20">Aug. 20, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH EMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is an interesting editorial in "Smalands Posten", one of the Swedish newspapers, which is sent regularly to The Swedish Tribune, Chicago. The headline of this editorial is; "Why does the Swede emigrate to America?"</p>
   <p>"One of the reasons for the emigration is eight months compulsory training of young men for the Army and Navy," says the editor of the article. He is wondering if "the Swedish government is doing the right thing towards its own country by letting these young men leave their country in large numbers?"</p>
   <p>Another reason for the emigration lies in the "little respect for the working man in Sweden," he says, "while the American worker is satisfied <pb facs="5423404_5_0138.jpg" n="2"/>that he does not need to humble himself before any bosses in America." But it is the editor's hope that "the growing respect for the common workers may increase in Sweden, even if it should take ten years to accomplish such a success for them."</p>
   <p>"The social disproportions would be leveled more quickly if the workers in Sweden would abandon their general strikes, and if the higher educated classes would let their children be prepared for private business, rather than for government work."</p>
   <p>"But there are several things the Swedish emigrants do not know about. Among them: the dollar in America is worth much more here than in Sweden, the vast difference between the various classes in Sweden, many American multimillionaires keep their servants in bondage without mercy, and they are able to buy protection of the law through bribes to suit themselves."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Our young people," the editor says, "are journeying to America to</p>
   <p>try to find better pay for their work, because their relatives in the United States are influencing them to come to America. But what about the outcome? Well, the examples which Swedish boys, without education, have been made wealthy and secured a good social standing are not confined to America alone. We can say that for every Swedish farmer boy, who has become a matadore in Chicago, Boston, or Minneapolis we can pluck two who have been that in Stockholm or Gothenburg,or in some small village in Sweden."</p>
   <p>"The living costs in America places the dollar on the same level as our Swedish "Krona" he writes, "and with the increased wages in Sweden, the workers are able to save one Krona here just as easy as a dollar in America."</p>
   <p>"But," he continues, "and here is just the answer why the people emigrate. When the worker in America comes back to Sweden and has saved a considerable sum of <pb facs="5423404_5_0140.jpg" n="4"/>of money as he could have done in "Kronen" in Sweden during the same time. In America, every dollar is worth $3.70 in Swedish Kronen!"</p>
   <p>"But how many come home? Let us make it more pleasant for our children to stay home. Let us make that much feared military course a pleasant, warm and happy instructive memory. Let us make it less hard for young people to make their living without so much preaching. Let us not put too many regulations, too many restrictions in their way, especially for our pioneers in the northern part of Sweden. The people here in Sweden have a wearisome time. The old, playing folk life is now artificial. The song has been put to silence or has flown to the church. The violin, which was always in every village before, is now exchanged for a piano at the homes of the more wealthy class. One is not a natural lover of music any longer, and one does not dance around the May pole, or on the green meadows, on Sundays in Summer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0141.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Is it any wonder that the young people don't like all these regulations? Is it any wonder that the young people are going away from all this wearisomeness?"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
