<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-30">Mar. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Well-Known Doctor Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column--sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. Alfred Hakanson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-30">Mar. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WELL-KNOWN DOCTOR IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column--sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. Alfred Hakanson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>News of the sudden death of the well-known and popular physician, Alfred Hakanson, spread among Chicago's Swedes last Thursday, causing deep-felt sorrow in many homes.</p>
   <p>A few weeks ago, he went south for a brief vacation, and was stopping in Mobile, Alabama, visiting a brother, when he suffered an attack of pneumonia. He died after a few days' illness.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hakanson was born in Geneseo, Illinois, May 12, 1866. His parents were pioneers in that part of the state. He was the youngest of five children.</p>
   <p>When he was still a young boy the family moved to Nebraska, where he attended <pb facs="5423404_5_0612.jpg" n="2"/>grade school, the high school at Oakland, and the Luther College in Wahoo. He graduated from the latter school in 1886 and then went to Augustana College in Rock Island, Illinois. After having studied there for some time, he registered at the University of Nebraska, and graduated from its medical school in 1890.</p>
   <p>He practiced for some time in Rockford, Illinois, and then moved to South Chicago, where he remained for two years. He became county physician there, and was one of the founders of the South Chicago Medical Society, serving for some time as its secretary. He also was one of the founders of the South Chicago Hospital, and served on its staff in 1899 and 1900.</p>
   <p>In 1895 he had taken a post-graduate course at a New York hospital, and four years later a similar course at the Polyclinic Hospital of Chicago. It was at this time that he began to specialize in ear, nose, and throat diseases. In 1901 he made a study trip to Europe, visiting some of the leading medical centers there. He worked for some time as assistant to one of the most prominent <pb facs="5423404_5_0613.jpg" n="3"/>doctors of London, England.</p>
   <p>During the last few years, Dr. Hakanson was on the staff of the Augustana Hospital here as head of the ear, nose and throat department. His private practice was quite extensive. He maintained two offices: one downtown, and one in the Edgewater district. Several Swedish societies, among them the Order of Vikings, engaged him as their physician. He was a valued member of the Immanuel Lutheran Congregation and a number of Swedish-American organizations, among them the Swedish Club and the Verdandi Lodge of the Independent Order of Svithiod.</p>
   <p>In 1892 he married Bertha Lindberg. She and a daughter, Evelyn, survive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
