<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-07-19">July 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">America Calls</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-07-19">July 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA CALLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A reader recently wrote us about a young man and a young woman who, in the early eighties, came to Chicago from the district of Norrbotten, Sweden. They worked here for quite a few years before they felt that they had enough money to found a home and get married. However, this was right after the World's Fair, when poor times set in here; they then thought it was better to return to Sweden and establish their home there. The husband obtained steady employment there with good pay, and the outlook was at first rosy. But the family increased, and so did expenses; when there finally were four growing boys to feed and clothe, the father and mother began to do some hard thinking about the future of these healthy, bright and lively boys. Agreeing that America offered better opportunities for the youngsters, they sold their home and returned to Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0066.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Sweden, much is being said and even done these days about providing workers with their own homes, consisting of a small, attractive red cottage and a plot of land, in order to discourage emigration, which is now tapping the nation of much of its best blood. It is even hoped that if such homes could be made available at low cost many emigrated Swedes would be tempted to return home.</p>
   <p>Such a cozy little cottage is fine on a colored post card and in the tourist bureau's yearbook, but the man with a family, who plans to live there, must take a more practical and long-term view, and, unfortunately, neither he nor his wife and children can eat the scenery. If he has any sense he will ask himself what kind of a future he and his dear ones may expect in such a place. As the situation is right now, the answer is not very satisfactory.</p>
   <p>America has a strange drawing power, especially on those who have once lived here. The case cited above is not at all unusual.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
