<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-03">Sept. 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Swedes Hear Oscar's Friend Dr. Waldenstrom, Riksdig Member Talks to Chicago Audience</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-03">Sept. 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDES HEAR OSCAR'S FRIEND DR. WALDENSTROM, RIKSDIG MEMBER TALKS TO CHICAGO AUDIENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P .9-2</p>
   <p>Dr. P. Waldenstrom a prominent member of the Swedish Riksdig, yesterday afternoon addressed in Swedish a large audience at North Park College, devoting himself almost entirely to a study of present conditions in Norway and Sweden. Dr. Waldenstrom, who long has been a close personal friend of King Oscar, wholly indorsed the course of the king in the recent rupture with Norway. He told of a strong Swedish opposition to a prince of that nation taking the offered throne of Norway.</p>
   <p>It was the speaker's belief that Norway would not long require the services of a king, as he regards that country as on the road to republicanism.</p>
   <p>Dr. Waldenstrom sees nothing but bright prospects for the future of his country, and while regretting the departure of Norway from the union, finds many reasons for believing good will come of the action, to Sweden at least.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0317.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The visitor is the guest of Rev. C. G. Bjork of North Park College, and while in Chicago in the past week he has met many leading citizens of his race. He expressed keen gratification at the prosperity and social prominence occupied by the Swedes of Chicago. He probably will leave to-morrow for Minneapolis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
