<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-03-23">Mar. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Beloved Swedish Pastor Passes Away</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-03-23">Mar. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BELOVED SWEDISH PASTOR PASSES AWAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, two colums-quarter of a page, full figure picture of Pastor Herman Lindskog.] Reverend Herman Lindskog, the pastor of St. Ansgar Church, passed away last Sunday night in his home at 841 Sedgwick Street after a month's illness from a liver ailment. The news of his death will be received with sorrow, not only within his own congregation and circle of friends, but by the thousands with whom he has come in contact during his long and useful career as a minister and spiritual leader.</p>
   <p>On Easter Sunday, 1912, he celebrated his twenty-fifth anniversary as pastor of St. Ansgar's, and had, up to that time, officiated at 4,573 weddings and 3,826 funerals; he baptized 6,120 babies and confirmed 1,614 boys and girls. During those twenty-five years he had but one vacation, a trip to Sweden in 1891.</p>
   <p>Pastor Herman Lindskog was born May 24, 1853, in Strangnas, Sweden. In the course of the same year, his parents moved to Stockholm, where he attended <pb facs="5423404_5_0684.jpg" n="2"/>the Katarina School and the Stockholm College. In 1875 he was ordained as a minister, and four years later he emigrated to America with his family, making his home in Rockford, Illinois. Here he served as pastor for eight years. Early in 1887 he was called as pastor by the St. Ansgar Swedish Episcopalian Congregation in Chicago. He accepted and took over his duties on Easter Sunday of that year.</p>
   <p>In this connection it is interesting to recall that next to the Old Swedes' Church in Wilmington, Delaware and the Gloria Dei Church in Philadelphia, St. Ansgar's here in Chicago is the oldest Swedish church in America. It has also been called the Jenny Lind Church, because that famous Swedish singer, during an American tour, donated a considerable sum to the church.</p>
   <p>With the passing of Pastor Lindskog the Swedes of Chicago have lost one of their most widely known and most highly esteemed personalities. In church and religious circles he was considered a pioneer, and he was a forceful orator much in demand as a speaker at both religious and secular gatherings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0685.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was also a very able writer, and poetry and translation were among his hobbies. But busy as he was with many other tasks he did not find time for extended literary activities. Behind his ministerial dignity was hidden a fine sense of humor, and he was a prized guest at banquets and other festive occasions.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Lindskog, whom he married in 1875, died two years ago, and Pastor Lindskog is survived by two daughters and a son, Attorney Thomas Lindskog.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
