<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-08-31">Aug. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Bridge Across the Ocean</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-08-31">Aug. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE BRIDGE ACROSS THE OCEAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Has that bridge across the ocean, which we have heard so much about, especially on festive occasions, finally become a reality? Is it true that it is being strengthened and widened and that it carries a steadily increasing flow of spiritual and cultural traffic? If that is really happening, if new supporting pillars are being erected and stronger spans constructed, much of the credit for this spiritual engineering feat should be given to such organizations as the Swedish Glee Club of Brooklyn, which has just returned from a tour of Swedish cities, towns, and rural districts.</p>
   <p>Last year, members of the Swedish Choral Club of Chicago made a triumphal pilgrimage to the land of their fathers. Most of them were born in America, and the old country does not, perhaps, mean as much to them as it does to the members of the Brooklyn club, most of whom were born in Sweden. But there was <pb facs="5423404_5_0236.jpg" n="2"/>plenty of sentimentality displayed during the choral boys' visit, and the reception which they received could not have been more cordial. The Swedes across the sea were thoroughly convinced that the second generation of Swedish-Americans have inherited the Swedish singing heart and the love of Swedish songs and melodies. There is no reason to doubt that the complimentary comments of Swedish critics were sincere, and that an element of pleasant surprise blended with the sentimental enthusiasm in the ovations accorded the singers wherever they went.</p>
   <p>Thus, when the Glee Club of Brooklyn arrived it had not only to live up to the reputation of Swedish-American song in general, but also to the high expectations created by the performances of its Chicago colleagues. It is no easy task to undertake a singing tour to another continent, even though it be a visit to one's own original homeland and one's own people, whose feelings one shares and whose songs one sings. But the Swedish Glee Club of Brooklyn did it in a manner which has won acclaim on both sides of the ocean, and which reflects honor not only on the Club itself, but on all Swedish-Americans, <pb facs="5423404_5_0237.jpg" n="3"/>whose representative it really was. It has forged another strong link in the chain which ties Swedes together wherever they may be, and the bridge across the ocean has been reinforced.</p>
   <p>While we compliment the Glee Club of Brooklyn on a job well done, we take this occasion to remind the Swedish-American public that our singing societies need deserve its support. Imagine what they could do under their present able leadership with the proper backing! Why should we not do for them in a small way what they do for us in a large way?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
