<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-06-03">June 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">John E. Ericsson Appointed Building Commissioner</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of John E. Ericsson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-06-03">June 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN E. ERICSSON APPOINTED BUILDING COMMISSIONER</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of John E. Ericsson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday it was announced that the well-known building contractor, John E. Ericsson, had been appointed building commissioner of Chicago by the newly elected mayor, Anton J. Cermak. The appointment was not entirely unexpected, and was received with great satisfaction by Ericsson's many friends, some of whom had feared that some one else might be given the job. He was approved by the City Council the following day.</p>
   <p>The new building commissioner is a native of Moheda, in the province of Smaland, Sweden. He attended grade school in his home district and later he attended higher schools in Stockholm.</p>
   <p>In 1884 his parents, Carl and Maria Ericsson, with all their children, migrated to America. The family's first home here was in Martin County, <pb facs="5423404_5_0403.jpg" n="2"/>Minnesota. At the age of sixteen, John began to learn the bricklayer's trade, and three years later he was a foreman. Later he superintended the construction of numerous large buildings, until, in partnership with his brother Henry, he established the building firm of Henry and John Ericsson, General Contractors. This firm was dissolved in 1906, and John Ericsson joined the Lanquist and Illsley Company, where he remained for a number of years, until he established a building firm of his own.</p>
   <p>Few Chicago Swedes have been so active in Swedish-American organizations as has Ericsson. His friends often, and with good reason, call him "the ex-president," for he has at one time or another served as president of many organizations, among them the John Ericsson League of Illinois, the Swedish Club, the Swedish Engineering Society, Svithiod Singing Club, and the Swedish National Association of Chicago. [Translator's note: The John Ericsson League of Illinois takes its name from the Swedish inventor, John Ericsson, who designed the gunboat "Monitor" of Civil War fame.] At present he is president of the Swedish Glee Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0404.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Ericsson's long experience in the building construction business makes him particularly well fitted for the post as head of the city's building department, and one may feel sure that he will discharge his duties in a creditable manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
