<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Pastor Alfred Anderson Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column, one fifth of a page, full face picture of pastor Alfred Anderson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">PASTOR ALFRED ANDERSON IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column, one fifth of a page, full face picture of pastor Alfred Anderson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the oldest and best-known Swedish-American Methodist preachers, superintendent of the Bethania Home for the Aged, Pastor Alfred Anderson, died suddenly last Friday from a heart attack.</p>
   <p>Pastor Anderson was born in Skarstad, Smaland Province, Sweden, March 3, 1851, and came to America July 4, 1866. After stopping in Chicago for a short time he went to Beaver, Illinois, where some of his brothers and sisters had already made their homes, and where he engaged in various kinds of work for about three years.</p>
   <p>In the year 1870 the Swedish Methodists established a school for preachers <pb facs="5423404_5_0615.jpg" n="2"/>in Galesburg, Illinois, and Anderson, who already belonged to that denomination, became one of the first students at the school. After graduation he was accepted on probation by the Central Illinois Conference, and ordained as a deacon in 1871, and as an elder in 1874. His early activities as a preacher took place in Iowa, and later on he served in New Sweden, Maine. At that time he also continued his studies at the Wesleyan University, of Mt. Pleasant.</p>
   <p>Subsequently he served as pastor of the following congregations: Galesburg, Illinois; Jamestown, New York; Andover, Illinois; the First Congregation of Chicago, the Evanston congregation, and, finally, the Lake View congregation here.</p>
   <p>In addition to his work as a pastor, Anderson was busy in other fields. For some time he managed the denomination's book store here, and he was also appointed superintendent of the Bethania Home. He was one of the founders of that institution, and it was always close to his heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0616.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Pastor Anderson was for many years a member of the committee on schools of his Conference, and also served as a delegate to the General Conference.</p>
   <p>It is not too much to say that few men, if any, have done more for the Swedish-American Methodists than has Pastor Alfred Anderson. Personally, he was a peace-loving, noble man, who was liked and respected by all his associates and by all who knew him.</p>
   <p>His wife died in 1919, and six children, three sons and three daughters, survive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
