<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-06-05">June 5, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Our Pioneers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-06-05">June 5, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PIONEERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In every Swedish-American publication that we receive, we read about Swedish pioneers in various sections of the entire United States.</p>
   <p>It is perfectly proper that the present and future generations of Swedish descent realize that we are under real obligations to our pioneers when we compare ourselves with the descendants of other foreign pioneers.</p>
   <p>Our pioneers conquered many serious stumbling blocks in farming, home building, business, education, arts, English, and so forth. They built and came into public notice, gaining unlimited acknowledgement throughout the country, in spite of the current expression "only a green Swede." Our pioneers were prominent in opening the Western territories to agriculture, in building the transcontinental railroads; they earned their bread by <pb facs="5423404_5_0106.jpg" n="2"/>the sweat of their brow in the field, shop, and the mine. They came here empty handed, put their shoulders to the wheels of progress and today the Swedish-Americans are in as high esteem as any other "hyphenated" Americans from the Atlantic to the Pacific.</p>
   <p>However, there is one attitude we regret in our present generation of Swedish-Americans. We are more or less inclined to criticize them as being stingy, slow, and old-fashioned. We think they should be more modern and up-to-date, but our pioneers had hardships to overcome that we have not had any experience with, so we do not seem to understand that our progressiveness and comfort is a result of their hard work. We should be more mild in our judgment of these old timers and should demonstrate our gratitude for the wonderful present their labors made possible. We should wholeheartedly express our gratitude for what they won for us as an example to future generations; otherwise, we ourselves, will be belittled by our own offspring, though we may be as conscientious as were our pioneers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
