<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-01-12">Jan. 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A Member of Sweden's Parliament Urges Swedes to Emigrate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-01-12">Jan. 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A MEMBER OF SWEDEN'S PARLIAMENT URGES SWEDES TO EMIGRATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the heading given above, Vestgota Posten informs its readers in Sweden that Rev. David Holmgren, who now is back in Sweden from his tour of America, has given a couple of lectures in Goteborg of such a nature as to lead the listener to suspect Mr. Holmgren of being an immigrant-procurer for some American firm.</p>
   <p>We had a suspicion that things might turn out this way. We had a suspicion that Reverend Holmgren's "facts concerning America" would be as far removed from the actual facts as were the "facts" presented by his predecessors. The difference consists purely in this: that while Mr. Holmgren's predecessors in the field painted America and conditions here in the darkest of colors, Mr. Holmgren has portrayed our country in colors <pb facs="5423404_5_0124.jpg" n="2"/>as bright as light itself. But the facts concerning America remain as obscure as ever to those who are listening to the tales.</p>
   <p>We had a suspicion of what was to come when Reverend Holmgren, in his lecture here in Chicago, blackened the old homeland, its institutions, and its people. Our suspicions were strengthened when he told us how splendid conditions were here, as if we did not know conditions here far better than Reverend Holmgren. Our suspicions continued when he took offense at the friendly pointers concerning our adopted land, which we offered him in our paper. Our suspicions were not lessened when he informed us that the inmate of a poorhouse in America is getting as good and as nourishing food as do the guests at the Grand Hotel in Stockholm.</p>
   <p>But then somebody hinted that Reverend Holmgren intended to turn the tables when he returned home to Sweden; there he would tell the facts about America and nothing but the facts. Well, what do you think of the "facts" presented in Goteborg, Sweden by Reverend Holmgren, member of the Swedish Parliament?</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0125.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He informed his audience that the average wages in America are $2.50 per day, and that carpenters receive $5.50 per day. We are of course grateful to Mr. Holmgren for this information, and we hurry to transmit the good news to our many readers; they will undoubtedly rejoice at the "facts" related. If the Swedes in America were only able to exist on the strength of these "facts," then their satisfaction with them would be redoubled. But alas! the "facts" need a trimming. If Mr. Holmgren had stated that the average wages in America are $1.25 per day, then he would have been quite close to the truth. And we beg to request Mr. Holmgren to send us a list of all the Swedish carpenters in America who are earning $5.50 per day while working at their trade. We would be glad to send each of them a free subscription to the Svenska Nyheter for one year. "For to him that hath shall be given."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
