<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1880-05-19">May 19, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">The Emigration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1880-05-19">May 19, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">THE EMIGRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: Large masses of immigrants who, tired of Europe, arrive at our shores every day, is a proof of our nation's prosperity.</p>
   <p>Information of American prosperity was spread with such speed to all civilized land that a renewed request to participate in the work of a free and strong people in its efforts for spiritual and economic independence was heard everywhere</p>
   <p>The millions here, who have friends there, serve as advertising agents. Their letters, sent home to the old country, contain reports of the impartiality and freedom of American life and of the respect and financial reward honorable work of different kind receives.</p>
   <p>Eighty one thousand two hundred sixty two immigrants came to New York during the first four months of this year,as against only 61,901 in the year 1873.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0210.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The reasons for such large masses of men deserting the places where they were born are, of course, different in each case, but we believe that the first and most powerful reason is the certainty of bettering their financial condition in America. That they really can better themselves in a very short time is so apparent that no one acquainted with the facts on each side of the ocean ever dares deny it.</p>
   <p>The majority of the immigrants who now arrive are already familiar with living possibilities in America. More than half of them go directly to places in the West, where they intend to settle. Many have sufficient means with which to buy land and necessary farm equipment. A large part of those arriving have been farmers before, but sold that meager sod, from which they could hardly feed themselves and their children, and are now trying to establish better homes in the West of America. These immigrants carry with them about sixty or seventy dollars each. It is estimated, that this year's immigration will go up to 500,000 persons at least, and if this is correct, the capital they will carry with them will probably amount to around thirty to thirty five millions of dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0211.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The question of emigration which seems to be a serious one in Sweden has been brought before the Swedish Parliament. Several speakers mentioned during the discussion in the Second Chamber of the Parliament, that the people fear the law of compulsory enrollment in military camps. This they thought was the cause for many of the sons of Sweden abandoning their native country.</p>
   <p>This has lately been denied by several newspapers, both in Sweden and in America. It is not so much the fear of this law, but rather the ill-feeling against the army system in Sweden which is sucking the best from the people and is driving the young Swede to a foreign country to find a home.</p>
   <p>It is the unwillingness to slave and to work and sweat only to support lazy people related to the Chief Executive, which causes many a Swede to seek his living in a country whose highest official must take care of his family himself and pay for his own journeys and recreations as common people do, The Swede is longing for a country, where work is respected and paid for where the workman has just as much to say in regard to public welfare as the <pb facs="5423404_5_0212.jpg" n="4"/>capitalist or the official, where one is "below the line," and where everyone is talked to and treated alike.</p>
   <p>He requests that the capital and not the worker should be taxed, that he himself shall decide the amount of taxes, and should choose his own officials in order that they may know that they are the people's servants and not its masters, masters who like to knock down the masses and trample law and humanity under foot.</p>
   <p>The Swede requests full liberty of conscience and that absolute right to decide in regard to his religion. Last, but not least, he wants a free press, because this has always proven itself to be a strong bulwark of liberty and an implacable foe of despotism.</p>
   <p>These demands are not new. For a long time they have been smoldering as fire under the ashes and the reason they are now in flame is,"the good times" in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0213.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>As long as the conditions in Sweden were poor there was no relief for the oppressed worker in Sweden. He had to be satisfied with his economical poverty as well as his political helplessness and other bad circumstances.</p>
   <p>Now things on this side of the Atlantic are clad in a brighter dress. A welcome place is open for him here. It is surely hard for every lover of its native land to see old Sweden lose so many of its able citizens, but we believe that it is for the best for that country.</p>
   <p>The medicine might taste bitter in the beginning, but in the long run its healing results will be noticeable.</p>
   <p>The mighty masters of that country will sooner or later learn to know that all citizens have the same rights. The immigrants will send home reports regarding conditions here. Some may go back to the old country after several years and spread the ideas they have inhaled here.</p>
   <p>Perhaps from this emigration, which in Sweden is looked upon with unfriendly <pb facs="5423404_5_0214.jpg" n="6"/>eyes, will rise a new day in our never to be forgotten native land, and maybe a new form of government, who knows?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
