<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-17">Dec. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Swedish American's Fest-In-Memory of King Oscar Ii.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-17">Dec. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SWEDISH AMERICAN'S FEST-IN-MEMORY OF KING OSCAR II.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This fest was held last Sunday evening in Orchestra Hall in memory of the departed Monarch. It was so well attended that not a vacant seat could be found. The program began with an organ solo by Dr. Falk, Vice Consul, J.R.Lindgren then introduced Rev. Erik Swan who led in prayer, and his bible text was listened to with reverence. Director J.R.Ortengren during the short time he had to prepare the song program did not have so many of the S.S.U. Chicago singers but nevertheless during this time many of the various song clubs had their own concerts or were otherwise engaged during the evening.</p>
   <p>The Svithiods Singing Club whose leader Prof. Ortengren decided at once that they should sing at the Song fest. And with them were about two dozen of the older singers from other Singing Clubs. And when they came up as the third number on the program they sang so well that we have hardly ever heard them sing any better. Farther on in the program they sang Stilla-Skuggor by (Geyer) and a later number "Stridsbon" by O. Lindblad under the leadership of Professor Ortengren.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Orators for this outstanding occasion was Dr. G.A. Andreen who spoke in English, and Dr. A.J.Carlson. The former is president of Augustana College, the latter Professor at the University of Chicago;Dr. Andreen spoke of King Oscar as a Monarch,and Prof. Carlson of King Oscar as a Man. Both speeches were splendid and Dr. Andreen's clear voice could be heard over the entire hall, he carried out his subject excellently. Dr. Carlson spoke Swedish, he had his speech written down, and it was splendid for those who sat near enough so they could hear it. Prof. Carlson's voice was rather weak so those who sat far away lost the splendid meaning his talk had. We should not forget the seventh number on the program - One of King Oscar's Poems. "Farewell To The Fatherland." The splendid speaker Arthur Donaldson was the man that read the poem and he took the public by storm. About this Memorial Festival we can say the whole affair did justice to the beloved King Oscar II.</p>
   <p>The cost of the whole affair was entirely assumed by Vice Consul J.R.Lindgren to whom all honor belongs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is seldom mentioned in connection with this festival but he has earned the highest esteem for its arrangement, for food and the steps taken for the carrying out of the whole affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
