<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-07-06">July 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Unveiling of Monument for "Herman Roos"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0830</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0830.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-07-06">July 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">UNVEILING OF MONUMENT FOR "HERMAN ROOS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 2, 1880 Herman Roos, editor of the Swedish-American, a representative man in Scandinavian circles, and prominently known as an advocate of the doctrines of Voltaire and Thomas Paine, was accidentally run over by a train on the Michigan Southern Railroad and very seriously injured.</p>
   <p>Every effort was made to save his life, but death ensued shortly afterward. Mr. Roos was a man of finished education, a graduate of Copenhagen University, a terse and forcible writer, and his influence among the Scandinavian free-thinkers of America was wide-spread and generally acknowledged. Since his untimely death his friends have been engaged in raising funds to erect a monument over his grave in Waldheim Cemetery.</p>
   <p>The work was completed some weeks ago, and yesterday a large concourse of Scandinavian citizens formally unveiled the monument.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0831.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The many friends of the dead journalist and writer proceeded by train to Oak Park, and thence to the cemetery by carriages. The arrangements for the impressive ceremony were in charge of Messrs. Magnus Elmblad, F. T. Engstrom, Charles Eklund, Nels Anderson, A. Lindquist, and C. F. Nelson.</p>
   <p>The "Svea Society" of which the deceased was an honored member, were present, carrying their beautiful society flags.</p>
   <p>Arriving at the grave, Capt. O. G. Lange read from manuscript a tribute to the lamented dead, during which the veil was taken from the column, displaying a Scotch granite monument twelve feet high resting upon a pedestal four feet in height.</p>
   <p>The monument is very plain, no attempt having been made at ornamentation.</p>
   <p>The following is inscribed upon the base in the Swedish language:</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0832.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Sacred to the Memory of Moons. Herman Roos of Hjelmsater, Sweden, who, as Editor of the Swedish-American, Fought Nobly for the Mastery of Common Sense and Reason, over Bigotry, Superstition, and Hypocrisy. In Honor of These Pinciples, Liberal-Minded Countrymen and Friends Throughout the United States Raised This Monument".</p>
   <p>Besides Capt. Lange, ex-Consul Sundell and Mr. Marcus Thrane also addressed the people in Swedish. The music for the occasion was supplied by Nitsche's band, and the Svea Singing Society sang several selections over the grave.</p>
   <p>Among the prominent Scandinavian citizens present were the Hon. C.G.Linderburg, P.M.Almini, A.G.Lundburg, M. Salmonsen, Dr. Paoli, Mr. E. Hegstrom, Marcus Thrane, L. P. Nelson, K. Nelson, and others.</p>
   <p>After completing the ceremonies, the friends returned by train to the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
