<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-04-07">Apr. 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Ranseen Is Seventy-Five</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. M. C. Ranseen]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-04-07">Apr. 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">DR. RANSEEN IS SEVENTY-FIVE</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. M. C. Ranseen]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Mattis C. Ranseen, pastor of the Swedish-Lutheran Nebo congregation here, and former president of the Illinois Conference of the Augustana Synod, observed his seventy-fifth birthday yesterday.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ranseen was born in Ljungryda, Blekinge, Sweden, and his father was Carl M. Ranzin [sic], a farmer. After having gone through the public school he attended the People's High School near his home for two years, and then studied for some time under a private tutor. He then taught school until 1867 when he embarked for America. For the first few months here he lived in Rockford, Illinois and Centralia, Illinois, whereafter he entered the Augustana Theological Seminary in Paxton, Illinois. He completed the four-year course, and was ordained as a minister in the Synod in June, 1871, during a synodal convention at Chicago City, Minnesota.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0625.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was first called to Dayton, Iowa, where he served as pastor for two years, whereafter he worked as a missionary for the Synod at Keokuk, Iowa, and organized two congregations there. Later on he served for two years in Elgin, Illinois and in Ottumwa, Iowa for four years. Finally, in 1879 he came to Chicago as pastor of the Getsemane Church, with which he remained until 1910, when he took charge of Nebo congregation.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ranseen can thus look back upon almost half a century of service with the Augustana Synod and he has held many responsible positions within this organization. While he was in Iowa he acted as president of the Synod conference of that state, and when he came to Chicago he was made president of the Illinois conference. After a period of six years he resigned, but was re-appointed in 1911 and occupied the honored position until last year when he asked to be released.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0626.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The pastor has also served as vice-president of the Synod, and as chairman of its general council, and also as a trustee of Augustana College and director in the Augustana Book Concern. He was among the founders of the Augustana Hospital and is still on its board of directors.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ranseen can look back on an exceptionally active and fruitful career, and thousands of his friends and associates join with us in paying him tribute on the occasion of his anniversary, and wishing him peace and happiness as he approaches the evening of his life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
