<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pastor Noted in Welfare Work</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Pastor Johannes Jesperson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pastor Noted in Welfare Work</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Pastor Johannes Jesperson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is common knowledge that the Swedish Lutherans of Chicago have been engaged for many years in extensive welfare work through an organization formed for that particular purpose: namely, the Chicago Lutheran Home Mission Society.</p>
   <p>The Society is holding its annual convention at this time, and proposals for the further development and extension of its activities are under discussion. For that reason, it is fitting that we introduce to our readers the man who for nearly ten years has directed the work of the Society. He is Pastor Johannes Jesperson.</p>
   <p>Jesperson was born in Dalum parish, Vastergotland, Sweden, October 14, 1858.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0510.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the early age of fifteen, he decided to go to America, and soon after his arrival here he entered Augustana College. In 1883 he began to study theology at that institution, and two years later was ordained as a minister in the Augustana Synod. His first post was that of pastor of the Swedish Lutheran congregation in Burlington, Iowa, where he remained for four years. He then became business manager of the Augustana College and Theological Seminary, which post he held for fourteen years. Later we find him as pastor of the Salem Swedish Lutheran congregation of Spokane, Washington. After having served in that city for four years, he was called to Coeur d'Alene, Idaho, as president of the newly established Lutheran school there, the Coeur d'Alene College. In 1914 the Chicago Lutheran Home Mission Society asked him to become its superintendent.</p>
   <p>In 1888, Pastor Jesperson married Mathilda Sofia Anerson, who was born in Skolfvened, Ostergotland, Sweden. She died in 1915.</p>
   <p>We cannot give here a detailed account of all that the pastor has accomplished <pb facs="5423404_5_0511.jpg" n="3"/>as director of the Swedish Lutheran welfare activities in this city, though it would make interesting and inspiring reading. His associates in this work know him as a faithful and untiring leader, and, all in all, as a man who is exceptionally well fitted for his task. The notable expansion of the Society's welfare work during the last few years is chiefly credited to him.</p>
   <p>He lives at the Lutheran Central Home, 1346 North La Salle Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
