<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-10-25">Oct. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Pastor Erland Carlsson: Obituary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-10-25">Oct. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">PASTOR ERLAND CARLSSON: OBITUARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The links to the old pioneers among the Chicago-Swedes are thinning out more and more. The bodies of Larson, Stenbeck, Sundell, and Lange have one after another been buried and now we are informed that Doctor Erland Carlsson- Pastor Carlsson- as he was best known among the Swedish-Americans in Chicago, died in his home, 1662 Barry Ave. on October 19th.</p>
   <p>Erland Carlsson was born on August 22, 1822 in Suletorp Elghult in the state of Smaland, Sweden. After he had completed his theological studies he was ordained priest in 1849, and had, as such several appointments, among them Assistant Pastor at the Cathedral in Vexio. Then he got a call-through Doctor P. Fjellstedt, to form a Swedish-Lutheran congregation in Chicago in 1853.</p>
   <p>We borrow now from the well known work, "The Swedes in Illinois."...</p>
   <p>"Those Swedes, who were the first ones who arrived to Chicago, were as we know, not so well off as they, who are now settled in Chicago. It <pb facs="5423404_5_0810.jpg" n="2"/>was very hard for the early settlers to make any headway here. They were poor, sick and disheartened and naturally, they went to their pastor at the Immanuel Church for advice and help. Thus pastor Carlsson was forced by the circumstances to appear as the Swedes wordly leader besides his spiritual work among them.</p>
   <p>He had to be everything for his countrymen; he had to preach for them on Sunday, run around in the city to get some work for them on Monday, try to straighten out some difficulties on Tuesday, meet and help a crowd of newly arrived immigrants on Wednesday, help them as an interpreter at a court on Thursday, write and read letters for some of them on Friday and do a dozen of things for them on Saturday.</p>
   <p>Many a one would have lost his courage - but pastor Carlsson held out. He held out even after both of the churches of Immanuel parish, one newly built, were changed into ashes by the Great Chicago Fire in 1871, when 340 of the families belonging to his parish were burned out. But the parish - in a great measure, due to his efforts, could celebrate <pb facs="5423404_5_0811.jpg" n="3"/>Christmas morning service in 1872 in the new church rebuilt after the Chicago Fire.</p>
   <p>Pastor Carlsson left Chicago for And over in the spring of 1875 to take care of a congregation, which would give him less work than in Chicago. After having been chairman for the Illinois Conference for many years he was elected President for the Augustana Synod in 1881, doing this work without pay until 1888, when he resigned on account of failing health. He had resigned in 1886 from the Andover parish and was appointed General Manager for Augustana College in Rock Island, from which work he resigned in 1888, moving to Kansas. It was here that Pastor Carlsson, who a couple of years ago was honored by Augustana College with the degree of Doctor stayed most of his remaining life. His health failed him more and more during the later years, and while visiting his old homestead, Chicago, and his daughter and son-in-law (Rev. Evald and his wife) he was called to his eternal home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0812.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It would be impossible that a man in Pastor Carlsson's position should escape rivalry and opposition and envy. But the arrows of slander pointed at him in his own time, have long fallen powerless; the majority of the Swedish-Americans in Chicago unanimously bless his memory. The Swedish Tribune, which as a political newspaper is neutral concerning Doctor Carlsson's religious work, cannot refrain from saying that few Swedish-Americans have done his countrymen so many and so important services as Doctor Erland Carlsson. ..</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
