<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1884-04-30">April 30, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">Words to Sweden's Workmen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1884-04-30">April 30, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">WORDS TO SWEDEN'S WORKMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: The Swedish Tribune of Chicago has a wide circulation in Sweden. We will, therefore, address ourselves to those, who intend to emigrate to the United States this year.</p>
   <p>"Consider very carefully before you take the final step to emigrate. Although the times are not so bad here, they are not so very good at present, To come here with empty hands is not advisable. Everything in the American business world is as it seems to be even in Europe now, not so lively. Some banks are failing, the income of the railroad companies is decreasing, the grain market is slow, exports unusually small, the factories are not working at normal speed, and no new enterprises are being undertaken.</p>
   <p>This statement is not written to show that America, as a whole, is entering a crisis, but, compared with the situation now mentioned and the enormous <pb facs="5423404_5_0156.jpg" n="2"/>army of workers which come here daily, it is understood, naturally, that life for the poor immigrant will be very hard. He has no other choice than to take his place in the long line and patiently watch for his chance to earn a dollar.</p>
   <p>It is to this class we speak. Those with some means and whose intention it is to be farmers can always be sure of success, because land is still free for occupation but not so,for the common workers. Those who are used to American customs can better stand the hardship than a newcomer, He will do well to stay at home until better times are at hand here. The spring immigration is now in full force. The stream cannot be stopped now. Those who arrive early have the summer ahead of them and can become settled more easily. Those whose intention it is to move over to this country later on in the summer or in the fall can follow our advice and be saved a bitter experience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0157.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, do not come here without money. If you possibly can get work at home, stay there until better times arrive in the United States. They will soon be here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
