<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-06-13">June 13, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish-American in Sweden.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-06-13">June 13, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH-AMERICAN IN SWEDEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editorial: The other day we met a countryman who had been visiting Sweden after an absence of some twelve years from his old country. He had made good in the United States to which country he has now returned. We asked him how he liked Sweden. "Well, he said,""I cannot understand why the home folks show such distrust to us Swedish-Americans." Why is it that we Swedish-Americans lost the favor of our people at home? They ought to know that ninety per cent of the Swedish immigration belongs to the honest worker and farmer class. They also ought to know that the life in America has an ennobling influence on the stranger. A few tolerant and broadminded Swedes admit that many a tough person, before he emigrated has come back home a real gentleman. And so it is. We dare say also that the Americanized Swede after some ten to fifteen years of living here stands a head higher than some of the people of the class he used to belong at home. Maybe he doesn't practice such excessive etiquette here as he did in his old country, but he shows both <pb facs="5423404_5_0377.jpg" n="2"/>the dignity and station he has attained through the school of life in his new country.</p>
   <p>Some of our Swedish newspapers tell us that many Swedish people do not like to be plain workers, but love to be employed in the government or in the City Hall. Maybe that is one of the reasons why a Swedish-American, who has worked himself into a good position in one way or another, is not so very well received at home? But he knows he is a free citizen in the land of free work. He, who despises the work despises also the worker.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
