<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-17">Oct. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Carl A. Nystrom]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0525</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0525.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-17">Oct. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Carl A. Nystrom]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Order of Svithiod, which conducts a large insurance business and which comprises sixty-five lodges with a total membership of about fourteen thousand, held its annual convention last July in Galesburg, Illinois. Among the new officers elected was Carl A. Nystrom, who became grand master of the Order. We herewith present a brief biography of our countryman.</p>
   <p>To start with, let us say that he is well known among the Chicago members of the Order, even though he has lived in this city but a comparatively short time.</p>
   <p>Carl Nystrom was born in Fjelmer, in Linkoping province, January 26, 1869, and came to America in 1894. He joined the Svithiod lodge Norden, No. 25, when it was organized in Kewanee, Illinois in 1903, and he has belonged to the Order ever since. When he later moved to Joliet, he joined the lodge Odin, No. 10, <pb facs="5423404_5_0526.jpg" n="2"/>in that city, and remained with it until he came to Chicago a few years ago. Here he became a member of Balder, No. 12.</p>
   <p>Nystrom is held in high esteem among the members of the Svithiod Order, and has been very active in the lodges of which he has been a member. He has also been on the board of directors of the organization for a number of years.</p>
   <p>He is employed as a smelting foreman in a large foundry, and is considered an expert in his line of work. His wife died last spring. He lives at 3913 North Kenneth Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
