<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-07">Dec. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-07">Dec. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Ambassador to the United States, His Excellency Lagercrantz, now visiting Sweden, has published some of his American experiences in an interview printed in the Swedish newspapers of Stockholm. Some of the papers containing the interview have arrived here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Editor of the Svenska Kuriren is very pleased to notice that the Ambassador is now in full agreement with this newspaper's opinion, that efforts should be made to eliminate certain bad conditions in Sweden so as to make life there as pleasant as possible. Then nobody would think of emigrating to the United States. His Excellency admits that the attempt to set in motion an emigration from America to Sweden, has been a failure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0301.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But he makes some mistakes in the interview when he says that the present crisis in the United States is "artificial" and that "the Swedes will not be affected by it." This latter statement is all wrong. The present crisis is acute all over the United States and it affects everybody.</p>
   <p>Finally,we regret that Mr. Lagercrantz repeats the old chatter concerning the Swedes' envy, which"prevents them from playing a greater part in American politics." He says, "if a Swede is nominated as a candidate for office, he must be elected with American votes, because the votes of his own countrymen are against him." This statement is also wrong. Every candidate is elected here with the votes both from the Americans and from his own countrymen. There is always envy among every nationality, race, or color, and there will always be. But in one point the Editor of this paper is in full agreement with Ambassador Lagercrantz, and this is the one in which he praises one Mrs.Myhrman in Chicago for her good work. That was the truest thing he has ever said.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
