<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish Insurance Man</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, profile of A. B. Slattengren]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish Insurance Man</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, profile of A. B. Slattengren]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As reported in last week's issue, Alfred B. Slattengren has been made secretary of the Mutual Trust Life Insurance Company, which has its headquarters at 30 North La Salle Street.</p>
   <p>Slattengren was born and reared in the North Star State, and, like so many other of her sons, received his higher education at the Gustavus Adolphus College in St. Peter, Minnesota. The exact place of his birth is Center City, and the date March 21, 1871. His father and mother were among the first Swedish settlers in that area. Young Alfred attended school in Center City. After having completed two years at the Gustavus Adolphus College, he transferred to the University of Valparaiso, Indiana, from which he <pb facs="5423404_5_0590.jpg" n="2"/>graduated.</p>
   <p>Before Slattengren became associated with the Mutual Trust Life Insurance Company he had been county auditor of Chicago County, Minnesota, for sixteen years. He resigned that position to become district manager of the insurance company's branches in Minnesota and in North and South Dakota, a position which he held until 1920, when he was appointed field supervisor, with headquarters in Chicago. In 1921, he became cashier, and his most recent promotion took place January 26 of this year when he was made secretary.</p>
   <p>Slattengren is a big, powerful fellow, the real viking type, and he has inherited the quiet intelligence and upright character of the people from the far North, who some fifty years ago began to immigrate to Minnesota and lay the foundations for a new life. Everything Swedish is dear to him.</p>
   <p>His wife was Amanda Jonason, a daughter of pioneers of Center City. They <pb facs="5423404_5_0591.jpg" n="3"/>have two sons and a daughter, and they live in Riverside, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
