<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Henschen Eighty Years Old</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Dr. William Henschen]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0581</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0581.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">DR. HENSCHEN EIGHTY YEARS OLD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Dr. William Henschen]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. William Henschen, well known throughout the country as a pastor and journalist, observed his eightieth birthday last Tuesday. Dr. Henschen is a native of Uppsala, Sweden's famous university center. He attended the university there, and became a Doctor of Philosophy at the age of twenty-one. After having studied physiology for a couple of years in Berlin, he became an instructor in Lund, Sweden, and later in Halsingborg. In 1870, he decided to go to America. His first stop was Florida, where he lived for two years. He then went to New York, where he devoted himself to newspaper work, becoming the editor, first of Nordstjernan, and, later, of Norden.</p>
   <p>In 1875 he joined the Swedish Methodist church, and was shortly thereafter appointed editor of its publication, Sendebudet. At the same time he became <pb facs="5423404_5_0582.jpg" n="2"/>a teacher at the Swedish Theological Seminary in Evanston. He held these positions unitl 1882, when he was called to the pastorate of the Swedish Methodist Church of Jamestown, New York. In 1885, Dr. Henschen went to Sweden, but returned to Chicago in 1889 to become the editor of Sendebudet for the second time. He remained in this capacity until 1911. Since then he has divided his time between church activities and journalism. It is in the latter field that he has done his most notable work.</p>
   <p>He is now living in retirement. Among his children is the well-known banker, H. S. Henschen. Dr. Henschen's wife died a few months ago. They had been married for more than fifty years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
