<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-03-16">Mar. 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Well-Known Pastor Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0719</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0719.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-03-16">Mar. 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">WELL-KNOWN PASTOR DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most prominent pastors within the Augustana Synod, Dr. C. A. Evald, pastor of the Swedish Immanuel Church here, died last Saturday at his home, 218 Sedgwick Street, at the age of sixty. He had been in poor health since June of last year, and became so critically ill a few weeks ago that no hope was held for his recovery.</p>
   <p>Dr. Evald was born in Kihl parish, Narke, Sweden, May 25, 1849, and was educated in the schools of Orebro. He immigrated to America in 1871, and immediately entered the Augustana Theological Seminary at Paxton, Illinois from which he graduated in 1872. His ordination took place shortly afterwards at Galesburg.</p>
   <p>He was first appointed pastor for the Augustana Congregation in Minneapolis, Minnesota, where he remained until 1875 when he moved to Chicago as pastor of the Immanuel Congregation, whose beloved leader and teacher he has been ever since.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0720.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Evald was an excellent religious orator, and was also much in demand as a lecturer on matters of public interest of a nonreligious nature. Among the administrative offices he held are those of secretary and president of the Illinois Conference of the Augustana Synod; for many years he was the secretary of the board of directors of the Augustana Hospital.</p>
   <p>In addition to his work as a pastor, he devoted considerable time to writing. He was on the editorial staff of the religious publication Grace and Truth for several years, and contributed regularly to The Banner of the Cross, Theological Periodical, and other church papers.</p>
   <p>In recognition of his outstanding leadership as pastor and religious author, the Augustana College and Theological Seminary of Rockford, Illinois, conferred upon him an honorary degree of Doctor of Theology in 1900.</p>
   <p>In 1876 Pastor Evald married Miss Annie Carlson, a daughter of Dr. Erland Carlson, she died in Stockholm in 1880, and three years later he married <pb facs="5423404_5_0721.jpg" n="3"/>her sister, Emmy Christine Carlson, who survives him, as do his three daughters.</p>
   <p>Funeral services for Dr. Evald will be held next Friday in the Immanuel Church on Sedgwick Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
