<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-09-22">Sept. 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Honored</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-09-22">Sept. 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN HONORED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For his services as director of the Swedish Singers Society, King Gustaf V. has rewarded Mr. John R. Ortengren with the Vasa medal. The medal has been turned over to the president of Augustana College, Gustav Andreen, for presentation at a banquet to be held in honor of Director Ortengren, who so well deserves the honor.</p>
   <p>The banquet will be held at the Svithoid Singers Club rooms September 29.</p>
   <p>Professor John R. Ortengren came to Chicago in the fall of 1888; he was born in Gastrikland, Sweden, October 5, 1862. At the age of 18 years, he began studying voice in Stockholm, and the following year, he sang at the Kings theatre. He later studied at a musical academy in Stockholm, and also in Paris. Soon after coming here, he became a professor at the Chicago Musical College. Here, he developed a real desire to cultivate <pb facs="5423404_5_0746.jpg" n="2"/>and promote the Swedish song in America. Later, he became leader of the Swedish American Elite Choir, which sang at a large festival in 1897 in Stockholm, and scored a huge success, receiving a medal as a reward. Ever since, he has been chief director for the western division of the Swedish-American Singers Society. The honor of directing the outstanding Swedish Choir in America, which in 1910, will visit Sweden, has been offered him. Professor Ortengren is fully deserving of the distinction bestowed upon him by the King of Sweden.</p>
   <p>We congratulate our friend, Mr. Ortengren, on this outstanding honor and urge him to always hold high his ideals of his native land and go on to higher heights.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
