<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-11-22">Nov. 22, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">How One Perish in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-11-22">Nov. 22, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">HOW ONE PERISH IN AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: If all persons, who arrived here spoke the truth there would not be so many emigrants, I am sure. These are the words a nice Swedish immigrant wrote in a letter to a Swedish newspaper. He seemed by this to try to do his part to stop the emigration.</p>
   <p>His first argument is the old one: namely, that, "millions have emigrated to America, tempted by the hope to obtain wealth quickly and easily, as well as attain more prestige socially, as well as other benefits," but he is very often mistaken concerning this concept.</p>
   <p>Some individuals might have arrived here tempted by such hopes but not the great mass of people. They have emigrated to the new world hoping to win a better existence with less hardship than at home, otherwise they would not work <pb facs="5423404_5_0184.jpg" n="2"/>so zealously; almost immediately after they arrive with a view to securing these benefits. When they land in New York, Boston or in any other Atlantic harbor they do not stay there hoping to be found by rich families and to be their heirs. They take the first train and go westward, where they take jobs on farms, factories, railroads or in any place where they can make a living, not to mention all those who take "homestead" and be come farmers at once.</p>
   <p>The correspondent does not view the matter in this way, which indicates that he has not yet had time to grasp the situation. He writes further that times in America are not good, America soil is not good, and that farming is combined with hard work.</p>
   <p>The Swedish newspaper who printed this letter takes this as an indicator of the situation here and adds to that if one does well thousands perish. Where they go, if they are killed or are made slaves or go to the poorhouse, we are not told, but they perish theses millions who entered here tempted by the hope <pb facs="5423404_5_0185.jpg" n="3"/>of becoming millionares, that's certain that's "the whole truth", using the words of that correspondent.</p>
   <p>There are at present about half a million Swedes in the United States including the American born.</p>
   <p>If this Swedish newspaper, who swallowed these "truths" really spoke the truth then 495,000 of them must have perished, in other words, must have vanished some where in the ocean of life and become wrecks.</p>
   <p>However, the newspaper has to admit that somehow these people are actually living. Then comes the question: What do they do? We do not think that we say too much when we insist that there are 30,000 Swedish farmers in America, representing 150,000 persons at least. Many of these farmers own several hundred acres of soil. Most of them have not less than 80 but generally 160 acres and very <pb facs="5423404_5_0186.jpg" n="4"/>few less than 40; and when we think of that the majority of them could not have owned one inch of land, if they had stayed in Sweden then it is not the "whole truth", to classify them with those who have "perished."</p>
   <p>There are just as many Swedish mechanics working for a weekly wage from $30 to $10 and many have their own comfortable, luxurious homes, and when one know that most of them never could have earned more than a scanty living we must admit that they have not"perished"but are doing very well.</p>
   <p>There are, of course, some people, who have not settled down anywhere, because they have not yet decided what profession they are going to choose or where they intend to live, but they are not, therefore, lost; they do not suffer, they make their living and are not any burden to anybody. They look around and sooner or later some happy discovery is made. This is the truth, the "whole truth" and nothing but the truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
