<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swede in the Steel Industry</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Einar Lindeblad]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swede in the Steel Industry</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Einar Lindeblad]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The subject of this week's Foreground article is one of our countrymen, who, during the twenty years he has spent in this country, has done a valuable service to the Swedish iron and steel industry. For the last six years, his activities have centered about Chicago and the Middle West, where he has been in close contact with industrial leaders. The man is Einar Lindeblad, Chicago representative of the Federal Tool and Alloy Steel Corporation, which is the successor to the Swedish Iron and Steel Corporation.</p>
   <p>Lindeblad was born in Gothenburg, Sweden, January 7, 1879, and came to this country in 1903. During the next fourteen years, he lived in New York <pb facs="5423404_5_0533.jpg" n="2"/>and in Montreal, Canada, in which country he was engaged as a mining engineer. Incidentally, he has the distinction of being the first to introduce Swedish iron and steel to the Canadian market on a large scale. In addition to other products, he imported considerable amounts of high quality boring steel.</p>
   <p>In 1916 he came to Chicago as the representative of the Federal Tool and Alloy Corporation, which handles the products of one of the oldest and largest steel concerns in Sweden. This Chicago branch takes care of the business in all states west of Pennsylvania. Naturally, Lindeblad's chief interests center about steel and manufacturing processes of steel products. He is a member of the American Society for Steel Treating and of the Machinery Club of Chicago.</p>
   <p>During the comparatively short time he has lived in this city, Lindeblad has become a highly valued and popular member of the Swedish Engineering <pb facs="5423404_5_0534.jpg" n="3"/>Society and of the Swedish Club here. He is on the Board of Directors of the latter organization. He also belongs to the Paul Revere Lodge, No. 998, the Paul Revere Chapter, No. 260, the Lincoln Park Commandery, No. 64, the Knight Templars, and the Medinah Templars.</p>
   <p>In 1917 he married Gene Miller, of Columbus, Ohio. They live at 4840 Kenmore Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
