<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-03-14">Mar. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Pastor Hjerpe Seventy Years Old</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Pastor E. G. Hjerpe]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-03-14">Mar. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">PASTOR HJERPE SEVENTY YEARS OLD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Pastor E. G. Hjerpe]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pastor E. G. Hjerpe, president of the Swedish Mission League of America, observed his seventieth birthday last Monday. He was feted on the occasion by the faculty of North Park College and the trustees of the North Park Mission Congregation.</p>
   <p>Hjerpe was born in Glafva, Varmland, Sweden, where his father was a blacksmith. As a boy he received a good schooling, so that when he came to this country in 1879, at the age of twenty-six, he was immediately admitted to Ansgar College, from which he graduated in 1881. Shortly thereafter, he became pastor of the Second Lutheran Congregation in Galesburg, Illinois. He remained there until 1888, when he was called to the Bethania Church in New Britain, Connecticut.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0551.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He served that congregation for twelve years, going from there to Jamestown, New York, as pastor of the Mission Church of that city. In 1906, he moved to Chicago as pastor of the Bethania Congregation of this city, and four years later he was made president of the Mission League, a post which he still holds.</p>
   <p>We cannot here give a detailed description of Pastor Hjerpe's work with the League. Suffice it to say that he has been an unusually active champion of its cause, both in speech and in writing.</p>
   <p>Few Swedish-American pastors have traveled as widely as he has. A few years ago he went to China to inspect the League's missionary establishments in that country and last summer he visited extensively in Sweden.</p>
   <p>In 1882, Pastor Hjerpe married Josephine Peterson, who was born in Galesburg, Illinois. Their home is at 3417 Foster Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
