<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-29">Sept. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Sven Linderoth Taken by Death</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Sven Linderoth]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-29">Sept. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SVEN LINDEROTH TAKEN BY DEATH</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Sven Linderoth]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known Swedish architect and Good Templar, Sven Linderoth, died last Saturday in his home, 1432 Marquette Road. He is mourned by his wife, nee Johnson, one son, and three daughters.</p>
   <p>Linderoth was born in Skane, October 14, 1859. When he was a year and a half old, his parents moved to Eskilstuna, and in that city he received his early education. But as the oldest of twelve children he was forced to strike out for himself. He went to Stockholm and obtained employment with a manufacturer. He certainly did not sleep on a bed of roses. But the boy was made of good stuff. While his fellow workers spent their evenings resting or seeking recreation, young Sven found time to put in a few hours of study. He managed to finish a course in a technical school, and at the age of twenty-three he established, together with the brother of one of his teachers, the contracting <pb facs="5423404_5_0623.jpg" n="2"/>firm of Ostlin &amp; Linderoth. A few years later, he embarked for America.</p>
   <p>It must be said of Linderoth's activities in this country that they were not always profitable. At the same time it is clear that he quite early made a name for himself among building experts. Only three years after his arrival in this country, he was elected a member of the Illinois department of the American Institute of Architects.</p>
   <p>In 1891 he went through a serious illness which for a long time caused a cessation of his activities. Later he devoted himself to the production of various building materials, which up to that time had been imported, and, therefore, were quite expensive. After some time, he succeeded in developing a type of glazed stone which was just as good as that imported from England and much cheaper. The manufacturing of this product took up most of his time for a few years, and the demand for it increased steadily all over the country.</p>
   <p>In conjunction with this factory, he opened up a school for people who wanted</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
