<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-05-28">May 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">New Bank President</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Robert Anderson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-05-28">May 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">New Bank President</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Robert Anderson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known businessman, Robert Anderson, has just been made president of the United State Bank of Chicago, succeeding the late Carl Lundberg, who died a few weeks ago.</p>
   <p>Anderson was born in Gustaf Adolf parish, Vastergotland, Sweden, December 11, 1870, and is thus now in his early fifties. He attended the public school near his home and then went to the city of Jonkoping, where he learned the painter's trade. In the spring of 1887, he embarked for America, and came to Chicago, where he has made his home ever since.</p>
   <p>During the first few years after his arrival here, he worked at his trade, and at the same time attended night school. After three years of this, he <pb facs="5423404_5_0497.jpg" n="2"/>opened his own paint store. In 1895, he and E. Osterholm went into partnership, and founded the firm of Anderson &amp; Osterholm, which prospered and became one of the best-known concerns in its line in the city.</p>
   <p>For a number of years, Anderson has been on the Board of Directors of the United State Bank of Chicago, and has also been vice-president of the institution. It was therefore no surprise when it was announced that he had been made president, following the death of Mr. Lundberg.</p>
   <p>Robert Anderson is well known and popular among the Swedes in the Englewood district, and has been active in the community life of his countrymen. He is a highly valued member of the Englewood Mission Congregation, and was a member of its Board of Directors for twenty-five years, serving up to the time of the last annual business meeting, when he asked to be relieved of his duties. But he is still superintendent of the Sunday school, a post which he has held for twenty years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0498.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1890 he married Selma A. Hultzen. They have two children, and live at 439 West 61st Street.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This bank appears to be a predominantly Swedish-owned institution. But I am unable to determine its correct name. In a news item in this issue, it is called the United States Bank of Chicago.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
