<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-10">Oct. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish-American Doctor</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Emil E. Torell]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-10">Oct. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish-American Doctor</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Emil E. Torell]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the subject of this week's Foreground article, we have selected a doctor who, even though he is still a young man, has earned a fine reputation for competence in his profession. And who is, in addition, a very personable fellow, well liked by all who know him. He is Dr. Emil E. Torell, whose office is located at 5412 North Clark Street.</p>
   <p>Emil Ernest Torell was born in Oakland, Nebraska, August 25, 1882, the son of the noted Augustana pastor, John Torell, who recently passed away. Young Torell entered Luther College in Wahoo, Nebraska, in 1895. It may be mentioned here that his father was among the men who made that institution what <pb facs="5423404_5_0528.jpg" n="2"/>it is today. Emil later transferred to Augustana College in Rock Island, Illinois, where he studied for four years, receiving his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1903. He then went to the medical school of Northwestern University, from which he graduated in 1907. The following two years he served as an interne in Augustana Hospital in this city. He then went to Escanaba, Michigan, where he became a member of the staff of the Cottage Hospital. He also was engaged as physician for the Chicago and Northwestern Railroad in that district. In 1911, Torell returned to Chicago, and began the general practice of medicine in the Swedish districts of Summerdale and Edgewater, where he has since remained.</p>
   <p>Dr. Torell belongs to several medical organizations, and is a member of the Ebenezer Congregation. He also takes an active part in the activities of Swedish societies, religious as well as otherwise. He is much in demand as a speaker. He makes friends easily, thanks to his own friendliness and winning personality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0529.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1908 he married Alice Lindberg, of Paxton, Illinois. They live at 1702 Carmen Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
