<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-21">July 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">A Slap in the Face</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-21">July 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">A SLAP IN THE FACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's Note.--A news item in the present number of the Svenska Nyheter informs the readers that the Russian government has refused to accept a protest from Jews in America, endorsed by the United States government, against the massacre of Jews in Kishinev. The position taken by the Russian authorities was that Russia could tolerate no interference by foreign powers into its domestic affairs.]</p>
   <p>As mentioned in another column in today's paper, the petition to the Russian government which originated in this country as a protest against the persecution of Jews in Russia in general, and with reference to the massacre at Kishinev in particular, has been left without the slightest consideration by the Russian government.</p>
   <p>This was a slap in Uncle Sam's face, but what business did he have to mix <pb facs="5423404_5_0330.jpg" n="2"/>in the matter, even though his highly praised love of humanity makes itself felt in the petition. The purpose to defend the persecuted Jews in Russia was noble, and it ought to be credited to Uncle Sam. But from the point of view of diplomacy, the United States committed a blunder as indicated by the attitude of the Russian government.</p>
   <p>There can be no two opinions concerning the massacre at Kishinev. The bloody deeds committed there were terrible, and the whole world was outraged at the occurrences. From all over the world voices of protests were heard against a government which, while perhaps not encouraging the persecution of Jews directly, yet it seems to have countenanced and even applauded the vicious acts which took place at Kishinev, and it has made no provisions for their prevention.</p>
   <p>Yet, the massacre at Kishinev was Russia's own affair, and no other nation as a nation had a right to mix in the matter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0331.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nobody believes now that the Jews in Russia will be aided by our government's intrusion into Russia's inner affairs, even though it may seem that this intrusion made a certain impression in St. Petersburg. More than one person acquainted with the Jewish question believes that in the future the position of the Jews will become more precarious than before, and that the happenings at Kishinev are simply a faint prelude to things which may happen in the future.</p>
   <p>The whole world, however, is taking favorable notice of the noble action by the United States in a case like the present. What no European power dared, the United States did, irrespective of the fact that Russia and our country long have been the best of friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
