<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-02">Feb. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Mission Leader Taken by Death</title>
[Half-tone, two columns, one fourth of a page, full face picture of Charles G. Petterson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-02">Feb. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">MISSION LEADER TAKEN BY DEATH</title>
[Half-tone, two columns, one fourth of a page, full face picture of Charles G. Petterson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Charles G. Petterson, financial director of The Mission Friend, and a well-known figure among Swedish-Americans interested in missionary work, died in his home last Monday from a heart disease.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petterson had been in poor health since last summer, but, energetic and active as he was, he kept on working until late in the fall, when he finally had to take to his bed, and for some time he hovered between life and death. However, just before Christmas his health showed a marked improvement, and he insisted on going to work again, in spite of the advice of his doctor that he take a long rest. After some time weakness overtook him again, and last Wednesday he had to give up and go to bed. He was conscious until the last, and died peacefully early in the morning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Carl Gustaf Petterson was born in Marback Parish, Smaland, August 18, 1851. He came to Chicago at an early age, and made his home on the North Side, which at that time was the center of Pastor Bjorck's activities. Petterson joined a mission group, and from that time until his death he was an enthusiastic supporter of Swedish-American missionary work. He became very active as one of the leaders within the Missionary Synod, and was one of the organizers of the later Mission League. During the following years he held important offices within the League, such as that of treasurer, an office which he held for several successive terms.</p>
   <p>His outstanding characteristics were straight-forwardness and a hearty kindliness. All who were associated with him liked him better the better they came to know him. He is mourned by his widow, three children, and a legion of friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
