<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-17">July 17, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Sweden and Swedish America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-17">July 17, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDEN AND SWEDISH AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Swedish-American Day at the Swedish World's Fair looked, in the morning, as though it would be a fiasco made by the heavy rain that fell. The decorations for the day were designed by and installed under the personal supervision of a member of the Chicago Swedish colony, Miss Lisa Johannson. The decorations were a work of real art.</p>
   <p>King Oscar of Sweden extended a hearty welcome to Swedish-Americans gathered, in which he compared the populations of Sweden and Swedish-America--Sweden has five millions, Swedish America two millions--these figures are not so large when we consider other countries, but if our people in all countries, as in America, accomplish the preservation of our Swedish culture and simultaneously forge ahead, reaching high places in their adopted country, it may <pb facs="5423404_5_0308.jpg" n="2"/>be truthfully said that "Unity makes for strength." To our esteemed Swedish-Americans go my wholehearted greetings. My fondest hope is that you will never forget or lose your love for your mother country, and that you may always use to advantage the culture of Sweden to the honor and glory of yourselves and us, in the old homeland.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. A. Enander of Chicago responded on behalf of the Swedish-American guests---.</p>
   <p>In spite of the fact that Dr. Enander was born and reared in Chicago and for the first time set foot on Swedish soil, he spoke literally perfect and fluent Swedish, for which he was cheered and complimented heartily. His expression of the American Swede's love for the mother country brought many tears to the eyes of our countrymen in the old homeland.</p>
   <p>"The greetings brought from Sweden to our countrymen here will beneficially strengthen the love crossing the seas in both directions to such an extent that we, of the press, especially of Chicago, hope it will not and cannot ever die."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
