<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-23">Oct. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Frank Gustafson Buys Fine Swedish Sculpture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-23">Oct. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">FRANK GUSTAFSON BUYS FINE SWEDISH SCULPTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As previously reported, an exhibit of Swedish art objects is now being held in the quarters occupied by the Swedish Art and Crafts Company on East Ohio Street. They have been brought here from Sweden by Tage Palm, head of the Firm.</p>
   <p>The exhibit contains some of the works of the celebrated Swedish sculptor, Carl Milles, and also Carl Eldh's remarkable bust of Crown Prince Gustaf Adolf of Sweden, the only one in existence besides the one owned by the crown prince himself. Those who know the reputation of Carl Eldh will have an idea of the value of this piece of art.</p>
   <p>The exhibit has attracted much attention, and one of its most faithful visitors has been our well-known countryman, Frank Gustafson, who, by the way, is somewhat of an amateur sculptor himself. The management was glad to notice his interest, but did not suspect that he had fallen completely for the <pb facs="5423404_5_0416.jpg" n="2"/>exhibit's outstanding piece, the excellent portrait bust of the Swedish crown prince. He did not seem to be able to tear himself away from it. Last Saturday he asked, in passing, how much the piece might be worth, and was told that there was not much chance that it would ever be sold, but a certain sum, a small fortune, was mentioned which would buy it.</p>
   <p>It seems that Gustafson had made up his mind beforehand, for he asked for a fountain pen and wrote out a check for the amount on the spot, and the sculpture was his; but it will remain in the exhibit until it closes.</p>
   <p>Gustafson has later revealed that he is planning to present the bust to the Chicago Art Institute, to be incorporated in its great collections, so that as many people as possible may have an opportunity to view this outstanding example of Swedish sculptural art.</p>
   <p>If he did not already have it in full measure, Gustafson has earned the esteem of his countrymen, and of all citizens of Chicago, for his public-spirited <pb facs="5423404_5_0417.jpg" n="3"/>action, and the more so, because he acted without pressure from any quarter. For that matter, this is not the first time he has quietly demonstrated his generosity. He dislikes all publicity concerning his donations. A few years ago, he donated five thousand dollars to the Swedish Tuberculosis Sanitarium in Denver, Colorado, and, a little later, a similiar sum to the Swedish Home for the Aged in Evanston. All he asks in return for his contributions to such deserving causes is that no fuss be made about it. But in this case the popular building firm owner can not escape a certain amount of publicity. [Translator's note: This article is accompanied by a half-tone, one column, fifth of a page, picture of Frank Gustafson].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
