<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1933-01-25">Jan. 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. David Nyvall Is Seventy Years Old</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. David Nyvall]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1933-01-25">Jan. 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">DR. DAVID NYVALL IS SEVENTY YEARS OLD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. David Nyvall]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A festive birthday party took place last Saturday evening in the North Park Mission Church. The guest of honor was the noted educator, lecturer, and author, Dr. David Nyvall, rector emeritus of the North Park College, who has now reached the age of seventy.</p>
   <p>We have not received a detailed report on what took place at this party, but we take it for granted that high tribute was paid Dr. Nyvall for the important role which he has played in the activities and progress of the Swedish Mission League of America.</p>
   <p>Nyvall was born in Karlskoga, Sweden, January 19, 1863. His father was the noted mission preacher, Carl Johan Nyvall, who was one of the pioneers of the <pb facs="5423404_5_0386.jpg" n="2"/>mission movement in Sweden. Young Nyvall received a good education. He attended school in Vasteras and Gavle, and after having graduated from college he entered the University of Uppsala, where he studied medicine for two years. Later he went to the Karolinian Institute of Stockholm where he studied for one year, until 1886 when he sailed for America.</p>
   <p>We cannot in a brief article give a detailed account of all the activities in which he has been engaged since he came to this country. In 1887 he worked as a private teacher in Minneapolis, Minnesota, and later he became a pastor of the mission congregation of Sioux City, Iowa. Still later we find him as associate professor in the Swedish department of the Chicago Theological Seminary. He left that position to become director of a Bible institute, which the mission people opened in Minneapolis.</p>
   <p>In 1894 he was appointed rector of the then newly established North Park <pb facs="5423404_5_0387.jpg" n="3"/>College here in Chicago, and with the exception of the period 1905-1912, when he headed the Waldon College of McPherson, Kansas, he remained with the Chicago school until his retirement.</p>
   <p>Dr. Nyvall has written several books and also contributed numerous articles to newspapers and periodicals. He has also been much in demand as a speaker, and whether expressed in speech or in writing his thoughts are based on thorough study and a deeply religious attitude toward life. He is still active both as a teacher and as an author, and we join his many friends in hoping that he will remain so for many years to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
