<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-07-15">July 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">E. C. Westman Is Dead</title><title level="a" type="sub">Founder of the John Ericsson League</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Edward C. Westman]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-07-15">July 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">E. C. WESTMAN IS DEAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">Founder of the John Ericsson League</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Edward C. Westman]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday, Edward C. Westman died in his home at 1547 Chase Avenue. He was sixty-nine years old.</p>
   <p>Chicago has lost one of its best-known and most highly esteemed Swedish-Americans with the passing of Westman. For many years he was the director of Blomgren Brothers electrotyping plant, which under his able management became a large and prosperous establishment. He was also interested in several other business ventures.</p>
   <p>With his passing the Republican John Ericsson League of Illinois also loses one of its leading men and most faithful supporters. He was really the <pb facs="5423404_5_0401.jpg" n="2"/>founder of the Swedish-American Republican League of Illinois, which was the forerunner of the John Ericsson League of Illinois and of other states, as well as of the National Ericsson League. He took a deep interest in these organizations and served them in various capacities.</p>
   <p>Edward C. Westman was born in Princeton, Illinois, October 11, 1861. His father was a native of Vastergotland, Sweden, and came to America in 1850. But even though he was born in this country, Westman was genuinely Swedish by nature and an enthusiastic supporter of everything that would promote the cause of his countrymen here. His political activities were based on this interest in Swedish-American affairs, and his efforts bore rich fruit.</p>
   <p>Personally Westman was kind of heart and a faithful friend who will be missed by many. He is survived by his wife, the former Elizabeth Linnarson, and two daughters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
