<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-04">Sept. 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[Miss Bergh Makes a Study of Chicago Charities]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-04">Sept. 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[MISS BERGH MAKES A STUDY OF CHICAGO CHARITIES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Martha Bergh, a member of the Chicago Swedish Colony, has dedicated her life to practical welfare work; she has made a deep study of the methods of most of our Chicago organizations. She has made her home at the Y.W.C.A. while making her study of the Bureau of Charities, the Relief and Aid Society, and other affiliates. Her idea is to put their methods into operation in her birthplace, Stockholm, Sweden, and if possible throughout her mother country.</p>
   <p>Miss Bergh is a member of the Sophia Hjelp-Forening (Sophia Aid Society) of Chicago, of which Queen Sophia of Sweden and Mrs. Theodore Roosevelt are honorary members; she is also a member of the Chicago Swedish National League, the Y.W.C.A., and the Chicago Lutheran Women's League.</p>
   <p>"There need be no fault with, or objection to an interest and effort put forth by an individual in several welfare organizations," said Miss Bergh. "Approximately twenty-five thousand Lutheran Deaconesses are connected with the inner, or home, mission of their native country, and with the foreign <pb facs="5423404_5_0305.jpg" n="2"/>missionary activity of their church, as well. America has much for which to thank Europe in respect to foreign mission methods, but American methods and ideals today surpass those of Europe. I know of no welfare work so far-reaching in Sweden as I have found in America. What the needy in Sweden require is prompt aid. In America, aid can be administered within an hour in urgent circumstances; in Sweden, the system does not permit this. In Chicago one may obtain aid wherever he applies for it, while in Sweden he must apply to his own organization. In Chicago, race, color, or station in life does not prevent one from receiving necessary aid; while in Sweden, he must prove citizenship.</p>
   <p>"In Sweden we are swamped with lectures on welfare but no good seems to follow, no improvement. Something more strenuous must be done to bring about changes for more efficient welfare work."</p>
   <p>From the time Miss Bergh received her inheritance from Sweden, she has given <pb facs="5423404_5_0306.jpg" n="3"/>her undivided attention to the methods of the Chicago welfare branches. The book she published on this subject has been highly praised by Queen Sophia and many other prominent Swedes. The book bears the title Allas Ret och Allas Skyldighet (The Rights of All and the Responsibility of All).</p>
   <p>Miss Bergh ignores the European objections to the activities of women in public welfare work, and expects plenty of opposition to start with; but the more barricades she overthrows, the greater will be her achievements. Her program is so sensible and convincing that we wish her every success in Sweden.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
