<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-05-17">May 17, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Max Hjortsberg. His Sudden Death Last Night</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0833</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0833.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-05-17">May 17, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">MAX HJORTSBERG. HIS SUDDEN DEATH LAST NIGHT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Max Hjortsberg, who was supposed to be on the sure road to certain recovery from the serious injuries received at Kensington on March 27, 1880, died last night very suddenly at his residence, 387 North LaSalle Street.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hjortsberg was born in Stockholm, Sweden, November 8, 1826, and was therefore, at the time of his death, nearly 54 years of age. He studied civil engineering when quite young, and at the early age of nineteen went to England where he was given charge of the construction of the docks at Hull a work of great importance both from a commercial and engineering point of view.</p>
   <p>In 1852 he came to this country and engaged in railroad building in southern Indiana and Missouri,</p>
   <p>He reached Chicago in 1854 and in the year following became Chief Engineer of the Chicago, Burlington, and Quincy Railroad, a position which he filled, with credit to himself and satisfaction to the Company which employed him, <pb facs="5423404_5_0834.jpg" n="2"/>until about a year ago. During this period of twenty-five years he did all the important engineering work of the road in Illinois, including the building of the massive structure which spans the Mississippi at Burlington and joins the two great states of Illinois and Iowa. Lately, as is well-known, he became the constructing engineer and architect of the new Pullman-Car Works in Kensington, the scene of the accident which in the end proved fatal.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hjortsberg was also a member of the Lincoln Park Board of Commissioners, the Historical Society, the Engineers' Club of the Northwest, and the British Society of Civil Engineers. He was a man of wide culture and prominent standing in the profession which he had so successfully followed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hjortsberg was twice married, his first wife being a daughter of Mr. N. W. Lester of this city, by whom he had no children. In 1869 he married Mrs. Hubbard, a daughter of Col. C. G. Hammond...</p>
   <p>Mr. Hjortsberg, though a member of the Congregational Church, always retained his connection with the Lutheran Church of his earlier years. The time of the funeral will be announced today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
