<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-05-04">May 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Leader within the Co-operative Movement</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, Full Face Picture of N. A. Hawkenson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-05-04">May 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Leader within the Co-operative Movement</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, Full Face Picture of N. A. Hawkenson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The co-operative idea has won many followers in this country during the last few years, and the movement has became more widespread than one dared hope a few years ago.</p>
   <p>It was not until the year 1909 that any serious attempt was made to interest the great public in co-operative enterprises, and to convince consumers of the advantages offered by such undertakings. Some of the early champions of this cause are still up in front, and the fact that the Co-operative Society of America now has 85,000 members and is operating 185 stores in and around Chicago is an indication of the rapid growth of the movement. The Society owns the People's Life Building in the Loop, which is valued at one million dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0609.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A Swedish-American, N. A. Hawkenson, is one of the leaders in the Co-operative Society of America, and at this writing he is in Europe for the purpose of studying co-operative methods as practiced in some of the countries there.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hawkenson came to America at the age of sixteen and went directly to Chicago. He was born in the city of Ystad, Sweden, and learned the machinist's trade there. After having attended the Armour Institute and the Worthington School of Engineering in this city he obtained employment with the S. Wilks Company here, and remained with it for thirty-one years.</p>
   <p>Besides being an able engineer he was also gifted as an inventor. He was frequently promoted until after sixteen years of service with the Company, he became its general manager. When he finally gave up this position to devote himself to other activities he was presented with an expensive watch in recognition of his valuable services to the organization. In this connection it is interesting to note that during the time he served as manager there was no labor trouble whatsoever.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0610.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Having been interested in the co-operative movement ever since he was a young man, Mr. Hawkenson resigned from his position with the Wilks Company in order to devote all his time to the activities of the Co-operative Society of America, of which he is a trustee. Among his closest co-workers are Harrison M. Parker and John Coe, but Hawkenson himself is credited with the organization's rapid growth during the last couple of years.</p>
   <p>He is a valued member of several Swedish lodges and societies, and an officer in some of them. Thus, he served first as vice-president and later as president of Svithiod Lodge No. 1 of the Independent Order of Svithiod. For a number of years he was the secretary of the Swedish Old People's Home Society.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hawkenson married twenty-eight years ago, and has eight children. His three oldest boys graduated from the Lane Technical High School, and were in the Government service during the World War. One of them is now attending the Naval Academy at Annapolis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
