<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-22">May 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Alfred Nobel; from a Speech by L.G. Abrahams On, D.D., Rn.O. Given at the Union League Club Banquet in Honor of Dr. Hjalmar,Ph.D.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-22">May 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">ALFRED NOBEL; FROM A SPEECH BY L.G. ABRAHAMS ON, D.D., RN.O. GIVEN AT THE UNION LEAGUE CLUB BANQUET IN HONOR OF DR. HJALMAR,PH.D.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11............Sweden is still one of the great powers, even if her statesmen do not, now, as in the past, lead the development of European politics. In that country there has never been a dearth of men who were leaders in things spiritual. In the great intellectual "contests," which have characterized our time, the country men of Polhem, Linne', Berzelius, and Tegner have often come off with laurel-crowns.</p>
   <p>Even though the Swedish people is not a mercenary people, even though the Swedish genius is of a deep going, meditative nature which only in high, idealistic endeavors can find an outlet for the powers within, and even though the material is not the end, but only the means, still it has more than once been demonstrated <pb facs="5423404_5_0361.jpg" n="2"/>what Swedish enterprise, business genius, and superior spiritual endowments could achieve. But when an Alfred Nobel, noble not only in honored name, but by precedence, when judged by personal qualities, was fortunate enough to pile millions upon millions and win for himself a dominating position in the world of affairs, still for him the ideal was not to be pushed aside for the material. Nobel rests in hallowed ground, and his memory is associated with spiritual endeavors, which forever will make the Malar-City one of the centers of intellectual accomplishments. Nobel was a prosperous business man, a prince of the money-world, but he retained also his high idealistic purposes. In regard to culture, talent and taste he was a literary man. For literature he also offered the proceeds of his prosperous life's work. Probably no one in any age has done so much to promote literature as Nobel. For literary achievement the Nobel Institute is a powerdul impulse. There are those, to be sure, who believe that Nobel was too cosmospolitan, and too little Swedish in founding his institution, but we are not here to pass judgment on that question; however, we should remember that true culture must be essentially cosmopolitan and literary culture study is no exception. In literature more than in anything else is mirrored the bright and dark sides of a people, its individuality and its spiritual <pb facs="5423404_5_0362.jpg" n="3"/>struggles. Literature depicts a people's way of thinking, and its cultural level. The Nobel Institute will be therefore, not only a center of union for the spiritually great of all nations; it will not only act as stimulus for literary endeavors in all countries, but also draw nations closer together. And what we value more highly, is that Sweden will be, through the Nobel Institute a world literary center.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
