<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-20">Feb. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Olof A. Toffteen, Noted Educator, Is Dead</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Olof A. Toffteen]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-20">Feb. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DR. OLOF A. TOFFTEEN, NOTED EDUCATOR, IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Olof A. Toffteen]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known educator and lecturer, Dr. Olof A. Toffteen, who has been active in Swedish-American circles for a long period of time, passed away last Thursday, February 14. The cause of death was a heart disorder, which has been troubling him for the last couple of years. Some time ago, he was forced to take an extended rest in bed, and even though he recuperated and resumed some of his activities, it was evident that he was a weakened man, and his end was not entirely unexpected.</p>
   <p>Toffteen was born in Haxarfue, on the island of Gotland, Sweden, June 26, 1863, and was thus in his sixty-sixth year at the time of his death. He attended the public school near his home, and then went to the college in Visby, from which he graduated in 1885. Later, he entered the University of Uppsala, where, <pb facs="5423404_5_0438.jpg" n="2"/>after an unusually short time, he obtained the candidate's degree in philology, and then began to study for a doctors' degree, specializing in philosophy, history, and classical languages. But this required money, of which Toffteen did not have much, and after some time he was forced to leave the university and returned to Gotland, where he became a pastor's assistant. Some time later, in 1888, we find him in America, and it seems that he planned a career in the church. He attended the Augustana Seminary in Rock Island for some time, and then went to Minneapolis, where he became the pastor of an Episcopalian congregation. During this time, he also published two books, The Church of Our Fathers and Myths and the Bible.</p>
   <p>In 1902, Toffteen moved to Chicago, and by that time he had abandoned his plans of making the ministry his life work. He entered the University of Chicago, and resumed his studies in Semitic languages. He obtained his doctor's degree in 1905, and was then made a professor of Semitic languages at the university. He was also appointed to a similar post at the Western Theological Seminary. During the following years, Dr. Toffteen occupied a prominent place among <pb facs="5423404_5_0439.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago's linguistic scientists, and was noted as one of the founders of the Oriental Society here. Later, he established a school of his own, the Scandia Academy, and continued his educational activities until some time during the World War. After the armistice, he went to Europe, but returned to Chicago within about one year. From then on, he devoted most of his time to linguistic research and to writing on scientific subjects. At the same time, he headed the so-called Academic Congregation, before whom he lectured every Sunday morning.</p>
   <p>Dr. Toffteen was particularly interested in problems concerning the origin of the Germanic race, and submitted certain theories of his own, which, even though they have not been generally accepted, may some time prove to have merit. He took a deep interest in a variety of subjects, and of him it may truly be said that nothing human was insignificant to him.</p>
   <p>His wife died some time ago, and he is survived by cousins here and by a sister who is living in Sweden. Interment took place in Rosehill Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
