<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-07-15">July 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Andrew Lanquist Passes Away</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-Known Builder</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Andrew Lanquist].

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-07-15">July 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ANDREW LANQUIST PASSES AWAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-Known Builder</title> [Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Andrew Lanquist].
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Andrew Lanquist, well-known within Chicago's building industry, and for many years head of the building construction firm of Lanquist &amp; Illsley, died last Friday in his home, 4636 Beacon Street, after a long illness.</p>
   <p>Lanquist was born in Wing, Vastergotland, Sweden, November 26, 1856, and came to America and to Chicago in 1881. This city was his home from then until the time of his death. He had learned the bricklayer's trade at home, and began working at it here. As so many other newcomers he went through some difficult times to start with. But after some time his employers realized that he was an able and trustworthy fellow, and he was made a foreman. A couple of years later he went into business for himself. In 1904 he became president of the firm of Lanquist &amp; Illsley, which during the following years erected many large buildings, among them the Wrigley Building and the <pb facs="5423404_5_0398.jpg" n="2"/>structure housing the State Bank of Chicago.</p>
   <p>As a builder Lanquist enjoyed a fine reputation both among the public and among his colleagues. For a number of years he served as president of the National Association of Building Trade Employers and of the Builders' Association of Chicago. He also headed the Associated Builders of Chicago and founded the Builders' Mutual Casualty Company. He belonged to the Swedish Club, the Union League Club, and several other organizations.</p>
   <p>For almost fifty years Lanquist was a member of the Immanuel Swedish Lutheran Church. On several occasions he demonstrated his generosity when a good cause needed money as, for instance, when he donated a considerable sum to the fund for the John Ericsson monument in Washington, D. C. He was among the leaders in the fund-raising campaign here in Chicago. He also donated ten thousand dollars to the John Morton Building in Philadelphia, and last winter he gave one thousand dollars to the Swedish-American Relief Committee for the benefit of Swedish unemployed here. Few people knew that he also donated a large sum <pb facs="5423404_5_0399.jpg" n="3"/>of money to the Swedish Home for the Aged in Evanston every year.</p>
   <p>Lanquist was a widower since 1914, and is survived by two married daughters and a sister. The interment took place in Rosehill Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
