<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-09-02">Sept. 2, 1909</date><title level="a">Birthday Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0710</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0710.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-09-02">Sept. 2, 1909</date><title level="a">BIRTHDAY FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday, Carl Simon Peterson, director of the Peterson Linotype Co., celebrated his birthday in a big way. He invited one hundred and fifty of his acquaintances, among them the members of the Swedish Glee Club, whose president he is, and the result was a splendid celebration. County Commissioner Chindblomn was the presiding officer. He introduced a dozen speakers and singers, among whom were State geologist C. H. Crantz; F. A. Linstrand; Alexander Johnson, publisher of Kuriren; A. P. Johnson, of the Record Herald's typograph organization No. 16; S. Harding, and the humorists Wenship and Crebs.</p>
   <p>Director Peterson thanked the speaker and invited his guests to enjoy the celebration. William Dahlen sang "Du Gamla, du Fria" (You're old, you're free), and Professor Ortengren sang one of his own compositions <pb facs="5423404_5_0711.jpg" n="2"/>about Charlie Peterson. Gustave Holmquist sang a solo. Sigurd Meck and Professor Balatka furnished the music.</p>
   <p>Carl Simon Peterson was born in Daglosen, Varmland on Aug. 29, 1873. He left the land of his fathers at the age of fourteen to come to America. At first, in 1888, he worked as a typesetter in Colorado, California, and the Sandwich Islands. In 1895 he came to Chicago and found employment as linotype operator in the Amerikanaren, where he worked until 1899, when he organized the Peterson Linotype Co., now one of the largest in Chicago as well as in the United States.</p>
   <p>In 1901 Peterson married Miss Thyra Hjertquist, daughter of Gabriel Hjertquist, managing editor of the Amerikanaren. Director Peterson is very young, only 36 years old, yet he has untiring energy, a <pb facs="5423404_5_0712.jpg" n="3"/>characteristic of Varmland's sons. He has made a name for himself already, and were he to wish it, he could now rest on his laurels, but Carl Simon is not of this caliber and has never been lazy. His ability will not sleep; it cannot lay idle, and Peterson is the same crafty representative now as before. Success has not gone to his head; he is the same quiet-spoken and steadfast friend that he was when he was the hard wage-earner at his craft. He is one of the craft's quiet men, one of those earnest souls who cannot be upset; he is a calm understanding progressive Swede, A long and successful life is wished him.</p>
   <p>Another one of the Swedish Glee Club's members, S. A. Swanson, celebrated his 54th Birthday the same day. He and his wife were Peterson's honored guests Saturday evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
