<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-10-10">Oct. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Man of the People Passes Away</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0647</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0647.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-10-10">Oct. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A MAN OF THE PEOPLE PASSES AWAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A leader from the transition period, also one of the oldest countrymen here, in respect to age as well as activity, was Charles Eklund, Cigar Manufacturer, who passed away Sunday at the Bethany Home, where he resided during his later years. He reached the ripe age of eighty-eight years. More remarkable is it that he retained the ideals of his youth, which perhaps, in this case, were the life sustaining elements.</p>
   <p>Carl Alfred Bengt Eklund, known here as Charles Eklund, was born in Stockholm, November 4, 1830. He learned the cigar making trade, and received his master's certificate in 1848. He arrived in America in 1865. After having spent a year in New York, he came to Chicago and settled like a "fire-brand." At the time of his entrance into the "Swedish World" in Chicago, when he soon was to play such an important role, he was 35 years old. Regarding his activities from that time up to the seventies, the late writer and author, C. F. Peterson, <pb facs="5423404_5_0648.jpg" n="2"/>who knew him well, has the following to say, in a biographic sketch in Valkyrian 1899.</p>
   <p>"During his first twenty years, not one Swedish political meeting, society meeting, picnic, or general gathering took place where he was not present with his glowing eloquence and harangue to arouse our countrymen out of their lethargy. He was all alone in the front of everything."</p>
   <p>The same writer further says: "Eklund's favorite working field was the "Labor-movement,' where he, in many respects, was way ahead of his time. It can be truly said that for twenty years he lived more for the common welfare among the Swedes than for his own. Many initiatives sprang out of his fertile brain in the form of Sick and Funeral Societies, Charitable Institutions, Immigrant Homes, Clubs and Committees. When the great famine struck Norrland, Sweden, he was one of those who worked hardest for a "fair," which netted ten thousand dollars for the benefit of the hungry in the Homeland. During all this time, he has worked at his trade, being content with <pb facs="5423404_5_0649.jpg" n="3"/>little, and never in danger of getting too much. He has now withdrawn from the front lines of the daily strife, which he is still watching with an open eye, in order to rejoice, when labor triumphs."</p>
   <p>This was written in 1899, and ever since from the same position, with a look not dimmed by the shadow of old age, has he viewed the ideas, for which he fought so vigorously in his youth, grow and bear fruit.</p>
   <p>Charles Eklund never grew old in soul or mind, regardless how many years were added to his span of life. He was true to his colors, washproof unto death.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
