<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-03-02">Mar. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Notable Swedish Artist</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0723</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0723.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-03-02">Mar. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A NOTABLE SWEDISH ARTIST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Swedish-American painting has several notable representatives in Chicago and among them is Charles E. Hallberg of 1013 North Park Avenue. Within art circles he has been holding the limelight since, a short time ago, one of his finest paintings, "The Atlantic," was procured by the Goeteborg Art Museum, Goeteborg, Sweden, which is known for its high standards, and the critical care with which it adds to its collections. As the name implies the painting has a marine motif, depicting the magnificent ocean in natural color nuances, with a sunbathed sky, drifting clouds, and majestic, white-topped waves. Nature's awe-inspiring beauty as seen by the loving eyes, and felt by the receptive mind, of a worshiping artist, has been masterfully reproduced. For a long time the ocean was Hallberg's home, and he has loved it ever since.</p>
   <p>Born in Goeteborg in 1855 into a poor home, he went to sea at an early age. The inborn artistic instinct which had been awakened within the boy during visits to the art treasures in the galleries of his home city,blossomed out <pb facs="5423404_5_0724.jpg" n="2"/>in the young mariner under the stimulus of sunsets on the ocean and other beauty impressions which flooded his impressionable mind during his travels on the seven seas.</p>
   <p>About twenty years ago he left the sea and came to Chicago where he obtained employment as a watchman in a bank. He fitted out a studio in the basement and began seriously to devote all his spare time to painting.</p>
   <p>Almost without any formal instruction, and under economic difficulties, he progressed, thanks to his iron will and artistic ambition, and was finally rewarded when two of his paintings were accepted by the Chicago Art Institute. Last year he exhibited several paintings at the Art Institute, including "The Atlantic" which attracted unusual attention and was valued at $800. Among his other outstanding works are "Sunrise" and "After the Storm", both with motifs from Lake Michigan, and characterized by the very individualistic conception of nature, and the remarkable choice of colors which are so typical of Hallberg.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0725.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After years of hard work and sacrifices he has now definitely "arrived": he is a member of the Chicago Society of Artists, and his name is known and respected among artists as well as among the general public.</p>
   <p>His countrymen have reason to be proud of Hallberg, and everybody who knows the soft-spoken and unaffected artist is happy over his success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
