<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0579.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>tailor's apprentice at the age of twelve. Later, he moved to Stockholm, where he worked at his trade. In 1880, he married Maria Augusta Fagerberg, and in 1882 both of them joined the Carl Johan Good Templar lodge, so that at the time of his death he had been a Good Templar for more than forty years.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1887, the couple emigrated to America and settled in Chicago. Here he joined several Good Templar lodges; later, he became a member of the Illinois Swedes society, in which he remained until his death.</p>
   <p>He had already taken the World Grand Lodge degree in Stockholm, in 1885, as a member of the Stockholm Grand Lodge. He belonged to the Illinois Scandinavian Grand Lodge of the Independent Order of Good Templars from the time it was founded, and he was a delegate to all its conventions. He held important offices in that organization as well as in the Illinois Swedes.</p>
   <p>The Ronnholm home is at 814 Roscoe Street. He is mourned by his widow and <pb facs="5423404_5_0580.jpg" n="3"/>a great number of friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
