<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-07-12">July 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery: John William Johnson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-07-12">July 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY: JOHN WILLIAM JOHNSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vestergotland is truly a country of opposites: fertile soil and unproductive heath; majestic, beautiful scenery and dreary, lonely stretches. This also holds for the mental make-up of the people who live there. In the South they are impulsive, lively and energetic; in the north more quiet, thoughtful and reserved; in the northernmost part of the province the inhabitants are said to hear the marks of solid security, caused by the age-old prosperity enjoyed in this section.</p>
   <p>John William Johnson is typical of the district in Vestergotland from which he hails, energetic and full of life. No wonder, therefore, that he has been successful here in this blessed country. He was born June 24, 1844, on a farm which was part of the Kallebacka estate, half a mile south of Bogesund, one of Sweden's oldest cities. His early life was rather hard. Already at the age of ten he had to go out in the woods, cut down trees, and pull them home <pb facs="5423404_5_0772.jpg" n="2"/>on a sled for firewood. But that kind of work builds hard muscles and a strong back, and in later years, he never regretted doing it.</p>
   <p>He worked at home and on other farms until 1868, and was then the happy owner of two hundred crowns and three fine new suits of clothing, and decided to try his luck in the promised land far to the west. The crossing, even by steamboat, took nineteen days at that time; he arrived in Chicago in the summer of 1868.</p>
   <p>His first job was as a farmhand in De Kalb County, but during the winter he worked in an Indiana lumber camp. Later on we find him as a stonecutter at Lemont, and as a railroad worker on the road which was being built between St. Joe and Buffalo.</p>
   <p>The strong youngster from Vestergotland was not afraid of hard work of any kind. He went in for stone masonry, which is harder work and requires more dexterity than brick laying.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0773.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By 1873 he had been working with stone and brick so long that he really understood these materials and their uses, and he decided to strike out for himself as a contractor. As such he has mostly handled street and sidewalk work, and one might say that he has specialized in curbstone-setting.</p>
   <p>The biggest job Mr. Johnson ever had was the stone work connected with the elevation of the Chicago and Northwestern Railroad; at that time he employed 175 men. In this connection we want to point out a particularly laudable trait in his character, namely, his just and considerate treatment of those who work for him. We know persons who have been in his employ for twenty-five years, and none of them have anything but praise for him.</p>
   <p>It is very interesting to talk to such an old settler as Mr. Johnson. During the thirty-six years he has been living in Chicago he has known personally all the more prominent Swedes here, and most of them were his friends.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0774.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Many are the struggling countrymen to whom he has given a helping hand, and quite a few he has actually set up in business.</p>
   <p>In 1875 Johnson married Miss Mathilda Peterson, by whom he has four children, three daughters and a son. The comfortable and well-furnished family home is at 5607 Indiana Avenue, and he also owns considerable other property. His offices are in Suite 918, 184 La Salle Street.</p>
   <p>Being of a very sociable nature, Mr. Johnson has been active as a Freemason, and holds the thirty-second degree within that order; he also belongs to the Knights Templar, Eastern Star, Mystic Shrine, and Scottish Rite; in addition, he is a member of the John Ericsson lodge of Odd Fellows, the society Svea, and the Chicago Masons and Builders' Association.</p>
   <p>Personally Mr. Johnson is jolly and good-natured; as a businessman, honest and alert; as a friend, helpful and faithful; all in all, a Swede to be proud of, and a credit to his fatherland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
