<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-11-08">Nov. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">American Child Sacrifices</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-11-08">Nov. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN CHILD SACRIFICES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anglo-Americans often complain about foreigners coming to this country and taking the bread out of their mouths. We have sought and, we believe, found some of the reasons why the native born worker often must move aside for his European competitor, who as a rule is more apt at his trade than his American brother.</p>
   <p>But our observations indicate that it is not only the workers who are born, educated, and trained for their trade in Europe, who often take the best jobs in American industry, but also their children, who are born in Europe and immigrate with them at an early age, before their struggle for existence has yet begun. This phenomenon also has its logical explanation, and official statistics concerning children employed in industry are enlightening in this respect.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0117.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These statistics show that fifty-four per cent of all boys under fifteen years of age employed in industrial establishments, are the sons of native born parents whose American ancestors have lived here for generations; fifteen per cent are American born, but their parents came from a foreign country, and four per cent are foreign born children who immigrated to America with their parents; twenty-six per cent are Negroes.</p>
   <p>The "practical" American who considers money all-important does not feel that he can afford to let his sons go to school and absorb knowledge until they are physically and mentally equipped to go out and earn their livelihood. While they are still in breeches their unwise parents send them into the factories, business houses, and mines to earn a little money. They have no time to learn a trade thoroughly. The apprenticeship is too long and the pay is too small. Therefore, they step right into any job they can get and toil hard until they reach the age at which they should really begin to work, but by that time they are almost played out.</p>
   <p>It is easy to see that these men who never had a chance to be real boys, play <pb facs="5423404_5_0118.jpg" n="3"/>and "raise the dickens" as boys should cannot have the energy, endurance, and interest in their work as their fellow-workers who have lived a normal boyhood, and then learned a trade which they have come to like and take pride in.</p>
   <p>The records actually tell us that if we go into a factory or mine and gather around us one hundred boys under fifteen years of age, we will find that more than half of them are the sons of Anglo-Americans.</p>
   <p>The less "practical" European-American also appreciates the monetary value of shamelessly exploiting child power in industry, but takes advantage of it to a much smaller extent. Of the one hundred boys, only fifteen can boast of having been born in this country of foreign-born parents.</p>
   <p>Finally, we come to the Europeans who, with their children, have immigrated to America, and who in the eyes of most Anglo-Americans are not "smart" at all. These foreigners have brought with them a sounder outlook in regard to the employment of children in industry. They do not believe that the individual or <pb facs="5423404_5_0119.jpg" n="4"/>society gains anything by taking the child out of school too early, and depriving it of the enjoyment of normal childhood, which is its birthright. They do not believe in driving a child out into the bitter fight for existence, where one needs strong muscles and an adult brain in order to win. That is why we find among our one hundred boys only four who have seen the Swedish fir forests, the Norwegian mountains, the English meadows, or the vineyards of Germany and Italy. These Europeans have learned to work for their children until the child is old enough and sufficiently equipped to strike out for themselves. In most cases this is the only inheritance they leave their offspring, and it is far more valuable than a few dollars and broken down health caused by overwork in childhood.</p>
   <p>If the Anglo-American wants to complain, he should complain about his own shortsightedness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
