<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-03">Aug. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration and an Unauthorized Announcement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-03">Aug. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION AND AN UNAUTHORIZED ANNOUNCEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to reports in Swedish newspapers which we have just received, emigration from Sweden increased considerably during the second quarter of this year as compared to the corresponding period of last year; but at the same time it is pointed out that the number of people who left the country last year was exceptionally low.</p>
   <p>Between April 1 and June 30, 5,247 persons left Sweden for other parts of the world by way of Stockholm, Malmo, Helsingborg, and Goeteborg, while during the first half of the year, 7,960 persons left the country through the above-mentioned ports, and 1,159 left by way of the Norwegian ports, Trondhjem and Christiana [Oslo]. Of these 9,119 immigrants, 6,315 were men and 2,804 women. Of the Swedish provinces, Vermland was represented by the greatest number, 807; Kalmar was second with 714. The city of Stockholm contributed 351.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0081.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In connection with this bit of statistics the Swedish papers are making much out of a purported announcement of increased control of immigration, published by the Immigration Commission of New York, and reported by the Swedish consulate of that city. The announcement states that in spite of the fact that no minimum amount of money which the immigrant must have in order to be admitted to the United States has been determined by law, it is nevertheless highly desirable that he have in his possession at least twenty-five dollars over and above the price of the railroad ticket to his destination, and even that is not any too much. In addition, the immigrant is required to be able to prove that he is not going to need private or public charity. In connection with this latter clause, the announcement makes it clear that certain types of assistance, which the immigrant may receive on his arrival here, will not be held against him when the decision is made in regard to his admission to the country.</p>
   <p>We have been informed from official sources that this announcement was both premature and unfortunate, inasmuch as it may so easily be misunderstood.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0082.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Congressman [A. J.] Sabath of Chicago, who often has gone to the front in Washington in behalf of the immigrants, has investigated the matter, and authorities in the capital have informed him that the announcement in question has no basis in law; in fact it is contrary to laws and regulations now in effect. It should, therefore, not be used as a deterrent by those interests in Sweden, which by all means wish to prevent emigration from that country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
