<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-12-17">Dec. 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">G. Bernhard Anderson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_5_0735</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0735.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-12-17">Dec. 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">G. BERNHARD ANDERSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among our readers, there are few who do not recognize the name G. Bernhard Anderson. In Chicago, he is personally acquainted with many of his compatriots, because he has been associated with many of them. He is a splendid speaker and is well received at various gatherings. It must be said that he has always represented himself and his nationality honorably.</p>
   <p>As a lawyer, he has won for himself an enviable reputation. He has handled large volumes of very difficult cases. The law firm, of which he is the head, has been judged as one of the best of its class, a distinction which it deserves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_5_0736.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was born in Jonkoping, Sweden in 1867. Since he was two years old, he has lived in Chicago. He attended the public schools here, then he went to Augustana College. He graduated in 1888 as valedictorian of his class. He went to Salt Lake City as a teacher, but after two years, he went to Harvard University, where, in 1891, he won an honorary degree. He then studied at Uppsala University for one year, returning to Chicago to practise law. In 1896, he took the bar examinations and received his degree. Besides his practise, he has been a teacher in the Chicago Law School. For his splendid work there, he was given the degree of L. L. D. As we mentioned in another section of this issue, beginning with our next number, he becomes an associate worker with the Svenska Amerikanaren. He has kindly consented to answer questions pertaining to law for our paper and readers, as he has done previously. We welcome him in our circle as we believe our readers <pb facs="5423404_5_0737.jpg" n="3"/>will be pleased to know that we are reviving this column in the Swedish Amerikanaren. The section of the paper where this article appears will be set aside for your questions, and we sincerely invite you to send your questions to the Law Editor, Svenska Amerikanaren, 35 South Clark Street, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
