<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-20">Feb. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Aldermanic Election</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, pictures of C. Hjalmar Lundquist and Oscar F. Nelson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-20">Feb. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALDERMANIC ELECTION</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, pictures of C. Hjalmar Lundquist and Oscar F. Nelson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, February 26, aldermen for Chicago are to be elected, and among the candidates are a few of Swedish nationality.</p>
   <p>In the Fiftieth Ward, which includes the Edgewater and Summerdale districts, where so many Swedes have their homes, Attorney Carl Hjalmar Lundquist, former assistant corporation counsel of the city of Chicago, is a candidate. It should not be necessary to bother with a formal introduction of this countryman, since he has been active for many years now in Swedish organizations here, especially in the Swedish Singers League, and has always been much in demand as a speaker on festive occasions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lundquist was born in Bofors, Varmland, Sweden in 1883, and came to Chicago when he was three years old. He attended grade school here, and then returned to Sweden with the rest of the family. While there, he graduated from college in Orebro, and then returned to Chicago, where he worked on both American and Swedish-American newspapers, and also handled the foreign correspondance of some business firms here. Later, he graduated from law school with honors. During Mayor Dever's term, he served as assistant corporation counsel.</p>
   <p>We have received the following communication from the Lundquist for Alderman Non-Partisan Organization of the Fiftieth Ward:</p>
   <p>"Carl Hjalmar Lundquist, candidate for alderman, has during the last few weeks received assurances of the undivided support of his countrymen in the Fiftieth Ward at the election which is to take place February 26. Thousands of Swedish and other voters are lined up behind him, and to all appearances <pb facs="5423404_1_0893.jpg" n="3"/>he is assured of victory.</p>
   <p>"Lundquist is absolutely an independent, non-partisan candidate, and among the thousands who have endorsed his candidacy are many members of the Swedish-American Republican Club. But he has never been invited by this club to appear before it and state his policies, as has wrongly been reported in some newspapers.</p>
   <p>"Those Swedish-Americans who, during the last twenty-five years, have had occasion to hear him speak, in Swedish as well as in English, are convinced that in regard to general knowledge and training, as well as other qualifications, he is well ahead of his opponents, and that if he is elected to the City Council he will not only represent his ward in an excellent manner, but will also be a credit to his countrymen.</p>
   <p>"In 1927, when Lundquist was a candidate for this same office for the first <pb facs="5423404_1_0894.jpg" n="4"/>time, he received almost thirteen thousand votes, only a few hundred less than he needed to be elected. At the present time, he is undoubtedly the most popular of the candidates.</p>
   <p>"During the years 1923-1927, he was assistant corporation counsel of Chicago, in which capacity he handled many important law suits for the city. This, together with his experience as a newspaper man and as a trusted employee of such business firms as Sulzberger &amp; Sons and the Emerson-Brantingham Company, which he served as head of their foreign departments, fits him admirably for a seat in the City Council.</p>
   <p>"The Fiftieth Ward has never had a Swedish-born alderman, and it is high time that this situation be changed.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"The Lundquist for Alderman Non-Partisan</p>
   <p>Organization of the Fiftieth Ward.</p>
   <p>"(Signed) John A. Freedain, Secretary."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0895.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the Forty-sixth Ward, Oscar F. Nelson is a candidate for reelection, having already served for three terms. Nelson was born and raised in Chicago, and was in the postal service in his younger years. Later, we find him as a trade union leader and as head of the factory inspection department of the State of Illinois. During Harding's administration he served for some time as federal mediator in labor controversies. He is a lawyer by profession, and is considered a man of ability and good judgment.</p>
   <p>During the last few years, it has repeatedly been said of him that he has been acting as a spokesman for Mayor Thompson. Nelson has answered these accusations by stating that during Thompson's present term only one administration proposal has been up for consideration: The introduction of motor buses on the West Side, on which a ten-cent fare would be charged. Nelson voted against the proposal and supported another one, which would provide buses linked up with the streetcar system, and would maintain the seven-cent fare. In regard to Nelson's candidacy, the Swedish-American Non-Partisan League has <pb facs="5423404_1_0896.jpg" n="6"/>adopted the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Be it resolved, That we endorse the re-election of Alderman Oscar F. Nelson on account of his many fine accomplishments and the service which he has rendered to the people, not only of his own ward but of the entire city, during the past six years, and on account of his altogether fine record during this time.</p>
   <p>"Be it further resolved, That we as an organization shall use all honorable means to secure his re-election."</p>
   <p>Nelson belongs to the Lutheran church, and is a member of the following organizations: The Viking, Svithiod, and Vasa orders, the Scandinavian League, the Swedish Club, the Nordic Country Club, and the Svithiod Singing Club.</p>
   <p>Among the candidates for alderman in the Forty-sixth Ward we also note <pb facs="5423404_1_0897.jpg" n="7"/>Carl Emil Liedberg, president of the Swedish war veterans. His campaign slogan is, "Honesty, Law and Order". He belongs to the Svithiod Order, and lives at 1010 Oakdale Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
