<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-08-11">Aug. 11, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Sympathy Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-08-11">Aug. 11, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">SYMPATHY MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With reference to an appeal to the Swedish Americans from the Swedish Association of Workers in Iron and Metal, a mass meeting was held on Sunday August 2, at Mayer's Hall. The meeting was called by the lodge Ljusbringaren (The Bringer of Light) of the Temperance Order Verdandi. The discussion centered on the question, "What attitude ought the Swedish Americans take toward the conflict between employers and employees in the Swedish iron and metal industry?" A considerable number of Swedish-American workers in Chicago were present.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened with the singing of "Sons of Toil." Mr. C. E. Kronlof was elected chairman of the meeting, and Mr. M. J. Ring, secretary. The discussion was opened by Mr. W. Frankel (formerly a member of the Union of Swedish Iron and Metal Workers), who gave a full report on the origin of the conflict and its present status. This was followed by a discussion lasting for two hours and a half, in which twenty-one speakers participated. It <pb facs="5423404_1_0605.jpg" n="2"/>was unanimously resolved to extend the sympathy of the meeting to the comrades in Sweden who are fighting for their right to organize. A committee was appointed to undertake a systematic collection of money for the benefit of the 20,000 workers who are victims of the lockout in Sweden. The committee consists of Messrs. W. Frankel, Axel Warner, Gust Engstrom, A. Ljung, and F. Warner.</p>
   <p>Information concerning the lockout will be given with pleasure upon inquiry, and subscription lists may be had from Mr. W. Frankel, 342 N. Franklin Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>M. J. Ring, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
