<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Courier, Weekly)</title><date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21,1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Worst of Scandals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0786</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0786.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Courier, Weekly)</title><date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21,1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORST OF SCANDALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A terrible state of unemployment and great sufferings prevails in America and especially in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday the unemployed and hungry people held a meeting, with the intention, after the meeting to march through certain parts of the city in order to gain sympathy and understanding of their difficulties. Certain signs were held aloft, "Hunger" - "Give us today our daily bread" - "We want work, not alms." Certainly these signs were not calls to riot, nor could they be included under the convenient designation, disorderly conduct.</p>
   <p>Police officers were supervising the meeting. But the officers present were not <pb facs="5423404_1_0787.jpg" n="2"/>there in uniform. Following custom of Czarist Russia, police officers in disguise were moving among the people present. In Russia, that type watchers are called provocators.</p>
   <p>No revolutionary or dangerous demonstrations occurred at the meeting. But when after the meeting, those in attendance prepared to march through the streets in columns, they were met by men in civilian clothes, who, without displaying any emblems of authority, ordered the attendants of the meeting to disperse, and, when their orders were not at once obeyed, began assaulting the people with clubs.</p>
   <p>Unemployed, starving but peaceful people were asking for work, were asking for bread. In answer they received blows and shots, and some were thrown into jail.</p>
   <p>It is a scandal that so many people are hungry in a country where we have such surplus of food that we are sending millions of dollars worth of it every day to other countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0788.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But the worst scandal is that even today we deserve the upbraiding by the Master: "When they asked for bread, ye gave them stones."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
