<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-26">Dec. 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">What Does Swedish-Mindedness Mean?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-26">Dec. 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT DOES SWEDISH-MINDEDNESS MEAN?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Certainly, Swedish-mindedness does not consist in one sided criticism and deprecations at everything within our own borders.</p>
   <p>But no more is it a mark of Swedish-mindedness to have become so enamored with the glamor of past days that one be unable to discern the ways of glory of the future, remaining blind before the glaring unequalities in the social conditions of the present day, and untouched and indifferent in the face of weakness and faults in the Swedish national life. The true national love of a people on the one hand, respects similar emotion <pb facs="5423404_1_0313.jpg" n="2"/>in every other people, and, on the other hand, does not consider every Swede an enemy, who honestly confesses that a great deal in the old country is not "alright as it is" now, just as the real independent personality also respects the demand for liberty in others, and also, as it is no proof of high worth to be blind to one's own faults.</p>
   <p>True Swedish-mindedness comprises a strong faith in the forces inherent in the Swedish land and people, and in the possibility of further development of these forces; a readiness to sacrifice one's personal advantages and gains in the fight against narrow prejudices and frozen forms; an eagerness to work for the welfare of the homeland; an attitude which increases in vigor in proportion as more and more of the sons and daughters of the country are becoming strong and happy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
