<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-09-11">Sept. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">President McKinely Shot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-09-11">Sept. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT McKINELY SHOT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President has been shot! Can it be possible? No one wishes to believe this sad tiding. Who can work, who can remain in the office? The flag is at half mast. Under the leadership of President McKinley, the good times in the United States have been restored. The republic is prospering as never before.</p>
   <p>In world affairs the United States has never been held quite so high as at present, thanks to McKinley. In the world of trade, we are commanding respect. All through the land, happiness and contentment reigned supreme. And now from a clear sky, comes the terrible news that the President has been shot.</p>
   <p>The man who shot him is an anarchist. It is his own confession and statement, <pb facs="5423404_1_0875.jpg" n="2"/>which he has made coldly. What has he accomplished? Who can tell? The full truth may never be known.</p>
   <p>Certain newspapers have persisted in pointing to President McKinley as an imperialistic and tyrannic President, and a usurper of the rights of the people. It is possible that these newspapers have no conscience, and that they are jumblers, who are but trading their cheap stuff for the sake of self aggrandisment. It is they who have brought about the tragedy at Buffalo. It is high time that we, as a nation take adequate and certain steps to rid our land of the pack of anarchists which infests it.</p>
   <p>The anarchist is dangerous to our entire form of government, the officials <pb facs="5423404_1_0876.jpg" n="3"/>of which are all on their death list. The hidden sword and dagger cannot be tolerated. So say we who love our land, our government, and our President.</p>
   <p>Carl Swenson</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
