<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-26">May 26, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Water Cure for Minds at Riot</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-26">May 26, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">WATER CURE FOR MINDS AT RIOT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At all times, there have been rioting people, with minds that call for action first, and thought afterwards, and there will always be that kind of people. They may be found within any one of the various classes in society, and within any one of the various age groups. The damage a dozen or so of this type of people may cause in an hour may be such as cannot be repaired in a generation. It is, therefore, in the interest of everybody to find means for making them harmless without hurting them more than necessary.</p>
   <p>In times of strikes, this riot type of people find their great opportunity for expression. But rarely do they belong to organized labor. On the other <pb facs="5423404_1_0682.jpg" n="2"/>hand, it happens frequently that they have been paid by the capitalist class to do damage to life and property, in order to turn the sympathy of the public from the working class. A threat made by one of these persons is taken up by some other thoughtless individual, then it is repeated by irresponsible ruffians, or by some thoughtless women--and soon a riot is under way.</p>
   <p>Then the police arrive on the scene. The officers' clubs find their marks right and left on the heads of guilty or innocent. Those who were curious and had pushed to the front, or who have been pushed forward by a steadily growing mass of people get the worst blows. Then a police officer may be hit by a stone, or by a piece of wood, thrown at him by some poor simp who is hiding behind the living wall of human beings. The policemen draw their guns, losing control of themselves. The packed together crowd of curious people begin to move. The circle around the policemen becomes closer, tighter. The guns of the policemen <pb facs="5423404_1_0683.jpg" n="3"/>begin to speak, and the mass of people fall back a few inches. In more serious cases, the police are reenforced by the militia. To escape blows from the gun butt, the cuts by bayonets, and even bullets, the mass recedes but a few inches, but now there are broken and bleeding heads; ambulances come to carry the wounded ones to some hospital. Perhaps the riot is quelled.</p>
   <p>If one asks the police if it were not possible to act in a more humane manner in dispersing of a crowd of people consisting mostly of the curious, the answer is in the negative. And yet, in the city of Bridgeport, Connecticut, the highest official of the city has proven that it may be done. Mayor Mulvihill understood that the real rioters were but few in the mass of five thousand people, who had gathered at a given place in the neighborhood of the street car barns. The sheriff and his constables applied their clubs diligently on the people without the Mayor stopping them. But when they started pulling out their guns, and the first shot was fired, the Mayor ordered them to put the guns back in their <pb facs="5423404_1_0684.jpg" n="4"/>covers. He then ordered the fire engines out, and the streams of cold water worked salutary on the people's over-excited minds. Soon the mass of rioters was dispersed. Drenched and ashamed, they hurried, each to his home--and calm prevailed.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped that this method of Mayor Mulvihill's for the suppression of riot might be accepted by the police forces in other cities.</p>
   <p>Plenty of cold water has a powerful effect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
