<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Singing in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH SINGING IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On page nine of the present issue of this paper is printed a letter signed "F. D.," which touches upon points of interest concerning the circle of Swedish singers in Chicago. The letter forms a sort of addition to the article we published in the previous number of our paper.</p>
   <p>We are quite willing to agree that the leaders within the singing association in Chicago are prone to compliment each other, and that the blame for the sad fiasco this past summer rests with them. We stated this in our issue of August 1.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0322.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The correspondent blames us, more or less, for "praising the general at the cost of the soldier." If by this he means that we are extending undeserved honor to Professor Ortengren as director, then we merely need to call to mind what once upon a time the Swedish Glee Club achieved under the leadership of Professor Ortengren. The leaders in song have not retrograded so as to become merely trade-like and a matter of self-satisfied habit, but rather that the singers came to consider themselves superior to the teacher and as understanding singing better than he. It is clear that under such circumstances, the director could not create enthusiasm in the singers. It is, by the way, quite impossible for a teacher to awaken love for a subject in the hearts of his disciples if the latter do not have any interest in the subject.</p>
   <p>We join completely with "F. D." in the permanent motto," Singing for the sake <pb facs="5423404_1_0323.jpg" n="3"/>of singing", but we doubt that it will be necessary to form a new chorus in order that the motto gain acceptance. We still have singers in Chicago who do not consider themselves superior to their leader. We still have boys with song in their voices, who do not believe that they know everything. We still entertain the hope of seeing men among the Chicago singers who will attend the rehearsals regularly, because they are warmly interested in Swedish singing. And to such men, the future belongs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
