<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-06-26">June 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Swedes and Norwegians in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-06-26">June 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDES AND NORWEGIANS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Svenska Dagbladet, of Stockholm, Sweden, sent over here, has an editorial with the headline: "National Harmony Abroad." Here, the author compares the various Scandinavians national unity in America one with the other.</p>
   <p>First, he finds it remarkable that the national consciousness comes to life abroad. Foreigners in Sweden, for instance, like to congregate very much within their own nationality, because one feels like a stranger in the new country, and prefers to be with one's own countrymen.</p>
   <p>The editor in this Swedish Stockholm newspaper then takes up the old question concerning the Norwegian-Americans supremacy over the <pb facs="5423404_1_0294.jpg" n="2"/>Swedish-Americans in regard to the strength of their love for their homeland, and says that the Norwegian-Americans have more church congregations than the Swedish-Americans. But we here in the United States are very doubtful concerning the correctness of this statement. We doubt also when he says that the number of the Swedish-Americans is seventy per centgreater than the Norwegian-Americans. The fact is, according to the latest census taken in the United States, that there are 665,000 Swedish born, and 403,500 Norwegian born in America. The Norwegians are often bragging about their two United States Senators. Well, we Swedes have had three Governors in Minnesota, and all three of them have been excellent officials, honoring the Swedish name all over the United States. Later on, as the years pass by, we are going to find many more Swedish and Norwegian names among office holders in the United States, when the new generation of Scandinavians have been more and more <pb facs="5423404_1_0295.jpg" n="3"/>Americanized. Then there will be no question regarding original nationality, but personal qualifications for the office they are seeking to obtain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
