<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-04-26">Apr. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Cultural Jubilee</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-04-26">Apr. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A CULTURAL JUBILEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The oldest Swedish-American educational institution was founded April 27, 1860, by a few persons who met for that purpose in the old Swedish church on Superior Street in Chicago. At that meeting a committee of four was appointed to make preparatory plans for a school, which plans were later to be discussed at a meeting in the Norwegian church of Clinton, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>This was the beginning of Augustana College of Rock Island, Illinois, which this year celebrates its golden jubilee, and which has been the nucleus around which eight other schools have been established in various parts of the county.</p>
   <p>In the early years Augustana was chiefly a school for the training of ministers, but it gradually expanded and has now for many years offered <pb facs="5423404_1_0138.jpg" n="2"/>complete college courses, and its theological seminary constitutes a separate department with a three-year course.</p>
   <p>Diplomas from Augustana are recognized by all American and Swedish universities, and many of its graduates occupy positions as teachers at leading colleges and universities, while others are scattered all over America and have made a name for themselves as doctors, jurists, writers, musicians and businessmen. About six hundred students have graduated from the theological seminary, and they are now engaged in religious work as ministers and teachers; quite a few are doing missionary work among the heathen.</p>
   <p>It is self-evident that this fifty-year-old school, in conjunction with the other younger and smaller ones, has made a most important contribution to the preservation and dissemination of Swedish culture here in our adopted country, and it is only natural that the Swedish-American press should be among the first to pay tribute to Augustana. Our newspapers and other publications are also champions of the Swedish cause, even though they 
<pb facs="5423404_1_0139.jpg" n="3"/>cannot point to such remarkable results of their long and faithful efforts.</p>
   <p>A fund-raising campaign is now under way in behalf of this foremost Swedish-American institution of higher learning, and the goal is $250,000. If one may judge by the public response, it will be a long time before Swedish-American cultural undertakings will wither and die for lack of popular support.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
