<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-12-20">Dec. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Unemployed in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-12-20">Dec. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNEMPLOYED IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Unemployment and its consequences in Chicago are more noticeable than in other places because many large factories which have been flowering during the period of duty-protection, are now idle and because the closed World's Fair tempted more people to come here than there was work for them even during the boom period.</p>
   <p>The newspapers in Chicago have related that it is the intention to solicit one million dollars for the benefit of the needy and this story has also tempted people to come here to get their share. But only a few thousand dollars have been collected so far and when we realize that the number of unemployed in Chicago - among them many Scandinavians - probably is more than one hundred thousand, then we know that there can't be much left over for strangers. It has been decided that only residents in need in Chicago are going to benefit of the help; strangers will have a hard time to get anything at the "soup-kitchens" or to get free tickets back home. Chicago is therefore one of the last cities to which needy workers should come in the hope of making a living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0799.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Acting Mayor Swift in Chicago issued a proclamation last Saturday to all well to do citizens asking them to make donations to the needy. A committee has been appointed for thus purpose, and has opened a Lakeside Free Kitchen at Randolph St. where free meals are going to be served daily: coffee and bread for breakfast and supper, beefstew and bread for luncheon. It as the intention of the committee to serve 20,000 persons every day. Work will also be offered the needy to clean the streets and to pay them with tokens which will be good for payment for meals and room.</p>
   <p>This intended play to help the needy is probably the best under the present circumstances. The cleaning of the streets has been amiss for a long time, but men can now do this work and have the satisfaction of being paid for their labor. Women and children, who cannot do any heavy work, will be taken care of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
