<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Expression of Thanks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.2.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 d</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">EXPRESSION OF THANKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11..................From Bethany College latest Director's meeting we have the following: Dr. Swensson reported the following donation from the Hon. C. A. Smith of Minneapolis, Minnesota, twenty-five million feet of lumber on the root from Mr. Smith's timber lands in Oregon. This lumber is not to sell for less than $25,000., with four per cent added, from the date of the expiration of Dr. Pearsons' Endowment Fund until date of sale. The name of the fund created by this gift shall be: "The Charles A. Smith Endowment to the President's Chair of Bethany college."</p>
   <p>The donation has a conditional clause namely: that Bethany College is to remain always under Lutheran control and ownership. The donation places a further condition in stating that it is necessary for the college to raise $75,000.00 in order to acquire the $25,000.00 by Dr. D.K.Pearsons of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0154.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following resolutions of gratitute were unanimously adopted:</p>
   <p>"Whereas the Hon. C.A.Smith has continually befriended Bethany College in many and valuable ways ever since the college was founded.</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Board has received official information that Mr. C.A.Smith has donated twenty-five million feet of lumber from his lumber lands in Oregon, said gift to be known as the Charles A. Smith Endowment to the President's Chair of Bethany College and said gift not to be disposed of for less than $25,000.00, therefore:</p>
   <p>Resolved: That the Board of Directors hereby extend to the Hon. C. A. Smith their most sincere gratitude and appreciation of this munificent donation, expressing at the same time their wish and prayer that the blessing of Almighty God, the God of our Sainted Lutheran fathers, may continue to rest upon the kind donor, his family and his business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0155.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Resolved: That the Board hopes that the splendid example of Mrs. Smith's benevolence may induce others to do likewise, in order that our dear college may be safely and fully endowed as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Resolved: That these resolutions be entered in the minutes of the body, and that they are given to the press for publication. The secretary is also instructed to send a copy to the Hon. C. A. Smith at Minneapolis, Minnesota.</p>
   <p>Dr. Swensson announced the subscription of $1,000.000 by Mr. J. E. Norling of Chicago who is the largest stockholder of Svenska Tribune and Fosterlandet.</p>
   <p>Resolved: That the Board learns with gratitude and satisfaction of Mr. Norling's subscription of $1,000.000 to our Endowment Fund, and hereby express their thanks to the kind donor."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
