<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-12-19">Dec. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Journalists on Visit</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-12-19">Dec. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN JOURNALISTS ON VISIT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twelve Scandinavian journalists, who at present, are here on a study trip at the invitation of the American Government, have been received with the utmost courtesy and hospitality wherever they have visited so far. Feasts, banquets, and entertainments have been the order of the day.</p>
   <p>Saturday, they arrived in the Swedish-American "capital", Chicago, where the three delegates from Sweden, together with the leader of the trip, as well as the Government's representative, Mr. Edwin Bjorkman, to be feted at a dinner at the Swedish Club, Sunday, December 22, at 6:30 P.M. This dinner will be informal. The price of admission is $2 a person to both the club members and their friends, and as many more as the large dining-hall will accommodate. The affair, which is arranged by the Swedish reception committee, will have as its main attraction a speech of welcome by the Swedish consul in Chicago, Consul General S. T. de Goes, and a festival speech by Congressman Carl R. Chindblom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The musical part of the program is in the hands of Gustof Holmquist, Mrs, Carl R. Chindblom, and Director Edgar A. Nelson. In addition, one can expect to be entertained by other well-known talents in the field of music, according to Chas. S. Peterson, who is Master of Ceremonies for the evening.</p>
   <p>The next day, Monday, at 7 P.M. a grand reception and dinner will be held in the Gold Room at the Congress Hotel in honor of the entire contingent and Mr. Bjorkman. The price is $3 per person. Reservations to this affair, where the city's most representative Scandinavian element surely will be present, are received by the treasurer of the committee, Mr. Carl Antonsen, Room 1008, 105 West Monroe Street.</p>
   <p>The guests will remain for five days, including the Christmas holidays.</p>
   <p>Most likely, the three Swedish delegates will be invited to spend the holidays privately in some of our more prominent Swedish homes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
