<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-05-09">May 9, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the "New Ones"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0800</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0800.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-05-09">May 9, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE "NEW ONES"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: Last year's immigration brought about 60,000 Swedes to America and if we add the number of those, who have arrived this year and are expected to come by the Fourth of July, the United States will have 100,000 Swedes whom we can call newcomers. We suppose that 80,000 of these future Americans of both sexes are breathing American air and eating American bread. But where, in the cities or in the country?</p>
   <p>Sixty per cent probably went immediately westward, as future farmers, but the remaining forty per cent, no doubt, have stayed around the places where they landed. Many of them, plain workers, secured good jobs in the cities, but just as many do not know any trade at all. They belong to that large class, which is trying to do the best it can, cruising between the rocks on life's ocean. One day they have work, another day they are without. Sometimes they have a few dollars, other days they are "broke". Here is our advice to these people.</p>
   <p>Do not stay another day in the cities, large or small. The only way you can make the future bright for yourselves and your families is to secure a piece <pb facs="5423404_1_0801.jpg" n="2"/>of land in the new states in the west. Dakota is not yet a state, but it is the goal of a tremendous immigration, not only from Europe but also from many older states. From Illinois thousands of old farmers are traveling to Dakota to build new homes on new grounds. The consequences of this tremendous invasion will be that the land will be more expensive to buy since more people are settled there. It will be more difficult to get hold of, but also more valuable for the owner's Soon all the better homestead land will be occupied and then people will have to pay the railroad companies and real estate owners what they request for their acres. They will not sell anything cheap where there is no more land the government can offer. Therefore, "young man, go west!" Don't stay in the cities, where the wages are low and the cost of living high. Go west. If you can't get land immediately or be your own farmer at once, it is better to be in the neighborhood of farm land. Opportunities to work are better, the cost of living lower, and you have a chance to get a piece of the soil, where you can stay and make your living, and die in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
