<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-03">Aug. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Frankly Speaking</title><title level="a" type="sub">Political and Economical Chronicle by Plebs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-03">Aug. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">FRANKLY SPEAKING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Political and Economical Chronicle by Plebs</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Most people who do not believe in ghost stories any more are still afraid of the socialist spook. It used to be said of the old-fashioned ghosts that if one looked at them closely for a little while they would disappear. And they did. You see, the ghosts did not exist except in the imagination of the observer, and when he mustered courage enough to investigate the apparition, he found that it was nothing.</p>
   <p>The same procedure will also do away with the socialist ghost. I do not mean the real socialism as an idea and plan of a better society, but the mistaken conception of it which is so prevalent in the minds of the general public, who are apt to consider socialism as a return to a primitive and barbarian society.</p>
   <p>This misunderstanding is chiefly due to the fact that so many people get their idea of socialism from those who are for reasons of their own, opposed to it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0817.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>when such people are given an opportunity to study the socialist program as interpreted by socialists, they experience a pleasant surprise. Not long ago I read in an English Sunday school publication the socialist platform prepared for a recent election campaign in England, and in it I could detect nothing that did not conform to the best ethical and Christian principles.</p>
   <p>The creators of the socialist scarecrow seem to believe that our present organization of society is the best possible--the most just, and the only one that conforms to the teachings of Christ. They also seem to have the idea that even the abolishment of the most glaring of the existing abuses constitutes a danger to our entire social structure. Some very unfortunate and undesirable conditions are so dear to them because they benefit from them. That is the chief reason why they resist any change, and point to anyone who advocates reforms as a dangerous individual. Their attitude is much like that of the defenders of certain religious doctrines who burned dissenters at the stake.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0818.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When Huss noticed an aged woman carrying wood to the fire on which he was to be burned to death, he exclaimed, "Oh, what holy ignorance!" This woman undoubtedly considered Huss a devil because she had been told that he was one, and in a similar manner many people see a devil in socialism. It is unwise to try abruptly to change the opinion of such a person. I have made it a rule to pretend to agree with him, in order to gain his attention and good will; but in our talks I manage to point out the desirability of improving certain phases of our social setup, and before he knows it,he has agreed with me on the important points of the socialist program, and is an eager advocate of reform. But if I told him that he is standing with both feet on the socialist platform, he would call me a liar.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to fight prejudice with reasoning. It is a state of mind that must be changed little by little.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
