<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-30">Aug. 30, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Hypocrite's Holiday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-30">Aug. 30, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE HYPOCRITE'S HOLIDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, the day of rest, is the day on which the hypocrite feels particularly holy. It is also the day when the laboring masses are released from their work, the day when the really religious person dedicates his time to worship and spiritual refreshment.</p>
   <p>On that day, the hypocrite enjoys his greatest triumphs. He who indulges in many questionable acts during the other six days of the week is very particular about the observance of the Sabbath. He considers it an unforgivable sin to spend the day with God-created nature, in the cool forest and sunny meadows under a blue sky, far from dusty streets and crowded dwellings and far from dry sermons in stuffy churches. To him, what is right during the week is a stark sin on Sunday. He denounces the sale and consumption of alcoholic beverages on that particular day, but votes for their dispensing during the week, when he himself is not averse to taking a swig of liquor. He may greatly enjoy watching a ball game on any other day, but on Sunday he becomes <pb facs="5423404_1_0250.jpg" n="2"/>so righteous that this pleasure and all other forms of entertainment are abhorrent to him. He approves of keeping the World's Fair open six days a week, but protests against admitting the public on Sunday, the only day the worker has a chance fully to enjoy its splendor. In this particular matter, he has the support of a pseudo-religious organ, which, with reference to the proposal to keep the St. Louis Fair open between 12 A.M. and 10 P.M. on Sundays, has this to say: "This would make it convenient for those who wish to attend Mass in the morning, and enjoy the amusement section, beer dispensaries, and dance halls in the afternoon and evening."</p>
   <p>We, who have not yet had the pleasure of visiting the Fair, are prompted to ask: Are these the chief attractions of the World's Fair in St. Louis? We thought the public would be given an opportunity to view great works of art, the paintings and sculpture by the world's masters. We had hoped to see there a demonstration of our technical progress during the last decade, to learn about modern architecture, our flora and fauna, and the treasures which are hidden in our mountain ranges and under the ground; we have also been looking forward to studying the latest achievements of our great industries. But it seems that <pb facs="5423404_1_0251.jpg" n="3"/>the author whom we cited above saw nothing at all of these things; he only noticed "the amusement section, beer dispensaries, and dance halls". Individual taste and preference are not to be disputed; it is quite possible that the writer was blind to the beauty and magnificence of the Fair, and able to see only such commonplace things as he has before his eyes every day.</p>
   <p>In the name of sound reason we ask: Why should not the Fair be kept open on Sunday? Why should not the thousands of workers who have handled every stone and every plank in the vast establishment be given an opportunity to enjoy the result of their labor on their day of leisure, when they have some respite from their struggle for existence?</p>
   <p>If our hypocritical preachers, Congressman, and newspaper writers would drop their motheaten cloaks of false righteousness, the world would be a happier place to live in.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
