<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-01">Dec. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Work, Rest, and Alcohol</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Knut Kjellberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0214</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0214.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-01">Dec. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">WORK, REST, AND ALCOHOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Knut Kjellberg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For work of every kind a source of power is needed, and heat is the power source for all the work performed by the human organism. Our life processes are maintained by a constant process of combustion, in which the fuel consists of various kinds of food..... To secure an increase in the capacity for work, an increase in combustion is necessary, and if an insufficient amount of fuel is supplied the body, the body itself will be attacked by the combustion process.</p>
   <p>Many people believe that alcohol is invigorating, and the reason for this belief is that alcohol, as shown by experiment, will dull the feeling of weariness. It is possible to effect a temporary increase in one's capacity for work by means of small doses of alcohol; but the quality of one's work generally suffers as a result of the use of alcohol. Alcohol produces a sensation of warmth,.... but careful experiments have shown that the use of alcohol lowers the body temperature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0215.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as mental processes are concerned we can say that alcohol impairs the faculty of self-criticism: under the influence of alcohol many foolhardy acts are committed. "Courage" is gained through the use of alcohol; doubts and timidity disappear, and the foolhardy acts easily become criminal acts. Further-more, the use of alcohol enables one to forget his sorrows and troubles.</p>
   <p>Every race employs some kind of intoxicant. The members of barbaric tribes possess an inherent desire to become transformed, once in a while, into a condition in which the individual is lifted above the routine of everyday life. In our civilized communities, alcohol plays an important role in achieving a similar purpose. Alcohol is employed to make social intercourse more pleasant. When people of the so-called upper classes come together at a social gathering to have a "good time," everybody knows that the beginning of such affairs is marked by stiffness and unnatural quiet. But alcohol soon infects the people with a more friendly and sociable spirit.</p>
   <p>When one is at work, one does not feel the need for alcohol: people at work have common interests which make living with their fellowmen endurable without <pb facs="5423404_1_0216.jpg" n="3"/>alcohol. Social intercourse when no common interests exist plays an important role in promoting the use of alcohol among the "upper" classes.</p>
   <p>As for the poor, who have but slight opportunity for enlightened pleasures, and for whom life is monotonous and sad-- the saloon is the only recourse. If social conditions were more pleasant for them; if their homes were more attractive; if pleasures of a nobler kind were offered them; and if their interests were directed along more enlightened channels, then their desire for intoxicants would certainly diminish.</p>
   <p>It is important, therefore, to work for better conditions and to promote more enlightened interests among the poor. The education of the public must be directed so as to achieve these aims. The purpose here is not merely to provide information, although this dissemination of knowledge will, in the long run, prove the most potent means of propaganda, but also to promote enlightened and elevating influences.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
