<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-01-12">Jan. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Employer Versus the Public</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-01-12">Jan. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE EMPLOYER VERSUS THE PUBLIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago, a manufacturer, discussing labor trouble at his plant, declared, "This is my property, and I do not permit anybody to tell me how to run my business. If I cannot deal with my workers without interference from the out-side, I will close my factory."</p>
   <p>We have heard similar statements many times. How unreasonable and childesh they are! They do not want public interference. Just let somebody break into a factory and steal valuable merchandise, machinery, or tools and see now readily the owner will permit public agencies--in this particular case the police department--to "interfere" and bring the culprit to justice. Or let a fire break out on his property and we will see how anxious he is to "handle" it himself. Of course, he does not even wait for these agencies to come to his aid, but calls them on the telephone and tells them to hurry up.</p>
   <p>And this is not all. The public already "interferes" in the employer's business <pb facs="5423404_1_0458.jpg" n="2"/>every day, and not only in cases of theft and fire.</p>
   <p>The state studies and approves his plans before he is permitted to build a factory, and also reserves the right to lay down rules in regard to working conditions in the plant and to see that they are observed. The state wields this power in accordance with the old basic rule, "The greatest good for the greatest number."</p>
   <p>If, therefore, the state should now take another step in the same direction, and decide to pass laws calling for obligatory arbitration in order to determine how much the employer shall pay his workers and even limit his profits by law, such a procedure would not be radical as it might appear at first thought.</p>
   <p>He who owns property does so because society has decided that the system of private ownership serves the common weal.</p>
   <p>Property is no more holy now than it was at the time when a man only owned what he could defend with his club. The same power which once upon a time put the stamp of approval on private ownership might now step in and say, "A few <pb facs="5423404_1_0459.jpg" n="3"/>individuals have abused this system which was supposed to be beneficial to humanity. It no longer serves the welfare of the majority and shall there-fore be abandoned."</p>
   <p>For the right to own property and for its protection the owner must expect to pay a price. This price consists of his submission to laws which lay down the rules under which he may exercise his rights.</p>
   <p>It would, therefore, be wise for employers in the management of their business and particularly in their relations with their employees, to consider carefully public opinion. It is a strong force, and men who think that they are big enough to disregard it will find that they are mistaken.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
