<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-04">July 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">July the Fourth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0827</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0827.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-04">July 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">JULY THE FOURTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July Fourth is with us, and indications are that the day is to be celebrated this year as it has been celebrated year after year in the past. There will be military parades, patriotic speeches by political grafters, prayers and thanksgivings, fires, gun salutes, national hymns, and flags unfurled from windows. The multitudes of people who do not own a square foot of land are expected to speak of "our country," the land of liberty and of valiant deeds; and ministers and teachers will tell us how free and how great is this country, and how greatly God has blessed us by making us citizens of this great republic.</p>
   <p>We shall have our festivals. We are to celebrate and rejoice that we have, <pb facs="5423404_1_0828.jpg" n="2"/>in America, some hundreds of multi-millionaires who are holding sway over us and over our needs; we are to rejoice that we have unhealthful and dangerous lodging houses, children compelled to work and strong men compelled to go idle; we are to rejoice that our country has veritable armies of vagabonds, prisons, insane asylums, churches, bawdy houses, poorhouses; we are to honor and salute the flag that wafted over Homestead, Hazelton, Coeur d'Alene, and Cripple Greek.</p>
   <p>It is fitting and right that we give our best tribute, on July 4, to those who in days past gave their blood and suffered martyrdom in their struggle to form a nation which, while still in swaddling clothes, acclaimed the principle of equality for all men: equality before the law, equality in the struggle for liberty and happiness. Joyously we ought to honor the <pb facs="5423404_1_0829.jpg" n="3"/>brave and noble men and women who, during long years, fought for the liberty of this land, the liberty of equal men. Yes, the men and women who gave their lives and their fortunes, who struggled through hunger and cold, were driven from their homes and were hunted through forests and jungle as though they were wild beasts - because they would not bow to the will of foreign despots. But for the modern American, degraded descendant of high-minded ancestors, who now lifts his head, and boasts of the liberty which through his ignorance and cowardice has been transformed into tyranny and despotism under ruthless moneymen - for this modern American our attitude can only be one of disdain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
