<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For and Against</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR AND AGAINST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While Prohibition has caused a decrease in the number of convicts in our pententiaries and the destitute cases in our charitable institutions, it has also caused more work for our courts and law-enforcing agencies. Because of the difficulties connected with the enforcement of Prohibition, many people who favored it have become somewhat disillusioned, and the interests that always were against it are now clamoring for a revision of the law so as to permit the manufacture and sale of beer and wine. The financial and other means, which were at the disposal of those that opposed the law in the first place, are still available, and everything is being done to place Prohibition in an unfavorable light.</p>
   <p>But on the whole, the principle of Prohibition has been accepted by the majority of the American people, and nobody who would undertake to advocate the return of the old-time saloon would now be taken seriously. The difficulties of enforcing <pb facs="5423404_1_0234.jpg" n="2"/>Prohibition probably are not so much greater than those connected with the enforcement of other laws the purpose of which is social improvement. Our criminal laws and the penalties provided by them are pretty well established, and have the support of the general citizenry, but in our large cities murder is a daily occurence, not to mention robbery and countless minor infractions of the law. Statistics show that there are more than one million persons in the United States addicted to morphine and opium, but nobody seriously proposes that the drug law be modified for that reason. It is regrettable that Prohibition cannot be enforced with one-hundred-per-cent stringency, and it is just as regrettable that the laws dealing with murder, theft, etc. are so frequently broken.</p>
   <p>Because of the unrelenting propaganda, some people seem to think that Prohibition Amendment may be repealed, but this is not so. The law cannot be repealed, but this is not so. The law cannot be repealed, but a change may be made in its interpretation so that beer and wine containing no more than four per cent alcohol are not considered intoxicating liquors. Certain local politicians are promising <pb facs="5423404_1_0235.jpg" n="3"/>the Italians of Chicago that they are going to get their wine back, but this is nothing but an effort to secure their votes.</p>
   <p>It can not be denied that Prohibition, as it operates today, has its undesirable aspects. Human nature being what it is, it is to be expected that there always will be lawbreakers among us. But neither can it before that it also has produced highly beneficial results. Its full effect will probably not appear until the coming of age of a new generation which has never had the opportunity to acquire the habit of drinking alcoholic beverages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
