<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">To the Lower Layers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-21">Nov. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE LOWER LAYERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a basic cause of the state of submergence of the working class, and this cause is the ignorance of the workers. On account of this, it is important to bring knowledge to the members of the working class.</p>
   <p>The brains of the worker must become accustomed to think clearly, logically, and in true sequence; the worker must develop ability to think independently. Only then will he be able to see the reason for the load under which he is struggling; only when he has learned to think will he be able to <pb facs="5423404_1_0164.jpg" n="2"/>realize his strength also. Not alone, but in union with others, will he be enabled to combat the evils and emancipate himself both intellectually and politically. He will become the master of the earth and its products.</p>
   <p>Do not wait for some Moses to lead you out of the "slavery in Egypt." Centuries upon centuries have passed, and you have waited and are still waiting for someone to lead. Think for yourselves. Be your own leaders. Others may betray you. But he who thinks clearly, logically, does not betray himself.</p>
   <p>We do not ask you to embrace our doctrines. Be manly, and from your own opinions, your own purposes. Do your duty towards yourself and towards <pb facs="5423404_1_0165.jpg" n="3"/>society.</p>
   <p>We observe that there is an army of 1,000,000 vagrants, 600,000 thieves, 500,000 fallen women, and 150,000 criminals in jail. But we also observe an army of self-sacrificing men and women who advise, aid, and support the poor ones. Even though you be a sole crusader for a better society, don't despair if ignorance is mocking you and speak disparingly about you, for children will grow up who will, in some future day, decorate the mound that marks your final resting place.</p>
   <p>Workingmen: be honest towards yourselves, your wives, your children; familiarize yourself with the burning questions of the day, and join hands with those who think and act along the same lines as yourselves. Standing alone, you are weak; united, you are strong.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
