<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-12">Dec. 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Signs of Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0993</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0993.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-12">Dec. 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Signs of Day</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first signs of the dawning of a new day have appeared on our political horizon. For ages, this horizon has been clouded in heavy darkness. Through the breach which the election campaign has opened in the bastions of reaction, the first cabinet of the Left is about to enter to take charge of that reform work which so long has been neglected, owing to the egoism of the small group which has held power in Sweden. As with the Russian cossack, so with the Swedish reaction: where his horse's hoof has trod, grass cannot grow. And this reaction has trampled practically all over the political and social life in Sweden; everywhere it has left traces of destruction. As if a tornado had passed over the land transforming it into a desert <pb facs="5423404_1_0994.jpg" n="2"/><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="[illegible]"/> <pb facs="5423404_1_0995.jpg" n="3"/>laid waste are of such enormous extent that it will require a long time and much labor to regain what is lost. And first of all, the new movement requires new tools, first of these, of course, is the universal vote, which the Swedish people, weighed down by taxes and military burdens, have waited for so long. In the field of legislation and administration, the old heaps of anachronisms are piled up. Here the task of renovating and of new construction will be enormous.....</p>
   <p>In a word, the new government must become a government of the Left, not merely in name but in fact....It will not do any longer to waiver in the course. The results of the election clearly indicate the presence of a determined people with definite aims....The fight against the reactionary forces of an oligarchic government must be carried on vigorously; new ways <pb facs="5423404_1_0996.jpg" n="4"/>of development must be designed for the building up of a new Sweden where every free citizen can feel at home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
