<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-09">June 9, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Discipline</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-09">June 9, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">DISCIPLINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Discipline is a necessary evil, although relying upon force, it brings liberty. Just as the individual needs to discipline his acts and thoughts in order to make progress in life, so must organized labor discipline itself in order not to become subject to discipline from the outside.</p>
   <p>In the rush for organization of labor in the past few years, autocracy within the unions has occasionally been given too free reign, and in consequence, a labor union has received the sharp lash of the whip of discipline, which, fortunately, is being swung by men who are able to see further then the mass of workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0679.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Relving upon its strength, now and again some trades unions have forgotten themselves to such extent as to believe that with immunity they could break contracts which they had entered into with their employers. The punishment for such breach of contract has not failed to follow the breach. Only a few days ago, President Slocum of the Blacksmiths' International Union suspended a local union of about four hundred members in Chicago because the members of this local had gone on strike in sympathy with striking blacksmiths' helpers, thereby breaking the contract which their representatives had signed with the employers, at the behest of the members of the union. For a similar breach, President Albert Young of the drivers' national organization suspended three hundred striking drivers in St. Louis. Both these presidents knew what they were about, and their actions were endorsed by every right-minded citizen. If a contract is not binding, there is no use entering into contractual <pb facs="5423404_1_0680.jpg" n="3"/>relations. Mr. Morrison, president of the Brotherhood of Railway Trainmen, said the other day: "We hope to see the day when we will disdain him who breaks a contract entered into--be he member or not of some labor organization--as utterly as now we disdain strike breakers."</p>
   <p>This wish of his appears to have been realized sooner than Mr. Morrison had dared to expect, or does not the action by Young and Slocum prove this? We hope that the clear visioned labor leaders may make it clear to our time and our people that discipline is a word that has a meaning in the labor union movement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
