<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Republican State League's Annual Meeting and Banquet at Hotel La Salle</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Grand Loyalty Demonstration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0952</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0952.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Republican State League's Annual Meeting and Banquet at Hotel La Salle</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Grand Loyalty Demonstration.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1..The above mentioned League held its 24th annual meeting and banquet at Hotel La Salle Saturday evening. The meeting was opened at noon by its vice-president, Charles H. Kjellquist from Rockford. Its president, Oscar E. Carlstrom of Aledo, captain of Artillery, and now stationed at Fort Logan, had received a furlough for the occasion and was present; he was greeted with a flattering ovation when Edwin A. Olson, Martin A. Carlson and Palmer Anderson, as honorary guards, escorted him to the speakers' rostrum. He opened the proceedings with a short eloquent speech on the now so burning question, whereupon the various committees were appointed.</p>
   <p>The delegates received a greeting of welcome, by the city's building commissioner, Charles Bostrom, in behalf of Mayor Thompson; this speech was answered by Mayor Martin A. Carlson of Moline. The first session was concluded with a patriotic speech by Captain Carlstrom, wherein he said that no truer patriots were found than the Swedes nor a better organization than the one <pb facs="5423404_1_0953.jpg" n="2"/>they represented. The second session began at 2:30 p.m. when Ensign Thor Norberg was asked to speak and he gave an interesting lecture on Swedish Gymnastics, as applied at the Great Lakes Naval Training Station. Reports from the various committees were then heard through their respective presidents.</p>
   <p>The committee on Powers of Attorney headed by J. A. Horberg from Cambridge, Illinois, reported 332 duly authorized delegates seated. In the Committee on Resolutions' Report read by Carl R. Chindblom, the entry of the united states into the war was warmly approved and promises were made to bend all efforts towards its successful termination. This resolution further praised the loyalty with which the Republican members of Congress supported the administration; compulsory military service for all, and the amendment for woman's suffrage; finally a wish was expressed that the Naturalizations Laws be changed so that less desirable immigrants may be excluded, and making it easier for the rest to become citizens.</p>
   <p>Senator Knute Nelson was welcomed as the guest of honor, and the Republican party was congratulated upon the election of Will H.  Hays as president of the Republican National Committee. The resolutions were unanimously adopted by the <pb facs="5423404_1_0954.jpg" n="3"/>meeting. Then followed the reading of several telegrams, reports from the Secretary and the Treasurer, and patriotic speeches by H. R. Rathbone and Edwin Bjorkman,  members of the Committee on Public Information.</p>
   <p>As officers for the ensuing year, the following were elected: Alfred A. Morton, Chicago, president; Philip Swanson, De Kalb, vice-president; John P. Friedlund, Chicago, secretary; Charles C. Erickson, Joliet, treasurer; Charles Eng, De Kalb; Swan Erickson, St. Charles; and Chester Olson, Henderson Co., Sergeants-at-Arms. It was unanimously decided to hold the next annual meeting in this city.</p>
   <p>As soon as the president was elected, State Senator Charles F. Hurburgh, handed the departing President, Caps. Oscar F. Carlstrom, the organization's emblem, which he received with deep emotions and thanks, expressed in well chosen words.</p>
   <p>John Ericsson Banquet.</p>
   <p>After the business sessions a dinner was given at the La Salle Hotel, where about 1,000 persons were present. Mr. Edwin Olson acquitted himself honorably <pb facs="5423404_1_0955.jpg" n="4"/>of his duties as the evening's master of ceremonies. Together with Mr. Olson at the speaker's table, we found Governor Frank O. Lowden; Senator Knute Nelson of Minnesota; Chairman of the Republican National Committee, Will H. Hays of Indiana; Attorney General E. J. Brundage, Congressman Medill McCormick, Henry H. Rathbone, Judge Harry Olson, Len Small, Charles Bostrom; Corporation Counsel Samuel A. Ettelson, Captain Oscar E. Carlstrom and Edwin Bjorkman. Other invited speakers were Congressman Irvine L. Lenroot of Wisconsin, who was unable to be present due to the senatorial campaign in Wisconsin, and Mayor Thompson who was in New York, but was represented by Corporation Counsel Ettelson.</p>
   <p>Senator Knute Nelson in his speech told of an episode in the naval battle between the "Monitor" and the "Merrimac" on March 9th, 1862, when he himself was on board the Frigate "Constitution" in the immediate vicinity. He also expressed his firm conviction, if John Ericsson were alive today, then the German submarine depredations would quickly come to an end. Whereupon he urged all who had friends and connections in Wisconsin to write them and ask them for God's sake to re-elect Irvine M. Lenroot to the senate, so that Wisconsin <pb facs="5423404_1_0956.jpg" n="5"/>would be represented by a loyal patriot, and the spot on the Northwest loyalty be erased.</p>
   <p>Attorney-General Brundage made a short speech, wherein he stated that in the veins of the Swedish-Americans the same blood flows which has stained the battlefields in every fight for liberty and democracy. The chairman of the national committee, Mr. Hays, spoke on the Republican Party and the formative work being done towards an overwhelming victory in 1920. There was a positive challenge to the Democratic Party to come out in the open.</p>
   <p>Congressman Medill McCormick in his speech praised the loyalty of the "Scandinavian" element in the "Nelting Pot." Mr. Ettelson likewise praised our Swedish citizens for their loyalty and trustworthiness, and pointed out how Mayor Thompson valued these qualities to the extent of appointing many Swedish-Americans to important and responsible positions in the city's service. The governor joined the preceding speakers in praising the loyalty of the Swedish-Americans; he had, however, particular praise for Senator Knute Nelson of his native state. The governor arrived rather late at the banquet <pb facs="5423404_1_0957.jpg" n="6"/>due to another appointment earlier in the evening.</p>
   <p>Between the speeches a quartette from the "Great Lakes" rendered a few songs and the "Taffelmusic" was furnished by an orchestra from the same place.</p>
   <p>Sunday morning a few of the "League's" leading members gave a farewell breakfast for Senator Knute Nelson before his departure for Washington, after which he was escorted to his train.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
