<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-12-06">Dec. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">We Protest against the Starvation System</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-12-06">Dec. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">WE PROTEST AGAINST THE STARVATION SYSTEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The city has at last taken steps to arbitrate the devastating and long drawn-out strike in the garment manufacturing industry, and at this writing it is reported that a satisfactory solution hinges on the decision of one single firm.</p>
   <p>As time passes it becomes more and more clear that the big employers, on whom most of the responsibility rests, are making use of the hunger system against their workers; this is an old and tested weapon which has brought them victory on previous occasions. There are said to be forty thousand workers involved in the strike, and at least one hundred thousand persons depend on them for their daily bread.</p>
   <p>The city's trade unions, as well as other organizations, have come to the aid of the strikers, and it is estimated that about forty thousand dollars <pb facs="5423404_1_0612.jpg" n="2"/>per week is thus being contributed by strike sympathizers. This is a large sum in itself but, when distributed, it amounts to only one dollar per week per striking worker. A few of these may have savings from which to draw, but the great majority are facing the winter without any resources of their own whatsoever. Such a miserable situation is apt to cool off even the warmest enthusiasm among the strikers for their just cause. Hunger and other privations will wear down even the strongest, and it stands to reason that they will be forced to throw themselves unconditionally on the mercy of their employers or, at best, accept a compromise which is in reality a defeat.</p>
   <p>However, public opinion will not readily sanction conditions imposed by a victor who has won by using starvation as a weapon,and it is to be hoped that the employers, who are now slamming the door in the face of the reasonable demands of their workers, will have sense enough to appreciate this fact. Even though they control millions of dollars, and have almost unlimited credit at their disposal, they will do well to consider that public opinion does exert a strong pressure on business and industrial policies, a <pb facs="5423404_1_0613.jpg" n="3"/>trend which is becoming more evident with every year. And no small group, no matter how powerful it thinks it is, can buck it successfully in the long run.</p>
   <p>We have, in a previous issue, presented the demands of the strikers. Briefly, the struggle centers about their right to organize, a new wage scale, and a number of minor adjustments of a more general nature. The employers complain that the workers will not "listen to reason," but we suspect that it is the other way around. An impartial arbitrator will find that on this occasion, as on most others, the workers are not unreasonable if humane and fair proposals are presented to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
