<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-12">Sept. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Night Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-12">Sept. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE NIGHT SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At this time of the year, classes begin in the night schools here in Chicago, as well as in many other communities throughout the country. They offer special courses for foreign-born people who wish competent instruction in English. In most cases, there is no charge, and since classes are held at night this instruction is within reach of everybody. All that is needed is the will and ability to learn.</p>
   <p>It is evident that the work being done in these night schools is very important. Immigrants from a variety of countries are placed side by side in these schools, and if a competitive spirit is occasionally aroused among the various nationalities, no harm is done. According to the reports of the teachers, the students in these schools are most attentive, since they realize that the instruction they are receiving will be very valuable to them as a means of <pb facs="5423404_1_0043.jpg" n="2"/>getting ahead in the world. There is, of course, no compulsion except the driving force within the pupils themselves. They realize that mastery of the subjects they are studying will increase their chances of success in life.</p>
   <p>There are indications that here in Chicago, at least, night school attendance will be higher this season than ever before. Among the pupils there will be a large number of young Swedes who have arrived here during the last year. This is indicated by the fact that a large number have already registered in English classes offered by Swedish-American organizations, among which are several churches.</p>
   <p>The fact that newly arrived Swedish men and women are anxious to learn the language of their new country gives cause for joy and pride among their older compatriots here, for it shows that they have in them the pioneer spirit. They want to make their mark here, and realize that in order to do so they must adjust themselves to the new environment, and, first and foremost, learn the language. This is the first prerequisite to becoming good and useful <pb facs="5423404_1_0044.jpg" n="3"/>citizens in the land which is to be their home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
