<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-08-14">Aug. 14,1906</date>.
<title level="a">[Growing Political Strength of Swedes]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-08-14">Aug. 14,1906</date>.
<title level="a">[GROWING POLITICAL STRENGTH OF SWEDES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Swedish Americans are not a little dissatisfied with the experiments of the politicians concerned--even a Michigan newspaper has the courage to protest against the methods of the party bosses, while in the east the voters are raving over the removal of the ballot box, and the trial of the new voting machines.</p>
   <p>Until recently a Swedish-American paper that dared to criticize the plans of the party bosses was a heretic and a scandal sheet. Practically all of this group of papers were conservative publications. Putting a Swede into a fairly prominent position was seen by the Swedes through a magnifying glass; the honor was so great. Furthermore if a Swede received an appointment as a watchman at a school, an extra policeman or a mailman, he had reached the top.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1085.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Time changes all things. Now the Swedes at least have the sense and courage to protest, with the result that they are shoulder to shoulder with the throng gathered around the political kettle. Swedes are no longer satisfied with promises for the future, or for the next election, and because of this situation, the American and the Irish political bosses are treating them more considerately and at times crediting them with brains and ability.</p>
   <p>The Swedes have always been welcome to a ride to the voting place on election day, or to partake in a glass of beer at a "party" blowout, but that was the end. As far as a job was concerned--"just wait awhile and we will take care of you."</p>
   <p>Now the Swedes are quite tired of waiting, and a nation-wide protest is making the bosses sit up and take notice. From Minnesota comes a protest regarding the neglect of the Swedes with reference to their position on the ballot. When in spite of the underhanded methods of the political bosses and their henchmen, we put our first Swede in Congress, the bosses began to handle <pb facs="5423404_1_1086.jpg" n="3"/>our countrymen with more consideration. That "in unity there is strength" is evident to party leaders, and now neither group dares ignore our Swedish colony as in the past, even as our press can no longer be held under cover.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
