<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-25">Jan. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Manifesto against Alcohol</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-25">Jan. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A MANIFESTO AGAINST ALCOHOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The declaration recently published by the Swedish Physicians' Temperance League and addressed to the Swedish people is a remarkable document, which should arouse interest also on this side of the Atlantic.</p>
   <p>In this manifesto scientifically trained experts present their experiences and the results of their carefully conducted research into the devastating effects of alcoholic liquors on the human body and mind. In it one also detects a strong undercurrent of fine humanitarian feeling and love of the fatherland, and in discussing its merits nobody can truthfully characterize it as the product of well-meaning but irresponsible and ignorant fanatics.</p>
   <p>The American temperance movement has, of course, been the subject of thorough study and discussion during the struggle for and against prohibition which is <pb facs="5423404_1_0202.jpg" n="2"/>at present going on in the Old Country. Many are sincerely opposed to prohibition on the grounds that it represents too great an infringement on their personal liberty, and they do not believe that much restrictions are beneficial to the people. Neither do they believe that a prohibition law can be efficiently enforced, and to them conditions in America offer ample evidence in support of such beliefs. In Sweden it is claimed, publicly and privately, that prohibition is a complete flop in the United States, even though those that are correctly informed and impartial know that this is not so.</p>
   <p>In spite of strong opposition, the temperance movement in Sweden has already gained such momentum, and has become so popular, that far-reaching results are bound to follow. Here in America, the movement has already deeply affected public opinion in regard to the liquor business and drinking habits, even in those localities where drastic liquor laws have not yet been put into effect. The change is unmistakable, and in our opinion it is only a question of time when the prohibition forces will be victorious.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
