<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-12">May 12, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">For Those Who Condemn Strikes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-12">May 12, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THOSE WHO CONDEMN STRIKES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"How can we know when a strike is justified?" is a question which frequently is brought up, especially at a time as the present when we find strikes going on practically anywhere. The quickest and surest way of answering the question is through the acquisition of information about the kind of work the strikers have been doing, and what wages they have received for their work.</p>
   <p>Let us consider the ironworkers of the American Bridge Company, who are now on strike. Compare the work they are doing with the wages they are receiving, and you will not need to wonder and question as to the justification for their strike.</p>
   <p>These workers are being paid four dollars or less for their work. But these <pb facs="5423404_1_0691.jpg" n="2"/>workers are the men who are building our sky-scrapers and our piers. Their work is as dangerous as is the work of the builders of church spires, and the latter are being paid from fifty to one hundred dollars per day. A wrong turn, a misstep by one of the ironworkers may send him and one or more of his comrades to death.</p>
   <p>"Our motto is, 'We do not die, we are being killed'," one of these workers recently said. "I have probably seen a hundred workers killed during work," says Frank Buchanan, leader of the strike of these ironworkers. "These men must not harbor the fear of death, for death is waiting for them every minute of their working time." In 1893, before these men had formed their union, they had to work ten hours per day, and for their work they received one dollar seventy five cents per day. Today, they are working eight hours per day, and are being paid at the rate of three to four dollars per day. Yet, if one considers the kind of work they are doing, their pay is ridiculously low. Many a boy who has just finished his public school training and has become reporter <pb facs="5423404_1_0692.jpg" n="3"/>for a paper is earning more than four dollars per day. John D. Rockefeller is earning $280 per second on the basis of an eight-hour working day.</p>
   <p>The ironworkers, of whom we are writing, join iron beams weighing more than one ton, and with these beams they construct building complexes, two hundred to three hundred feet in height. Frequently this scaffold consists merely of an iron beam, about six inches wide; and on either side the worker looks down into an abyss. In winter, when the north wind is raging, and raindrops have become ice on the sides of the iron beams; when snowflakes blind the eye and the cold makes the body numb, then is death twice as near at hand as in the days of summer. But in heat or cold, whether sick or well, the ironworker must be on his job, or he will receive a cut in his wages. His only vacation comes when there is cessation of work on his job, and he is obliged to look for new employment.</p>
   <p>For his dangerous and health destroying work he does not receive more money <pb facs="5423404_1_0693.jpg" n="4"/>per day than the amount which is paid for a seat in one of our better theatres, or the price of a cablegram.</p>
   <p>When the first tower of the East River Bridge in New York was finished, a newspaper reporter climbed to the top and took a photo of the construction from up there. For this his "brave feat," as a newspaper expressed it, he received fifty dollars. In an article later which he wrote about his daring undertaking he stated that not for a million dollars would he repeat the trip. And yet, every man who was working on the construction of the tower had to struggle at his work for more than two weeks before he would receive fifty dollars, and no newspaper was extolling his "bravery" in doing so.</p>
   <p>The directors of the American Bridge Company are sitting comfortably in expensive leather upholstered chairs as they dictate to the industrial world. They ought to consider that beneath their feet, on the iron beams which support the floor of their office are dark-red spots - spots that indicate the places where some ironworker lost his life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0694.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And you who participate in the cry about "strikers who are starting trouble again", how would it appeal to you to exchange places with these ironworkers?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
