<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-12-08">Dec. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Unemployment Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-12-08">Dec. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The kettles in the free soup kitchens are on the fire. In all of our large cities there are great numbers of unemployed. Employment agencies report that every day they have to turn away hundreds of applicants for work. Privately, one hears daily of shutdowns of factories, but information of that kind is not made public. Thousands of workers have been laid off in the formerly very prosperous automobile and rubber industries. The same situation exists in the textile industry. In many other businesses, employees are working only half of the time.</p>
   <p>However, acute unemployment does not yet exist. Many workers who were laid off have been rehired at lower wages. There seems to be a systematic effort to reduce wages all along the line. In no other way can the present situation be logically explained. In industries where a wholesale layoff of workers has taken place, it is claimed that price reductions cannot be effected with the prevailing high wages.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0774.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The manufacturers are talking of the consumers' "silent strike". If it is a strike, it is one of necessity. The consumer simply has not got the money.</p>
   <p>The manufacturers ought to realize that the higher the wages, the more they can sell of their products, and the better the price they can get. If, in addition, they were wise enough to be willing to operate with a somewhat smaller profit, they should be able to come down to earth without being hurt too much in the fall.</p>
   <p>The employers ought to show as clearheaded an understanding [of the situation] as did those workers who, on their own initiative, took a cut in pay in order to avoid a layoff or a reduction of working hours.</p>
   <p>So far, more has been done to bring down wages than to lower prices. When both were going up, prices were in the lead. The demand for necessities cannot diminish to any great extent, since people both here and in foreign countries <pb facs="5423404_1_0775.jpg" n="3"/>must have clothing, food, and other products necessary for the maintenance of life, just as they have always had to have these necessities. But they may, of course, have to lower their standard of living somewhat.</p>
   <p>Lack of demand for goods, therefore, cannot be accepted as the only reason for the wholesale layoff that has taken place lately--especially in view of the fact that cheap labor is being imported from foreign countries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
