<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-27">Oct. 27, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Mitchell on Organieed Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-27">Oct. 27, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">MITCHELL ON ORGANIEED LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. John Mitchell, the young president of the coal miners' union, spoke last week before the Civic Federations' meeting here in Chicago. Mr. Mitchell said:</p>
   <p>"There is a class of people, few in number but of high character, who, on account of prejudices and Mistaken ideals, remain outside of the ranks of organized labor. They are men imbued with a fanatical belief in the rights of the individual, the right of every individual to do whatever he wishes regardless of the effect of his acts on his fellowmen. This, however, is a philosophy of the Robinson Crusoe type, and is not suitable for our time and our circumstances.</p>
   <p>"The majority of the non-organized workers are not of this type; they are merely stupid and lazy. There is, however, a group within organized labor but not consisting of members of labor unions, which ranks but slightly above the class of habitual criminals. This is the group of professional strikebreakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0665.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"In saying this, I do not mean to imply that every strikepreaker is a criminal. Some strikebreakers are former union members who have been expelled from the organization for unbecoming behavior; others never did belong to any union, nor did they ever gain their living by means of honest work.</p>
   <p>"In our large cities there is a growing class of men who live in the manner of unemployed men, accepting any kind of work that may be offered them. They consider nothing except the pay in connection with the jobs offered. The members of this class drift about the streets and alleys while honest people are working, and they work, or pretend to work, when honest people are striking.</p>
   <p>"Some of these people may have been driven to this way of life from dire poverty or heavy reverses, but a similar defense may be urged in favor of thieves and murderers.</p>
   <p>"There are also strikebreakers whose very purpose in life seems to be to hurt others, and such persons have frequently been employed in connection with strikes, both as strikebreaking workers and as private policemen."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
