<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-03-26">Mar. 26,1907</date>.
<title level="a">Police in Chicago Want More Pay.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-03-26">Mar. 26,1907</date>.
<title level="a">POLICE IN CHICAGO WANT MORE PAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One day last week,the city council took up the question of higher pay for the Pat's, who are trusted with the star and baton; they are called Chicago's Police. They have been getting $18.00 a week to begin with, or $75.00 per month; now they want $1,400 per year, after really becoming at home in the police uniforms. If the policemen were the kind of men that protected life and limb, house and home from thieves and ruin, then it would not hurt to make them happy, especially,those who deserve happiness. Chicago's bluecoats could not be recommended to the council as really performing their duties as law enforcers. They are a poor lot of drones, that draw pay from the city and accomplish nothing. Yes, it has happened that Mr. Police once in a while, on the spur of the moment, when his anger arises, he gets in an argument with a bad man or woman with his police star's authority, they are taken to jail.</p>
   <p>For that reason apparently they want higher pay. But let us find out, who Pat was before he was taken on as a policeman? Rather difficult in the first <pb facs="5423404_1_0306.jpg" n="2"/>place. First he lived on his father's farm in Ireland ; later he came to America and worked as a ditch digger, or a mason, possibly some other low paid manual labor where seldom a salary of more than $9.00 a week was paid. But at last the Pat's get in as policemen, and immediately received $18.00 per week. Now they think $18.00 is too little and want nearly twice that much. To talk about their work as ditch diggers or masons is useless, and the work they accomplish when they actually drag their feet along the streets, or lean against a house, or when they rest with the cook, or hang in the saloon when some one offers them a drink, or in some gainless manner kill time.</p>
   <p>Say what you wish, but a more worthless worker,who works for pay ,as Chicago Policemen,cannot be found in the whole world. Just read the reports in the newspapers about all the crime on the streets, and in the private homes, always the same condition, no police could be found until long after the crime took place. Once in a while, not always, a bluecoat comes puffed up and gruffly states, not seldom, that unless the offender was half beaten too death it was not worth while. But once in a while they arrest <pb facs="5423404_1_0307.jpg" n="3"/>the one who has been in trouble before. This has happened and is happening. But for that matter, why talk about the Chicago Policemen? As long as they consist of Pat's,nothing better can be expected. Possibly,a change would take place if Mr. Busse was elected Mayor, and Chicago's Irish strength and management would get a different view.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
