<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Language in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH LANGUAGE IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the latest issues of the Swedish newspaper Dagens Nyheter, which recently arrived here from Stockholm, contains the following: "We wonder if the Swedish language is dying out in America. The Swedish Augustana Synod is the general organization for The Swedish Lutheran Churches in the United States, having a collage in Rock Island. It is now said that the Swedish language is being driven back more and more not only in the classes there but also during meetings of the young people's clubs, where the English language now mostly dominates among this Swedish-American youth, who later on are supposed to educate the Swedish-American children."</p>
   <p>Yes, maybe this is a sad thing to know but our prophesy in this matter a couple of years ago is now going to be fulfilled, namely that this college is either going to be a completely American school, <pb facs="5423404_1_0289.jpg" n="2"/>or it will disappear entirely. The author of the article in the Stockholm paper is wrong when he talks about the "Swedish-American youth." There is no such youth! Only the parents are Swedish-Americans, but their children-like the Norwegian-Americans, German-Americans-will become exclusively Americans without any "prefix." It is an old proverb as old as the streets, that "one must adopt the customs where one goes." A custom in every country is to talk the language of that country.</p>
   <p>When they now read in Sweden, in their newspapers, that the Swedish language has been introduced in the American schools as one of the topics, they will think, of course, that this will no doubt help to preserve the Swedish language in the United and that it will be used conversation and in writing by the "Swedish-American youth" in the American schools.</p>
   <p>Then we ask: "How much French or English does one get in the public <pb facs="5423404_1_0290.jpg" n="3"/>schools in Sweden during one or two hour of instruction? Maybe the Dagens Nyheter knows that? Then they can use their own imaginations to realize how it is <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to teach the Swedish language to the American youth, who get their instruction in that language. It is not right to accuse the Augustana Synod for lack of interest in the preservation of the Swedish language in America, which the Synod has now almost given over to the Swedish-American newspapers. This matter is now in very good hands because we will preserve the Swedish language very clearly in both speech and script.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
