<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-13">Aug. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Times Are Good for Some People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-13">Aug. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">TIMES ARE GOOD FOR SOME PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Testimony given in connection with the merger of the Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company and the Bethlehem Steel Corporation, revealed that Eugene M. Grace, president of the latter, who receives a salary of $12,000 a year, was given a secret bonus for 1929 which amounted to the tidy sum of $1,623,000. So far this year, the Board has voted him a bonus of $701,968, and since last January 1, he has, according to his own testimony, earned a total of $5,450,000 besides his regular salary. Other high executives of the Corporation have also received bonuses, totaling several millions of dollars.</p>
   <p>A board of directors which has the nerve to vote this kind of bonuses to its own members must have the corporation's auditors pretty well under control. How could they otherwise manage to hide, from the stockholders and the public, <pb facs="5423404_1_0405.jpg" n="2"/>such heavy inroads on the net profit? To be sure, the profits are enormous, and the stockholders get their fixed dividends, but these million-dollar bonuses really amount to more than just "drops in the buckets". However, we will let the stockholders worry about that. But how do such incomes look, seen on the background of present economic conditions, throughout the country?</p>
   <p>This kind of distribution of corporate profits is quite a common procedure, even though the general public does not hear much about it. A similar situation came to light a few years ago in the Botany Worsted Mills, a corporation which gained notoriety at the time of the Passaic strikes. This organization's Board of Directors voted bonuses totaling one and a half million dollars at the same time that they reduced the wages of the workers to a level below the starvation point. The bonuses were subtracted from the corporation's taxable income, but tax authorities were not so easily fooled. The case reached the Supreme Court, which ruled that the bonuses received by the directors "are not to be considered as compensation for work rendered, but as <pb facs="5423404_1_0406.jpg" n="3"/>a special method of distributing profits".</p>
   <p>Is it possible that the work performed by such a man as Grace is actually worth the immense sums that he is earning? Some newspapers seem to think that it is, and point out that an error in judgment or some miscalculation on his part might result in losses to the stockholders running into millions of dollars. Well, those who are so inclined are free to believe and accept such explanations. The director of such an enterprise is himself a stockholder, perhaps holding more stock than anyone else, and when he strains body and soul to make profits, he does so in his own interest, in order to collect dividends for himself. The responsibility does rest on him, but he, in turn, depends on the correctness of data furnished him by experts, who receive only moderate salaries, and whose bonuses, if any, are as chicken feed compared to his. And even if losses are sustained one may rest assured that he and his fellow directors get theirs, even though there may not be much left for the rank and file of stockholders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0407.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Read 'em And Cheer Up" is the caption used by one newspaper over an article containing the names of corporations which for the first half of the current year are showing net profits of from two to ten million dollars. It is cheerful news for the stockholders, but the workers who have been laid off by these same companies, their fellow unemployed, and all other poor people, certainly have no cause for rejoicing.</p>
   <p>If times are so good for the corporations and their directors one should think they would consider it their duty to do something for the millions of workers who today are unable to provide daily bread for themselves and their families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
