<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-03-30">Mar. 30, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Our First and Only Chance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0881</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0881.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-03-30">Mar. 30, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OUR FIRST AND ONLY CHANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have before us an old book. It is Svenskarne i Illinois (The Swedes in Illinois), printed in Chicago in 1880. It contains the history of the Swedes in this state, the first such history ever printed. From its yellowed pages we read chapter after chapter where it relates how men of Swedish blood were the first to settle and break soil in almost every county in the northern part of the state. And the history of the cities, which were comparatively young when the book was written, also bears testimony of Swedish energy, initiative, and achievement.</p>
   <p>We learn from it that we Swedes have traditions in this state, and no one should be surprised when persons of Swedish nationality reach high positions <pb facs="5423404_1_0882.jpg" n="2"/>and become influential in its affairs. Rather one should expect the many descendants of the rugged pioneers and of those who have followed them, to play a more conspicuous role in the political life of the commonwealth than is actually the case. On several occasions people from other states, struck by the strong Swedish element here, have been known to ask, and with good reason, "Why don't you have a Swedish governor in Illinois?"</p>
   <p>This year the voters of Swedish ancestry have the opportunity, the first one they have ever had, to vote for a Swedish candidate for governor of this state. A few years ago another man of our nationality did seek this high office but a couple of weeks before the election he was double-crossed by tricky politicians. This time we have a candidate who is accustomed to standing on his own feet, and who from his earliest childhood knew hard work, sacrifice, and struggle. The man is Attorney General Oscar E. Carlstrom.</p>
   <p>Several months have passed since Carlstrom opened his campaign for the <pb facs="5423404_1_0883.jpg" n="3"/>Republican nomination for the highest office in the state, and since then several other candidates have appeared on the horizon, but none of them possess the qualifications of our countryman, and none of them are so familiar with the daily toil and problems of the descendants of Illinois pioneers. Born on a poor homestead, Carlstrom became acquainted with work and hardship at a tender age, and his entire career has been one of useful work. He is, therefore, a worthy representative of the Swedish race.</p>
   <p>On this occasion it is more important than it ever has been that we form a united front. The Swedes of Illinois have never before had an opportunity to elect as governor of the state, one of their own. A similar opportunity may never present itself again. Unity and energetic, well-planned work are therefore necessary during the few remaining weeks before the primary election, if we are to be victorious. Unfortunately, there are Swedes who support <pb facs="5423404_1_0884.jpg" n="4"/>opposing candidates. There are various reasons for such action and the principal one is immediate personal advantage which has been promised them from other quarters. But let them go on their way. The rest of us who have the Swedish cause at heart will give Carlstrom all of the support that we can. For he deserves it, and we know that if he is elected governor he will discharge his duties in a manner which will reflect glory on our race and benefit every inhabitant of the state.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
