<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-01-03">Jan. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Co-Operation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-01-03">Jan. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL CO-OPERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States Department of Agriculture has for some time been making a thorough study of the co-operative movement and its chances for success in this country. The chief of the Economy Bureau of the Department recently made an address in which he emphasized certain essential principles on which a sound development of the system must rest. Here are some of them:</p>
   <p>In the first place, it is important that every farmer who joins a co-operative undertaking should fully understand the idea on which the organization is based and its purpose, and that he should keep in mind that its turnover must be large enough to cover the cost of operation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many co-operative enterprises undertaken by farmers have failed because the members have not been bound by contract to make specific deliveries of their products. They may have declared themselves ready to make certain deliveries at a certain time, but when that time arrived they were unable or unwilling to fulfill their obligations.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is of the utmost importance that the business be managed by capable men and that bookkeeping and accounting be properly done. When details of organization and Methods of operation have become well systematized, and the business is running smoothly, it is in many instances unnecessary to hire outside help.</p>
   <p>The official in question declared that whenever a co-operative enterprise has failed, the causes were, as a rule, to be found in lack of adherence to one or more of these basic principles. To adopt sound business methods <pb facs="5423404_1_0716.jpg" n="3"/>is just as imperative for an undertaking of this kind as it is for any other business venture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
