<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-02-18">Feb. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Scandinavians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-02-18">Feb. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCANDINAVIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seventy Swedish citizens of the North Division held a meeting at Svea Hall, corner of Chicago Avenue and Larrabee Street, last evening and organized for the purpose of representation of their nationality in the city, town, and country governments. It is said there are from 16,000 to 18,000 Swedish residents on the North Side, and they cannot obtain the representation in the management of public affairs that their numbers entitle them to.</p>
   <p>S. A. Miller occupied the chair, and Rod Sylvan acted as Secretary.</p>
   <p>The proceedings were carried on in the Scandinavian tongue.</p>
   <p>At a previous meeting Messrs. Sundelius, Engstrom, Olson, Sylvan and Patterson were appointed a committee to draw up articles of organization, and they <pb facs="5423404_1_1063.jpg" n="2"/>reported. The name adopted is the Swedish Political Club of North Chicago, and only Swedish citizens of the North Side and Lake View are entitled to membership in it. Some discussion took place over the matter of admitting those who were members of other political clubs, and an amendment to one of the articles was offered, which provided for the exclusion of any Swedes from the club who belonged to Republican, Democratic, Greenback, or any other party organizations, but it was voted down, and any Swedish voter living in the district indicated above was made eligible.</p>
   <p>The usual number of officers was provided in the articles for the government of the organization, and the report of the committee was finally adopted without alteration.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected for the ensuing year: President, F. T. Engstrom; First Vice-President, S.A.Miller, etc. etc......</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A petition to the Judges of Cook County requesting nomination by them of S. A. Miller as a Justice of the Peace from the North Side, to represent the Swedish people, was read and approved........</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
