<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-10">Aug. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Swedish Mayor for Chicago?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0916</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0916.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-10">Aug. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A SWEDISH MAYOR FOR CHICAGO?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Swedish-American newspapers all over the country are currently reporting that Chicago's Swedes have united for the purpose of electing Congressman Frederick Lundin the city's next mayor.</p>
   <p>These rumors are an aftermath of the circular in behalf of Mr. Lundin which some time ago was received by Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter and the other Swedish-American papers in Chicago, all of whom either reprinted it in full or published excerpts from it. Immediately the American dailies, that ordinarily are not much interested in what the Swedish-American press says or does found it opportune to make big news out of this incident, and inform their readers that certain Swedish newspapers are pushing Congressman Lundin as Mayor Busse's successor. We suspect that they were prompted by the same interests which originally <pb facs="5423404_1_0917.jpg" n="2"/>distributed the circular.</p>
   <p>This newspaper does not question Congressman Lundin's qualifications for the office, and neither do we feel that Chicago's Swedes have in the past received the political recognition which they rightfully deserve. But we would like to know who is responsible for the above-mentioned circular. There was no signature, and it would certainly be interesting to hear the names of those who take upon themselves the authority to endorse Mr. Lundin's candidacy in the name of the Swedish voters of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Do we see the figure of Senator Lorrimer lurking in the shadows? His political star is now in the ascendancy, and inasmuch as he will soon take Lowden's place on the Republican National Committee, he may be planning to obtain control of Illinois politics as well as of the state's federal machine. Naturally, he will keep an eye on Chicago, and his political power will not be complete unless the mayor of Chicago is one of his vassals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0918.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In our opinion the single circumstance that a mayoral candidate is Lorimer's man is enough to cause his defeat at the polls unless counteracting considerations are brought forth of sufficient importance to outweigh the dislike and distrust which the city's voters justly or not, have for the Democratic-Republican Senator.</p>
   <p>In the game of politics nationalistic sentiment, or rather the nationality racket, often is the deciding factor, and that is the reason why men like Lundin and Smulski are so useful. Congressman Lundin's nomination as Mayor Busse's successor will depend on whether or not the forces opposing Lorimer are stronger than the Scandinavian voters' desire to see one of their own elected mayor. Lorimer has always represented the corporations, a circumstance that certainly does not appeal to the Swedes, and in view of the fact that Lundin on several occasions has acted as the Senator's right hand, it is to be feared that he will continue to do so, even as mayor, and that Lorimer will use him for the purpose of obtaining control of the politics of the state.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0919.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the other hand, many Scandinavians may feel that if we are going to have a Lorimer man for mayor anyway, he may as well be a Swede.</p>
   <p>The secrecy which surrounds the sponsors of Lundin and the authors of the now famous circular makes a bad impression. One is forced to suspect that they are not sincere, and that their action constitutes what in the political parlance is known as a "feeler".</p>
   <p>We do not know the situation within Polish and Italian political circles, but we do know that the time has passed when some political boss carried the Swedish-American vote in his pocket.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
