<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-03-21">Mar. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Our Sisters Who Serve</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-03-21">Mar. 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SISTERS WHO SERVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again and again, the question presents itself to us how it happens that our Swedish sisters in maid service are so highly considered and gain the good will of their employers, as is so often testified by them. Yet, the answer is easy to obtain, if one merely is willing to listen.</p>
   <p>What is the answer? Simply this: that the Swedish girls doing house work, generally take interest in the tasks they have at hand, and the man or woman who performs the assigned tasks with eagerness and interest will ever be highly regarded.</p>
   <p>The other day, in one of the fashionable homes in Chicago, an exhibition was <pb facs="5423404_1_0355.jpg" n="2"/>given of specially prepared foods by our Swedish maids. Nearly all the highest prizes were won by Swedish girls.</p>
   <p>On the same occasion prizes were given for long, faithful service. Of the nineteen prizes, six went to Swedish girls. It is also true that among Swedish girls a considerable number will never win a prize of any kind connected with their housework. The fault is with themselves; they are too flighty. They remain in a position a couple of weeks, perhaps a month, then they get tired of the place, and move. Of course, there are places where self-respecting girls simply cannot go on working; but in equally many cases the place is good, but the girl, impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
