<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-05-25">May 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chindblom for Judge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-05-25">May 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHINDBLOM FOR JUDGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the judicial election in Chicago, next June 7, Swedish-American voters will have an opportunity to show their appreciation of a countryman who in an honorable manner has discharged his duties in positions of trust, and has demonstrated unusual ability as a lawyer and fitness for public service. For among the candidates for judge of the Circuit Court is the well-known lawyer and orator, Carl R. Chindblom, who has been nominated by the united Progressives and Republicans, and whose name, therefore, appears on the Republican ticket.</p>
   <p>Chindblom is a man in his prime and well acquainted with conditions in Chicago, for he was born and raised in this city. Since 1900 he has practiced law here, and is known for his solid knowledge and that fine judgment and balance of mind which are so necessary for people that are called upon to make important judicial decisions.</p>
   <p>He has proved his fitness for public office by serving as attorney for the state health commission and, for two terms, as County Commissioner. In fact, he is so well known that it is not necessary here to go into details in regard <pb facs="5423404_1_1116.jpg" n="2"/>to his qualifications for the office which he is seeking. It is enough to say that Mr. Chindblom has been tested and has passed all the tests with flying colors. His countrymen in Chicago are glad for this opportunity to prove their esteem and loyalty at the polls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
