<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-13">Nov. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Prominent Swedish-American Trade-Unionist</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-13">Nov. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">PROMINENT SWEDISH-AMERICAN TRADE-UNIONIST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Frequent notices in the local Swedish-American press call our attention to the important role played by Swedes in American trade-union circles, and today we take great pleasure in presenting a man who is held in high esteem by his colleagues, and who has even been honored with political recognition. He was a candidate for State's representative from his district on the Socialist ticket, and even though he was defeated pulled no less than 6,458 votes.</p>
   <p>G. E. Strom was born in Falun, Dalecarlia, on December 8, 1863, in which city he also received his public school education. He came to America in 1879. By trade he is a cement finisher, but for the last four years he has been business agent for the Cement Workers' Union. His experiences as a representative of the workers have led Mr. Strom to the conclusion that it is sheer folly for the latter to go on strike on an empty stomach, since in that case the employers have all the advantages. He thinks that the workers' <pb facs="5423404_1_1161.jpg" n="2"/>best weapon is the ballot, for which also the capitalists have a healthy respect, and he is looking forward to the time when workers will vote workers into the legislature and the senate; then, in Mr. Strom's opinion, the situation will be reversed, and the capitalists will have to send delegates to the workers, instead of as is now the case, the workers asking their employers for a hearing.</p>
   <p>Also in other districts labor's Swedish-American candidates have made a good showing, according to incoming reports, even though the number of votes cast for them were not sufficient to bring about their election. It is, however, becoming more and more apparent that Swedish voters are inclined to give their votes to Swedish candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
