<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-01">Jan. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-01">Jan. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the luncheon of the Swedish Chamber of Commerce, held last Tuesday, at the Morrison Hotel, Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Stanler gave a short, but most interesting lecture on dried <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> commodity in this country. The lecturer represents Svenska Medicinal <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> (the Swedish Officinal Plant Society) which has its main office in Stockholm. This organization was formed about ten years ago, when it was noticed that the apothecaries in Sweden <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> a rather large number of dried blueberries each year, which were imported from Germany. This seemed rather strange, when Sweden among other things, is an eminent blueberry land. At length, it finally came to light that Germany purchased the fresh blueberries from Sweden, pressed the juice from them and re-shipped the shells in the form of dried blueberries to the North. When this was discovered, it was then decided to dry the <pb facs="5423404_1_0443.jpg" n="2"/>berries at home, and with this in view, the Swedish Officinal Plant Society was founded. This society has since broadened its work to the extent that at the present time, it owns about forty drying establishments in various sections of the country.</p>
   <p>After experimenting with success in drying blueberries by electricity, it was decided to experiment with drying lingonberries by this same method. The experiments succeeded exceptionally well. The dried lingonberries are now sold in the winter not only in Sweden, but they are also exported to the other Scandinavian countries. America, too, has the opportunity to take advantage of the usefulness of this commodity. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> pointed out that through the drying process the dried lingonberries became sweeter than the fresh berries, because they undergo about the same procedure as grapes do when they are pressed into raisins. He also said that no more than one-third of the sugar is used in the preservation of the dried berries <pb facs="5423404_1_0444.jpg" n="3"/>than would be needed if they were in their fresh state. Further, the dried berries are much lighter in weight and thus cost but a fraction of the price for fresh berries. Above all, the Swedish lingonberries are tastier than any other. Finally, the lecturer made it known that at the present time he is negotiating with a number of large American firms in regard to sole rights as distributors, so that the berries may be obtained in every well-known grocery store in America. The lingonberries are packed in Sweden, in cartons that also make a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> impression upon the buyer. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that these Swedish berries will have a great future in this country, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> lingonberry jam.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
