<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-19">July 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Railroads and Uncle Sam</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0426</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0426.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-19">July 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE RAILROADS AND UNCLE SAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From one point of view the current railroad strike is a joke at the expense of the public. By the "public" we mean the great mass of people who are not directly involved in the controversy.</p>
   <p>The railroad corporations have been guaranteed six per cent interest on their stock by Congress, and, considering the "water" content of the stock, this guarantee is equivalent to a ten per cent dividend on the capital actually invested. The corporations do not, therefore, have to worry whether the railroads are operating or not. Their income is guaranteed. Good old Uncle Sam is their protector, and pays the dividends even on their watered stock. On the other hand, it is quite possible that the unions will collapse from <pb facs="5423404_1_0427.jpg" n="2"/>exhaustion in their attempts to maintain wages and opportunities for work.</p>
   <p>If the farmers enjoyed the same consideration from Congress as do the railroad corporations, they,too, would be guaranteed operating expenses; fair wages for themselves as well as for their wives and children, who, as a rule, work on the farm; and, in addition, six per cent interest on the capital investment represented by their property. We dare say the farmers would accept such a guarantee with joy. They would not then have to lie awake nights worrying about drought or other causes of crop destruction. Even if no crops were harvested they would merely have to present their bill to the United States Treasury.</p>
   <p>But if our dear old Uncle should take care of everybody in this manner, who would pay the taxes which would make it all possible?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
