<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-01-14">Jan. 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Large Cities Encounter Large Difficulties.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-01-14">Jan. 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LARGE CITIES ENCOUNTER LARGE DIFFICULTIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Complaints that in the large cities, particularly New York and Chicago, we find large numbers of unemployed, in New York over 100,000 men and in Chicago at least 25,000. These figures seem unnecessarily high but if it was only half or one fourth as many it would be too many. Best of all would be if each one who wanted work could get it. The why of the large number of unemployed cannot clearly be explained.</p>
   <p>The large cities are the stopping place of the unemployed during good times as well as during the bad, but in bad times more come to the large cities, in fact the number has doubled, in hope of better chances then in the smaller centers. That the workers who are unemployed should become more numerous when they gather at a particular place is only natural. Of the unemployed here in Chicago it is a question as to whether one fourth are Chicago's workers.</p>
   <p>To persons in small cities who for the time being find themselves out of <pb facs="5423404_1_0790.jpg" n="2"/>employment, our advice would be not to go to New York or Chicago seeking work. As soon as the factories start up the old employes have always been given the first call and strangers had to wait till last. To maintain themselves in the large cities cost just as much as in the smaller one. A word to the wise is enough.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
