<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-09-10">Sept. 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Rotten Street Car Line Transaction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-09-10">Sept. 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">ROTTEN STREET CAR LINE TRANSACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A commercial transaction put over that many call a drag in affairs, can be said of Charles T. Yerkes. When he came to Chicago, "so they say," he had four-hundred thousand dollars in his pocket-book. To begin with he purchased an interest in the North Side Street Car Co.and before anyone suspected it, he had gained such power in the company that his word was law.</p>
   <p>A few years later he began to dabble in the West Side Company, and in the same way became powerful with that company too. That he made great improvements cannot be denied. But he borrowed about $25,000,000.00, and naturally, he mortgaged the company's property. His other activities can be pointed out. He boomed the City Railway Company's affairs, as a horse trader booms his old plugs at a horse sale. When he had with water and wind and other methods screwed up the affairs of the company as high as he could, he sold his interests - if we are not mistaken - for about $36,000,000.00. Then he bowed Chicago a farewell to go to London, there to double his millions many times with under-ground railways. We do not care to <pb facs="5423404_1_0463.jpg" n="2"/>comment further on his London affairs, only to say that he followed the plan used here of driving the stock up to unheard-of figures on the market, and then selling out.</p>
   <p>What did those get, who came after the smart financier? The Chicago companies, both North and West Side, are bankrupt. To make the companies affairs sound, a large loan would be necessary. The question is, how could you borrow money on property with a first mortgage of over $25,000,000? Those who are holders of the railway stocks will have a hard problem to meet, particularly, if they try to get the present price of the watered stock which is practically worthless.</p>
   <p>There were many who wondered at Charles T. Yerkes high financing during the time he played his tricks. Those who could not see, and fell for his schemes have lost, and their losses are not small. They could not see the magician at work. Now they can see, but it is too late.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
