<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-09-16">Sept. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Our Honored Comtemporary, Skandinaven</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-09-16">Sept. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OUR HONORED COMTEMPORARY, SKANDINAVEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The Scandinavian) is scolding Mayor William Hale Thompson for not fulfilling his promises. Behind the Skandinaven in this attack is the Daily News and Victor Lawson, valuable friend of the paper. No man, says the Skandinaven who has sought the office of Mayor of late years, has been as generous with his promises as Mr. Thompson. Thus he spoke before being elected: "I assume personally the responsibility for the capability of the police department ----We know that Chicago has been a place where criminals might feel safe. But we also know that the mayor can put an end to this situation and at once. If I be elected I shall guarantee the city a capable and honest police administration." That much for the election promises. Now as to the accusations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thompson"says the Skandinaven." now has been Mayor for four months, but it appears that the city is yet a place where criminals may feel safe... Although <pb facs="5423404_1_1040.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Thompson promised more than his predecessors in regard to freeing Chicago from crime, the fact is that he has done less than the average in this respect. This can hardly surprise anybody who has observed his commission on Civil Service, seeing that this commission has spent more effort in arousing suspicion against the enemies of criminals such as c.g. the Merriam Investigation's Committee, than in making the police force capable of coping with crime."</p>
   <p>So far the Skandinaven (after the Daily News). There are points in the article in Skandinaven that might be affectively ridiculed. We shall merely point here to the facts that four months are not a long time in which to make revolutionary changes in the police administration of the city but that in spite of the brevity of time, surprising results have been attained according to an authority whom neither Skandinaven nor the Daily News will dare to call in doubt. Harry Olson, the most formidable rival of Mr. Thompson for the office of mayor, supported for this office by both papers mentioned, said the other day before a large audience, that never before in the history of Chicago had there been less crime in the city <pb facs="5423404_1_1041.jpg" n="3"/>in proportion to the population.</p>
   <p>This statement was made four months after William Hale Thompson had entered upon his duties as mayor, by a man whose knowledge of the question of crime statistics nobody can deny and who, in this case, cannot be suspected of partisanship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
