<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-21">July 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Private or Municipal Waterworks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-21">July 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">PRIVATE OR MUNICIPAL WATERWORKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Indications seem clear that we are speedily approaching the time when private capitalists or corporations are no longer to own or have charge of the water-works in our municipalities. A few years more, and the water-works will belong to the people. In proof of this, we may mention that of the forty cities in our country having more than one hundred thousand inhabitants, thirty-one own their waterworks. The nine cities in which private parties still have charge of the water-works are San Francisco, New Orleans, Indianapolis, Denver, New Haven, Paterson, St. Joseph, Omaha, and Scranton. The inhabitants of two of these cities--New Orleans and Omaha--have already resolved that as soon as the licences of the water companies expire, the municipalities will take over the works, and in San Francisco, Indianapolis, and Denver, there are strong movements in the same direction. In 1900, there were ninety-seven cities of thirty thousand to one hundred thousand inhabitants, and of these, seventy owned their waterworks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0492.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The capitalist press, witnessing with regret one source of revenue after the other taken away from its friends and from itself, is ever ready to explain the cause of these movements to be the spirit of envy which is ruling the present age, and in case such a public undertaking were to run at a loss, from one cause or other, this press points to the fact with poorly concealed glee, raising its voice in warning against municipal ownership. In the socialization of the waterworks, we see simply a protest by the people against the entrance of private capital into undertakings which ought to be outside of its domain. Simply let it be supposed that some poorly paid workers at a waterworks owned by private parties were to strike for higher pay. What would be the result? No water in the homes, loss of property, illness, death. And these contingencies the people do not want to risk.</p>
   <p>The capitalists press has now ceased to complain of the inability of municipalities to run the waterworks in a businesslike manner and to the satisfaction of the users. Instead, the press is now raising its voice <pb facs="5423404_1_0493.jpg" n="3"/>of warning against the taking over of the systems of lighting by municipalities of gas and electricity. We do not need to point out to the wide-awake readers of this paper that....the same causes which might bring about a strike at a waterworks might produce the same effect at a gasworks--and the people of a city would be compelled to walk about in the dark....</p>
   <p>....The thinking public might well try to paint for itself the type of life one would be compelled to lead in a city such as Chicago if the coal barons, the railway kings, the gas magnates, and the water lords were to discharge their workers and stop production--and of course they have a legal right to do so. Perhaps if such things were to happen, we might not be willing to root for private property.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
