<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Pay Cash!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">PAY CASH!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"He who does not use his eyes will lose his cash," says an old Swedish proverb, and more than one Swede has had occasion to realize its truth.</p>
   <p>Again and again we receive letters from Swedes who have fallen victims to the nicely placed traps of the shrewd Israelite businessmen. They have permitted themselves to become ensnared by the so-called "easy payment" plans. One letter-writer begs us to warn the Swedes against one of these firms to whose shady tactics he has fallen victim. This firm is not exceptional; there are hundreds of similar ones, and we warn against all of them.</p>
   <p>Flashy advertisements, posted here and there, tell the readers that such-and-such a firm will completely furnish four rooms for $99. The <pb facs="5423404_1_0546.jpg" n="2"/>advertisement is enticing, and young people who are thinking of getting married go to the business house and make their selection. It is so easy to start housekeeping this way. There is a down payment of a few dollars, and then payments amounting to just a few dollars per month, until the total is paid. Nothing is said about the high rate of interest to be paid on the balance until the contract is about to be signed, and it happens all too frequently that by that time the buyer is not sufficiently attentive. The furniture bought for $99 will actually cost far more when principal and interest are paid. The buyer then had reason to complain.</p>
   <p>"Business is business," the dealer argues. He is taking considerable risks; the buyer might be a dishonest person who, at his first opportunity would sell the goods he had bought on "time" and then disappear. The dealer is being cheated time and again, and he in turn must skin his honest customers.</p>
   <p>In Sweden the credit system was considered the ruination of the merchant; <pb facs="5423404_1_0547.jpg" n="3"/>here it is the ruination of the customers.</p>
   <p>We strongly advise all the Swedes in Chicago and elsewhere: pay cash! You will get your goods at lews cost; you will get better wares for your money; and you will be treated more courteously.</p>
   <p>Shun the "easy payment plan"! In keeping on the "easy payment plan" you build palaces for Jews while you yourselves may have to be content with a bed of straw.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
