<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-05-21">May 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Youth and the Swedish Language</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-05-21">May 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN YOUTH AND THE SWEDISH LANGUAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who attended the convention of the Vasa Order in Detroit a little more than a week ago were very pleasantly surprised at the proficiency in the Swedish language that was demonstrated by the children's clubs which took part in the interesting program. Several of the youngsters spoke Swedish so well that one might think they had been brought up in the old country, and there were those in the audience whose eyes became moist when they heard the kids sing and recite in their fathers' language.</p>
   <p>The members of the Order who have spent much time and effort on the activities of these children's clubs deserve credit. Not many people possess the special personal qualities which are required in successful organizers and leaders of such clubs. We should be grateful to those champions of the Swedish cause, who so unselfishly sacrifice time and give their best so that Swedish-American <pb facs="5423404_1_0105.jpg" n="2"/>children may have an opportunity to learn the language of their mothers and fathers, and who do not become discouraged by the many pessimists who repeatedly declare, "It can't be done; children born in this country do not care to learn Swedish." The work of these club leaders, was, of course, duly appreciated by the officers of the Order, who expressed their deepfelt thanks.</p>
   <p>It is undoubtedly true that the children's interest in the Swedish language depends to a large extent on the attitude of their parents. If the latter have made it a point to implant in their offspring an interest in the language and an inquiring curiosity concerning the old country, it is quite easy to teach them to both read and speak Swedish. And when children from such homes get together in a club, the task of the teacher becomes easier and more interesting</p>
   <p>We have before us a letter written by a subscriber living in Michigan. He thanks us for the interest which we have taken in his daughter. This little girl has to walk six miles to and from school, but has, nevertheless, found time to learn Swedish well enough to enable her to write a letter, some time ago, to <pb facs="5423404_1_0106.jpg" n="3"/>our "Free Words" department, and one may imagine her pleasure when she received an answer from a girl whose home is in Sweden. The correspondence continues, and our friend is learning right along. Another Swedish-American girl noted these letters and decided also to send a contribution to "Free Words".</p>
   <p>There are many who will smile doubtfully and tell us that these examples represent only isolated instances. Well, maybe so. But such interest, evidenced by Swedish-American children, deserves encouragement, and it should be made clear to them that their knowledge of Swedish and of Sweden is a treasure which will always be of value to them.</p>
   <p>If we are to develop in Swedish-American youth a sincere and lasting interest in the Swedish language and culture, it is necessary that parents realize their obligations in this respect, and some co-operation and assistance on the part of Sweden herself is also highly desirable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
