<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-07">Nov. 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Worker Is Worthy of His Hire</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0467</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0467.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-11-07">Nov. 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKER IS WORTHY OF HIS HIRE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Carl was his name and he had been in America one year. He was working for the manufacturing firm, Brouch &amp; Jimley,which, like other beginners in industry, had to battle for existence.</p>
   <p>Times were hard, and Carl was working with that enthusiasm and accuracy which is the usual custom with the newcomer. He was receiving six dollars per week in wages.</p>
   <p>The foreman in the order department was taken ill; he was getting big pay, ten dollars per week. Carl had shown special interest in the work he had handled, and now he was given the job as foreman. No increase in wages was given him, however, still he was satisfied. He had the chance to learn, so he worked hard and waited for better times to come.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0468.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Business increased for the firm; orders came in large numbers. The foreman, who had recovered from his illness, came back to work for a couple of weeks, then he received a better job, and job as foreman in the Brouch and Jimley Order department fell to Carl, yet his wages remained six dollars per week.</p>
   <p>One day Carl entered the office, and in his broken English, requested pay at the same rate as his predecessor had received. "We will speak of that later," said the chief, "haven't got time now. You just go back to work."</p>
   <p>But Carl was not satisfied, he wanted a definite reply, and since the chief could not spare him, he agreed to pay Carl the ten dollars as demanded.</p>
   <p>The work went on. Many a night did Carl spend in the warehouse working <pb facs="5423404_1_0469.jpg" n="3"/>to keep things straight. Never did he receive a word of approval, though he was first at work in the morning and stayed latest at night.</p>
   <p>The new year came, the busy season was over; Brouch &amp; Jimley had earned a great deal of money. The earnings were divided between the two partners, and Brouch, who was the leader in the business, decided to take a recreation trip to California. Before leaving he wrote a letter to Carl which was to be given him the following day, then he left. In the morning, Mr. Jimley delivered the letter to carl who gratefully took it, thinking that it would contain words of appreciation for the extra work he had done, perhaps even a salary raise. He opened the letter and read: "The busy season is over, and we feel compelled to reduce your wages to eight dollars per week. No special intelligence or ability is required for the work, and after all, six dollars would be sufficient pay for the type of work required."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0470.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Something seemed to tighten in Carl's throat as he read, and when the day's work was over, he resigned his job.</p>
   <p>On the following morning, one read the following advertisement in the papers: "A young, intelligent man, who intends to advance, will find a good position with the firm of Brouch &amp; Jimley. Wages to start at $5. per week."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
