<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Boycotting the Profiteers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">BOYCOTTING THE PROFITEERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unreasonable increase in the price of sugar has further raised the already high cost of living, and is imposing additional hardships on workers' families and others of small means. This increase in price is caused not by any scarcity of sugar, but solely by the machinations of jobbers and speculators, who are so hungry for profits that they would gladly skin the public in order to enrich themselves. This unwarranted rise in prices has so embittered the consumers that a boycott of the sugar industry has been undertaken.</p>
   <p>It is the women who have taken up the fight against the profiteers, and we hope they will keep it up until victory is theirs. The boycott movement started in New York, and has spread to Chicago and other large cities throughout the country. It is being led by women's clubs, which are sending out <pb facs="5423404_1_0416.jpg" n="2"/>leaflets urging housewives to refrain from buying sugar at the present outrageous price, or at least to limit their purchases to the smallest possible amount. The housewives have nothing to lose by such a procedure, and if the great majority of them participate in the boycott, the price will be forced down. At the sugar exchange in New York a considerable fall in the quotations has already taken place. If the women do not weaken, final victory is assured.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
