<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Carl Swensson on Labor and Trusts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">DR. CARL SWENSSON ON LABOR AND TRUSTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6. From Pittsburg comes the news that measures and steps are being taken to call a national convention of workers and workers' organizations representing the Iron and Glass industries in Chicago about the first of July. The objective will be to bring about a strongly united organization of two million workers to oppose the trusts, because they do not favor labor and since capital has organized itself, no sensible person can blame the workers for doing likewise. One cannot help but realize that the rich have carried this action on the part of labor through the Trust Movement. In fact anyone can perceive it.</p>
   <p>The under-signed is opposed to Trusts of all kinds among rich and poor; in the state and the church. I am a child of Reformation, a free American citizen and believe in individual freedom to the very greatest degree possible. Recognition <pb facs="5423404_1_0521.jpg" n="2"/>of the individual and individual rights is one of the great principles of the Reformation or Protestantism. The same is true of our early American forefathers.</p>
   <p>But where are we going now. -</p>
   <p>A Steel Trust of a million dollars! The object of it was said to be to produce more cheaply. However, as soon as the Trust was established, steel rails increased in price two dollars per ton. Yes it is pleasant to think that another fifty million dollar Trust is now being established which will at least be an aggravating thorn acting as a billion dollar inducement next.</p>
   <p>President Schwab tell us that a cultured person is not so through self determination. Hurah! for Schwab! Yes, Schwab says that a cultured person, who for example, has taken student examinations cannot or would not strive with all his soul to only earn money. Hear ye the words? The greatest objective in the twentieth century is to earn money by the millions. Is it a dream or is it a reality?</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0522.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now there will be a workers' trust. Who has not awaited it? I was about to say, who does not wish its success under the circumstances? In a billion dollar enterprise the worker becomes a number only. Why, then, not combine the numbers? Why not count them like money? Yes! that is the thing to do now. Force will meet force. The Money Princes have carried those of small means to be ruined. The Workers' Princes try to force Workers to become their spineless tools in and for the winning of a planned victory against capital. Who does not perceive it, and deplore it, but the longer both are left at large, so much more difficult will it be to remain as one people</p>
   <p>If the giant organization becomes a reality among the workers, they will probably be able to force the Trusts. But only if they present a united front long enough, and are not too low in their demands. On the other hand increased wages are not taken out of the pockets of the Trusts. The consumer pays of that.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0523.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As to how this situation will be met no one can fortell. The whole matter is an affair that as yet lacks vigor and direction. However, let us consider American people have an usual amount of "common-sense," when confronted with serious social questions and problems.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
