<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-08-30">Aug. 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Candidates</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face pictures of Albert Swanson and Charles Gustafson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-08-30">Aug. 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN CANDIDATES</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face pictures of Albert Swanson and Charles Gustafson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the next primary election in Chicago there will be one regular and one independent Republican ballot. On the latter are two well-known countrymen, Albert Swanson of 2842 Shakespeare Street and Charles Gustafson of 1144 Newport Avenue. The former is seeking the nomination for Clerk of the Probate Court; the latter is a candidate for County Commissioner. Both are able, highly respected men, well qualified for the respective offices.</p>
   <p>Albert Swanson was born August 31, 1870 in Farlof parish, Skane, Sweden. He came to America in 1877 and to Chicago two years later. He went to school and obtained his business training here, and is and is how in the dry goods business at 2064 Milwaukee Avenue. His standing among his colleagues is indicated by the fact that since 1902 he has been trustee and president of the Milwaukee and Armitage Avenues Business Men's Association. He has been an active member <pb facs="5423404_1_1137.jpg" n="2"/>of several Swedish organizations for years and at the present time is president of the Society Nordstjernan (North Star), which he represents in the Swedish Home for the Aged League. He is also a member of the Svithiod lodge Mimer. This is the first time he has sought a public office.</p>
   <p>Charles Gustafson was born November, 1866 in Lekeryd parish, Jonkoping, Sweden. He emigrated to America in 1890 and came to Chicago the same year. For the last eighteen years he has been with the firm of Butler Bros, and since he first came here has been very active in Swedish-American social life. He belongs to the Maccabee lodge Norden Tent, and has been its president for five years; he is also a member of the Viking lodge Drake and of King Oscar lodge. For a number of years he was president of the Swedish Home for the Aged League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
