<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-29">Oct. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Go to the Polls!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-29">Oct. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GO TO THE POLLS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We urge all our countrymen throughout the land, and particularly in Illinois, who have the right to vote, to go to the polls next Tuesday. The right to vote is a privilege which should be highly valued by the citizens of a free country. It is, in fact, their duty to take part in the election of officeholders and lawmakers. In these difficult times it is of special importance that able men and honest representatives be placed in high positions, and the voters should conscientiously study the records and programs of the various candidates so that they may be able to pick the men who will render the best service to their city, county and state.</p>
   <p>Few national groups enjoy a finer reputation for high quality citizenship than do the Swedes, and there are in America numerous legislators and high officials of Swedish ancestry. A Swedish name on the ballot merits confidence, and often receives more votes than any other. For the coming election the Republican <pb facs="5423404_1_0889.jpg" n="2"/>ballot in this city contains several good Swedish names, and among the candidates we will especially call attention to Congressman Carl R. Chindblom and Harry Olson, chief justice of the Municipal Court. Both of these men are seeking re-election, and their victory should be assured, thanks to their recognized ability and past record. Other outstanding candidates are Judge Wm. E. Helander, candidate for county judge, Albert O. Anderson and Axel Lonnquist, candidates for the office of county commissioner.</p>
   <p>The senatorial election is drawing much interest. There are several candidates, but the leading contestants are the Republican candidate, Ruth Hanna McCormick, the Democrat, James Hamilton Lewis, and Lottie Holman O'Neill, who is the Anti-Saloon League's candidate. The two women are both counted as "drys," but Mrs. McCormick makes the reservation that as a representative of the people she will feel bound to the decision of a state referendum. And that is, of course, as it should be. However, this reservation caused Mrs. O'Neill to be put up as an opposing candidate. She is a good woman, but has no chance of being elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0890.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The votes that she receives will come from Mrs. McCormick's party and thus help the Democrat, Lewis, who is soaking "wet". And his election will certainly not help the temperance cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
