<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-30">Oct. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The People and Their Judges</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0927</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0927.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-30">Oct. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE AND THEIR JUDGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The People and Their Judges" is the main subject of daily discussions throughout Chicago and in all colonies of the foreign born at the present time.</p>
   <p>When a person's life is at stake or when he is in danger of losing his property because of an unreliable judge or jury, the latter's party preference should make no difference nor should the exposed man's party affiliation have any bearing on the decision of judge or jury. In other words, partisanship should be ignored and justice, pure and simple, should rule.</p>
   <p>In all elections we have voted for the candidate that we thought was the most impartial and just. The progress of our enterprises depends on the administration of such justice and on our confidence in the judicial honesty of the men we have elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0928.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In reference to the judicial branch of our Chicago government, we would have our readers think over and answer the following questions:</p>
   <p>Are trusts, corporations, and party bosses making a last stand effort to dictate the nominations and election of judicial and other candidates in their own interests?</p>
   <p>Or, are their efforts put forth to make it impossible for the people to elect trustworthy judges, thereby getting justice, instead of partisan selfishness and unfairness?</p>
   <p>Have you ever had a friend (a trust, corporation or party boss), who made inquiry into the political life of the candidate, when he knew the candidate was a little friendly to his trust, corporation or party boss.</p>
   <p>Have you noticed that corporation councils are all Republican in Republican districts and Democratic in Democratic districts. Also, have you noticed that they who enjoy special privileges try so hard to elect judges who grant them?</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0929.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is it not advisable for us to ignore party politics and vote for the candidate, who, we are convinced, is a man of dependable honesty dispensing justice to all, regardless of his party affiliation?</p>
   <p>Why should not we, the citizens, take the judiciary out of politics and elect men of real character and ability.</p>
   <p>Is it not more important to the average citizen to elect a judge they known is honest and just than to elect one because of his political or church status?</p>
   <p>In another column of this issue we present a list of candidates from our Swedish colony. Those mentioned in this article, we heartily recommend as men of unlimited ability and of an unassailable record. We shall look forward to a strong vote in their favor throughout our colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
