<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-02">Aug. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-02">Aug. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To many people a strike is chiefly a manifestation of the unreasonable and selfish attitude of the workers. They consider it an imposition on the innocent public, inasmuch as the latter is made to suffer for it. Whether they are employers or workers, they always belong to the great third party, the public, and are not directly involved in the conflict. These people do not ask whether or not the strike is justified, they are simply annoyed at being disturbed in the enjoyment of their own well-filled meat pots. They feel secure and satisfied, and fail to realize that in the long run a strike concerns everybody. The great public, in the final analysis, consists mainly of employers and employees, and sooner or later their own personal interests will be at stake as more and more industries become involved in similar conflicts.</p>
   <p>If, therefore, one will look impartially at the current struggle between the packing house workers and their employers, one will find that it also concerns <pb facs="5423404_1_0634.jpg" n="2"/>himself. One must take sides.</p>
   <p>We certainly do not wish to imply that the workers are always right, but in this particular case we declare that the packing plant owners are all wrong. They were paying the majority of their workers seventeen and a half cents per hour for doing dirty work in ill-smelling surroundings. They know that this is a starvation wage, and that the work performed is actually worth more; they also know that their profits justify a higher scale and still they steadfastly refuse every request for a raise. They were willing to increase the pay of the best paid workers, the skilled ones, but not that of the workers in the lower brackets. The strike was called, and we should not forget to give credit to the skilled workers who called the strike, not to gain anything for themselves, but to help their less fortunate brethren. This is a fine example of selfishness giving way to solidarity.</p>
   <p>The strike was called off on the condition that all strikers were to be reinstated within fifteen days; no discrimination was to be made, and the wage dispute was to be settled by arbitration. When the workers returned to their <pb facs="5423404_1_0635.jpg" n="3"/>jobs, about two per cent of them were taken on and the rest dismissed. Those who had been most active in organizing work--and they also happened to be the most efficient employees--were given the gate, while former employees, who had not worked in the packing plants for many months, were called back. The packers had shamelessly broken the agree went for the evident purpose of crushing the workers' organization, so a new strike was declared. The workers had to take this action, for the sake of themselves and their families, and also for the sake of the working class in general. They had to fight to obtain justice.</p>
   <p>We never had any use for strike-breakers, who, so to speak, knife the workers in the back. In this particular case they deserve our deepest contempt, and we sincerely hope there are no Swedes among them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
