<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-22">Sept. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Friendliness of the Catholic Church to Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-22">Sept. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">FRIENDLINESS OF THE CATHOLIC CHURCH TO LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Catholic Church with its many diplomats and intrigue-makers has always tried to maintain an appearance of friendliness toward labor. And it has succeeded in this even up to the present day. Every now and then the Catholic priests will state from their pulpits that their Church is the true friend and protector of the workers. The toiling children of the earth will find a safe haven in her arms, if they would only follow the teachings of the priests and adhere to the ways outlined by the leaders in the Church. And the Catholic clergy has always managed to find the way out of every difficult impasse it has gotten into and to steer its ship safely through all the reefs that infest its course.</p>
   <p>It sometimes happens to human beings, however, that they meet obstacles which can neither be surmounted nor buried. Such an obstacle the Catholic Church <pb facs="5423404_1_0581.jpg" n="2"/>has encountered in our day in its attempt to appear friendly toward labor. Before this difficulty the leaders of the church have found it necessary to pause and take counsel. This obstacle is the class-conscious labor movement and the sense of solidarity which finds expression in the organization of labor unions.</p>
   <p>Before this problem the diplomatic corps of the Catholic church stood baffled. First the clergy sent out warnings to their church members against the agents of the unions, and when this did not help, they undertook to keep them away from the unions by harsher means. Time and again, a ban would be proclaimed against the labor movement which threatened to undermine the hegemony of the Church and the clergy over the workers who were members of the Church. Those workers who had become impatient with the "unsatisfactory food" supplied them year after year by those who have charge of the welfare of souls soon came to realize that in order to win out in the fight against organized capital they would have to join the labor movement and take part <pb facs="5423404_1_0582.jpg" n="3"/>in the work of the unions. And this was the signal for the fight which is now going on between the leaders of the Catholic Church and organized labor.</p>
   <p>One of the priests who has recently drawn attention most strongly to himself in connection with this fight is the Reverend Father Ward of Beloit, Wisconsin. He stated, some time ago, that neither he nor any other priest in the Catholic Church would grant absolution to any member of the typographers' union.</p>
   <p>For us Swedes, of course, all this seems childish, and we think, perhaps, that this ban by the Catholic Church will have but little influence upon the progress of the labor movement. The fact is, however, that one retarding influence of the ban has been great. The Catholic Church still has an immense hold over its members and over those who have been schooled in its "truths". Yet it is gratifying to learn that this ban was first proclaimed against a labor organization which, we venture to assert, consists of as intelligent workers as are to be found in our country. The attitude to be taken by these men with regard to the ban will determine a precedent for other workers who <pb facs="5423404_1_0583.jpg" n="4"/>belong to labor organizations and at whom, sooner or later, a similar ban will be hurled.</p>
   <p>We hope that the typographers will make it clear that they fear neither the ban of the Catholic Church nor its threats; that they are men of free and clear minds, who are content to let the clergymen keep their absolutions; that they are ready to take their stand as fearless and free men in their fight against organized capital and its hooded servants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
