<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-24">Nov. 24, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">How Can Strikes Be Prevented</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0649</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0649.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-24">Nov. 24, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">HOW CAN STRIKES BE PREVENTED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question arises when one is alone or in company with others, how can strikes be avoided? How can a community escape those strangling expressions of unsettled economic conditions? But there has been either no answer at all, or an answer Which gave no real solution to the question. Under the present social and economic conditions,when people do not hesitate to trample upon the rights of others if thereby they be enabled to win some economic advantage, however slight, one can hardly expect to settle a struggle between capital and labor in an equitable manner. For so far from having common interests, the interests of the two factions are diametrically opposed to each other.</p>
   <p>Thousands of strikes can be prevented, and many have been prevented. But <pb facs="5423404_1_0650.jpg" n="2"/>the interests at stake in such cases have involved only a few workers and some employers of little import. In some factory or shop where employers and employes come in daily contact there is a possibility to prevent strikes, largely perhaps because the employer himself has been a worker and knows that the "laborer is worthy of his hire." When one's thoughts turn to the question of the possibility of avoiding strikes, the labor conflicts to which one seeks a selution are the large ones which threaten to cripple the industrial Hevelopment, such conflicts as the railroad strike in 1894, the miners' strike in the year 1902; the textile strike last spring, and now the street car strike here in Chicago. All these conflicts in which organized capital and organized labor have been opposing each other while armed to their teeth could have been prevented if the capitalists interested in the industries in question had found it suitable to accept the workers' proposals of settling the dispute by arbitration.</p>
   <p>The stock market aristocrats, however, had "nothing to arbitrate." To <pb facs="5423404_1_0651.jpg" n="3"/>them, the power of money was everything, and to this power they decreed that the hundreds of thousands of over-worked and poorly paid workers should bow. The money aristocrats demanded the right to determine for themselves the matters which held their interests, and they would not permit any outsiders to mix in the matters. But when straightforward sincere attempts to settle differences thus were met with disdainful refusal, then it is small wonder that the workers would strike. For after all, the workers, too, have rights in our capitalist-ridden society.</p>
   <p>But the conclusion cannot be drawn from what we have said above that the disputes between capital and labor, in all these cases could have been settled by an arbitration board, unless this board was appointed by the United States government.</p>
   <p>An arbitration board is usually composed of three members, one for each of the parties to the conflict, and a third, acceptable to the two factions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0652.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Nobody is so honest that he can not bought," is an old saying, and unfortunately, the saying probably is nearly correct. The representatives of capital have immense sums of money at their disposal, sums which might tempt even the most honest man. The representative of labor, usually a poor workingman, and the third member of the board, some man of the middle class, might be bought--and capital has won in its battle against labor... Experience has shown that the ordinary arbitration board is not satisfactory in confiicts between companies whose capital runs into the millions, and their workers. Not just because the workers lose in most of those arbitration settlements, but because every victory thus bought by the companies means a "nail driven into the coffin" of the general public; it means a "knife at the threat" of our industrial life and our national liberty.</p>
   <p>There is but one way in which conflicts of the type referred to may be prevented: the socialization of these enormous industries. With the railroads belonging to the people, for example, the railroad strike of 1894 would not have occurred; if the coal mines had belonged to the people, the strike at these mines in 1892 would have been an impossibility, and the <pb facs="5423404_1_0653.jpg" n="5"/>public would not have been skinned to the very bone by a few coal barons. And if the street cars in Chicago had belonged to the people, we would have no street car strike these days, and the Selicemen of the city would find time to protect the citizens and their comes from those parasites who resemble the corporations in this manner in which they rob the people.</p>
   <p>Not until the time when the nation and the municipality take hold of our natural resources and our means of communication will the far-reaching strike occurrences be prevented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
