<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-01">Dec. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Respect for the Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-01">Dec. 1, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">RESPECT FOR THE LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our country, as well as in other countries, there is a class of people who, whenever a strike occurs, whether it be a big or a little strike, will loudly complain of government by the rabble. The people of this class possess an astonishing ability to exaggerate matters and conditions which perhaps deserve a mild reproof. They are easily capable of converting a mosquito into an elephant and a mere brick into a two-story solid granite building.</p>
   <p>We observed some examples of this sort of exaggeration during the days of the streetcar strike here in Chicago. If some small boy threw a stone at a streetcar, it was rumored that the motorman or the conductor had been mercilessly slain; if a block of wood fell on the street in front of a streetcar, the story went around that the street had been blockaded. If some person sympathizing with the strikers placed on the tracks a stone weighing in the neighborhood of a hundred pounds, it was immediately stated that at least a hundred men would be required to remove the stone from the <pb facs="5423404_1_0646.jpg" n="2"/>tracks. If some fifty law-abiding persons were seen standing at a street corner, it was said that a mob of three thousand had gathered, ready at a word to threaten or to beat up a conductor or motorman. The newspapers of the East are also adept at telling about bloody encounters between the police and the "rabble".</p>
   <p>The sober observer in Chicago saw nothing of all this. He only observed that a strike was going on in Chicago; that the strike lasted two weeks; that not a drop of blood was shed on account of the strike.</p>
   <p>Yet those very people who shouted about lawlessness and government by the "rabble" could find nothing to complain of in the behavior of the corporation which did its part in provoking the conflict. They closed their eyes both to the illegal acts of this corporation and to its defiance of the officers of law.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0647.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Far be it from us to desire "the death of any sinner"; yet we cannot refrain from calling attention to certain illegal acts committed by the streetcar company.</p>
   <p>According to the laws of the State, the company is obliged to supply its cars with vestibules, in order to protect the conductors against storms and the cold. (In passing, it may be stated that a few years ago, a motorman was found dead at his most: he had frozen to death.) The lawabiding company has taken no steps to comply with the law mentioned. The company, furthermore, has defied the order of the city council concerning transfer tickets; it declined to comply with the city council's order to supply cars with cowcatchers until it had lost a number of damage suits brought in the courts against the company. Only then did the latter find it advisable, for reasons of economy, to comply with the order in question. The agents of the company have been found guilty of bribing members of the juries hearing damage suits involving the company.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0648.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When one considers all these facts, it would seem that the gentlemen of the corporation would be better advised to pocket their complaints and to stop crying about lawlessness and government by the rabble.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
