<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-01-19">Jan. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Against the Trade Unions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-01-19">Jan. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST THE TRADE UNIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week we quoted from an article written by the secretary of the Illinois Federation of Labor, Victor A. Olander, in which he called attention to the strong and dangerous movement which is on foot for the purpose of destroying the trade unions. He declared that it is chiefly through court orders that the powerful employers' associations are trying to shatter the workers' organizations. Certain courts, he stated, are willing tools in the hands of those associations.</p>
   <p>The situation must be pretty bad when the Federal Council of Churches of Christ sees fit to censure the conduct of the employers. The Council has expressed deep apprehension over a movement which is giving rise to industrial unrest and bitter relations between employees and employers at a time when the country <pb facs="5423404_1_0558.jpg" n="2"/>needs unified action more than ever before. The Council's statement voices the same sentiment and the same unprejudiced opinion as that expressed in the report of the Interchurch World Movement in regard to the steel workers' strike.</p>
   <p>Just a few weeks ago, the president of the Bethlehem Steel Corporation appeared as a court witness and admitted that his corporation refused to sell its products to business organizations that employ organized labor. This is only one example of the methods which are being employed to crush the unions. This particular practice is especially reprehensible because it results in the withholding of construction steel from the market at a time when there is a shortage of buildings in the country.</p>
   <p>One can hardly fail to be struck by the irony in the popular expression, "the American plan", according to which this country is supposed to be run. Does the lynch law operate according to "the American plan"? Thanks to "the American plan", hundreds of thousands of willing workers are now walking the streets in search of a job.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
