<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Much-Needed Reform</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A MUCH-NEEDED REFORM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The woman-suffrage amendment has now become law, and the women of America have finally obtained political equality with the men. This is, of course, as it should be. But there still remain injustices and unfair conditions that should be corrected, and our efforts in behalf of reform are by no means over. Voices are now being raised, demanding a new amendment to the Constitution for the purpose of invalidating the various state divorce laws, and in their place creating a uniform federal law which would be operative in every state in the Union.</p>
   <p>When one considers the numerous divorces granted by our courts in recent years, and the resulting marital scandals, the need for such a law becomes evident. The undersirable conditions cannot be done away with under the <pb facs="5423404_1_0258.jpg" n="2"/>present system. Not long ago, a well-known jurist declared that he could not see why a uniform divorce law was not as necessary as a uniform bankruptcy law.</p>
   <p>The federal divorce law might be administered by the local districts courts, as is the case at present with the immigration laws. If that is done, it will not be so easy to circumvent the law. Remarriage before the time required by law has elapsed could more easily be prevented; and it would also become easier to catch men who have abandoned their families, as well as those who, after divorce, have been ordered by the court to pay a certain amount of money for the support of wife and children. Some of these men try to avoid their duty by moving from state to state.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
