<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-10-19">Oct. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Drastic Liquor Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0208</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0208.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-10-19">Oct. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A DRASTIC LIQUOR LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Manufacturers and dispensers of alcoholic beverages are dissatisfied with the new liquor law which has just been adopted by the state of Michigan. There are several clauses in it which they do not like. The law forbids the sale of liquor to minors and intoxicated individuals, and furthermore, the wives, the children, and the employers [of family heads], as well as public authorities, are empowered to forbid its sale to certain persons. Concealing screens are forbidden in saloons, and the law makes it a serious offense to adulterate whiskey and other alcoholic drinks. It also provides that a second offender not only loses his license, but shall never obtain a new one; the decision in this respect is not left to the discretion of the licensing authorities. The law also determines the number of places in which liquor may be sold in each locality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0209.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It certainly should be possible after so many trials and experiments to formulate a law regulating the manufacture and sale of intoxicating liquors which would adequately protect the rights and interests of everybody concerned. It seems to us that the new Michigan law is not only a step in the right direction, but should actually be welcomed by the distillers and brewers. They should have sense enough to realize that if proper laws are not instituted to protect society against the evils which undeniably are inherent in the liquor trade, the public will demand absolute prohibition. The American people have already clearly demonstrated that it wants effective action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
