<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-04">July 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Real Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-04">July 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">REAL ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past week twenty-four real estate transfers took place in Chicago, in which the buyer, the seller, or both were Scandinavians. The list follows:</p>
   <p>S. R. Hunford to John A. Johnson, South 52 Avenue, north of Ontario Avenue. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>S. M. Gunderson to Michael Mahoney, Harrison Street, west of South 40 Avenue. Price, $850.</p>
   <p>E. A. Swedman to Adolph Rhein, Humboldt Boulevard, corner of Fairfield Avenue. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>G. Anderson to Wm. J. Fry, Johnstone Avenue, west of Sacramento Avenue. Price, $2,575.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0535.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>E. A. Larson to Ira J. Gear, lot 792 North Monticello Avenue. Price, $4,000.</p>
   <p>E. Austin to Anna T. Larson, Columbia Street, east of Leavitt Street. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>Margaret Dahlin to Louis S. McMillan, Prairie Avenue, between 60 and 61 Streets, Price, $25,900.</p>
   <p>L. Ekdahl to Peter J. Boylar, Seipp Avenue, south of 70 Street. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>First Swedish Building and Loan Association to Stanley Kurowski, Artesian Avenue, north of Fullerton Avenue. Price, $1,850.</p>
   <p>A. Carlson to Lulu A. Carlson, Erie Street, east of Lincoln Street. Price, $1.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0536.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Eric A. Larson to Edwin Austin, Hamlin Avenue, north of Huron Street. Price, $12,000.</p>
   <p>C. Lakberg to Nels A. Nelson, Haulina Street, south of 72 Street, Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>F. Schroeder to Laura Kelson, Dover Street, corner of Montrose Avenue. Price, $8,000.</p>
   <p>G. A. Jaeschke to Martin C. Anderson, Eastwood Avenue, west of hamel Street. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>J. Burz to Nellie E. Carlson, Spaulding Avenue, south of 51 Street. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>E. W. Vander Veen to F.O. Bergstrom, 111 Street, west of Princeton Avenue. Price, $1,850.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0537.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>W. Ralph to Ludwig Petterson, Indiana Street, east of Willow Avenue. Price, $3,800.</p>
   <p>S. Kruse to Andrew G. Swanson, Avenue H, corner of 104 Street. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>Patrick J. McDonough to Hans N. Peterson, 74 Street corner of Coles Avenue. Price, $1,250.</p>
   <p>J. C. Peterson to Albert R. Rhein, Princeton Avenue, north of 57 Street. Price, $2,300.</p>
   <p>C. A. Carlson to Wm. Konze, Justine Street, north of 66 Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>J. S. Hair to Anton B. Nelson, Francisco Avenue, north of Humboldt Boulevard, Price, $1,680.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0538.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A. Anderson to John Schultz, Maplewood Avenue, south of Potomac Avenue. Price, $8,500.</p>
   <p>J. Woline to Gustaf Lundquist, Nebraska Avenue, south of Dickens Avenue. Price, $2,200.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
