<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-25">Sept. 25, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Labor and Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-09-25">Sept. 25, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR AND POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our opinion labor made a big mistake by deciding to ignore politics. In America the people are supposed to rule and those who ignore politics neglect their own duty.</p>
   <p>If the labor organization had one member at the central soat of government of each state and in the national governmental body, the interests of organized labor would be more conscientiously looked after and more efficiently handled. Partisanship could then be used to the advantage of labor, and better laws could have been made and enforced. As things are now, the existing laws are against labor. To accomplish anything, labor is forced to resort to wholly or nearly illegal methods.</p>
   <p>Several small reform parties have been organized from time to time; had there been affiliation and co-operation with them, labor would have been able to attain many of the advantages so strongly desired. Had this been done, not <pb facs="5423404_1_0564.jpg" n="2"/>so many promises would have been broken by the big parties. Both the Democratic and the Republican parties have taken up reforms proposed by the Populists. Had labor joined with the Populists, the combined backing and influence would have put through many advantageous laws.</p>
   <p>A number of craft unions have decided to tie up with the Socialists, or, as it is known in Germany, the Social-Democratic Party. They say that both the Republican and the Democratic parties are parties of the capitalists; that is the reason why neither of these parties can or will do anything for the laboring class and the farmer. And what is more, the manufacturer, mine owner or railway magnate, wants cheap help so he can make some profit.</p>
   <p>The organization of a party is for the purpose of electing certain men to various offices and of having laws passed that are beneficial to the public in general and the party in particular. If labor, as one man, would join a party, they would be strong enough to have some authority, but scattered among several parties, they are helpless. If labor would enroll in one party they could demand and get promises from the candidates, which the party would not dare break.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0565.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>True enough, there are sections of this country where the workingman dares not vote according to his judgment. If he votes contrary to the demands of the employer, he may be discharged for his independence or the plant in which he and others, who have gone against the boss, work, may be shut down, forcing the employees to pack up and go elsewhere in search of a living. Keeping out of politics cannot change such conditions. In order to win one must fight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
