<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-06">Aug. 6, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Whose Fault Is It?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0762</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0762.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-06">Aug. 6, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">WHOSE FAULT IS IT?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The situation on the labor market has improved somewhat during the last few months but there is still much unemployment in the larger cities. Increased activity is expected next fall but many economists declare that no real and lasting improvement will be forthcoming until the general public regains its confidence and comes into the market, causing a more lively turnover of all goods.</p>
   <p>It has often been pointed out that the country's supply of raw materials and money has not dwindled since the crash of last year, and this is undoubtedly correct.</p>
   <p>A crisis like the one we are going through now is chiefly of a psychological nature. A few people have accepted the idea that we are in <pb facs="5423404_1_0763.jpg" n="2"/>for a period of bad times, and have succeeded in convincing others that this is so. The idea takes hold and spreads until we really have a depression of great magnitude. Here is an illustration of how such a crisis, or panic, as it has more correctly been called in the past, originates: An old woman enters a streetcar, followed by some twenty other people, all of whom are in a hurry to get to their various jobs. The old lady becomes confused and fumbles about in her purse for her carfare. Those behind her have to wait, and while she is still fumbling the traffic light turns, causing a long delay. The motorman and the conductor, as well as the waiting passengers, become nervous, and the regular flow of traffic has been temporarily halted due to the nervousness of one old lady.</p>
   <p>Some people tell us that unemployment is caused by overproduction, but that is only a half-truth, of which the building industry in Chicago provides a good illustration. For a number of years there was unusual activity in <pb facs="5423404_1_0764.jpg" n="3"/>this field, but right now thousands of building workers are idle. Is Chicago overbuilt? Not at all. There are thousands upon thousands of old structures in the city which ought to be torn down and replaced by new, modern buildings. A trip on an elevated train will convince one that at least seventy-five per cent of the houses along the line need repairs of some kind, especially painting. If all the needed work were actually started, there would, within a short time, be practically no unemployment among building workers here. There are, of course, a good many people who are forced to postpone expenditures of that kind, but there are also quite a few who can well afford them. They are just holding back, waiting for better times. There is no lack of money in the country, but those who control it consider it wise to hold on to it until the depression is over. This nervousness or lack of courage is evident everywhere. If those that have money could shake off that feeling of uncertainty, we would soon have good times again. Congressional resolutions and measures taken by the Government mean little, unless they <pb facs="5423404_1_0765.jpg" n="4"/>stimulate the general initiative of the nation.</p>
   <p>In the final analysis it is the sum total of confidence, energy, and progressive spirit of individuals that determines whether or not we shall have prosperous times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
