<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-11-14">Nov. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">For Better Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-11-14">Nov. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FOR BETTER SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few years, Chicago's school system has become somewhat discredited. The teachers are, as always, doing their best, and there does not seem to be anything wrong with the discipline. But the authorities who direct the affairs of the schools have become involved in scandals which have aroused the rightful indignation of the public. In addition, they have neglected to undertake an adequate building program. The result of this neglect is well known. Many of the old school buildings are overcrowded, a situation which greatly hampers instruction and also endangers the health of the pupils.</p>
   <p>Under such conditions, it is gratifying to know that the voters at last Tuesday's election authorized an increase in takes for the benefit of the schools. The proposal went over with a great majority, which indicates that Chicagoans are fully aware of the importance of maintaining the efficiency of our schools, <pb facs="5423404_1_0123.jpg" n="2"/>and that, in spite of the shortcomings of certain school officials, they are prepared to make sacrifices in order to secure a good public-school education for their children.</p>
   <p>It would not be good if the citizens were not aware of the importance of their schools. In a city like Chicago, where million-dollar sky scrapers are continually being erected by private individuals, there certainly should be enough money for much-needed school buildings. The right-thinking citizen does not object to an increase in taxes when he knows that the money will be used to improve the city's educational facilities. But he does kick, and rightly so, when his money is being wasted by unscrupulous officials.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
