<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-08-18">Aug. 18, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Judge Not, That Ye Be Not Judged</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editoral)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-08-18">Aug. 18, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE NOT, THAT YE BE NOT JUDGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editoral)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago, the secretary of one of the labor unions in New York was arrested and charged with having embezzled twelve thousand dollars. He was found guilty and was sentenced to five years of heavy labor. This occurrence was related in the press all over the country. Editorials were written to inform the public how wicked the leaders of labor really are. The editors' hearts were saddened and even hurt by the thought of the "poor, deceived, and deluded workers," who now had a chance to see a labor leader as he really is.</p>
   <p>To make matters worse, a thousand dollars of the embezzled money was to have been paid to the striking coal miners in Pennsylvania; instead this sum found its way into the pockets of the secretary of the labor union. Men who, during the days of the strike, were calling down blessings that were not of God upon the miners were now greatly distressed over the lot of the people in the mines, who had been so <pb facs="5423404_1_0489.jpg" n="2"/>cruelly mistreated. Newspapers which had never contributed a cent to mitigate the conditions of the strikers now experienced "a pang in their hearts" when the embezzlement became known, and doubly condemned this man who had already been given his punishment.</p>
   <p>We were somewhat lost in wonder at this phenomenon of tender expressions on the one hand and expressions of hatred on the other. Perhaps the reason for the outbursts was that the kind of embezzlement which came to light in this case is very rare in labor circles, and there was a desire to make the most of this case so as to frighten laboring men away from the unions by convincing them that their leaders were deceiving them. If such were the intention, the seeds of distrust that were sown fell upon stony ground.</p>
   <p>Now permit us to direct attention to another case of embezzlement, which has not been, and probably will not be, commented upon as widely as the one mentioned above. The treasurer of the aged preachers' aid society of the Methodist church in New England has disappeared, taking with him $75,000. This man, who is <pb facs="5423404_1_0490.jpg" n="3"/>supposed to have a considerably greater knowledge of Christian principles than the secretary of a labor union,... stole the money that was to have served as a pension fund for aged preachers. He is as much a criminal as the secretary of the union in New York, and we merely mention his misdeed in case some of our more religious-minded brethren in the newspaper field should feel the urge to warn church members against their religious leaders in the same way that they recently warned union members against labor leaders. This is in accordance with the rules of logic--or how about it, Kalle Swensson!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
