<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-03-16">Mar. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Carlstrom Is the Man</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-03-16">Mar. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">CARLSTROM IS THE MAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican John Ericsson League of Illinois is no longer what it once was, a champion of political equality, and it is not following the lines laid down by its farsighted founders. The organization was formed for the purpose of arousing the political consciousness of voters of Swedish nationality, and of creating in them a sense of unity and a desire to make their influence felt in the affairs of the state. We know that the task was not an easy one but, thanks to the able and energetic leadership of the late Edward C. Westman and his co-workers, much progress was made, and the League became an important political factor in our state. Qualified Swedish political candidates could always count on its support, and it should be said to its credit that many of the men who came from its ranks are now honorably discharging their duties <pb facs="5423404_1_0886.jpg" n="2"/>as legislators and high officials of this state.</p>
   <p>But the founders have now all passed away, and we are sorry to say their successors are not following in their footsteps. We have now in Illinois a gubernatorial candidate of Swedish ancestry, Attorney General Oscar E. Carlstrom, who is a man of extraordinary ability, and in ever respect well qualified for the high position. He is highly respected by the people of this state, and has the support of many prominent Republicans, among whom may be mentioned Howard P. Savage, former commander of the American Legion. Mr. Savage ranks Carlstrom first among the Republican candidates, and declares that he is the only one of them who has a chance of winning next November. One would, therefore, take it for granted that his candidacy would be endorsed by the Republican John Ericsson League when that organization held its convention last week in Joliet. But among the resolutions that were adopted on that occasion there was no endorsement of Carlstrom. That fact <pb facs="5423404_1_0887.jpg" n="3"/>discredits the League and its leaders in the eyes of many, who with good reason may ask themselves why it exists at all. By its action, or rather lack of action, this once great organization may well have pronounced its own death sentence.</p>
   <p>This refusal of the Joliet meeting to endorse Carlstrom is a challenge to the Swedish-American voters of Illinois. They should now unite behind him at the primary election, April 12, to secure his nomination. If he is nominated chances are that Illinois will have a Swedish governor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
