<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-10-17">Oct. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">A Present Day Luxury</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0823</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0823.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-10-17">Oct. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">A PRESENT DAY LUXURY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Will somebody be kind enough to tell us in plain words what an Ambassador really is doing to deserve his salt?</p>
   <p>As far as we can see, he is a great humbug, an expensive nonsense, a miserable being, and a hungry parasite. But we are ready to look at him differently if somebody will be kind enough to inform us what he is accomplishing to make him deserving of the political piece of pork. The Ambassador is a piece of inheritance from days of old. We have accepted him, and are paying for him exactly as we have accepted, and are paying for other institutions of former days.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0824.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To mention an example of the uselessness of Ambassadors, what good did Joseph Choate, United States ambassador to England, accomplish during the years in which he has held this office? He has drawn his salary. This salary is, of course, in the eyes of the plutocrats, too low, but for the people who pay the taxes it is plenty high.</p>
   <p>What has Joseph Choate ever accomplished which might not have been accomplished equally well by way of letter or telegram?</p>
   <p>If one looks carefully in the news columns day by day, one will find that Joseph Choate has been the guest of Count Lazymask, of the Marquis of DumbBums, of His Grace Lord Porridge-Proud, but how does this help the people, <pb facs="5423404_1_0825.jpg" n="3"/>the people who are paying his salary? Further, we learn that our Ambassador has had audience with King Edward VII, and that the Mayor of London has given a dinner in his honor, all of which may be very agreeable to Mr. Choate, but what does it benefit the people?</p>
   <p>Is there no other way in which the good relationship between two nations may be maintained?</p>
   <p>Once upon a time, perhaps, conditions were such that Ambassadors were not superfluous, but it is no longer so.</p>
   <p>Under ordinary circumstances, an Ambassador is an attachment, as useless as a tail would be for a monkey. A tail is needed by a monkey, and Ambassadors <pb facs="5423404_1_0826.jpg" n="4"/>may have been a necessity before humanity arrived at today's level of development. Now he is a mere piece of luxury, a parasite, a political vagrant, an attachment which every nation ought to get rid of. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
