<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-23">Feb. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Co-Operative Restaurant "Idrott"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-23">Feb. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE CO-OPERATIVE RESTAURANT "IDROTT"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual shareholders' meeting of the restaurant "Idrott" was held last Friday in the dining room of the restaurant. Forty-eight shareholders and delegates attended. New officers were elected, and the manager, Oscar W. Larson, was reappointed. Mr. Hellstrom was re-elected president of the board of directors. The 1920 report was submitted, and showed that gross sales for that year amounted to $55,000. The literary committee's report was also read before the meeting, and showed an income, including gifts, of $300 [Translator's note: A rental library, consisting of Swedish literature, is operated in connection with the co-operative restaurant].</p>
   <p>It was decided to buy $500 worth of shares in the Union Press [Translator's note: The Union Press is a Scandinavian printing establishment (possibly Swedish-owned) which specializes in the printing of Scandinavian language newspapers, pamphlets, books, etc.]. The meeting further voted to donate <pb facs="5423404_1_0729.jpg" n="2"/>$50 to the Swedish Study League, and $100 to Altheen [Translator's note: I do not know what Altheen is]. A request from the American Co-operative Association that "Idrott" buy shares in its organization was turned down.</p>
   <p>In regard to the question of the building of a "Peoples' House" in cooperation with the Norwegians and Danes of Chicago, it was stated by several speakers that most of the Swedish organizations on the North Side did not seem to be much interested in such a project. But "Idrott's" board of directors, as well as shareholders, were urged to keep the idea alive, so that it may materialize some time in the future.</p>
   <p>The sum of $350 was voted for the expansion of the library.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
