<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-03">July 3, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Privileged Saloon Neepers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-03">July 3, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">PRIVILEGED SALOON NEEPERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's wise Council decided that saloons would be limited to one for every five hundred inhabitants. According to this ordinance, the present figure being one to three hundred, the population of Chicago must be doubled in number before another new saloon may be opened.</p>
   <p>One may truthfully call this ordinance partial and discriminatory. They are fostering a monopoly, making privilege attainable by rich individuals. Of course, there are many large high class saloons, whose owners are well pleased with the possibility of putting small competitors out of business, while no more large competitors can open for a number of years.</p>
   <p>Unexpectedly and for the first time the brewers and the Anti-saloon League have agreed that the new ordinance will do more harm than good.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0533.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The City Council has no more right to stop some individuals from opening saloons than it has to dictate the number of doctors, lawyers, undertakers, meat markets, hack drivers, and so forth.</p>
   <p>The saloon keeper purchases the right to do business for a big price. Carters and transporters pay their mite for the privilege of hauling stuff around town. If the City Council has a right to say how many saloons are to be allowed, it also has the right to give the Wells Fargo, American, Adams, or Pacific Express Co., the exclusive privilege of transporting merchandise and so on in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We sincerely hope that the mayor will veto this foolish ordinance and stop the Council from creating a monopoly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
