<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">Sept. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Conference on Unemployment</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">Sept. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Conference on Unemployment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many people surely must have been wondering at the apparent indifference on the part of the authorities toward widespread and steadily increasing unemployment. During the last session of Congress not a single definite proposal was submitted to aid the six million unemployed people or their families. It is hard to believethat our Congressmen do not know anything about the miserable conditions which exist in many parts of the country because of unemployment. Thousands upon thousands of people are in actual want, and it should be remembered that in addition to the roughly six million persons who have no work at all, there are millions of others who are working only part time at reduced pay.
   </p>
   <p>Secretary of Commerce Hoover, who has called a national conference for the purpose of discussing the unemployment situation. It is possible that this conference will lead to some effective action, but in view of the [slight] <pb facs="5423404_1_0770.jpg" n="2"/> benefits accruing [to the workers] from similar conferences in the past, we confess that we do not expect much of it. What can such a conference do? What means has it at its disposal for putting into operation such decisions as it may make, and such measures as may be proposed for the alleviation of suffering among the unemployed?</p>
   <p>There are throughout the country a great number of public improvement projects which ought to be started and completed, but the Government at the moment is unable to finance them. When Congress convenes next month, ways and means of starting public improvement works may come up for consideration, but it is safe to say that months will pass before any definite proposals will come to a decisive vote, and by that time winter, which is the hardest time for the unemployed, will be practically over.</p>
   <p>A large percentage of the unemployed are war veterans, and government spokesmen declared recently that if the proposed bonus should be paid to them now, the treasury would go broke.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0771.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Under these conditions no effective measures for aid to the unfortunate workers can be expected to result from the conference called by the Secretary of Commerce. The cry of "increase production" was frequently heard immediately after the war. The result was overproduction and more unemployment. In view of past experiences, it is not likely that the conference will recommend that kind of cure now. Neither is it likely to suggest that more land be put into cultivation. For in spite of the fact that the cost of living is rising, one of the greatest problems confronting the Government right now is the surplus of farm products and how to find an outlet for this surplus without too much loss to the farmers.</p>
   <p>If the conference should actually urge employees to create more work at fair wages, and if the latter should comply with such a request, the result would undoubtedly be overproduction again. Opportunities for increased exports are small, and will remain so as long as the more important European countries are not in a position to buy more from us. They are in desperate need of increasing their own exports to this and other countries.
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0772.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Hoover is an able man, capable of doing great things, and the future will show to what extent the conference which he has called will serve to alleviate the distressing unemployment situation.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
