<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title><date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
      <title level="a">The Idrott Restaurant</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title><date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
     <title level="a">The Idrott Restaurant</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Shareholders of the Idrott Co-operative restaurant held their annual meeting February
    10 in the dinning room, 930 Belmont Avenue.</p>
   <p>The financial report showed that gross sales in 1921 amounted to $49,255.75 and that
    the net profit was $4,249.14.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar W. Larson, who has managed the establishment so ably for the last two and a half years, is resigning, and will be replaced by Mrs. Mathilda Mattson, who has been working in the restaurant for three
    years, and who is very popular with the patrons.</p>
   <p>This restaurant is not operated as an ordinary business undertaking; it is worth noting that shareholders receive no dividends from the annual net profit. One may truthfully say that it is operated for
    the benefit of its customers, and that its chief purpose is to obtain publicity and good will for the
    <pb facs="5423404_1_0722.jpg" n="2"/> co-operative idea.</p>
   <p>Profits are to be used to finance other co-operative undertakings. The pinciples on which this business was founded were further emphasized and expanded at this meeting. Previously, there were no provisions for the disposition of the property in case the restaurant busness should be discontinued. It has been decided that if and when this should happen, its cash and other assets are to be distributed among other organizations which are actively engaged in humanitarian work.</p>
   <p>There has been some talk of buying or erecting a building so that the enterprise could be under its own roof. This question came up for discussion, but it was decided to defer consideration of the plan until conditions are more favorable. However, the shareholders voted to open a new restaurant in the neighborhood of Balmoral Avenue and Clark Street as soon as a suitable place can be found. The organization then put the finishing touch on the meeting by demonstrating its humanitarian spirit: it voted $3,000 for the starving people of Russia. This
    <pb facs="5423404_1_0723.jpg" n="3"/>action certainly reflects credit on the
    donors.</p>
   <p>The Idrott restaurant has spacious quarters, and is a suitable place in which to meet friends. There is a good assortment of newspapers from Sweden. Coffee is served at small tables, Swedish style. Breakfast, lunch, and dinner are served at specified  times. There is also an excellent library of both Swedish and American literature, which is open to the public.</p>
   <p>All in all, Idrott deserves your patronage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
