<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-16">Mar. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Changed Conditions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-16">Mar. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">CHANGED CONDITIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is evident to any observer, and impartial investigations have confirmed the fact, that the present unemployment situation in the United States has thus far not caused as much disturbance and suffering as similar situations did in former years. Reports indicate that business has not yet felt any serious effects of unemployment, and consequently the number of people out of work has not increased. This gratifying condition undoubtedly is simply another of the many beneficial effects of national Prohibition. Many workers have saved the money that they would otherwise have spent for beer and liquor. These accumulated reserves make it possible for them to carry on during a period of bad times. The worker stays at home now, instead of spending much of his spare time and his money at the corner saloon regardless of whether or not there are bread and potatoes in the pantry at home.</p>
   <p>The elimination of the saloon is the greatest contribution that the present <pb facs="5423404_1_0240.jpg" n="2"/>generation has made toward order and real freedom in this country. During periods of unemployment in former, pre-Prohibition years, it could never be truthfully said, as it is being said today, that "not a single case of disturbance among the unemployed workers has taken place". The secretary of the Community Union in Detroit, Michigan, where there about 125,000 unemployed, gives Prohibition the credit for the peace and order which prevails in that city and all over the country.</p>
   <p>Except for the German newspapers here, which always support the beer interests, and a few of our Swedish contemporaries, there are not many publications in this country that still oppose Prohibition. Among those that do, is one of New York City's largest dailies, and that paper recently sent a representative to study conditions among the workers in our industrial centers. In his dispatch from Akron, Ohio, the reporter said, among other things: "I have found business and industry in Akron at a pretty low ebb, but have not seen a single bread line or soup kitchen." The newspaper in question would undoubtedly have been happy if it could have demonstrated that Prohibition had nothing to do <pb facs="5423404_1_0241.jpg" n="3"/>with the lack of feeding stations for the unemployed in Akron. But the reporter's dispatch ended thus: "This is certainly a happy contrast to the miserable conditions which exist among the workers in industrial centers of the 'wet' countries of Europe."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
