<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-04-06">Apr. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Unemployment Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0783</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0783.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-04-06">Apr. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thinking persons cannot help but feel the deepest sympathy for unemployed people, that is to say, those that want to work but can find nothing to do. But the general attitude toward these unfortunates is far from what it should be. In many communities the authorities treat them as if they were vagrants or even criminals, with the result that many of them are actually forced to become homeless tramps and resort to crime in order to eat.</p>
   <p>The season will soon be here when the wheat-producing states begin to call for harvest workers. In May of last year the labor bureaus of the states of Kansas, Missouri, Oklahoma, and North and South Dakota wired the Department of Labor in Washington, informing it that one hundred thousand workers were needed for the harvest, and offering from two to six months' work at $2.50 <pb facs="5423404_1_0784.jpg" n="2"/>to $3.00 per day. Workers responded by the thousands, a great many of whom were not fit for this kind of work, and those that had no money rode the rods to get to the wheat belt. When they arrived no attempt was made to distribute them where they were needed. Sioux City, Iowa, for instance, had called for five thousand workers, while only five hundred were actually wanted. The surplus was driven out of town with clubs, fire hose, and revolvers. In South Dakota several would-be harvest workers were killed.</p>
   <p>In most southern and western states, men moving from place to place in search of work are considered a danger to the community and enemies of law and order; constables and deputy sheriffs receive so much a head for arresting them. Strangers from other states provide the most lucrative field, for, as a rule, they have no friends or relatives who can come to their aid, and the treatment to which many of them are subjected defies description. It is therefore readily understood that those who have tried this experience once do not want to repeat it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0785.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the other hand, there are many opportunities for work in the country in the summer time, and it ought to be possible to work out a system whereby unemployed persons equipped to take advantage of these opportunities are to be assisted in doing so, to the mutual benefit of themselves and their employers.</p>
   <p>The unemployment problem has become more or less acute in many of our states during the last few years, and little or nothing has been done to meet it. The state of Idaho has led the way in this respect, its Governor having recently signed a bill providing for public work projects. The bill, incidentally, was submitted to the legislature by its lone Socialist member, Earl W. Bowman. It has now become law, and unless it is invalidated by the courts, it should serve to protect able-bodied men who are willing to work from privations caused by circumstances over which they have no control.</p>
   <p>This law is the most notable measure so far taken by any state toward the solution of the unemployment problem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
