<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-03-08">Mar. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Spy System Within the Industrial World</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-03-08">Mar. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SPY SYSTEM WITHIN THE INDUSTRIAL WORLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A while ago, a judge in Chicago issued an injunction against a striking printers' union. The injunction decreed that the strikers must not in any way whatsoever interfere with the persons who were taking their places in the printing plants. The union then engaged two girls to take down the names of the girls who were working during the strike. This, according to the judge, amounted to contempt of court, and the union now stands accused of this offense.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to discuss the question of whether the union was right in spying upon the strikebreckers. Opinions may differ on this point. There are reasons against spying; there are also reasons in favor of the action by the union. From the point of view of the employers, the union has committed a terrible crime, punishable by nothing less than imprisonment. We intend, however, to call the attention of the reader to the <pb facs="5423404_1_0567.jpg" n="2"/>great difference between Spy and spy.</p>
   <p>Taking for granted that the printers' union in question did engage spies, yet the union has simply done what the employers' association, as well as individuals employers, have been doing right along without being blamed in the least for their acts.</p>
   <p>In every large factory in the country, one will meet one, two, or more such spies. Frequently, these spies belong to the notorious Pinkerton league. In a few cases, there are some Judas individuals among the workers themselves. These spies are not to be confused with labor foremen, whose task simply is to see to it that the work be done carefully and quickly. The task of the spy is to keep track of those "socially dangerous individuals," who dare to mention about the matter of belonging to some labor union. Cowardly, the spy sneaks over to the non-suspecting worker, listens to his words, expresses his agreement with everything said, then hurries to the employer with the story of what the worker has said. The employer does not want to have "agitators" in his employ, and soon the fellow who <pb facs="5423404_1_0568.jpg" n="3"/>had imagined himself to be the citizen of a free country, with the right to freethinking and speaking, finds himself without a job.</p>
   <p>"Oh, well," you say, "he will be able to find a job with somebody else." Perhaps, and perhaps not. The system which was effective during the days of the railroad strike in 1894 is effective today, only more so. The name of the "agitator" is put on the blacklist, and boycott is declared against him by employers everywhere.</p>
   <p>No criticism is leveled by the courts against this type of spying. But when the class against which this spying is applied a single time applies the same weapon on a small scale, then investigation is made by the court; then the perpetrators are sentenced.</p>
   <p>If the employers are hiring detectives, or are inducing workers to spy on the activities of their fellow workers, it is considered a proper way on their part of "taking care of their own interests." If a labor union is <pb facs="5423404_1_0569.jpg" n="4"/>choosing some of its members to spy upon strikebreakers, then it is called "tyranny by organized labor."</p>
   <p>In vain do we seek the logic in this; in vain do we search for justice in this dual attitude. If it be an offense against the law for the labor union to employ spies, certainly the employers, who rely so greatly upon the spy system, must also be judged guilty.</p>
   <p>We do not like espionage in times of peace, but we blame the employers far more severely than the labor unions; the latter have copied the idea from the former, spying being the only means at hand by which the workers are able to defend themselves in the struggle that is going on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
