<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-10-25">Oct. 25, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Railroad Accidents or Mass Murder?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-10-25">Oct. 25, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">RAILROAD ACCIDENTS OR MASS MURDER?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that railroad accidents are getting to be an almost daily occurrence, thousands of Americans are wondering if anything can be done to prevent this awful massacre on our railroads' right of way. Millions of people are mourning the loss of their dear ones, who have last their lives in some train collision, while the railway magnates are busy calculating the profits on their watered stock, not bothering about ways and means of protecting the lives and well-being of their passengers.</p>
   <p>We venture to say that most of these collisions and other accidents could be prevented if the owners would only sacrifice a part of their enormous profits. If double tracks were built in those sections where the traffic calls for them, and if the train personnel were granted such working hours as would permit them twelve hours of rest out of the twenty-four, the number of accidents would be greatly reduced.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0474.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When one considers that most of the roads are single-tracked, the workers overworked, the tracks in poor repair, and any bridges in a dilapidated condition, it becomes evident that "accidents" are bound to happen. We prefer to call them murders, even premeditated murders, but the guilty ones are not being brought to justice. The following incident illustrates the condition: a short time ago a freight train collided with a passenger train in the vicinity of Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, casing the death of two men. After an investigation, the engineer of the freight train, Fleishutt, on blamed for the accident, arrested, and brought before a court. His attorney asked Jude Swartz of Horristoam to make it clear in is instructions to the jury that if it could be proved that the defendant was unduly overworked and tired or sick at the time of the accident, he should he declared innocent; but the judge refused to give such instructions. We could not, or did not want to, see any mitigating circumstances in the case, even though witnesses testified on the stand that at the time of the accident, both the engineer and his fireman had been on uninterrupted duty for twenty-four hours. The railroad company which had ordered Fleishutt to put in such unreasonable hours was not even censored for its conduct. Should he have refused [to obey <pb facs="5423404_1_0475.jpg" n="3"/>the order], the chances are that he would have lost his job. Due to sheer exhaustion, he fell asleep at the throtale, with the result that his train ran headlong into the other one standing on the track.</p>
   <p>When society permits private persons or corporations to own and operate railroads it is its duty and right to make sure that proper precautions are taken for the protection of the railroad employees as well as of the general public, even though such precautions cost the operators considerable money. We have not yet reached the point were money is valued higher than human life.</p>
   <p>The railroads should be compelled to build double tracks where necessary, and to reduce the working hours of their employees to decent levels. To be sure, this will cost money, but not any more than they can well afford, if one may judge by the enormous annual dividends that are being paid to stockholders.</p>
   <p>According to reports issued by the Interstate Commerce Commission, the railroads of this country have, during the last nine years, paid out in dividends over three and one-half billion dollars, and during the same period of time more <pb facs="5423404_1_0476.jpg" n="4"/>than half a million persons have been killed or maimed by these modern pirates of the traffic lanes. In plain words: They are the victims of the railroad owners' greed her profit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
