<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-27">Aug. 27, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Society and the Unemployed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0756.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-08-27">Aug. 27, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY AND THE UNEMPLOYED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lawmakers who feel their responsibility, and others who are interested in the welfare of the working people, have been shocked by the misery caused by the current unemployment situation. They have submitted various proposals, which, if followed, are expected to enable society to deal more efficiently with similar situations in the future. Plans are being discussed and resolutions adopted, but their sponsors neglect to address themselves directly to the Government, demanding help for those who are suffering now.</p>
   <p>It seems that under the present set-up nothing can be done for them. Society was not prepared for such a contingency, and could not handle it when it appeared. The result was a breakdown. Much damage has been done, and the repair job will take time. The Government, under the leadership of the <pb facs="5423404_1_0757.jpg" n="2"/>President, has intervened actively but not effectively enough, since industry has declined to co-operate, and there are at present no means by which it can be forced to do so. Our industrialists are taking it easy for the time being, and the present crisis, just like all the previous ones that this country has gone through, will be permitted to run its course.</p>
   <p>Several proposals have been submitted for a program that would aid in the prevention of extensive unemployment and diminish hardships caused by it. The plans suggested by the Minnesota State Federation of labor seem to us the most practical. They call for state or federal unemployment insurance, a shorter working day and week, and a public work program, which would be held in readiness until a period of unemployment set in. The Federation considers that unemployment insurance payments should go into effect as a last resource, to provide the unemployed with a means of existence, but steady work is more to be desired from the point of view of both the worker and of society. In this machine age it should be comparatively <pb facs="5423404_1_0758.jpg" n="3"/>easy to adjust working hours to the labor supply. According to the plans, the public works would be held in reserve for an eventual surplus of workers.</p>
   <p>A society which cannot provide work for those of its citizens who are willing and able to work has no claim to the loyalty of those citizens, and from their point of view it is not worth defending. Our lawmakers must not, therefore, push such proposals aside as soon as the present crisis has passed. Instead, they should adopt them or similar measures now, so that the nation will be ready to meet the next crisis when, and if it comes, or still better, so that it may be prevented from developing at all. Crises of this kind are more devastating now than they have been in the past, for, with the gradual disappearance of the middle class, an ever-increasing proportion of citizens is affected by them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
