<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-17">Aug. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Swedish Good Templar Veteran in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-17">Aug. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Swedish Good Templar Veteran In Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of C.E. Ronnholm]</p>
   <p>There are a great many Swedish Good Templars in Chicago, and one of the most prominent among them is C.E. Ronnholm, whose picture adorns the top of this column. For more than thirty years he has taken an active part in the temperance movement among the Scandinavians of this city, and has done much to advance the cause. A short biography of this veteran is of special interest now, when the ideas for which he stands are gaining in popularity throughout the country.</p>
   <p>Ronnholm was born in Norrland, Sweden, January 29, 1846--in the city of Gafle, to be exact. At the age of twelve he started in as an apprentice to learn the <pb facs="5423404_1_0182.jpg" n="2"/>tailor's trade in the city of Soderhamn. In order not to miss anything he even took a special course in tailoring and cutting at a trade school. Later on he moved to Stockholm, where he worked for several years. In 1880 he married Maria Augusta Fagerberg. Two years later they both joined the Good Templar lodge Carl Johan.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1887 Ronnholm and his wife immigrated to America, and settled in Chicago. After a short time he joined the Good Templar lodge "The Swedes of Illinois," of which he is still a member.</p>
   <p>Already, back in Stockholm, in 1885, he earned the World's Grand Lodge degree, and when the Scandinavian Grand Lodge of Illinois was founded here he became a member. Since then he has held many important offices in the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0183.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Ronnholm the temperance movement has had a faithful and energetic champion, and his fine humane qualities have made him loved and respected by everybody who becomes associated with him.</p>
   <p>For many years now he has been employed by the big tailoring firm of Delang &amp; Company on Michigan Avenue, and his home is at 3414 North Halsted Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
