<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-09">June 9, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">In the Land of Equality</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-09">June 9, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE LAND OF EQUALITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Give me not poverty, give me not riches, but grant me each day my required food." Thus prayed in days of old a man of God. Few of the Christians of our age are praying thus, and least of all, the hypocritical oil king, John D. Rockefeller.</p>
   <p>According to information from trustworthy sources, Mr. Rockefeller is the richest individual in the world. The Standard Oil Company, of which he is practically the sale owner, is worth $500,000,000. During the last few years, his income from this undertaking has amounted to $40,000,000, per year, or slightly less than $1,000,000 per week. His annual income from other business undertakings in which he is interested amount to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, so that he has an annual income of about 75,000,000. This means that <pb facs="5423404_1_0499.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Rockefeller's annual income is greater than the enormous amount which the famed king of finance of his day, William H. Vanderbilt, left at his death. Mr. Rockefeller as more cash than any ten money princes in New York taken together, including Russell Sage, the Vanderbilts, and the Goulds.</p>
   <p>Are we able to grasp fully what power is word of money possesses? Do we realize that by one move, a single act, a single word, he is able to extinguish the happiness and hope of thousands? Upon his word of omnipotence, industries stop their activities, banks close, workers become idle, idle, thus compelling them to beg for bread, though they were willing and eager to earn it by the sweat of their brow. Mr. Rockefeller is able to conjure a financial crisis whenever he may wish, and in his shrewdness he <pb facs="5423404_1_0500.jpg" n="3"/>gains on the crisis. He is the uncrowned autocrat of our country, ore danger us for our people than is the Russian czar for the Jews. If we realize this and act accordingly, then the day will come when we will not need to fear him or his like-minded brothers. If we come to realize that the oil wells which Mr. Rackefeller controls are the property of the nation, that our country belongs to the people, and not to Mr. Rockefeller, then the power of the latter would soon be broken. As long as the people sleep while Mr. Rockefeller is awake, he is in his proper right; for "might is right" in our age.</p>
   <p>Seventy-five million dollars per year net income! More than two hundred thousand dollars per day! To make a comparison between the income of Mr. Rockefeller and the wages paid to workers at the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in Philadelphia for a ten hour working day: according to public statistics, <pb facs="5423404_1_0501.jpg" n="4"/>the 90,000 workers now on strike in Philadelphia received before the strike an aggregate wage of $125,000 per day, or about $1.09 per worker. Yet the saying is that America is the land of equality!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
