<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-08-01">Aug. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Study of Languages</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-08-01">Aug. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE STUDY OF LANGUAGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This newspaper has always emphasized the importance of the preservation of the Swedish language among our nationals in this country--as a companion, so to speak, to their English. We believe the knowledge of one or more foreign languages is an asset to any person, and makes him more valuable to his country. Nothing widens his spiritual horizon more than the study of languages. The language of a country opens the door to the cultural treasures of that country. This is one reason why the immigrants have made such an immense contribution to the development of America. As soon as they mastered the language of their new country, they began to transplant the best in their Old-World heritage, the fruits of thousands of years, to their new homeland, which has benefited greatly therefrom. For this, America is indebted to her immigrants. Thanks to them, she is today the leader among the nations of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0109.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Englishmen and Americans are known for their indifference to the study of foreign languages. Their attitude seems to be that the knowledge of one world language is enough for anybody. But the smaller nations have found it more or less necessary to study foreign languages. However, of late, educators in this country have begun to realize the importance of the study of languages, not only the languages that are important in international diplomacy and commerce, but also those of the smaller nations, which are worthy of study for purely cultural purposes. A striking example of this attitude is the incorporation of the Scandinavian languages in the curriculum of several American universities and colleges.</p>
   <p>An innovation in this field is being introduced by the University of Delaware, which is sending a group of students abroad for the purpose of studying languages. Arrangements have been made for a group of eight juniors, led by a faculty member, to study for one year at French universities, during which time they will receive the usual credits. These students are thus given a fine opportunity to study modern languages, to broaden their education by 
<pb facs="5423404_1_0110.jpg" n="3"/>travel, and at the same time to maintain their relationship with their own alma mater.</p>
   <p>It seems that this procedure is bound to benefit everybody concerned. If it is taken up by other universities, and if it proves successful, it may well become an established practice of the American educational system.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
