<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-12">Dec. 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">How Swedes Are Being Fooled</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-12">Dec. 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">HOW SWEDES ARE BEING FOOLED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nowadays it is silly to be a burglar. There are so many other surer and more elegant ways of stealing that nobody but a stupid bungler would choose the old-time crude, dangerous way.</p>
   <p>On opening one of the large English Sunday papers, one will find long rows of advertisements for collectors, whose sole work will be to go about collecting money a few hours per day, for which work he is to receive $20 or $25 per week. When the simple-minded reader notices this, he thinks it quite splendid to get $20 per week, all the time wearing fine clothes for merely having to fool the people. He applies at the place of the <pb facs="5423404_1_0315.jpg" n="2"/>advertiser, and everything is declared to be in first class order, except for the little matter that the advertiser must have a couple of hundred dollars as security so that a collector bent on dishonesty would not be tempted to abscond with the money collected. Our simple-minded reader will frequently have saved a few hundred dollars, and he turns them over to the advertiser without suspicion. The rest follows in due season; the advertiser flees; the fine "collector" deplores the decay of morals in our time, and the lack of honesty in America, but not of his own stupidity.</p>
   <p>We have seen Swedes send money to all kinds of fakers. One person advertised for patents which he claimed to be able to sell at a high price. There was, of course, the item of $20 to be sent with the application. Hundreds of Swedes have forwarded their money as required and afterwards hearing nothing about the matter; perhaps they do not even receive an answer to their letter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0316.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The other day a Swede saw an advertisement about a partner needed with money to buy one half of a lucrative business. He paid $600 cash, and a few days later, he had lost it all.</p>
   <p>The Americans are not so often fooled in this manner. They say, "if anybody be able to impose on me, alright; let all the world have its try at me; my permission is freely granted; I admire those who can fool me."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
