<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-08">May 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Want to Get Rid of the Italians</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Swedes on Milton Avenue Want to Rid the Neighborhood of Italians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C (Italian)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-08">May 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">WANT TO GET RID OF THE ITALIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Swedes on Milton Avenue Want to Rid the Neighborhood of Italians</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The buildings on that part of Milton Avenue nearest to East Chicago Avenue are known as "Little Hell".</p>
   <p>Most of the buildings belong to Swedes, and until recently they were mostly occupied by Swedes. During the past few years, however, a large number of Italians have moved in, and the property owners are complaining that prices have fallen greatly on account of the influx of the Southerners. The latter, it is said, do not keep their places clean; they tear up the cedar blocks of the sidewalks, and they also bring the district into disrepute in many other ways, it is said. The property owners held a meeting a few days ago to consider means of improving conditions. Sven Olin [Swede] acted as chairman. At the meeting, it was strongly urged that the only way of improving conditions would be to increase the rent for all less desirable tenants, thus forcing these to move. One of the speakers mentioned that a few years ago the price of lots in <pb facs="5423404_1_0379.jpg" n="2"/>the neighborhood was $120 per foot but that now the price had fallen to $70, and that at present the lots were difficult to sell no matter how low the price charged. The meeting agreed to seek the removal of junk shops from the neighborhood, since the air is being contaminated by these shops.</p>
   <p>In the meantime the Italians of the neighborhood were holding a protest meeting against the attitude of the Swedes, and this protest meeting was held at Swea, Hall. The Italians were very angry and many threats were uttered against the Swedes, but finally it was decided to try to arrange matters through negotiation. "But", said the Italians, "if our antagonists are not willing to arrange the matter peacefully, then we shall find other ways to protect our rights."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
