<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-11-04">Nov. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The True Calling</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis of Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-11-04">Nov. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRUE CALLING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis of Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of late a movement has been started for the inauguration of vocational training in the public schools. The purpose of this training is to equip each child for its life work. The movement is unfortunate, and its objectives ill considered. A general training in industrial arts ought to be provided for all children in the schools. Such training will make the children more self confident, giving them a practical turn of mind. Vocational training for children, to be practical, would require, first of all, that the vocation a child is to pursue when grown, should be known in childhood. Such knowledge could be obtained only, if, (a) the child had sufficient knowledge thus early of its own abilities and bents, as well of the nature of the various vocations that might be open to it, or, (b) some method were known whereby some grown person, that is, the teacher, could determine the true vocation for the child. Experience and <pb facs="5423404_1_0058.jpg" n="2"/>experiments have shown that neither the wishes of the child nor the opinion gained from outside, through tests, is reliable.</p>
   <p>(a) Four hundred six children at the age of about twelve years expressed in writing their choice as to life work. Their written statements were preserved and, years afterwards, their choice of work as recorded compared with the choice actually made in adult years. Only five out of the four hundred and six had, as adults, followed the choice of work made when children.</p>
   <p>(b) Professor Munsterberg of Harvard has provided tests to show the fitness of persons for various types of work. Experiments made at a large university on the basis of these tests gave results that were very unsatisfactory, even ridiculous. Other attempts to determine, through observation,in childhood, what is the true vocation of the adult to be, have proven equally futile.</p>
   <p>The question of ones life work is one for the mature individual to determine. A broad course of general education and practical training forms the necessary <pb facs="5423404_1_0059.jpg" n="3"/>background for choice of work, and basis for the special training required for successful execution of such work; but such choice and vocational training are for the more mature years. To impose them on childhood, can only lead to unfortunate results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
