<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Primary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRIMARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The state and county primary election will take place next Thursday, and among the candidates are a number of Swedish-Americans. Below we will briefly outline the political careers of some of them.</p>
   <p>Samuel E. Erickson is seeking the Republican nomination for State Senator from the twenty-ninth district, and he is the only candidate.</p>
   <p>Erickson came to America with his parents in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> In his youth he was employed as a telegrapher, and later on as a clerk in the abstract department of Cook County. He served six terms in the legislature during which time he sponsored much important legislation, and in 1905 he received much publicity when he proposed that the State of Illinois donate $5,000 to the needy people of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Sweden. This marked the first time such a proposal was ever made in an American legislature.</p>
   <p>Erickson declined to take the pay which he had coming as a state representative <pb facs="5423404_1_1133.jpg" n="2"/>on the grounds that he already was on the state pay roll, which was a rather unusual attitude for a politician. He is a present a deputy shettiff.</p>
   <p>John A. Swanson was born in Chicago in 1874 of Swedish parents, and has practiced law here since 1895, his office being located at 79 South Dearborn Street. He is now seeking the nomination as State Senator from the thirteenth district.</p>
   <p>Swanson is in favor of more comprehensive primary elections and other reforms which are now under consideration. His candidature is a gesture in recognition of the large Swedish-American electorate in the thirteenth district, and he is endorsed by the Legislative Voters' League. His home is at 6842 Washington Avenue.</p>
   <p>Deputy Coroner William Ostrom is seeking reelection to the legislature from the third district. He is a member of many important Committees. He lives at 3136 Princeton Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
