<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-17">Nov. 17, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Street Car Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-17">Nov. 17, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT STREET CAR STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whenever the workers in an industry or a transportation system strike, they will know in advance that there is a class of people who will criticise them for this no matter how just the strike is, and however orderly conducted. But on the other hand, the strikers will have the undivided acclaim of a certain other class of people, no matter how foolish and unjust the strike be. The extremes touch, as it were. In order not to be carried away by one group or the other of these extremists, it is necessary to consider the matter in question from the point of view of both workers and employers.</p>
   <p>Here in Chicago we are now in the clutches of a big strike which might have been avoided, but which, unfortunately, has been started, thanks to the underhanded policies of one of the parties to the strike. Every just and clear-thinking citizen must of necessity line up on the side of the workers in the <pb facs="5423404_1_0658.jpg" n="2"/>present case, even though the demands they put forth for the solution of the conflict were excessive. The workers will be glad to place the question of increase in wages into the hands of an arbitration board for decision.</p>
   <p>To start with, neither the employers not the street car company would listen to the suggestion of an arbitration board at all, but as the threat of strike loomed, they realized that it was necessary for them to do something in order to gain the sympathetic attitude of the public. So the Company declared, through its representatives, that it was willing to place the matter of wages into the hands of an arbitration board, but the other matters in question could not be arbitrated since the Company was the "servant of the people, and could not arbitrate questions touching upon this service." This sounds well, of course, from a company which permits its passengers to "hang" by straps all of eight miles morning and evening. Wonders if an arbitration board would not be able to see as clearly as these directors of the street car company, who rarely if ever stoop to travel in the cars of their company's system.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0659.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The company knew in advance that the workers would not accept this "drop of mercy," but it wanted to gain time. The workers demanded once more that all the questions at issue be placed before an arbitration board. Mr. McCulloch, the representative of the company, requested time for consideration. The workers assented. When his answer was received, it was found to be an exact copy of the one received previously. Then the workers called a mass meeting, and at this meeting it was decided to strike. The company requested postponement, and it was granted. One week passed, and Mr. McCulloch requested an additional delay of four days. The conservative press warned the workers not to act in haste. They were advised to grant the delay requested. The workers had learned to know the real reason for the plea. They knew that Mr. McCulloch was working for time to import strike breakers from other parts of the country so as to be able to completely crush those impudent fellows who had dared to ask for more reasonable working hours and a slight increase in pay. So they replied through their representatives that they could only hold off action twenty-four hours longer. Since most of the directors of the company <pb facs="5423404_1_0660.jpg" n="4"/>are living in Chicago, it would have seemed that the twenty-four hours granted would give time enough for these men to settle the question of arbitration, but the directors did not find it so. And thus the strike was started--a fight which we wholeheartedly wish the workers may win.</p>
   <p>Our readers may have been told that the strikers have broken the contract which they had entered into with the company in January 1902, when the workers were granted a raise in pay of three cents per hour by an arbitration board. The fact is that both parties to the contract in question considered the award by the arbitration board binding for only one year, until January 1, 1903. The arbitration board explained, however, that the award was binding until September, 1903. The workers accepted the interpretation of the board, and it was not until after the date mentioned that they began speaking of a pay raise and of their intention to strike.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
