<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-12-02">Dec. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Free Church Bible Institute</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Gustav Edwards]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-12-02">Dec. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE FREE CHURCH BIBLE INSTITUTE</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Dr. Gustav Edwards]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bible Institute and Academy of the Swedish Free Church, located at 4211 North Hermitage Avenue, has an extraordinarily large number of pupils this year. The fall term started September 8, and since then the number of students has increased by seventy-three. [Translator's note: It appears that students are admitted at any time during the term.] And they represent various denominations, countries, and states.</p>
   <p>The academy includes a four-year high school course, which is recognized by the University of Illinois. The school also offers a two-year Bible course identical with the one previously given in co-operation with the Moody Bible Institute, and also a three-year seminary course. In the latter department the number of students has doubled during the last year.</p>
   <p>The institution is housed in a building which belongs to the Free Church, but <pb facs="5423404_1_0134.jpg" n="2"/>it is becoming crowded, and plans are being made for the building of an annex in the near future.</p>
   <p>Women's organizations of several Free Church congregations gave a shower at the school, and for the benefit of it, a couple of weeks ago. A large number of people attended. Among other organizations which help to support the institution is the Fireside Friends, which numbers some seventeen hundred members, all of whom have pledged a certain amount of money.</p>
   <p>The director of this school, the official name of which is the Swedish Free Church Bible Institute and Academy, is Dr. Gustav Edwards who has held the post for several years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
