<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-03">Dec. 3, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Bank Is the Heart of the Business World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-12-03">Dec. 3, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE BANK IS THE HEART OF THE BUSINESS WORLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the public we can say: If a panic comes you rush to the banks to draw out your deposits with the greatest haste: Does the business want the banks ruined in that way then the business world is on its own resources. When the bank cannot be of service to the small and large builders and building is not being done the building trade workmen are idle. When the manufactures cannot on pay day make a loan at the bank they must close. When the banks are in real distress, the largest part of the working people are idle.</p>
   <p>The bank is the business worlds heart. It draws money from the business worlds workers who have money to save, but does not want to hide it away elsewhere or lend it to individuals who at the time need money. The money earned by a worker and is to be paid today is usually put in the bank the day before. The loan made today for such payrolls must be paid tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Persons that understand the real mission and service the bank renders in the business <pb facs="5423404_1_0461.jpg" n="2"/>world will understand that it is of importance to all the people. All the people who are friends of good times are always friends of the good bank cashier because the bank in their commercial life is the same as the heart to the body. The heart is of course our existence. So with the bank's existence and the business world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
