<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-08-01">Aug. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-08-01">Aug. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rumor, the ever busy rumor, has information on hand that one or more envious, evil-minded, and mean, pigmy souls are the cause of the unsatisfactory attendance from the point of view of numbers at the concerts given by the Union of Swedish Singers in America at the Auditorium. It is rumored that the envious person or persons, a few days before the concerts had explained that all the tickets had been sold, none remaining. This, according to the rumor, was the sole reason why the attendance at the concerts was not as large as expected, or as might have been desired. We do not know who the persons, referred to in the rumor might be. Yet we cannot refrain from pointing out the ridiculous aspect of such intimations. A rumor of this kind ought to be totally disregarded, certainly not believed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the Lund University chorus visited Chicago, similar rumors were circulated, and four to five days before the first concert, the rumors had some truth in them. This, however, did not stop the crowds from coming. The rumor was not believed, simply because people did not want to believe it. Two days before the concert, all the tickets were sold, and the thousands who came too late were informed of the situation, yet they would not believe. Hundreds of them remained in line at the ticket window at the Auditorium on the evening of the concert, believing that they might yet be able to obtain a seat. Evidently, the Swedes are not so strongly taken by rumors that they would relinquish the hope of enjoying beautiful singing, simply because some Tom, Dick, or Harry, tells that all the tickets have been sold.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0337.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We wonder if the fault be not with the committee on arrangements, first of all. As everybody knows the Bellman festival at Riverview Park was announced on every corner. It was stated that this festival would be the crowning feature of the song meet, and that Mrs. Hellstrom would sing there. And the tickets? Only twenty-five cents!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
