<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-02-16">Feb. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Man of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0908</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0908.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-02-16">Feb. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAN OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Tuesday, February 23, primary elections will be held in Chicago, and the city's voters will pick their candidates for mayor. Nowadays the people themselves select these candidates, and the primaries are therefore now of much greater significance than they were in the days of the convention system, when the candidates were nominated by delegates who were more concerned with the intricacies of machine politics than with the wishes and welfare of the electorate. It is important that the voters participate in the primaries to make sure that the best candidates' names are placed on the ballot.</p>
   <p>For such a city as Chicago a mayoralty election is, of course, of the utmost importance, and the greatest interest is now centered about the aspirants to the office of chief executive of the city. Among the many candidates is Chief <pb facs="5423404_1_0909.jpg" n="2"/>Justice Harry Olson, who enjoys a national reputation as a jurist, and who is both respected and liked for his legal ability and personal integrity, coupled with a generous amount of common sense.</p>
   <p>Chief Justice Olson is a Republican candidate for mayor, and his prospects of success in the primary are fine, for he has the support not only of Republicans but also of the Progressives and of independent voters outside of the major parties. He is a man of the people and a self-made man, who is under no obligation to any special group. He possesses that independent spirit and healthy balance of mind inherited from his forefathers, and as chief justice he has demonstrated great talent for leadership.</p>
   <p>As is well known, Olson is of Swedish ancestry, and it is only natural that Swedish-American men and women of Chicago should be proud of such an illustrious compatriot. It is, therefore, entirely unnecessary for us to urge them to cast their ballots for him at the primary next Tuesday, and thus secure his nomination.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
