<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-02">Nov. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Beneficial Ordinance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-02">Nov. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A BENEFICIAL ORDINANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sunday closing of the saloons in Chicago constitutes a notable victory for the temperance forces, and the beneficial effects of the ordinance are already noticeable. Thousands of dollars that were formerly spent in saloons have now bought food and clothing for families whose providers were in the habit of spending most of their weekly wages for liquor over the week end. And what is more: Thousands of workers who would otherwise wake up Monday morning with a terrific headache are now able to report for work in good condition. The Pullman Company, for instance, reports that on the Monday following the first "dry" Sunday no accidents occurred in the plant; this was the first time in many years that such a record had been attained. The explanation is undoubtedly that the men came to work with a clear head.</p>
   <p>The liquor interests claim that the Sunday closing hurts Chicago's business in general, pointing out that the $350,000 which was spent for alcoholic beverages over Sunday is now withdrawn from circulation. But this argument is entirely misleading. It has been shown that in the large State Street department stores, sales <pb facs="5423404_1_0177.jpg" n="2"/>on the Monday following the Sunday on which the ordinance went into effect increased considerably over sales on previous Mondays. And sales of household articles during October broke all previous records for that month.</p>
   <p>Such data speak for themselves, and the humanitarian aspects, which we have not touched upon here, are of even greater importance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
