<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-23">June 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">As Points the Hand</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-23">June 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">AS POINTS THE HAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Day after day in long articles our conservative newspapers have assured us and the great class of toilers that Socialism never will gain foothold in the United States. "The Socialists' political doctrines and theoretical dreams will never find echo in the minds of the free American workers." "The teachings of Socialism are not readily applicable to our country." "In Europe, among the slaving, suppressed, and poorly paid masses, Socialism may seem suitable, but not so for our intelligent, diligent population, with universal suffrage as a universal right."</p>
   <p>These and similar expressions have found their way from platforms and pulpits, and have been carried to the workers through the press. But these conservers <pb facs="5423404_1_0863.jpg" n="2"/>of present day social and political systems have but a faltering faith in their own prophecies, for they have found it necessary to form circles and societies, political and religious, for the purpose of fighting "this evil," which "can never strike root among our people," but which, in spite of all said to the contrary, is winning new victories every day.</p>
   <p>--The Socialist element has not been idle.--</p>
   <p>Motions of socialistic tendencies have been presented at workingmen's conventions, but up to the present, they have been rejected, though the pluralities against them have not been large. A decided change has taken place of late, however.</p>
   <p>About a week ago, the great Western Federation of Miners, at the eleventh <pb facs="5423404_1_0864.jpg" n="3"/>annual convention in Denver, Colorado, by 125 votes against 20 adopted the following radical resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas the natural resources upon which man depends are being speedily concentrated into the hands of a few privileged people; and</p>
   <p>Whereas political independence is but a plaything and a phantom, while the toiling millions in the industrial field are slaves; and</p>
   <p>Whereas no man in the great army of workers can attain his full rights as a man as long as he must beg for employment from some other man; and</p>
   <p>Whereas capitalism can never be divorced from the ruling power, nor the wage slavery be done away with until the natural resources, machines, the <pb facs="5423404_1_0865.jpg" n="4"/>means of production and distribution have been taken from the hands of the few by means of the political power of the many, and made the common property of all to be employed in the common interest of all; and</p>
   <p>Whereas the Socialist party is the only political party anywhere which demands that the land, the machines, means of production, and distribution should belong to the people as a whole, and that the worker has the right to the full fruits of his labor; be it</p>
   <p>Concluded that the delegates to the Western Federation of Miners at the eleventh annual convention of the Federation reject the political creed adopted at the tenth annual convention of the Federation, convinced that the principles of the Socialist party, if applied would bring about better conditions <pb facs="5423404_1_0866.jpg" n="5"/>for woman, the queen of our home, and for the children, the budding sprigs of an emancipated generation."</p>
   <p>This may be a mere beginning of movements to come in a near future. Other large labor organizations are likely to follow in the near future. The example has been set.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
