<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-22">Sept. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The Right to Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-22">Sept. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE RIGHT TO STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have previously mentioned, the workers in about a dozen Chicago bakeries went on a strike some time ago, after demanding a nine hour working day. The employers responded by closing their bakeries, proclaiming a lockout which affected all the men in their employ, whether organized or not. Thus the struggle got under way.</p>
   <p>About a week after the beginning of the strike and the lockout, the employers brought suit against the labor organization and demanded damages of $20,000, the amount which the employers claim to have lost because of the strike.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, as we know, the workers have been considered as having the right to stop working whenever they chose, and as yet a legal way has never been found which would prevent the employers from discharging their workers and <pb facs="5423404_1_0670.jpg" n="2"/>Closing their plants. The suit brought against the labor organizations has found its way to the Supreme Court. We have yet to learn what interpretation this court will give to the law which bears on this suit.</p>
   <p>There can hardly be any doubt that the employers have lost $20,000 because of the strike and lockout. The question is, however, whether the employers are to be granted the right to recover this amount from the workers. If, as we have but slight reason to think, the court were to hold the workers responsible for the employers' losses, then the judgment in this case will become a precedent for hundreds of similar suits between employers and employees. Our judges would soon find no time for anything else but deciding damage suits in which first the employers and then the employees were the complainants. For we may reasonably assume that in a labor dispute the losses incurred are not confined to one side alone. All the lockouts which have been proclaimed and all the black-listing which is being done against workers who are undesirable to their bosses have not left the workers affected untouched by any losses. The planned persecution which some of the 'soulless' corporations initiate against wide-awake and class-conscious workers <pb facs="5423404_1_0671.jpg" n="3"/>has brought sorrow and suffering into many a home. But did those who have been persecuted in this manner ever bring suit for damages against their persecutors? Or did they ever obtain any compensation for all the sufferings sustained through the class struggle?</p>
   <p>With all this in mind, we dare to hope that a just decision will be reached in the suit which the bakeries have brought against their workers who are fighting for more reasonable working hours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
