<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-20">Nov. 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">A Countryman in Public Welfare Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-20">Nov. 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">A COUNTRYMAN IN PUBLIC WELFARE WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large number of our countrymen are occupying conspicuous positions in Chicago in various lines of endeavor.</p>
   <p>Such a man, a short outline of whose life history we will forthwith present, is our popular compatriot County Agent John W. Belmont, who early in life set out on a career of public and political service, after first having learned the printing trade.</p>
   <p>Mr. Belmont was born in Jonkoping, Sweden, on December 14, 1833, and came to Chicago with his parents at the age of four. Ever since he has made his home on the Northwest Side or in Lake View. He attended Chicago's public schools and the Chicago Athenaeum, and learned the printing trade. For some time he worked as a foreman in Missionsvennen's (Friend of the missions)printing shop, until in 1882 he opened his own establishment on the South Side.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He served for some time as Grand Jury Clerk, later for a period of six years, as Deputy Circuit Clerk, and subsequently as County Commissioner for two years. During this latter period he was also chairman of the court house committee. On January 11, 1905, president Brundage appointed him County Agent.</p>
   <p>In 1898 he married Miss Catharina Aiken; they have one child, and live at 811 Clifton Avenue. In his position, which entails great responsibilities, Mr. Belmont has ample opportunity to demonstrate his outstanding humane qualities, together with his keen judgment and understanding of human nature.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
