<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-04-13">Apr. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A Revolt against the Mighty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-04-13">Apr. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A REVOLT AGAINST THE MIGHTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Leaders of the progressive element in Congress, who succeeded in preventing the introduction of a general sales tax, have been denounced by the conservative press for not having sense enough to realize that such a sales tax would be the best possible means of balancing the Federal budget. From the point of view of these critics such logical means as, for instance, tax on property and higher income taxes, would not be desirable. It is true that they probably would not bring about the desired result, for those who have wealth are smart enough to withdraw their money from business and industry and invest in tax exempt securities.</p>
   <p>As a result of the long drawn out depression those of the middle class who <pb facs="5423404_1_0395.jpg" n="2"/>still have money left for investment are easily counted. Only the wealthy have capital to invest in business and industry, and they have already placed it to the best advantage. A general sales tax is practically the only means left now of squeezing more taxes out of the poor. It seems clear that if the budget is to be balanced and no more taxes can be obtained from the overworked sources the rich will have to cough up, and here is where the shoe pinches.</p>
   <p>The progressives in Congress, with their lack of organization and unity, have done the best they could to champion the cause of the underprivileged masses. Their opposition to the sales tax was in effect a revolt against the mighty financial interests, who control the major political parties. The banking magnates and industrial tycoons, through their greed and lack of foresight during the good years, did much to bring about the depression, <pb facs="5423404_1_0396.jpg" n="3"/>and now they also want to chart the nation's course during the period of reconstruction. Time and again they have put their stamp on political decisions, and it is easily recognized, for they favor everything which tends to place the economic burden on the backs of those who are already poor, while they escape with their wealth intact.</p>
   <p>They have been preaching optimism, for it is fairly easy to be optimistic when one has plenty of money, and they even expected the unemployed to share their happy outlook in the certainty that good times would soon return. And when finally the suffering became too great and widespread to be endured because optimism, be it ever so strong, will not feed people, these leaders advocated private charity, and if the aid thus given by goodhearted citizens was not sufficient, the balance was to be contributed from the revenue of local governments. Under such procedure the rich would still remain safeguarded, and the Federal Government would not be called upon to provide work for the unemployed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0397.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The result was increased unemployment, more bank failures, and less confidence in the present administration. The capitalists began to get scared. Security values dropped, and distribution of dividends ceased. Before long those who had been so deeply concerned about the demoralizing effect of Federal aid to the unemployed began to plead for just such help for themselves. The result was the creation of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation, which had at its disposal two billion dollars for the purpose of bolstering deserving big business and financial enterprises which were on the verge of collapse. The poor were left to find succor where they might.</p>
   <p>When it became clear that increased revenue was necessary in order to balance the budget, the Democrats played up to the capitalists by proposing a sales tax. This was also what the Republican leaders wanted, but they <pb facs="5423404_1_0398.jpg" n="5"/>lacked the courage to come out in the open with their plans. However, thanks to the opposition of the progressive group in Congress, the sales tax measure was defeated. This action is a promising sign of the times, for it shows that we have legislators who have the will and the courage to wage a battle in behalf of the small man and against the mighty financial interests. Unfortunately the progressives in Congress have no strong united organization behind them, and isolated effort often become frustrated. But they are doing the best they can under the circumstances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
