<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-31">Aug. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Knowledge Is Power</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-31">Aug. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">KNOWLEDGE IS POWER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In thousands of homes throughout the country a very important question is being discussed at this time of the year. It is the old recurrent one, whether or not the son or the daughter of the family is to return to school for the coming term, or join the ranks of the wage earners, with such educational equipment as he or she already has acquired. The decision is of the utmost importance not only to the youngster but to the family and society as well. Our future as a nation is influenced by it.</p>
   <p>In making such a decision the economic resources of the family must be considered, but we would say that, if it is at all possible, the young ones should be encouraged and permitted to continue their studies. Few people will deny the truth of the old adage that knowledge is power, and particularly in this age there can be no doubt that the young men or women with a <pb facs="5423404_1_0061.jpg" n="2"/>solid and well-rounded education have better prospects of winning their battles in the struggle for existence than have those that lack this equipment. Even if it does require sacrifices the young should attend school as long as possible,for it helps them get more out of life both materially and, what is more important, spiritually.</p>
   <p>The world needs educated men and women to fill the positions of responsibility and leadership. There is always plenty of room for leaders, while there is congestion among those that can only follow. Our public schools and institutions of higher learning offer young people the best tools with which to carve their future happiness and well-being.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
