<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-10-07">Oct. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Sunday Closing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-10-07">Oct. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE SUNDAY CLOSING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Hale Thompson has done what none of his predecessors dared; he has ordered the police to enforce the old law about the closing of saloons on Sundays, and has notified the dealers that they will be deprived of their liquor licenses if they defy the order.</p>
   <p>The matter had been discussed during the election campaign, and Mr. Thompson stated at that time, on inquiry, that he stood for the enforcement of every law. In spite of this, the closing order came as a surprise both to the "Wet" and the "Dry". Carter Harrison, the former mayor, on being interviewed about the order said that it surprised him greatly; that he did not believe the majority of the people in Chicago wanted the law enforced; that Mayor Thompson ought to have held a referendum in Chicago on the question of Sunday closing before issuing the order.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have never had great respect for Carter H. Harrison's intelligence, and his statement as mentioned shows that our opinion was correct. It must be clear to all thinking people that it would be destructive of all order in society if a referendum were to be undertaken to decide whether a given law was to be enforced. Such referendum would make all law-giving worthless. Under our system, a law must be enforced as long as it is law, and the law officers have no right to lay down on the enforcement.</p>
   <p>If referendum is wanted in the present matter, the question to be put to the people could only be as to whether the closing law should be abolished. Such a question may be put to the people of Chicago, but the decision in the matter would rest with the legislature. In order to give the people of Chicago the right to determine the question, the legislature would have to carry through Mayor Thompson's bill for home rule for Chicago. It was said that the so called" Deneen" men in the legislature had received orders to desist from <pb facs="5423404_1_0244.jpg" n="3"/>voting in the matter and thus the bill fell through. If Mayor Thompson's proposal had become law then would Chicago have won the right to self-rule not merely in regard to the question of liquor, but in all questions of importance only for this city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
