<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-10-29">Oct. 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">County Commissioner Carl R. Chindblom</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-10-29">Oct. 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">COUNTY COMMISSIONER CARL R. CHINDBLOM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before the next issue of the Swedish-American is published, our readers will have voted at the big election. We hope that among the victors we will find our countryman, Carl R. Chindblom, as you already know, he has, for the past two years, held the office for which the Republican's again are nominating him. During his term of service, he has shown an energy and honesty which not every man can equal.</p>
   <p>Chindblom is a man who has always worked for the interest of Swedish-Americans. He possesses a liberal foresight, and strong integrity, which have made enemies for him, but only among those who do not possess these virtues. All who want to know what is right, should as one man support our countryman on Election day. We have long known Chindblom both as a man and as a public servant. He has steadily grown stronger in both respects.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0921.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is a Swedish-American in the fullest meaning of the word. He was born on the North Side thirty-eight years ago. His parents taught him that it was an honor to be a Swede, and to be able to speak the Swedish language. Few, if any, born in this country can speak our language as accurately as Chindblom. He is a fluent speaker and speaks Swedish and English with equal ease.</p>
   <p>During his two years as County Commissioner, he has served on special committees of research, to the full satisfaction of all concerned. No Swede should disregard him on Election day. He is worthy of your vote. Give it to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
