<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-25">Sept. 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Injunctions in Labor Disputes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-25">Sept. 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">INJUNCTIONS IN LABOR DISPUTES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is high time that working conditions in the textile and clothing industry in the East be investigated so that the American public may be fully informed of what is going on. It is already well known that wages are pitifully low, and that the strikes are caused by the workers' determination to obtain higher pay. But what is the real cause of the great bitterness which characterizes these struggles, and what is it that sets worker against worker and often results in violent and bloody encounters?</p>
   <p>The employers often resort to the so-called injunction in order to discourage the workers' fighting spirit. A short time ago a federal judge in Pennsylvania issued a decree forbidding the garment workers' union to carry on organization work in his district. Just at that time a strike was in progress in the Philadelphia garment industry, and it would not be surprising if the employers should <pb facs="5423404_1_0608.jpg" n="2"/>decide to seek the aid of the courts to prevent union organizing efforts.</p>
   <p>Senator La Follette of Wisconsin suspects that something is wrong, and has introduced a resolution in the Senate calling for an investigation of the circumstances under which that injunction order was issued. We compliment the Senator on his initiative. It is to the advantage of the workers that full light be thrown on such cases, and that they be subjected to impartial scrutiny, for their cause is a just one and they need not fear the light. Moreover, an aroused public opinion is the best ally they can have, but it demands clarification of the issues before it takes sides.</p>
   <p>It is, of course, quite possible that this injunction was not issued for the purpose of helping the employers break the strike. The judge may have had more valid reasons for his decision. But if it is found that he resorted to this measure in order to prevent the workers from organizing for self-protection, then both he and the employers should be strongly rebuked.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
