<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-12">Nov. 12, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Election Results</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-12">Nov. 12, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION RESULTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The results of the election which took place November 4, show that the American electorate has changed its mind since the presidential election in 1928, when the Republican party won a decisive victory. Hoover was elected by an overwhelming majority, and the voters gave the Republicans a wide margin both in the Senate and in the House of Representatives. But at this writing it looks as if the Democrats will control both houses of the Congress.</p>
   <p>There are several reason for this turnabout by the voters. The rain causes of it are undoubtedly the distressing unemployment situation, and the hard times which have hit the entire nation. People are inclined to blame such upheavels on the administration and on the party which is in power. The current situation is no exception, and the Republican defeat was a logical outcome.</p>
   <p>It is evident that prohibition and the Volstead Act have also played an important <pb facs="5423404_1_0230.jpg" n="2"/>role in this election. The Republican campaign leader, Senator Fess, of Ohio, declared that prohibition was not an issue this time, but a "wet" Democratic senator was nevertheless elected from his own state. "Wet" Democratic senators were victorious in several other states, among which were New York and Illinois, where they won by majorities which took on the proportions of landslides.</p>
   <p>Especially significant is the result in Illinois, which is ordinarily a Republican state. But its voters elected as senator, the Democrat Lewis, an outspoken opponent of prohibition, who during the campaign declared that if he were elected senator he would do everything in his power to have the prohibition amendment repealed. In spite of that he received a majority of between seven and eight hundred thousand votes, and thanks to his great majority in Chicago and Cook County, most Democratic candidates in that part of the state were swept into office.</p>
   <p>The deplorable local conditions in Cook County also contributed to the <pb facs="5423404_1_0231.jpg" n="3"/>Republican defeat. The waste of public money has increased the tax burden, especially for the small home owners of Chicago. To the many other grievances must now be added the local unemployment situation and the unwillingness or inability of city and county authorities to do anything about it. The people had simply lost confidence in the administration and wanted a change. The political power in Cook County is now in the hands of the Democrats, and the future will show whether or not they are able and willing to use it for the benefit of the community and the welfare of all the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
