<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-08">Sept. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The Police Receive Donations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-08">Sept. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLICE RECEIVE DONATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The other day, the chief of police received from the Illinois Malleable Iron Company a gift of one hundred dollars to be applied to the pension fund of the Chicago police force. This donation came as a grateful acknowledgment of the work done by the members of the police during the recent strike at the company's plant.</p>
   <p>This occurrence, insignificant in itself, gives rise to a series of reflections which culminate in the question: Is it right for the police to accept donations from such quarters as the one mentioned? Of course, anyone is free to draw his own conclusions, but the occurrence is certainly not without significance to the workers in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>As we see the case, the following aspects appear: Capital and labor, each <pb facs="5423404_1_0673.jpg" n="2"/>seeking to promote its own interests, come into conflict. The workers stop working, and the plant is closed. An injunction is issued against the workers which prohibits them from speaking to people who come to seek work at the plant, and also forbids them from congregating in an open field in the neighborhood of the factory. Police officers are dispatched to keep order. The strike, continues for weeks. Under the protection of the police, strikebreakers start working in the factory. The strikers seek to persuade the strikebreakers to quit working; as a result, they are arrested and taken away by the police. The strike comes to an end, the workers have lost out. Thereupon the manufacturer whose plant is involved sends a letter of thanks to the police, and donates one hundred dollars to the pension fund of the Chicago police force.</p>
   <p>Is there any impartial individual who dares to deny that such an act places our police force in an unfavorable position before the public? Does it not appear as though the officers must have been playing a partisan role, acting in the interests of the manufacturer? Is it not an attempt to bribe the police <pb facs="5423404_1_0674.jpg" n="3"/>officials and every man on the force so that they would play a similar role in the future? We believe that this is the case, and we believe that in order to remove every suspicion in this direction the money donated by the Illinois Malleable Iron Company to the police pension fund ought to be returned to the donors.</p>
   <p>It is easy to show that the company donated the money in question for selfish reasons. If they had wanted to show their appreciation of faithful execution of duty and superb courage in the face of danger manifested by police officers, why did they not send a gift to the pension fund at the time when the brave Officers Devine and Penell fell victims to the bullets of murderers? These two men displayed a courage far greater and nobler than that shown by their comrades while protecting strikebreakers who were threatened by no danger whatever.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0675.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As we have already said, if the police officials desire to rid themselves of the indirect accusation brought against them by the Illinois Malleable Iron Company as a result of the donation made by the company to the pension fund, then the gift must be returned to the donors. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
