<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-09">Mar. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">For It</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-09">Mar. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> FOR IT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>England is complaining that American coal is driving the English out of the European markets. The American product is selling at Copenhagen, Rotterdam and other centers at <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>10.50 a ton, while the price of English coal is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>12 a ton. However, even more remarkable, is the fact that American coal is sold in Holland and other faraway countries for fifty cents a ton less than the price being charged right here in Chicago, and to all appearances the dealers are not at all facing ruin. Such a situation may look like a mystery, but it is not. It is easily explained, when placed under the proper light.</p>
   <p>A Senate committee, which was appointed to investigate the coal situation has found that more than twenty Pocahontas coal corporations in West Virginia made millions of dollars last year. During the three first quarters <pb facs="5423404_1_0435.jpg" n="2"/>of 1920 one of the corporations, capitalized at $178,000, produced 122,000 tons of coal, and made a profit of $478,000. None of these companies had a profit of less than 35 per cent on the invested capital, and in the most extreme case it reached 67 per cent a year. These profits were taken out of the packets of American consumers.</p>
   <p>There is now a bill before Congress proposing regulation of the entire American coal industry. The bill requires that both mine owners and coal dealers be licensed, and it authorizes the President to determine maximum prices and take other regulatory measures; it also empowers the President to cancel the licences of those who do not conduct their businesses in accordance with the law. The bill further paves the way for the Government to take over the mines, if necessary, and sell the coal directly to the consumers.</p>
   <p>Such regulation has been suggested several times before. Already, during the war, the Government had the authority to put them into effect, but <pb facs="5423404_1_0436.jpg" n="3"/>nothing has been done, and the coal barons continue to charge all that the trade will stand--fifty cents more per ton in Chicago than in Rotterdam.</p>
   <p>Congress should take action now to correct this preposterous state of affairs. If it does not do so, one is forced to conclude that our elected representatives put the private and selfish interests of the mine owners before those of the American public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
