<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-08-04">Aug. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Oscar R. Hillstrom</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_1150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_1150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-08-04">Aug. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">OSCAR R. HILLSTROM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the primary next Saturday our landsman Oscar Hillstrom of Kensington will be waiting for votes as a Republican candidate for county commissioner. His hope for the nomination will be put to shame as every Republican in his Ward, the 33rd are pledged to him. He is without a doubt the strongest candidate the Republicans could nominate. The Calumet Weekly Index local paper in the Calumet region has worked hard for him and have written that he is one of the thriftiest Swedes in this part of the land.</p>
   <p>Oscar Hillstrom is a smolening by birth,born in 1862 and came to the W.S. in 1883 at the age of twenty-one years. He lived in Indiana at first but in 1886 he moved to Pullman and worked a few years in the Pullman shops where he became a department manager. But Hillstrom wanted to be in business for himself. He did not want to be a hired hand. He there fore set up and established himself in business and has done well as all thrifty people do. He has built as fine a building as we find in Kensington. He is not exactly a child in politics; he has during the past twenty years taken a strong interest in the locality and was deputy sheriff and later <pb facs="5423404_1_1151.jpg" n="2"/>receiving teller in the country treasurer's department. Besides that he is a strong society friend, a member of Free Masons, Knights of Pythias, Royal League and North American Union. He seems to find time in all affairs, political and the various societies work. But he is as was mentioned before a smolening and has a good portion of the energy that those people seem to own. The Republicans in his Ward have not put forth an opposing candidate as no one would want to compete with Hillstrom who is both well known and respected by large and small in the Ward. This is the first time he has been a candidate for an office of importance, so remember him on August 8.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
