<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-04-25">Apr. 25, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Scandinavians Win Praise</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1883-04-25">Apr. 25, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCANDINAVIANS WIN PRAISE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The editorial of the Swedish Tribunen of April 18th in regard to the number of Swedes in the United States has won the attention of many American and German newspapers in Chicago. Not one of them are in doubt as to about our calculation at the number of the Swedish-Americans is at least twice as large as the census shows.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Times has an editorial on the matter and says that the census always has been unreliable, but the office of the census ought to know, say the Times, that the work of the census-taking cost the country a lot of money, and continues:</p>
   <p>"The Scandinavians to not force themselves to secure favors. They are tolerant and broadminded. They come here not only to stay but also to adapt themselves to our customs, to speak our language, and to love our institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0392.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They have never requested that their language be introduced in the public schools. A large number of the Scandinavians attend the evenin school to learn to speak English. English services are conducted every Sunday in most of the Scandinavian churches, which language also is used in their Sunday schools. The Swedes, Norwegians and Danes are satisfied with this country and make America their country. The consequences are that we do not hear so much of Swedish-Americans as we do of other nationalities. It is possible that many Scandinavians forget to declare that they were born on the other side of the ocean and, because they spoke such very good English when they answered questions, put up to them, the census-takers took it for granted they were native Americans."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
