<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-04-17">Apr. 17, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Ingratitude--The World's Reward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0269</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0269.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-04-17">Apr. 17, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">INGRATITUDE--THE WORLD'S REWARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The truth of the old saying, regarding the world's ingratitude, has been proved thousands of times and we regret that the case of a Chicago Swedish family proves it again.</p>
   <p>A poor old eighty-four year old man, who, in addition to his advanced age, is hampered by blindness and helplessness, is refused a home and care by his own children.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Ward, 155 North Western Avenue, until recently, had given the old father, Philip Lindemann a home, (since the mother's death three months ago). Mrs. Ward found it too much of a burden to care for [him] alone and had her brothers brought into court to force them to help support their father. John Lindemann, the oldest son, refused, stating that the old man was not his father neither were the others his children. They all washed their hands of [any] responsibility concerning the old man.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0270.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The story told by the son was to the effect that their (the children's) name was Lindau, not Lindemann, as their real father (Lindau) had left his wife and children for army service during the U. S. Civil War and had never returned. At the end of the war, Lindemann came home and was presented to the children as their father. He had made his home with and supported the mother and children for many years. Lindemann and the mother were supposed to have been married and the children adopted. He was a good provider for the family but he was only a step-father to the children, so they are under no obligation to him. Their independence is supported by the absence of the marriage certificate and adoption papers.</p>
   <p>The youngest son, a plumber in Galesburg, Illinois, offered the old man a home but Lindemann refused, preferring a home where there were no children.</p>
   <p>The children cannot be legally forced to support the old man, who has no papers to verify his standing, so, it appears that he will become a public burden. He who supported and educated a family will not now be cared for by the family in return. The ingratitude of the world is clearly exemplified by this group. May these ungrateful persons have the same experience later in life, which they, in our opinion, deserve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
