<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-02">June 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Capitalists at War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_1_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-06-02">June 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITALISTS AT WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tendency to destroy on the part of workers on strike is a topic frequently discussed. But what about this tendency to destroy among the lords of capital?</p>
   <p>Perhaps one example taken from the whole will illustrate how the economic fight is carried on among them.</p>
   <p>War has broken loose between George J. Gould, owner of the Wabash Railroad, and A. J. Cassett, manager of Western Pennsylvania Railroad, and defender of its interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So far, no property belonging to either of the two railroad companies has been destroyed, but the Pennsylvania Railroad has destroyed property of the Union Telegraph Company to the value of millions of dollars. And why? Because George Gould, who is holding controlling interest in the Company, dared to push the tracks of the Wabash Railroad into Pittsburg, thereby starting competition with the Pennsylvania Railroad into Pittsburg, there by starting compesition with the Pennsylvania Railroad which formerly was without a competitor in the field.</p>
   <p>In order to get revenge at Mr. Gould for his rashness, the Pennsylvania Railroad demanded that he remove from the property of the Railroad all the telegraph poles belonging to the Telegraph Company.</p>
   <p>The battle about this has gone on both in Wall Street, New York, and before the courts. Mr. Gould obtained a court order enjoining the Pennsylvania <pb facs="5423404_1_0506.jpg" n="3"/>Railroad from molesting the property of the Telegraph Company. Mr. Cassett appealed to a higher court, and had the injunction set aside. No sooner did he have the order setting aside the injunction in his hands than he dispatched an army of one thousand men to the locations in question, having ordered them to cut down all the telegraph poles along the line. Soon 14,000 miles of wire and 40,000 telegraph poles had been destroyed. The poles are valued at eight dollars each, the wire at about $500,000, and the work involved in the placing of the poles and securing the wire to them, at $180,000. The total loss to the telegraph company was at least one million dollars.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cassett and the Pennsylvania Railroad were not satisfied with this. They demanded that Mr. Gould pay for the work of destroying the property. The Pennsylvania Railroad wants payment for the work of cutting down the poles, and freightage for hauling them away to be burned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_1_0507.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Cassett will receive no punishment for thus destroying the property of other people. But suppose during a strike some hothead were to cut down a single one of these 40,000 telegraph poles, would he have been left unpunished?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
