<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-12">May 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Marshall High School and Hebrew</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. A. L [ipsky] (Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-12">May 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MARSHALL HIGH SCHOOL AND HEBREW</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. A. L [ipsky] (Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several years ago, while the writer of these lines was a member of the Board of Education, he was placed on a committee whose duty it was to revise the course of study as pursued in the High Schools. Among the studies to be considered was the one of ancient languages and literature-such as Greek and Latin and when these were taken under consideration the writer presented the case of Hebrew as strongly as he could. The arguments he used were that even as a dead language Hebrew had as many claims in its behalf as the other languages-that is it was a culture medium; good for mental training and possessed a large and important literature,-and because it was the language of the Old Testament was as important an influence in the history of civilization as any one contribution made by any race or any people. In addition thereto, it was a living language, since it was being used by many thousands of Jews in their daily intercourse, was written by many thousands more <pb facs="5423972_1_0296.jpg" n="2"/>than spoke it and was read by enough Jews to warrant the publication of daily newspapers, weeklies, monthlies and general literary works as well as scientific, historical, philosophical books.</p>
   <p>These arguments prevailed and when the Jewish students in the High Schools learned that the study of Hebrew would be possible in regularly accredited high school courses many hundreds indicated their desire to take up the subject.</p>
   <p>And then real difficulties arose. Teachers, suitably prepared, could not be procured. Many applied, it is true, but while they had splendid equipment as Hebraists they were unable to meet the general requirements for high school teaching. Finally two teachers were secured and classes were started at the Marshall and the Medill High Schools. These classes were large and continued for years though circumstances have compelled the dropping of the work at Medill. The Marshall classes are still at work and they are flourishing.</p>
   <p>At Marshall High School the work has taken such a hold that the students of <pb facs="5423972_1_0297.jpg" n="3"/>Hebrew are organized in a Hebrew Club which meets regularly and renders programs composed of musical numbers, Hebrew addresses and declamations and winds up with refreshments and a social half-hour.</p>
   <p>Now, we are interested to know that such activities as the study of Hebrew and Hebrew literature are being carried on, that the work done years ago as a public official still bears fruit. But we are much more concerned with the problem of arousing public interest and securing moral support for the study of Hebrew in the public High Schools. The matter should not be left to the interest or curiosity of the pupils themselves, although that interest has been splendidly shown. The general Jewish public should be vitally interested in this matter and should create a general public opinion to arouse enthusiasm for the study of Hebrew. It is probably easier to get competent teachers now than it was formerly and the Jewish students are more inclined to take up Jewish studies now than they were. Let the parents of high school students "boost" the study of Hebrew and impress on their children that this study is a much worth while and as valuable, either practically or culturally, <pb facs="5423972_1_0298.jpg" n="4"/>as any other study they may choose from the curriculum. [Editor's note: This article is in English originally. It has not been edited in the usual manner.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
