<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The New Scandal with the Sacramental Wine Business</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW SCANDAL WITH THE SACRAMENTAL WINE BUSINESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prohibition agents arrested a few people in Chicago, a few days ago, who were accused of carrying on a large business in sacramental wines. The chief director of this enterprise is a rich Italian from California who is an owner of many vineyards. Among those arrested were a few Jews who were supposed to have been the middlemen between the wealthy, California, wine merchant and the rabbis of the various cities. According to the prohibition law every member of a synagogue is entitled to buy ten gallons of wine a year.</p>
   <p>An official of a certain railroad company who guarded all the shipments of oil, furniture, and iron that were to be distributed on the freight cars going to the various cities was also arrested. Another one of those arrested confessed that he was the "go-between" between the wealthy wine merchant and the rabbis of the various cities. He would buy all the permits from the rabbis at twenty-eight cents apiece and sell them to the wine merchant for thirty-four cents. In this manner the sacramental wine business flourished on a large scale: there were many agents and dealers scattered from California to New York. According <pb facs="5423972_1_0556.jpg" n="2"/>to the evidence gathered by the prohibition agents from those who were arrested, the business in Chicago alone amounted to $1,600,000.</p>
   <p>These are the facts regarding the arrest of the wine merchants. We can easily imagine what sort of an impression this incident will produce in the non-Jewish world. Whatever the impression may be, it will not be an altogether false one. Furthermore, the problem does not only concern those few Jews who were arrested (the Jews are not the only group in America which deals with the "forbidden article"). Many of the arrests made from time to time include the names of prominent Yankees. The chaos produced by the prohibition law has corrupted very many people in American society--many of whom had served as special government agents. They were supposed to defend the law; instead they were found guilty of disobeying it themselves!</p>
   <p>Moreover, we are not interested so much in the number of Jewish bootleggers as we are in the number of rabbis who are being drawn into the sacramental wine business and who make deals with their permits. This action brings shame not only on the Jews as far as the Gentiles are concerned, but also on the Jews as <pb facs="5423972_1_0557.jpg" n="3"/>a nation. We cannot expect all the three million Jews in America to be righteous. We can, however, expect the few hundred rabbis in America not to allow men in their profession to become smugglers and wine peddlars. We expect men in their profession to be righteous one hundred per cent: at least not to peddle permits or sell their permits to an Italian for twenty-eight cents.</p>
   <p>We know that a majority of the rabbis in America are true, respectable people who are actually a source of pride to the community they lead. We also know that many of the so-called rabbis who are engaged in the sacramental wine business are not rabbis at all. Moreover, we know that some of the "real" rabbis, who play an important part in communal affairs, are mixed up in the sacramental wine business and have filled their pockets through sacramental wine deals. Jewish public opinion must, therefore, turn to the respectable rabbis. They should attempt to weed out that dangerous and filthy element among the clergy which brings shame and disgrace to the Jewish name. They should come out openly and condemn their colleagues in the severest manner. Such a step will bring them honor and respect from all the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
