<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-13">Oct. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Our Western Liberalism]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-13">Oct. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[OUR WESTERN LIBERALISM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many things can be said when we compare our city with the largest city of America. Chicago belongs to the West. This is one reason why her populace is more democratic. In New York the spirit is still that of Europe with all the old traditions which are brought here by the immigrants. Here the foreign element is more readily Americanized, thus permitting them to participate sooner in governmental affairs.</p>
   <p>Illinois has given women her franchise, New York has not. Chicago is more liberal in her dealings with the school teacher than is New York.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Young, superintendent of schools, criticized the New York Educational Board for dismissing a teacher who dared to become a mother. This puts an "official label" on married women as undesirable. In other words, school teachers are officially forced to remain old maids, or to adjust themselves to other work entirely.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0226.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our local educational board, as Mrs. Young explains, places no obstacles in the path of our married women teachers who become mothers. We did have, at one time, the same ruling they have there, but she, the woman superintendent, of Chicago schools has done away with it.</p>
   <p>The very fact that a woman, a very capable and fitting person, is at the head of our education in Chicago is in itself a good indication that our people are more liberal and broadminded than those of the Empire State.</p>
   <p>It is no wonder that a strong sentiment was shown for Mrs. Young, who resigned because her work was being narrowly limited. The public had judged the true value of this woman and insisted that she be given more power to execute her good plans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0227.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Progressive forms of government in the people's representation will come from the West. Riches come from the East where industry is highly concentrated. Chicago, in spite of her great size, that somewhat hampers progress, will play the "first fiddle" in having one of the most liberal and democratic governments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
