<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-18">Mar. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The First Duty for Women Voters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-18">Mar. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST DUTY FOR WOMEN VOTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every Jewish mother wishes earnestly that her child will grow up to be an educated man or woman. Practically without any exceptions, all Jewish parents spare no efforts to give their children a good education. But unfortunately all parents cannot attain this desire.</p>
   <p>Why? Simply because of the high cost of living, and the low wages people receive. To keep a child in school doubles the cost of living.</p>
   <p>Knowledge, the most essential thing, costs too much.</p>
   <p>With a broken heart, the mother sends off her child, for the first time, to work. And in her heart the poor child envies her girl friend who attends school. The working girl has an inward feeling of wanting to continue her education. She would also achieve success in school. But life <pb facs="5423972_1_0221.jpg" n="2"/>calls her to the shop....</p>
   <p>America is noted throughout the world as being "the land of unlimited opportunities." To a certain extent this is true. In what regards the acquisition of an education, it seems at first thought that the way is open to unlimited opportunity. But is it really unlimited?</p>
   <p>The unfortunate children of 14 and over, who fill the department stores, shops, and factories in this metropolis, prove that the talk about unlimited opportunity to acquire an education is not entirely true.</p>
   <p>Since the high schools began to add the higher science to their curriculum, the cost of going to school has been skyrocketed, especially for a poor family which has two or three children attending school.</p>
   <p>There are many States in America in which the schools furnish the students with books and other necessary supplies. But in Chicago it is difficult, even probably impossible, to institute this, due to various reasons. At any rate, the matter was never brought before the lawmakers, and perhaps will never be <pb facs="5423972_1_0222.jpg" n="3"/>brought before them.</p>
   <p>It is the women's duty to see that education costs less. If all of us women voters are persistent enough, we will triumph.</p>
   <p>We should not be too exacting at the beginning. Let us for the time being brush aside the question of free textbooks, and take up the smaller things which are not so trivial at that.</p>
   <p>A child who goes to high school spends half a dollar a week for car fare. This amounts to two dollars a month. In a household where two or more children attend high school, transportation amounts to several dollars a month. For the entire study course, the grand total is a heavy sum.</p>
   <p>Why shouldn't high school students have free transportation to and from school?</p>
   <p>The city will not lose anything and yet thousands of poor children will profit by it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0223.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Sisters, this will be very easy to achieve, should you only wish to.</p>
   <p>Press the alderman for whom you shall vote next month, to promise to introduce an ordinance to this effect in the City Council, and see that it becomes a law.</p>
   <p>The women of Colorado point with pride to having advanced the opportunity of acquiring an education in the State of Colorado. For this they deserve credit.</p>
   <p>Let us execute a law providing free transportation for high school children, and that will be accredited to us.</p>
   <p>Let us show the men that we know how to make good use of our privileges by attempting to improve and alleviate conditions. Women voters, remember your duty!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
