<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-05-02">May 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Yiddish and Hebrew in the Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-05-02">May 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">YIDDISH AND HEBREW IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, the board of education voted to accept the recommendation of the superintendent of schools that the Yiddish and Hebrew languages should be taught in the Chicago schools. This means, of course, that teachers [of Yiddish and Hebrew] will be assigned only to those schools where there are a sufficient number of pupils [registering for the classes in Yiddish and Hebrew]. The vote on the recommendation totaled twelve to four in its favor.</p>
   <p>The question of teaching these two languages has been discussed for the last few years; but, for some reason, it has never been definitely answered. However, when our Mr. Harry A. Lipsky was appointed a member of the board of education, the Jewish students, realizing that they had a member of their own people to represent them, raised the issue again with renewed energy. With petitions from the students and societies in his hands, Mr. Lipsky brought the problem of teaching Hebrew in the schools to Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, the school superintendent. The superintendent's office took up the question with the entire school board; and after much discussion, the board <pb facs="5423972_1_0305.jpg" n="2"/>recommended, by a vote of twelve to four, that [the Yiddish and Hebrew languages should be taught in the public schools].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
