<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-04-17">Apr. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[Standard Club Meets]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-04-17">Apr. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[STANDARD CLUB MEETS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the annual meeting of the Standard Club, the following communication from the University of Chicago was read: To the Members of the Standard Club. Gentlemen: I am reminded that a year ago, when we were in the utmost danger of failing in our efforts to secure the establishment of the University of Chicago, the Club came to our relief. The subscriptions your committees handed me aggregated $25,350.00, and enabled me to meet the conditions imposed upon us, and thus secure the establishment of the University. It has been felt by the denomination that inaugurated the movement and by the Board of Trustees of the University, that the action of the Standard Club was one of notable public spirit and liberality.</p>
   <p>It will be held in lasting and grateful remembrance, and we hope to erect on our campus a memorial that will tell the story to coming generations.</p>
   <p>I should like to have the Club know that a greater proportion of the Standard subscriptions have been paid than of that of any other class up to date. There has been paid by your members $14,020.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0273.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This large proportion, much larger than we could demand, has been paid with such cheerfulness and kindness, and with so many expressions of interest as to make my own work of collection easy and delightful. - Yours very truly, G. W. Goodspeed, Sectretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
