<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Laziness and Negligence</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LAZINESS AND NEGLIGENCE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That is the main reason why so many Jews in America have not been naturalized. In every large city in this land of ours, there are masses of Jews who have not taken out their citizenship papers yet. This is an absolute fact.</p>
   <p>Why this condition? Why should a Jew who has already lived in this country five years, not be registered among the citizens of this great free republic? That is a hard question. Although Jews who have already lived here 15 or 20 years, have carried on big business, or are land owners, have large bank accounts, or may not possess all these good things at all, they make a good comfortable living, and when you <pb facs="5423972_1_0536.jpg" n="2"/>put the question to them, "Mister, how come you are not a citizen yet?" they will have nothing to answer. But after all, it is not such a hard question to find a suitable answer. The main reason why so many Jews are neglecting their naturalization papers, is just simply negligence...They are constantly in fear and do not realize why. They are too lazy to grasp at something very important. However, there are also a great many Jews who have taken out the first papers only, and cannot wait for the appointed time to get their second and final citizenship papers. Although these Jews are sometimes too lazy to learn by heart the points they must know to get their final papers, such as the number of states in the Union, the number of wards in the city, who are the lawmakers of our country and cities, etc., nevertheless when they finally do get their second papers, <pb facs="5423972_1_0537.jpg" n="3"/>they do not fail to show their appreciation, and are quite happy over it. A Jew, who has lived here five years and is still not an American citizen, has committed a crime against himself, against his children, against his nation and against this land of ours.</p>
   <p>There should not be any thing to hold him back from becoming an American citizen. The Jew has no country which will treat him better than this land of freedom....</p>
   <p>There are special places where you can study citizenship, and learn all there is to know about obtaining the necessary first and second papers. On the West Side, the Chicago Hebrew Institute will help you learn how to become a citizen; on the North Side, the Educational Alliance; and on the South Side, the Sinai Social Center. At each one of these places of study, you will find people who voluntarily give their services for the good cause of informing and teaching immigrants how to become citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
