<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bacon says "Philosophy when superficially studied, excites doubt; when thoroughly explored it dispels it". That in formulating our theories and philosophy as respecting the Institute, we have explored and not studied, you will admit, after you will hear the illustrated review of activities for the year, that our Superintendent, Mr. Philip L. Seman, will bring to us tonight. Further and more complete details of each department and each class is brought to you by our monthly messenger, "The Observer", which is, as you know, devoted entirely to Institute news. Therefore, it is no longer necessary for me to review the educational side of the Institute as heretofore, and will devote my Report entirely to the Administrative part of the work.</p>
   <p>And this very fact that we no longer require repetition to emphasize the need of our existence must prove to our friends as it has to me that we have, as we claim, at last crystalized our philosophy into concrete form:</p>
   <p>The highly satisfactory results in our classes - English, civics, public-speaking, art, music, and the drama verified by figures and careful comparisons from year to year, to my mind should prove without any doubt to the layman what social thinkers and social workers have always conceded; namely, that progress in human society must be constructed upon education, because the function of <pb facs="5423972_1_0218.jpg" n="2"/>education is to guide and control the formation of habit and character on the part of the individual, as well as to develop his capacity and powers so that he shall become an efficient member of Society.</p>
   <p>The summer curriculum, consisting of kindergarten, domestic-art, gardening, story-telling, afternoon-games, athletic exercises, talks on hygiene, was as usual conducted outdoors all summer. The tennis courts and baseball grounds were filled to capacity throughout the season.</p>
   <p>True of nature, to those who sought and loved her best, she must have yielded ample reward. On September 1st, 1914. Dr. Joseph Pedott severed his connection with the Chicago Hebrew Institute, and in appreciation of his services rendered to the Institute, the members of the Board fittingly presented him with a set of resolutions and had it inscribed in their Minutes. Mr. Philip L. Seman of New York succeeded him. Mr. Seman brings to us the result of many years of social work and experience, and the Institute was fortunate to have been able to enlist his services. Mr. Seman is carrying out and developing the principles of the Institute, to make social intercourse express the growing sense of the economic unity of Society, <pb facs="5423972_1_0219.jpg" n="3"/>which makes toward a greater Democracy and multiplies opportunity to make charity more and more unnecessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
