<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-13">Mar. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Drunkeness</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-13">Mar. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DRUNKENESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>M. Poincare, President of France, recently visited a large hospital in Paris. When he, accompanied by high officials, entered the Doctor Lucion Clinic, he met a patient whose ghastly appearance frightened him. The doctor informed the President that this patient was a habitual drunkard.</p>
   <p>At the same time, the doctor showed that research made by hospitals on the effects of alcohol revealed that out of 111 who drank moderately, sixty of their children died; out of eighty who drank slightly more, seventy-three children died; out of 117 who drank excessively, 220 children died.</p>
   <p>If these horrible facts are true of France, where liquors are weak, what could we say of America, where liquors are strong?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To us, however, the fact alone that alcohol is the chief cause of infantile mortality, is enough to make us understand that the opposition against inebriety is, from every standpoint, justifiable. The claim that by declaring war against alcoholism we will encroach upon personal liberty has lost every significance long ago, because no father will approve of such "personal liberty," as will bring death upon his children.</p>
   <p>Bad as it is that drunkenness gives rise to infantile mortality, still worse are its effects on the surviving children born unto drunkards. These children remain everlasting victims of sins which they never committed. When a child manifests incapacity in school, it is frequently due to the fact that his parents overindulged in drinking. It is practically an established fact that 60% of the idiots, criminals, and prostitutes come from parents who consumed too much alcohol.</p>
   <p>Upon considering how much hard-earned money is freely spent on drinks and the results thereof, we can readily understand that the campaign against drunkenness bears a great social interest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
