<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In the Chicago Hebrew Institute</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE CHICAGO HEBREW INSTITUTE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a letter to the Courier, Mrs. Julius Stone, recording and corresponding secretary, gives a general view of the activities of the Chicago Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <p>The Institute seeks to elevate the character, morals, and sincerity of those, who come in contact with it. It is impossible to point out each separate accomplishment and make a total of how many persons were benefited spiritually through the facilities of the Institute. The work is not a daily figure; it begins with the child, and its influence affects all the people, regardless of age.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The aim of the Institute is constructive work; the effect is to elevate the individual above material help.</p>
   <p>Education is the object; the brain of the Jewish immigrant is like a sponge, which absorbs everything. Given an education, he gets the chance to help himself, thereby eliminating charity.</p>
   <p>A community where each of its members knows and fulfills his duties as a good citizen is entitled to the praise of every intelligent person. To prepare the individual to accept this idea, the Institute is making big preparations to broaden the circle of activities of its civic and citizenship department. For this purpose, Chicago is being divided into districts. The thickly populated districts, where Jews predominate, will be canvassed at first, house to house, by capable persons, who <pb facs="5423972_1_0546.jpg" n="3"/>are familiar with this kind of work. The object of this canvass is to find out, who among the Jewish people is not as yet a citizen, and the reason for it; whether or not they have their first papers, and why they did not apply for the second papers. How long they have been in this country; what are their social circumstances, and how they make a living.</p>
   <p>Literature, written in Jewish, will be printed and distributed free of charge through the canvassers, which will enlighten the masses as to the importance of citizenship.</p>
   <p>Many persons neglect to take out their citizenship papers, simply because they are not familiar with the legal procedure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0547.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For this reason, the Chicago Hebrew Institute has established a citizenship bureau under the supervision of authorities in this field, where, regardless of cost, expert advice and legal aid is extended to those, who are anxious to become citizens of the United States. This service is being given absolutely free of charge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
