<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-14">May 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Jewish University?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0117</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0117.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-14">May 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A JEWISH UNIVERSITY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is a truly "American" university? Is it a college which seeks a registration representative of every State, creed, and race, attaining this cross-section of "All-America" by the introduction of geographical, religious, and racial tests, thus sacrificing the pristine American policy of the "open door"? Or is it the State and municipal college, which remaining staunch to the principle of free opportunity undertaken with ambition and effort, throws its portals wide and thereby receives into its midst representatives of one or two nationalities, numerically preponderant in the neighborhood? Which is more "American," to sacrifice a principle for diversity, or to retain a principle at the cost of diversity? Is a New England Baptist College, dominantly British, or an Atlantic Presbyterian College, dominantly Scotch, more "American" than a mid-Western State College, largely Scandinavian-Nordic, or a New York City College, nine-tenths Jewish? <pb facs="5423972_1_0118.jpg" n="2"/>You deplore concentration as a "defeat" for "our ideals of America". Concentration in the case of the Jew, as well as of other ethnic-religious groups in the United States, seems inevitable; neither the open nor the one-fifth closed door in education can prevent it. Fractional percentage enrollment at Columbia has meant concentration in the City College; at Barnard, concentration in Hunter; at Harvard, in local Boston colleges. Inasmuch as 2,500,000 Jews live in Atlantic States, and the Jewish population of New York, even without immigration and with increasing country-wide distribution, is not destined to decline, many of us would welcome a new Metropolitan University, nonsectarian and non-propagandist, which might act as an auxiliary and reservoir to drain off the surplus numbers of Jewish students who might freely enter without being stigmatized as an "alien influx", and where no "Jewish problem" as such would ever arise to torment us.</p>
   <p>Because the American Jewish community is inextricably interwoven with the <pb facs="5423972_1_0119.jpg" n="3"/>economic, political, and cultural life of the land, it will never permit itself to be isolated or suppressed. We ask for the opportunity to develop a maximum Jewish program as the highest means whereby we can cultivate a maximum American program. Knowing Jews as we do, we can vouch for their veritable religion of service to the common American cause. The major question, however, still abides: Will America permit the Jew to serve her in line with his own unique genius? Or will America repudiate the free-will offerings we bring to her shrine of the spirit?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
