<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A Quiet Revolution Among College Students</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A QUIET REVOLUTION AMONG COLLEGE STUDENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of students of Northwestern University gathered yesterday at a church in Evanston, to discuss the most important political and economic questions of the day.</p>
   <p>At this conference the question of the possibility of a new war was discussed, and of the ninety-six delegates thirty eight voted against war in any form and declared that if America has a war, and regardless of what ever alibis may be presented to cause it, they will reject the <pb facs="5423972_1_0111.jpg" n="2"/>military uniforms and will object to being drafted as soldiers. This resolution against war was the one most opposed.</p>
   <p>There were similar resolutions somewhat milder in form. One of them carried by a vote of 94 to 15, expresses the thought that America is not willing to engage in preparedness for a second war.</p>
   <p>When one considers the fact that the Northwestern University is supposed to be a strictly aristocratic institution, supported by many Chicago millionaires, only then one can judge the significance of this event, which gives an idea of the trend of thought among American youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0112.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The factor that brought about the students' decision to discuss the economic problems of America, is also very interesting, although it corresponds with the thinking of our American youth, which is yet too ignorant and too childish when it comes to important social subjects.</p>
   <p>For this reason it is very interesting to see the students beginning to consider the autocratic power that prevails in colleges such as the authority taken by the trustees in rejecting students that are not to their liking.</p>
   <p>Much more effective is another resolution against the millionaires who support this aristocratic university. This resolution reads:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0113.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"We protest against any additional taxes being paid out by the big capitalists, because their money was obtained as a result of labor exploitations."</p>
   <p>We do not know how the trustees will deal with such revolutionary students when the list of resolutions is presented to them, but one thing is positive, if these resolutions express the attitude now prevailing among the students, the autocrats of the college will be obliged to swallow it and say nothing.</p>
   <p>By no means does this imply that we can already, from these occurrences, expect a revolutionary outbreak in the conduct and order of the American <pb facs="5423972_1_0114.jpg" n="5"/>colleges. There is no doubt that such events will make a deep impression on the average American and will force him to consider more closely such and similar social questions.</p>
   <p>It is especially important to consider and become interested in this new phenomenon in the life of American students, particularly if we remember the type of students of fifteen or twenty years ago, and the "heroism" that many of them manifested in their time of great strikes, when they looked upon scabbery as a sacred obligation.</p>
   <p>Yes, this is a beautiful symbol of the present time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
