<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-05-22">May 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[Concerning Foreign - Language Teachings]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-05-22">May 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[CONCERNING FOREIGN - LANGUAGE TEACHINGS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The discussion of the Union League Club of the question, "Shall Foreign Languages Be Taught in Chicago Public Schools?" brought out three strikingly different views. Dr. Hirsch supported the opinion frequently expressed in these columns, that since 75% of the public school children of this city do not pass beyond the primary grades, it is unjust, useless, and even foolish to devote any of their limited time to a study which they will never master, when their efforts might much more profitably be devoted to the thorough study of English. Of the usefulness of German in high schools and of the desirability of studying that and other languages where the time is available, there can be no doubt. Mr. Head, the second speaker, opposed the teaching of any language but English, and the money that is now devoted to German, he thinks, should be put to better use. "No child," he said, "should leave our public schools without a sufficient knowledge of Chemistry and Mechanics." What would a sufficient knowledge be?</p>
   <p>Ex-Governor Hoard, of Wisconsin, would try to overcome foreign hostility in our public schools, by having taught in them the languages of all foreigners. The <pb facs="5423972_1_0307.jpg" n="2"/>foreign languages to be taught include German, Swedish, Russian, Polish, Bohemian, Gaelic, Hungarian, Turkish, Italian, Spanish, Portuguese, French, Welsh, Manx, Low Dutch and many more.</p>
   <p>The simple problem of our public schools, as stated by the Herald on many occasions and by Dr. Hirsch in his address on Tuesday, is this: More than 75% of the children leave the schools before they are twelve years of age and without entering any grade but the Primary. What is the best we can do in less than six years, beginning with the elements of Reading, to give these children rudiments of knowledge to fit them for life? Is it by teaching them a lot of foreign languages which by no miracle of industry or precocity they can acquire? Is it Chemistry and Mechanics? The proposals are equally absurd. Children in Primary grades should be taught thoroughly the literary elements of knowledge in English, the language in which they must think if they live in this country; and these elements are most effectually taught in conjunction with the training of the senses - the eye and the hand being, especially valuable for their development.</p>
   <p>What may be undertaken for children in higher grades is another matter. Let us look first to the 75% in the Primary grades, who are never to enter a higher grade.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0308.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As to them, the study of foreign languages is a waste of public money and a grievous wrong to the pupils.</p>
   <p>Editorial, Chicago Herald.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
