<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-04-29">Apr. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">School and Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-04-29">Apr. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL AND POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish citizens in Chicago are expressing their dissatisfaction at the City Council's action in rejecting the approval of the re-appointment of the president of the Chicago Board of Education, Mr. Jacob M. Loeb.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to delve into deep inquiries as to whether the malignance that the aldermen have shown to Mayor Thompson is justified or not. The political disputes between the parties in the City Hall are of very little concern to us. But when it concerns the effective management of our schools, it is a different thing entirely.</p>
   <p>We Jews have a special respect for schools, a sentiment of reverence that is practically glorified. The slightest attempt to play politics with public schools must arouse anger and wrath in the hearts of the Jews.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jacob M. Loeb became renowned as president of the Board of Education of <pb facs="5423972_1_0191.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago by his devotion to the interests of the schools; by his fearlessness in the defense of these interests; by the battles which he so courageously carried on against every obstructing influence that swarms about the Chicago school system. The Chicago press and the intellectual circles of Chicago recognize his services as the head of the Board of Education. The position is an honorary office, yielding nothing but responsibility. On what political grounds can the City Council reject the affirmation of his re-appointment?</p>
   <p>It is true that Mr. Loeb had made many enemies in his fight against the Teachers' Federation. His enemies endeavor to spread the rumor that he is an opponent of union labor. At the same time, the Carpenter's Union, the Engineer's Union, the Plumber's Union, and all other unions with which Mr. Loeb comes in contact, as president of the Board of Education, consider him as their friend. Mr. Loeb does not believe that the teachers' profession is a trade that can be organized. He believes that teaching is a profession that depends upon the personal ability and devotion of the teacher. He has very often stated that he <pb facs="5423972_1_0192.jpg" n="3"/>believes in the organized strength of teachers, not only so that they may seek better wages, but also so that they can improve the profession, to the advantage of the hundreds of thousands of children of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Such disputes between a president of the Board of Education and a teachers' union must not be turned into a political issue to the detriment of the schools.</p>
   <p>No reason was given for the withholding of the confirmation of Mr. Loeb's re-appointment. There are no grounds for this other than spiting the Mayor, who recommended the re-appointment. And this situation will make the Jewish citizens realize the action of the City Council.</p>
   <p>If Mr. Loeb does not qualify for the presidency of the Board of Education, let it be pronounced publicly. But political vengeance should not transform the schools of Chicago into a political football.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to conceal our sentiments about this matter; as mentioned above, <pb facs="5423972_1_0193.jpg" n="4"/>we are deeply interested in the subject of public schools. They are sacred to us. We are convinced that the Jewish public will consider the action of every member of the City Council who is attempting to play politics with the school a serious crime.</p>
   <p>Mr. Loeb became prominent throughout Chicago by his ardor, his devotion and tireless work for the schools. It is an insult to Chicago to question his re-appointment for even a period of two weeks.</p>
   <p>The Chicago public will pay particular attention to the Aldermen who vote against the confirmation of Mr. Loeb's re-appointment at the next meeting of the City Council; especially the Jewish citizens, in whose eyes any attempt to play politics is a crime.</p>
   <p>We are sure that the public opinion of Chicago will not tolerate further postponement of the confirmation of Mr. Loeb's re-appointment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
