<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-01">May 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditations of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-01">May 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATIONS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One lad was killed, another fatally injured, and five or more other persons were injured in the annual clash between freshmen and sophomores at Northwestern University. The officials of the University are quiet about the affair, although [since] the kidnaping of a freshman three years ago, who has never since been located, and was probably injured or murdered, the college has had its lesson. What surprises us is that the police permit hazing and other such illegal performances at the universities when they ordinarily would pack off such disturbers of the peace in patrol wagons to their stations and have them sentenced to jail or the house of correction on disorderly charges. The university which permits hazing is unfit to be considered as a place for the cultural and moral instruction of the youth, and the officials who permit such practices are certainly in some measure responsible for the dire consequences that sometimes result. Three years ago when a young student by the name of <pb facs="5423972_1_0121.jpg" n="2"/>Mount disappeared under very mysterious circumstances, the officials declared that they would not allow the recurrence of such an event. But they did permit it and now what will they say? What they may say, to our mind, is more immaterial than what the parents of the young men and women who attend the school can say. If the parents of the students of the university made their opinions felt, we doubt not but that such savage practices as hazing would quickly disappear from the curriculum of the colleges.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
