<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-06">Mar. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Federal Control of the Educational System</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-06">Mar. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FEDERAL CONTROL OF THE EDUCATIONAL SYSTEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a strongly worded statement, the National Educational Association, which held its annual convention recently, condemned any proposal of a government educational system. It voiced its opposition to any type of Federal control over the educational institutions of the country. The National Educational Association particularly condemned the bill introduced in Congress which would subsidize educational institutions. Professor Engels of Harvard University condemned the bill as "highly dangerous" to the democratic institutions of our country.</p>
   <p>As is well known, America is the only civilized country where the educational system is not in the hands of the central government. The education of the people is, in all other civilized countries, the task of the central government. Although the municipalities in those countries have more or less wide powers in <pb facs="5423972_1_0137.jpg" n="2"/>the matter of education, the chief control is concentrated in the hands of a ministry of education, which means that in democratic countries the education of the country lies in the hands of the people.</p>
   <p>The situation in the United States is entirely different. The Federal government has no authority whatever over the educational institutions. The city and county governments have exclusive control and ownership of the lower educational institutions, while the universities and colleges are only partly maintained and controlled by the state governments. In most cases, those institutions are kept up and controlled by private philanthropy.</p>
   <p>The history of the development of the American schools accounts for the great difference between the United States educational system and the educational system prevalent in all other civilized countries. In Europe, the education of the youth was formerly exclusively in the hands of the church, and when the modern state began to free itself from the influence of the church, it took the education of the people out of the hands of the clergy, and the schools simply <pb facs="5423972_1_0138.jpg" n="3"/>passed from the control of the clergy to the control of the state. The church had never had the opportunities in America that it had in the old country. Here, from the very beginning, the schools were exclusively private undertakings, and only later, did the state and county governments begin to introduce the public school system, and still later, the state governments themselves began either to build or to subsidize universities and colleges.</p>
   <p>The fact that the American school developed in a different way from the modern European school is surely no reason why the school system should remain outside the sphere of the Federal government. On the contrary, this is the best argument in favor of it, since it is a higher stage of development in our educational system. The municipal public school was a great improvement over the preceding private school, and the subsidized state universities and colleges were a still greater improvement over the small, private colleges. Federal universities and colleges would be, in the same way, a still greater improvement over the state and city universities and colleges. It would, first of all, put an end to the harmful influence which private philanthropy exerts over the educational system.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0139.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>No one denies the truth of this claim, except those who personally benefit from it.</p>
   <p>Private philanthropy means private control. Private control of commerce and industry may be good or bad, but there is no disputing the fact that private control of the nation's education is bad. The education of the people is neither an industry nor a business, but an institution for the spiritual development of our youth. Private schools maintained by private means for a definite purpose may be legitimate, even desirable, but public schools supported by private means are in an entirely different category. The same distinction can be made between private schools kept up by the church, under the open control of the church, and public schools which would be under the masked control of the church. The former is legitimate in a free country; the latter would be regarded as very harmful.</p>
   <p>Any form of Federal control--say according to the bill introduced in Congress --of the higher educational institutions would make unnecessary and would remove <pb facs="5423972_1_0140.jpg" n="5"/>private philanthropy from the educational system, thus giving the system the character of a people's educational system--by the people, and for the people. The arguments which were brought up against Federal control, at the conference of the National Educational Association, do not stand up under criticism. In these arguments one can discern the desire to keep up the present system of private philanthropy, which means private control.</p>
   <p>The chief arguments against Federal control are that first, it will weaken the initiative of the local populations to maintain and manage their own schools, and that second, it will strengthen the bureaucratic power of Washington. These are old arguments against enlarging and widening the jurisdiction of Congress and of the Federal government.</p>
   <p>These arguments may or may not be just when applied to other problems, but they cannot be applied to this problem. Federal control can be applied only to the higher educational institutions, leaving the lower public schools to the initiative of the local governments. In regard to the second argument, about <pb facs="5423972_1_0141.jpg" n="6"/>the fear of enlarging the bureaucratic power that is responsible to the entire nation is preferable to a private philanthropic bureaucracy which is responsible to no one, and which can follow, without hindrance, its own private aims and interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
