<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-08-23">August 23, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The School. -</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Lee K. Frankel</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-08-23">August 23, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL. -</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Lee K. Frankel</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the home has apparently suffered through the rapid inroads of science, if there is chaos and disillusionment where there should be peace, what has happened to our great instrument of education, the school, as a result of scientific progress? Singularly, there has been a remarkable growth for the better.</p>
   <p>While our educational methods may still be in process of flux, educators have realized that earlier methods should be abandoned. The educational fields no longer depend purely upon the pedagogues. Modern school systems employ psychologists, psychiatrists, mental hygienists, and pediatricians to prepare curricula and assist in the training of children.</p>
   <p>Modern pedagogy is based upon the theory that the child is an entity and must be taught as such. Each phase of the child's life must be considered. Its home, its home environment, its physical condition, and its heredity are factors which enter into its subsequent development. The extent to which these are considered and applied will make for a normal or an abnormal child.</p>
   <p>Has there been similar progress in our Jewish religious schools? Inquiries among those who should know, have brought the confession that our religious <pb facs="5423972_1_0383.jpg" n="2"/>schools are sadly lacking. Curricula, in most instances, are formal and for mass instruction. The differentiation of the Jewish child by reason of his religion is not recognized. A mental hygienist recently stated that one million school children are headed for insane asylums, due to maladjustments in their school and home training. If these occur with the average child, may they not occur even more frequently in the Jewish child who from birth is differentiated from other children? Are the doubts and uncertainties of our modern Jewish youth due, in part, to inadequate and unintelligent training in their childhood?</p>
   <p>A survey of our system of religious instruction would probably lead to marked changes in curricula and to greater coordination between the school and the home. Such a survey should be made by experts in psychology, psychiatry, medicine, and pedagogy. They would probably recommend the organization of Jewish parent-teachers associations to effect better contacts between the home and the school, and better cooperation between the teacher and the parent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
