<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-05">Nov. 5, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">We Must Maintain Our Yeshivoth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-05">Nov. 5, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WE MUST MAINTAIN OUR YESHIVOTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Formerly, when Jews lived in their own land, Eretz Israel, there was no need for special schools and Yeshivoth [theological seminaries] to be founded to educate Jewish youth in the ways of their fathers. It was natural for Jewish youth to love the powerful Jewish nation--the United Kingdom. The Jewish youth could rightfully be proud of his people, its lore, literature, customs, and religion.</p>
   <p>When the Jews lost their homeland, however, the large and powerful Jewish nation ceased to be a free people and became a wandering people. They sought a moment of respite wherever the goodness of mankind overcome its prejudiced views. And thus, as a nomadic people, they, by force of circumstances, were compelled to adopt the language and customs of strange peoples at the expense of their own heritage. This process was curtailed, however, when they established institutions of their own whose objective it was to perpetuate Judaism in the hearts of the young people, and keep alive the hope that the Jewish <pb facs="5423972_1_0474.jpg" n="2"/>people will once again return to their homeland and establish themselves as a cultural nation whose mission it will be to spread wisdom among the nations of the earth.</p>
   <p>With this view in mind Rabbi Johanan ben Zakai established the Yeshivah at Jabneh, and our great sages throughout the centuries established other institutions of learning.</p>
   <p>Where are our modern Jabnehs? Where are our modern leaders? We have small Hebrew schools and Talmud Torahs; but do they begin to compare with the public schools? Our Jewish citizens have sufficient funds to build synagogues which are empty except on Saturdays and holidays; yet they do not deem it necessary to set aside funds for building schools which will disseminate learning, and will create greater respect for our people than all the synagogues will ever be able to do. We do not say that synagogues should not be built; we do say that synagogues should not be built at the expense of schools. These temples and synagogues may be valuable at the present time; but, unless we teach the younger generation the fundamentals of Judaism and the beauty of the synagogue, <pb facs="5423972_1_0475.jpg" n="3"/>they will lose all contact with it. We must have educational institutions in Chicago--modern Jabnehs--so that our youth will understand the synagogue and attend it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
