<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-25">May 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Glorious Hebrew Demonstration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-25">May 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A GLORIOUS HEBREW DEMONSTRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hebrew play presented by the students of the Marshall High School in Temple Judea, which was reported in yesterday's Courier, was one of the most beautiful Hebrew demonstrations that we have ever witnessed in Chicago. This Hebrew demonstration proved that American-born and American-reared children can acquire a fine knowledge of Hebrew and simultaneously continue their general education without any interference.</p>
   <p>The students of the Marshall High School, who participated in the performance of the Hebrew play written by their Hebrew teacher, Mr. Seligman, showed that they not only have a fine knowledge of Hebrew but also understand something about Judaism and the Jewish spirit. Before the curtain was lowered on the first act, an orchestra composed of Jewish students of the Marshall High School played Jewish melodies, and from their playing it could be seen that <pb facs="5423972_1_0285.jpg" n="2"/>the children are imbued with Judaism. They played Chassidic melodies and a medley of others, and their playing evoked joy on all the countenances in the assembly. The Hebrew class at the Marshall High School is not a class like the Latin or Greek, in which the children become familiar with the rudiments of a dead language. It is much more than that. It gives the children an opportunity to acquaint themselves with the essence of the language and with the spirit of a people who have created immortal values in that language, religious, ethical, and literary. If the children of all the Talmud Torahs (Hebrew schools) in Chicago would acquire such a knowledge of Hebrew as do the students who attend the Hebrew classes at Marshall High School, we would have in a very short time a generation of Herraists in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Let the presidents of our Talmud Torahs answer the following query: Why can Jewish children, attending the Hebrew classes at the Marshall High School, acquire a knowledge of Hebrew, and why do our Talmud Torahs, where Jewish children spend many years, produce so many ignoramuses? We do not know how many hours per week Hebrew is taught at Marshall High School, but it is certain that <pb facs="5423972_1_0286.jpg" n="3"/>in the Talmud Torahs more hours are expended on the study of Hebrew. At Marshall High School more time cannot be devoted to Hebrew than to any other language, such as German, French, Latin, Spanish, etc. But in our Talmud Torahs Hebrew is taught at least three hours a day, i.e., eighteen hours a week. In no high school in America and in no gymnasium in Europe is one subject taught more than six hours a week, and the Marshall High School, too, cannot devote more than six hours a week the most to Hebrew, and still the Jewish children at Marshall High School learn Hebrew, whereas the old-fashioned Talmud Torahs keep the children not four but six and seven years, not one hour a day but three hours, and when they leave the Talmud Torahs they don't know anything about Hebrew and very little about Judaism. Why is this so? To this query the presidents of the Talmud Torahs owe an answer to the Chicago Jewish public and especially to the parents who send their children to the Talmud Torahs.</p>
   <p>Upon seeing what the Hebrew classes of the Marshall High School do for Hebrew <pb facs="5423972_1_0287.jpg" n="4"/>education, we are convinced that the old-fashioned Talmud Torahs are a waste of time; energy, and money, and such a waste must not be permitted.</p>
   <p>From the above-mentioned Hebrew demonstration, we can learn a number of things.</p>
   <p>The Marshall High School organized Hebrew classes because there is a man on the West Side who understands the value of Hebrew education and who induced the Jewish students, as well as the principal, to establish Hebrew classes. This man is Harry Lipsky, general manager of the Courier. We owe thanks to him that Marshall High School now has Hebrew classes, which are attended by hundreds of Jewish children. The Hebrew classes at Marshall High School are steadily becoming larger and within time they will become an important center of Hebrew education in Chicago. If there were practical idealists like Mr. Lipsky in other parts of the city, every high school in Chicago would have Hebrew classes and a generation of Hebraists would develop from those classes, and by that means our whole problem of education would become simplified. But is there another Harry Lipsky in Chicago?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0288.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If the Jews in other parts of the city would do as much for Hebrew as Harry Lipsky, thousands of Jewish children who do not attend a Talmud Torah for social and psychological reasons would now be receiving a good Jewish education together with their general education, and we would have in Chicago less ignorance and less illiteracy than we have.</p>
   <p>The Talmud Torah is considered by many parents as a charitable institution attended by poor children, and for that reason they do not wish to send their children to it. They are either in no financial position or too indifferent to engage a private teacher for the Hebrew education of their children; consequently, the latter grow up without any Jewish education. However, if every high school would have such Hebrew classes as the Marshall High School, Hebrew would have a social position entirely different from the one it now has.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as there is only one Mr. Lipsky in Chicago, we shall have to ask him to carry out in other high schools what he carried out in the Marshall High <pb facs="5423972_1_0289.jpg" n="6"/>School, and then the question of Hebrew education in Chicago will be partly solved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
