<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-19">Feb. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Prohibition and the Clergy]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-19">Feb. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[PROHIBITION AND THE CLERGY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rabbi Leon Fram, in his speech before a large audience in Temple Judea, sharply criticized the clergymen of America who seek, through various ways, to force their will upon the majority [of the people] of this country. He pointed out that thanks to the narrow mindedness of the men in clerical garb we have prohibition, and that thanks to them, we will be forced to have two rest days during the week.</p>
   <p>"The clergymen," he said "have robbed the American people of a part of the personal freedom to which every man in this country is entitled. They have robbed the people here of their right to drink a glass of beer or wine, and they are endeavoring now to have Washington declare Sunday as the rest day of the week, so that the Jews, who observe Saturday [as the Sabbath], will be unable to work or to do business on two days of the week. The general public will have to go to church on Sunday, and will resent this infringement of their liberties."</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fram also pointed out that a few clergymen downstate have tried, <pb facs="5423972_1_0573.jpg" n="2"/>unsuccessfully, to force "rural morality" upon Chicago. He concluded his speech by saying that "jingo nationalism destroys the American tradition of freedom and hospitality, and that the Jews should unite with the liberal men and women of this country and fight, so that a minority shall not become the ruling power here."</p>
   <p>The Tribune yesterday featured Rabbi Fram's speech prominently.</p>
   <p>Besides the Yiddish speaking rabbis, many English-speaking rabbis hold the same opinion as Rabbi Fram, but since the prohibition law has gone into effect, nobody has come out as openly against the clergymen as Rabbi Fram; he expressed himself so strongly that the English press took notice of it. More power to you, Rabbi Fram!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
