<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-08-11">August 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 at Education Day Picnic Sunday</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-08-11">August 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">25,000 AT EDUCATION DAY PICNIC SUNDAY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than twenty-five thousand men, women, and children attended the "Education Day" festivities last Sunday at Kolze's Electric Park. "Education Day" was sponsored by the committee representing the Va'ad Ha'Chinuch of the Kehillah and the Hebrew Theological College. Families from all parts of the city were streaming through the gates from the early morning until late at night.</p>
   <p>The program began with the singing of the "Star Spangled Banner", and an invocation by Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, who greeted the gathering in the name of the local Rabbinate. Superintendent William J. Bogan of the Chicago Public Schools was the principal speaker of the day, and he stressed the intellectual and spiritual contributions of the Jews during the Diaspora.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Greetings to the gathering were delivered by Moe Rosenberg, who pleaded for harmony and cooperation in Jewish life. Ald. Jacob M.Avery of the 24th Ward, Lawndale, spoke on the importance of Jewish religious education and its continuing need in the city.</p>
   <p>Other speakers on the program were Cong. A. H. Sabath; N. H. Balotin, chairman of the Va'ad Ha'Chinuch; Mrs. M. S. Shapera, president of the Frauen Verband, and Mrs. P. Olschwang of the women's committee. Irving Nelson gave a rendition of Bialik's "Hamasmid". The choir, under the direction of A. A. Olepky, sang several Hebrew songs.</p>
   <p>A flag drill on the grounds concluded the afternoon program, which was under the direction of Dr. Meyer Waxman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0367.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the evening the Hebrew Singers' Union, with Cantor Giblichman as soloist, rendered several numbers of sacred and folk music. Speeches were made by Rabbi S. S. Siegel, chairman of the Education Day Committee, and Rabbi Menahem B. Sacks, director of the Kehillah.</p>
   <p>The First Aid tent, complete in every detail, was under the direction of Morris L. Hirschman of the Washington Park Hospital.</p>
   <p>The Va'ad Ha'Chinuch of the Kehillah supports actively twenty-three Hebrew schools, and the Hebrew Theological College is one of the largest institutions of higher Hebrew learning in this country, educating several hundred young men from every part of this country and Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
