<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-07-11">July 11, 1931</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-07-11">July 11, 1931</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem, it seems to us the immediate problem, is to devise a method to take up the slack which is caused by the depression. We suggest a careful examination of applicants for admission to the seminaries - careful but not exacting. No one really can tell who will, under American conditions, make the successful rabbi. There have been surprises and disappointments. But with a reasonable admission list there ought to be inaugurated for the ministry what the law, and what medicine has done long ago. The ministry ought to serve an interneship. It would serve many purposes. It would do the new graduate good to be in the hands of an older colleague for two years. The young graduate is academically trained, it is presumed, but the actual working conditions of the ministry are strange to him. There is an art, in the ministry, as well as a science. They have to conduct classes and Sunday schools; they have to take their place in the community; they have personal problems of the members in which their advice is sought. The companionship of the interne rabbi with an older man would give him the practical capacities. The term of years should not be longer than three years. Rabbis have to perform marriage ceremonies, funeral ceremonies, etc. It is ruinous to a rabbi to work under direction too long a time. It destroys his initiative. The position of assistant rabbi is in most cases damaging to the assistant <pb facs="5423972_1_0379.jpg" n="2"/>and galling to the senior. After the three years the interne rabbi can go to his own congregation rich in experience.</p>
   <p>And the institutions ought to be instructed that they are to send no new graduate to a congregation in which he will not serve an interneship. For the congregations this interneship of a young rabbi would be a boon. It would give the congregation an educational director. It would know that it has the same one in reserve in case of sickness. The congregation would be bound to the cause of Israel more firmly, for it would not cost so very much. Congregations with a membership of six-hundred would just have a few dollars more a year, per member, to pay in membership dues. There are enough congregations of requisite size now in American Israel that could immediately take up all the graduates who have no positions at the present moment. For the time being, this plan of the interneship would take up the slack and when the economic conditions improve, the interne rabbis will be in a position to march out into the rehabilitated or new congregations.</p>
   <p>And what a boon it would be to the rabbis in large congregations to have an interne rabbi. Few people can quite appreciate just what has happened to the rabbi of a large congregation. His time is snatched from him by all kinds of tasks, some important; some important only to the people for whom the task is <pb facs="5423972_1_0380.jpg" n="3"/>being performed. Some of the tasks could be shifted to the shoulders of the interne, who in the performance of the task would gather experience, and the older rabbi could reserve his time for a little more study, research, and thought. Is it an accident that no graduate of the Hebrew Union College over fifty years ago, as yet lived to see a seventieth birthday? In a very serious way the ministry has been devouring the rabbis. The stress, and wear and tear of the ministry has crippled and shortened the lives of rabbis so that at a time when they should be in the best position to teach and to give of the wisdom of gathered experience, they are already worn out. The tasks of a community have, long ago, before the appropriate time, smashed the ideals and the possibilities of scholarship.</p>
   <p>American conditions permit the rabbis to have books, but prevent the reading of them, unless the rabbi is willing to use night hours for his reading. And so for the benefit of all, we urge seriously the interneship plan for the American rabbinate.</p>
   <p>G. B. L.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
