<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Work for Young Boys</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WORK FOR YOUNG BOYS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A multitude of young boys, over 16 years of age, will shortly leave high school and college, to spend a two-month vacation. In this multitude there will be a few thousand Jewish boys in whom we are particularly interested, and for whose sake we wish to say a few words.</p>
   <p>The question now confronting these young men and their parents,- and to most of them it is a burning question, - is what are these young men going to do during these hot summer weeks.</p>
   <p>To many parents it is a question of health. The child went to school for a period of ten months, had his own troubles, and shared the troubles of his family. Due to poverty there were probably times when he lacked food and proper rest. Now the hot summer, and a few weeks of fresh air would do him good. But the question is, how can poor parents, who work hard for a livelihood, afford it? In many cases it is necessary for the boy to look for work. The child can earn a few dollars a week by getting a job in the <pb facs="5423972_1_0188.jpg" n="2"/>city, which would do no good to his physical condition.</p>
   <p>In other cases, it is a question of the young man earning something in order to be able to continue going to school when vacation ends.</p>
   <p>Never before have such opportunities presented themselves to young boys, as this year.</p>
   <p>Work on farms is the way out. We know how the average city Jew will look upon this suggestion. He will make a wry face and say that this kind of work is good for a non-Jew. Others will say, "City boys don't have the strength to do farm work." In normal times their objection would be justified; farmers have very little consideration for their workers. But the demand for farm hands is so large this year that farmers are hiring all men available, thus enabling a young man to bargain in advance as to working hours and lodging. There is also a demand for young men on modern farms that are run like a business, where the working hours are not <pb facs="5423972_1_0189.jpg" n="3"/>too long and the comforts do not vary from those in the city.</p>
   <p>Such a position serves a two-fold purpose: 1. It offers work that will create new energy for another school term. 2. Wages received are not smaller than at any city job.</p>
   <p>There are many agencies here where young men can avail themselves of such jobs. Thousands of young boys will take advantage of this opportunity. It would be desirable if the Jewish young men would join this multitude of vacation workers on farms. In addition to the earnings and the healthy exercises a young man gets, he completes a practical education that money cannot buy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
