<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1932-10-27">October 27, 1932</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1932-10-27">October 27, 1932</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Board, a report was made on the problem of Jewish education. The method of financing a system of Jewish education under the J. C. has been the subject of serious thought and discussion. The commmttee is of the belief that a form of Jewish education is desired by a substantial part of the Jewish community and that it is of benefit to the children who are involved in the various educational processes.</p>
   <p>Accordingly, the committee submitted the following recommendation to the Board as a solution of the problem - that with respect to the allocation of subscriptions, the organizations in the J. C. shall be divided into two groups, those organizations dealing primarily with economic and charitable problems and those organizations dealing primarily with educational and cultural problems.</p>
   <p>For the present all the affiliated organizations of the J. C. shall be classified in Group A with the exception of the Board of Jewish Education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0041.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Group B shall consist of the Board of J. E. and other members that may be included hereafter.</p>
   <p>Subscribers to the J. C. may elect what proportion of their subscriptions shall be used on behalf of Group B. Subscriptions not so designated shall be allocated to Group A.</p>
   <p>This recommendation was to be discussed again in the future by the Board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
