<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Annual Meeting, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1905-04-03">April 3, 1905</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Annual Meeting, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1905-04-03">April 3, 1905</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Report of Executive Board) Schools.</p>
   <p>The total enrollment of the religious school at the Temple was 186, excluding the membership of the confirmation class conducted by Dr. Hirsch, as shown by the report of the School Committee. Of these, ninety are boys and ninety-six girls, taught by six teachers, and the average attendance during the entire term was eighty-six per cent of the enrollment.</p>
   <p>The attendance at the confirmation class was forty-five.</p>
   <p>Special festivals for the celebration of Chanukah and Purim feasts, with appropriate entertainment and instructive features for the children were had.....The report of Miss Julia I. Felsenthal, superintendent of Sinai Mission School....shows a total enrollment of 393 children with an average attendance of 271, being about sixty-nine per cent; and ten teachers together <pb facs="5423972_1_0477.jpg" n="2"/>with a singing teacher and superintendent. Of this force, seven teachers are voluntary, two of whom are former pupils of said school, and three teachers are paid for their services.</p>
   <p>The superintendent of this school suggests that if a somewhat larger appropriation would be granted by this congregation, in order that more of the teaching force might receive renumeration for service, it would tend to enhance the value of the school by insuring a more rigid compliance with the rules as to attendance of the teachers, and with somewhat increased means, more applicants might be taken care of, as fully 150 children who applied for admission had to be turned away for lack of room. At this school the pupils range from second grade to high school, and as to the classes of the community from which they are drawn, it may be said they cover all grades, from the squalid to the most refined in manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
