<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-25">Apr. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Hebrew and Loshon Kodesh</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-25">Apr. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">HEBREW AND LOSHON KODESH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In connection with the annual conference of Hebraists in New York, a large New York Jewish newspaper deems it timely and befitting to remind its readers that Hebrew has made no progress during the past twenty years, because it has not been close to the Synagogue.</p>
   <p>The New York newspaper claims that Loshon Kodesh [the holy tongue] was thirty years ago much more valuable and a more serious factor in American life than modern Hebrew. It concludes its argument against Hebrew with the remark that Hebrew must not and cannot be a movement.</p>
   <p>It is true that twenty-five or thirty years ago there was in America a relatively small number of immigrants who read and wrote Loshon Kodesh. With their passing <pb facs="5423972_1_0291.jpg" n="2"/>away, that period of Loshon Kodesh has become extinct. The young Jew in America cannot convince himself that Hebrew is merely Loshon Kodesh, i.e., a religious article, for we are living in a very irreligious epoch, and if the young Jew in America would have to accept that concept of Hebrew and, together with Loshon Kodesh, swallow many things in which he does not believe, there would be no remnant of Loshon Kodesh in America today. Just as the young generation does not attend the synagogue, so would it not take an interest in Loshon Kodesh.</p>
   <p>The transformation of Loshon Kodesh into Hebrew did not succeed in keeping the young generation close to everything pertaining to Judaism.</p>
   <p>As a religious article, Loshon Kodesh became extinct with the passing away of the old generation, and the number of Hebraists is mounting from day to day. Hebrew as the language of the Jewish people is growing and developing even in America. But Loshon Kodesh, as a religious article, is not only dead in America but also in Europe and Palestine as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0292.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Europe and Palestine as well.</p>
   <p>There are in America today fifty thousand Jewish children who understand Hebrew. They understand Hebrew because they have studied Hebrew and not Loshon Kodesh. Now that they have acquired a knowledge of Hebrew they are bound to Judaism and we know that they will remain Jews. If they would have no knowledge of Hebrew, they would not remain Jews, at least not productive Jews. Through Hebrew they can be attracted to all Jewish traditions, and, as Hebraists, they are, in every respect, against all destructive tendencies in the life of our people, such as Reform, assimilation, and so forth.</p>
   <p>While we recognize the value of Hebrew as the preserving and cementing force in our life, we do not, for a moment, lose sight of the shortcomings of modern Hebrew instruction and the tendencies which prevail in modern Hebrew education. The pressure to make Hebrew entirely independent of religious life and to pivot the whole of Judaism on Hebrew alone, is too farfetched. Hebrew must not be completely separated from the Jewish religious traditions, just as it must not <pb facs="5423972_1_0293.jpg" n="4"/>and cannot be only a part of religion. Hebrew is, after all, a language, and it is not the purpose of a language to regulate the relationship between the individual and the Creator. That is the purpose of religion. The language can, and does have religious functions. But a purely religious language is nonsense--and it is no less nonsense when modern Hebrew teachers today seek to isolate completely the Hebrew language for the Jewish religion, because between Hebrew and the Jewish religion there are more intimate ties than between any other language and religion. This historical fact must not be ignored.</p>
   <p>If the modern Hebrew teacher will take into consideration the historical relationship between Hebrew and religion, and will be more moderate in his verdict, modern Hebrew, then, will not be opposed by ultra-Orthodox elements. On the contrary, modern Hebrew instruction will be more productive in every respect.</p>
   <p>There is something lacking in modern Hebrew. Most Jews do not know what is lacking and are, therefore, very friendly toward it. What modern Hebrew lacks is the spirit of the Jewish tradition--historical orientation--and sooner or later modern Hebrew will have to return to the historical tradition, but this does not mean that Hebrew will again become Loshon Kodesh.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0294.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For the past fifty years, Loshon Kodesh has not created anything. Whatever it did create was inspired by the spirit of modern Hebrew. And they [the creative works of Loshon Kodesh] are worthless. The new Jewish national literature is Hebraic and not Loshon Kodesh. Chaim Bialik, the prince of our national poetry, is a Hebraist and not a Loshon Kodesh poet.</p>
   <p>Hebrew has its flaws but in due time they will be removed, whereas Loshon Kodesh has, since long ago, been dead.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
