<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">December 1918-January 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">December 1918-January 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our students spend three hours an evening in class three times a week, and by thus doing, we hope that they may complete the regular high school course in slightly more than two years; for those of exceptional ability, an even shorter period may suffice. We divide our course into five terms, each divided into 24 weeks. Following the regular course of instruction, the student carries no more than three subjects in any one term. These becomes necessary because of the very evident difficulty, namely:- the fact that they are employed all day long and that they must have time to prepare their work in order to further facilitate the progress of the student.</p>
   <p>We have adopted methods of teaching of a scientific character, which are calculated to effect the greatest possible economy in time and effort on the part of the student. We have been successful in securing professional high school teachers of large experience and established reputation.</p>
   <p>The tuition is $20.00 a term of 24 weeks. Those who find that they cannot pay the entire amount at one time, pay only $8.00 at the time of registration, plus $1.00 as a registration fee, and the balance at the rate of $3.00 per month. The following is an outline of the course:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>English 1 (A) The development of a working knowledge of spelling, punctuation, grammar sentence structure and frequent composition. (B) class readings selected from :- Days of Ancient Rome, The Talisman, The Rhyme of the Ancient Mariner, The Merchant of Venice and Ivanhoe. (C) assigned outside reading with written reports. ( Text...Hitchock's Enlarged New Practice Book.)</p>
   <p>Ehglish 2 (A) Further grammar study, the structure of the paragraph, exercises in narration , description exposition and argumentation. (B) Class readings selected from Julius Caesar, Twelfth Night, Tale of Two Cities, and Silas Marner. (C) Assigned outside readings.</p>
   <p>English 3 (A) The principles of rhetoric, the choice of words, good usage and salecisms. Frequent compositions required, which are corrected and discussed by the instructor. (B) English Literature. Class readings selected from Macbeth Idylls of the King Henry V and Democracy Today. (C) Assignmed outside readings. (Texts....Herrick and Damon, New Composition and Rhetoric; Halleck New English Literature.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0176.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>English 4 (A) Structural principles of sentence paragraph, and whole composition. The choice of words and detailed study of the kinds of composition. (B) The History of English Literature..The American Literature. (Textbooks and Lecturers) class readings:- Hamlet, The Princess, and Macauleys Essays. (C) Outside readings. (Texts...Helleck, New English Literature and Long, Outlines of American Literature.</p>
   <p>Algebra 1.....This course includes a thorough and comprehensive study of the fundamental operations, factoring, fractions, simple and simultaneous equations, graphs, involution, radicals and quadratic equations. (Text...Hawkes, Luby and Truton. Algebra.</p>
   <p>Algebra 2...This course begins with a review of Algebra 1 and includes a further study of quadratic equations, and graphs. Among the advanced topics are;- the binomial theorem, progression, ratio and proportions, and Logarithms. (Text....Second Course in Algebra, by Hawkes, Luby and Touton.</p>
   <p>Plane Geometry...The course in Plane Geometry includes the material covered in a standard text on the subject. (Text..Plane Geometry, Wentworth and Smith.) Solid Geometry......(Text....Solid Geometry, Wentworth and Smith)</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0177.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Latin 1...Elementary grammar as presented in D'ooges First Year Latin. Special emphasis of practical application of the language in copious translating from and into Latin.</p>
   <p>Latin 2..Widening of grammar study especially in usage of cases, tenses and modes. Harkness Complete Latin grammar as manual exercises in translating into Latin. Selections from Caesar's Commentaries, Cornelius Nepos, Sallustius.</p>
   <p>Latin 3...Grammar review in connection with exercises infree reproductions. Selections from Cicero's Orations, Philosophical Works and Epistles, and Roman Legal Procedure.</p>
   <p>Latin 4.....Selections from Ovid's Metamorphases, Vergil's Aeneid, Odes of Horace, Roman Antiquities and Topography.</p>
   <p>French 1....Thorough drill in pronunciation and spelling based on phonetic principles, grammar with special attention to verbs, regular conjungations, indicative made. Fraser and Squaire, Lessons 1-XLVII. Conversational exercises, reading of easy prose.</p>
   <p>French 2.....Irregular verbs, subjunctive mode syntax. Fraser and Squaire</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0178.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Lessons XLVII and XCII. Reading of short stories easy plays, conversational exercises and free reproduction.</p>
   <p>French3....Grammar review, outline of history of French literature. Reading of selections from classic and romantic period. Selection of short poems; The (short) modern novel; Themes and Conversation.</p>
   <p>French 4....Commercial and Scientific French.</p>
   <p>German I....Through instruction in fundamental grammar, including declensions of nouns, pronouns and adjectives, auxiliary verbs and the outlines of weak and strong conjugation. Enough elementary syntax to make possible the early reading of simple texts; direct method as far as practicable.</p>
   <p>German II....Systematic study of verbs, passive voice, imperfect verbs, and subjunctive mode. The princi<gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>les of German syntax. Etymology and derivation as an aid to understanding of Anglo-Saxon relation to German. Reading of several short stories with exercises in free reproduction, conversational German.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0179.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>German III. Systematic review and widening of grammar study. Reading of classics. (Schiller, Goethe, Lessing and so forth) Outline of History of German Literature. Essays in German on Literary and Historical Topics.</p>
   <p>German. IV. Scientific German, Outline of Modern German Thought, especially in science and commerce.</p>
   <p>Ancient History....Earliest man---the story of Egypt, Syria and Mesopotamia.. their contributions to Civilization. The Greeks---their political, social, economic, religious, intellectual and artistic life, and its value in modern times. The Romans---their government---their expansion and system of world Empire---their political life and its elation to modern governments.....Text....Webster's Ancient History.</p>
   <p>Medieval and Modern History. Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire-----the migrations of the nations---the Empire of Char<gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>emagne feudalism---the Crusades---the Renaissance and the Reformation---The dynastic and Commercial wars of the 17th and 18th centuries---the French Revolution---The Creation of the French Republic and Italiam Kingdom---Rise and Fall of German Empire---The World Expansion of Great Britain---the World War and its results......Text......Robinson's Modern Times.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0180.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>United States History....Colonial Period....Political Economic and Industrial Conditions. The Revolution and the Creation of the Constitution....the Story of our Territorial Growth.....the Slavery Issue and the Civil War...the Development of the West and South.... Economic Changes in Last Half Century and Present Problems.....Text....History Of The American Nation...McLaughlins</p>
   <p>General Science....This course includes an elementary treatise of the following subjects;- Force and energy; hear and combustion; elements and compounds; electricity; light; sound; simple machines; earth science; plants; animals; physiology and sanitation. The course is a non-mathematical treatment of the high points in science had has a two-fold purpose:- (A) To prepare students for more technical courses in Science, (B) To give studnts a scientific understanding of the familiar phenomena and laws of nature.....Text...The First Year of Science...Hessler.</p>
   <p>Physiology and Sanitation....A treatise on the structure and workings of the human body supplemented by a course in practical methods in sanitation. The latter includes a brief study of the kinds of disease----producing organism, the prevention and treatment of various diseases, first aid, and discoveries in medicine.....Text....Sanitation and Physiology....Ritchie <pb facs="5423972_1_0181.jpg" n="8"/>Physiography.....This course includes a studyof the gases of the atmosphere, factors of climate, interpretation of weather and contains maps, weathering and erasion, rivers, lakes and shores, The effects of physiography upon trade plant and animal life, are considered....Text...Physiography...Salisbury</p>
   <p>Physics.....An elementary course including the fundamental principles of the mechanics of solids, liquids and gases, heat, light, sound and electricity. This course presupposes a knowledge of one year of Algebra and one year of Plane Geometry. About one hald of the time is devoted to experimental work. Text....A High School Course in Physics.....Gorton.....Manual.....Experimental Physics.....Smith, Fower and Burton....</p>
   <p>Chemistry.....This course emphasizes the essentials of elementary chemistry with a detailed study of elements and common compounds. Considerable drill is given tothe understanding of molecular formulae, valence, and the writing of simple equations. Consideration of chemical theoryis emphasized <pb facs="5423972_1_0182.jpg" n="9"/>only when necessary for the understanding of essentials. Frequent drills in stoechiometry are given. About two-thirds of the time is devoted to laboratory work. Text....Elementary Chemistry....Alexander, Smith..... Manual.....A Laboratory Outline of Elementary Chemistry....Alexander Smith....</p>
   <p>Political Economy.....A discussion of the growth of the science; the development of the present industrial system; wealth; the laws govering supply and demand production; Capital and Labor; value; interest; credit money; present day economic pro lems, such as Tariff, Socialism and Co-Operation..... Text.....Elementary Principles of Economics....Ely and Wicker.</p>
   <p>Civics.....Nature and forms of government; The genesis of the union; The Federal Government, its nature, organization and powers; The Government of the State, County and Town and City problems; Suffrage and other present day questions. Text...Advanced Civics....Forman.....</p>
   <p>Shorthand....Munson System, which is simple and very widely used..... Typewriting....Touch Method, now approved and used in all large merchandise concerns. (To those that graduate from our Commercial Department, we guarantee positions.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
