<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past nine years, we have been accredited by the University of Illinois, and on January 14, 1928, we received the following communication from Professor H. A. Hollister, high school visitor of the University of Illinois, which reads: "On my recommendation, as a result of a recent visit, the Council of Administration has approved the renewal of accrediting your high school for a term of two years, or until June 30, 1930. The enclosed card should be permanently filed in your office as property of the school."</p>
   <p>The credits referred to in Dean Hollister's letter are as follows: Algebra 11/2 credits; Plane Geometry 1; English Composition 1; English Literature 3; Latin 3; German 2; French 2; Hebrew 2; Ancient History 1; Medieval and Modern History 1; Civics 1; Economics 1; Business Law 1/2; Physiology 1/2; Physics 1; Chemistry 1; and General Science 1/2.</p>
   <p>The school has been accredited, as stated, for the past nine years, and it is our hope that it will continue to be such for many years to come. Many of our graduates are attending some of the leading Universities in the Middle West.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0051.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many have already graduated andare following one of a dozen professions. We have made it our business to keep intouch with the universities regarding the students who have graduated from our high school, and it is gratifying to state that we find that in most instances they represent exemplary students in the schools they are enrolled.</p>
   <p>With the excellent faculty andthe splendid physical facilities, which include a library, lecture hall, class rooms, laboratories, as well as recreational lounges for the students, and a faculty of excellent experienced teachers, which represents some of the best high school teachers in the city, we should continue to grow in numbers as well as in service rendered.</p>
   <p>This it may be evident that our student body is of a kind which fully deserves the efforts made by us in its behalf. It is a serious, hard-working lot. It is not, therefore, only a pieceof Americanization work that we are doing here in our high school, but an actual achievement in human improvement that we are effecting. Our students may not all become leaders of the Jewish community of their generation. They will all, nevertheless, be better citizens, better human beings and will be able to contribute more to the general social body of our community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
