<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-19">Mar. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Bishop Manning's Appeal against Evil of Divorce</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-19">Mar. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">BISHOP MANNING'S APPEAL AGAINST EVIL OF DIVORCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appeal issued by Bishop Manning, principal clergyman of the Episcopalian Church in New York, to all religious organizations, including the Jewish, for a united fight against the evil of divorce, will find no response in Jewish circles. Bishop Manning represents the Christian view of marriage, which is fundamentally different from the Jewish standpoint, in which marriage is a contract that can become null and void if both parties find a life-partnership impossible.</p>
   <p>The Christian religion demands the impossible--[the continuation of] the nuptial ties between husband and wife under all circumstances. On the other hand, the Jewish religion takes into account human nature, and experience shows that despite the most liberal Jewish marriage and divorce laws, Jewish family <pb facs="5423972_1_0612.jpg" n="2"/>life is comparatively stronger and purer than non-Jewish family life. The scandalous divorce trials with which the press is overrun each day, do not involve Jewish couples. Seldom are they Jewish, and if they are Jewish, they are usually "Americanized" Jews, i. e., Jews who have lost their Jewish traditions and who are neither here nor there. What the Jews need, is not to make divorce laws more stringent, or to prohibit divorce entirely, but rather to fortify the ancient Jewish traditions of a pure family life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
