<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Great and Free American Public School</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Seligman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Italian)</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>I C (Swedish)</item>
     <item>I C (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>I C (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT AND FREE AMERICAN PUBLIC SCHOOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Seligman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: This is the second article of a series dealing with the American public school system. The first article appeared on January 16, 1922.]</p>
   <p>Many of us immigrant Jews have a very poor opinion of the American public school. The radical dislikes American capitalism and considers the school to be worthless because it is a capitalist institution. The religious Jew sees the American school absorb the child's best years [in secular study]. He sees that his child has to devote so much time to school studies that he has very little time left to study the Torah, and that he must do that studying, hurriedly, in the evening. The religious Jew, therefore, considers the public school to be of little value.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0143.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are also [other] Jews who do not have a good word to say about the schools. It is not a question of principle with them. Those critics, each in his own way, consider the time their children spend at school to be wasted. It seems, to judge by their expressions, that their children go to school because they have to, and not because they want to.</p>
   <p>What are the chief complaints? The first complaint is with regard to the duration of the course of study. Why should it take eight whole years? Many of us think that compared to the Talmud and its commentaries, the course of study in an American school is an easy one. We think that a child does not have to spend so many years in order to gain the little knowledge that the American school can give him.</p>
   <p>There is some truth to that complaint, as far as the Jewish children are concerned. The Jewish child has a keen mind, is quick-witted and comprehends easily. The local Board of Education is aware of that fact. Mr. Mortenson, the school <pb facs="5423972_1_0144.jpg" n="3"/>superintendent, has a very high opinion of the Jewish child. Had the other groups within the local population shown the same capabilities, then the course of study would have been reduced from eight to seven years, and perhaps less.</p>
   <p>The public schools were created for everybody. The Board of Education must take into consideration the small percentage of subnormal children, for whom it is necessary to assign to special rooms and classes, because the children are mentally weak and need special care to enable them to become, if possible, useful members of the community. The Board of Education must not, however, create special classes for a whole group of children who are, generally, more capable than the average child of other groups.</p>
   <p>The children of other nationalities, such as the Polish or the Italian, have a less intelligent home environment than the Jewish child. The school, therefore, must do more for their education. Perhaps an eight-year course is not long enough for them. The longer they stay at school, the better it is for <pb facs="5423972_1_0145.jpg" n="4"/>the city and the country. On the other hand, the Germans and the Scandinavians are much more capable, and their environment is better, but they are slow in their development, their mental faculties do not work quickly, but proceed slowly, at a leisurely tempo. These groups also must have an eight-year course. This applies as well to the children who, we say, are native Americans, because those children have inherited their mental capabilities from their forefathers who were immigrants. How can we Jews, a small minority, demand that the eight-year course be shortened in our behalf? We, ourselves, are afraid of [being considered] exceptions; it may arouse envy or hatred, which will be very harmful to us.</p>
   <p>When the eight-year course was introduced, the authorities took into consideration [the fact] that the population of our big city was composed of many nationalities; they considered the average capabilities of a city child (the capabilities of a country child surely do not exceed those of a city child), the average home from which the child comes, and many other things which have a direct or indirect bearing upon the problem. The child that shows better than average capabilities <pb facs="5423972_1_0146.jpg" n="5"/>is rewarded by receiving better marks for his work. In many cases, he can skip a half or a full grade. It so happens that in the Jewish districts the population is very dense, the schools are overcrowded, many schools have to work overtime and have two shifts, because of space shortage. Of course, the possibilities of skipping half a grade, are greatly reduced. They are building new schools every year in every neighborhood, and it will take a little time until there is adequate space in the schools. In a great city like Chicago, the shortage of space is unavoidable.</p>
   <p>The public schools know very well what is going on in this wide world, and, from time to time, they make changes. They are considering now the problem of an eight-year course, and the possibility and desirability of shortening it. It was proposed that the course in elementary school should take only six years. They want to lengthen the high-school course to six years, the last two years being considered as college work, thus reducing by two years the average university course. These proposals are being seriously discussed in pedagogical <pb facs="5423972_1_0147.jpg" n="6"/>circles, in Chicago and elsewhere. It is quite possible that this plan may be put into effect, although, as mentioned above, there are many obstacles, due to the fact that the population of our city is composed of so many nationalities.</p>
   <p>First of all, let us have less of that belittling attitude. Let us not entirely belittle the work of the public school, because this or that child could finish the course in less time. If we consider that the school has to serve the population as a whole, we will find that it is doing useful work. From our own, narrow point of view, we have some just criticism of the school system, but the school system has to serve not a small part of the population but the entire population. Furthermore, our complaint cannot be adjusted quickly due to many obstacles. Instead of criticizing, it would be better if a committee of prominent individuals were to see the superintendent of schools, and discuss with him our complaint about the long course. Maybe that would speed up the realization of the plan for a six-year course in the public schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0148.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>To be interested in a child's education does not mean to belittle what is being done in the schools, but to demand improvement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
