<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-31">July 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Rabbi Isaac Elchanan's Theological Seminary of New York vs. the Hebrew Theological College of Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By S. Z. Fineberg. (President of the Students' Organization of the H. T. C.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-07-31">July 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">RABBI ISAAC ELCHANAN'S THEOLOGICAL SEMINARY OF NEW YORK vs. THE HEBREW THEOLOGICAL COLLEGE OF CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By S. Z. Fineberg. (President of the Students' Organization of the H. T. C.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For several decades the Rabbi Isaac Elchanan's Theological Seminary of New York has been educating our American-Jewish youth, has imbued them with spiritual aspirations, instilled into them lofty ideals and planted in their hearts a love for traditional Judaism. What the New York institution has done in its respective city, the Hebrew Theological College has been doing in Chicago. Both institutions of learning have been serving as reservoirs of our traditional faith, from which disseminated knowledge and wisdom. From these sacred Yeshivahs have come forth profound scholars who are genuinely the champions of our religion and people.</p>
   <p>During the entire time that the two American Jewish seminaries have been training and educating young men to become rabbis, they have been doing their commendable work without recognizing each other's accomplishments. There has always existed an indifferent attitude toward each other. But now, however, a complete change has taken place. It is apparent that both institutions are beginning to realize that they have many things in common. And since it has <pb facs="5423972_1_0397.jpg" n="2"/>finally dawned upon them that they have similar ideals, aims, and ambitions, they have planned and arranged certain means and ways whereby a closer and more intimate relationship between both Yeshivahs can be created. One of these ways will be the institution of a friendly rivalry in the form of debates. These debates are to be held annually or semi-annually; alternately in Chicago and New York.</p>
   <p>At present the first debate has been scheduled to occur in Chicago on Wednesday evening, September 7, in the gorgeous theater-auditorium of the new magnificent building of the Jewish Peoples' Institute, which is located on the corner of Douglas Blvd. and St. Louis Ave., across from the Hebrew Theological College. The Students' Organization of our Yeshivah has invited the Students' Organization of the New York Yeshivah to send a debating team composed of three of its best debaters and orators, who will represent it is a debate against three of our selected debaters. New York has accepted our invitation and challenge, and on September 7, Chicago Jewry will have an unusual opportunity to witness an epoch-making event; namely, the first debate between the two greatest Yeshivahs in this country.</p>
   <p>This debate will be entirely conducted in the English language. The question to be debated is: Resolved, That the parochial school system is the sole <pb facs="5423972_1_0398.jpg" n="3"/>solution to the problem for the permanency of traditional Judaism in this country. New York selected the affirmative side and Chicago will argue the negative view of the question.</p>
   <p>It is almost needless to make a request that Chicago Jewry should not fail this great event when they will have the first opportunity to listen to some of the cleverest debaters in the Jewish world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
