<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-15">Oct. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Melting Pot</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-15">Oct. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO MELTING POT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Chicago Hebrew Institute the new season of activities has opened in various fields such as the institute employs each year to build its people mentally as well as physically. Last Sunday at a meeting, the Institute Lecture Association worked out a plan for the lecture season for the coming winter.</p>
   <p>The first lecture will be held Wednesday Nov. 5th, on the theme: "Should Women Demand the Same Rights as Men?" by Mr. Harris J. Bridges. The second lecture will be Nov. 12th, on "Bergson's Philosophy," by Prof. B. H. Boynton of the Chicago University. Thus each week an important and interesting lecture will be given.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0549.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The large public that attends these lectures, concerts and other activities, may expect great things this season, because of the capable and energetic new superintendent, Mr. Philip Seaman.</p>
   <p>The 27th and the 28th of October will be devoted to an interesting oratorical contest at the Hebrew Institute proper. Members of various older and younger clubs will participate and prizes will be awarded to the winners. Those wishing to participate will be entered all during this week. But everyone must bring a copy of his speech not later than Oct. 25. Participants will also be required to pay a 50 cent fee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0550.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Starting also this Sunday will be the concert season at the Hebrew Institute under the direction of the well-known director, Mr. Alexander Djukovsky.</p>
   <p>The concert will start punctually at 2:30 p. m. These concerts are very popular and attract a large attendance. There is a rich selection in the opening program. Mr. Djukovsky will also render a violin solo.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0551.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The children of the Duvorah Sabbath School will celebrate the Succos Holiday this Saturday at the Bes Hamedrish Hagodol on Maxwell Street. Mr. S. Hurwitz will speak about the holiday.</p>
   <p>On this day, too, the children of the Ivnah Sabbath School will celebrate Succos at 7 p. m. in the evening. The main speaker will be Rabbi Budzinsky.</p>
   <p>The first lecture of a series of monthly lectures, dealing with international, state and local government, will be held this Friday evening at Hull House, under the auspices of the Young Women's Sufferage Alliance. The public is invited to attend.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0552.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The following speeches have been arranged by the Order of the Knight of Zion for Sunday evening:</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Shulman will report on the congress in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>M. Abrams and H. Stoneberg will address a massmeeting in Rock Island, Ill.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Silver and Judge Bragstone will address a meeting in Gary, Ind.</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Schulman will speak at the Bney Mosha Shul, the first day of Succos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
