<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-23">May 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditations of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-23">May 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATIONS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is to be Boys' Week-- a week dedicated to the children of the nation. Boys will flaunt their school flags to the breeze; boys will carry banners and placards with written messages, to express their devotion to the tasks of their elders when they grow up to be old enough to do their bit in the drama of life. Surely there is much that is inspiring in the celebration of Boys' Week. Unforunately the boys that will march and disport themselves merrily will be limited to those groups who are not at work in the factories and offices and other places where boys are employed. The law forbids boys below fourteen to work and below sixteen to work what is called a full man's working day. Some provision is made for school for boys for such as must go to work at fourteen. Some day perhaps no boy or girl will go to work under twenty, as in a perfectly enlightened society no young men or women, who have not yet really reached adult manhood or womanhood, really should. Some day <pb facs="5423972_1_0116.jpg" n="2"/>education will be compulsory to a much later age than the present and provision will be made to avoid the necessity of young men and women to earn a livelihood for themselves or even their relatives, when they have not completed the necessary training that should be the legitimate right and heritage of all children of the race. Some will argue and say that not every person requires an education up to the age we have indicated above, that we are dreaming of a Utopia, which is neither necessary nor wise, but let us call their attention to the fact that not long ago there were no compulsory educational laws at all and children went to work at an age when they should have attended an elementary school, being too young for higher classes. Education is a good thing and we cannot have too much of it. Our boys and our girls need fewer celebrations of weeks or days dedicated to them in principle but not in fact, and more years dedicated to them both in principle and in fact. When that time does finally come, we will be glad that it has become so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
