<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-04">Sept. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">To School</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-04">Sept. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TO SCHOOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new school term is about to begin. We refer here to the secular school, to the public school, and not to the Jewish school. Tomorrow, hundreds of children will again pick up their books and tablets which they have neglected during the hot summer weeks, and will begin again to study the basic principles of their education and knowledge--the weapons they will have to use later on in their struggle for existence.</p>
   <p>Among this vast army of children, there are also our children--Jewish children. It is for their sake that we wish here to say a few words. Some parents, who often think about the future of their children, may find food for thought in what we are about to say, and in some way benefit therefrom.</p>
   <p>At one time Jews did not study with a view to earning a livelihood. Study was <pb facs="5423972_1_0195.jpg" n="2"/>wholly separated from material advantage. Individuals studied because it was their sacred duty to do so. We had little method or system in our teaching. Perhaps this was not entirely necessary because our studies were not aimed at their advantageous application to our daily life. They dealt mostly with the past and served only to maintain our ties with the past.</p>
   <p>This, however, was only possible in times when the necessities of life were limited. People did not require much for their subsistence. It did not take any special skill or art to eke out a livelihood.</p>
   <p>In the last couple of generations, conditions in the more civilized parts of the world have undergone a complete change. The struggle to earn a livelihood has sharpened, and life has begun to require more essentials. Work has become a necessity. Jewish children threw aside education and started to learn a trade. They became tailors, locksmiths, carpenters. Only experienced craftsmen taught them these trades. They learned these trades without system or method, [just] as they had formerly studied the Talmud. They discarded book <pb facs="5423972_1_0196.jpg" n="3"/>knowledge as if it were useless. Thus, a horrible condition of illiteracy developed among Jews. There arose a generation which sought to forget the past, and lived only for the present. They used books merely for pastime, and not for study.</p>
   <p>In the meanwhile, society, on the one hand, began to develop the mechanical instruments, the machinery, which revolutionized all the methods of production, and on the other hand, national consciousness began to develop among nations who viewed the past as a valuable guide to the future.</p>
   <p>The Jew finds it difficult to adapt himself to the changing conditions. He lacks the equipment for it.</p>
   <p>Great numbers of immigrants came to America and found a new home here, a home which offered them countless opportunities, and which enabled them to earn an easier livelihood. The desire to study eventually awakened in the Jew, but it was no longer a desire to study the past. The desire to study has been <pb facs="5423972_1_0197.jpg" n="4"/>carried over to secular studies. Just as the traditional Jewish mother wanted her sons to become rabbis, so every Jewish mother of today wishes to see her son become a doctor, or a lawyer or a big businessman. Our ties with the past, our friendly relations with our own people are being entirely neglected. To our own detriment, we are drifting toward another extreme.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to realize what is going on in the world at this time. The world, and the nations in it, are now seeking to adapt themselves to democratic institutions. This is the significance of the World War, and this is also the significance of the unrest which we are witnessing in America. Knowledge which has no practical application to life will soon prove to be of little value. The engineer, the chemist, the agriculturalist, the physician--in short, he who can make his academic knowledge socially useful--will have a secure position in society. Even big businessmen, millionaires, will not be as secure, because the nations are constantly placing larger taxes on enormous wealth, on large inheritances, on large incomes, and in the course of time these taxes will take away the wealth of the rich. One revolution in a country can destroy all the huge fortunes. But in wartime, as in times of peace, the man qualified to <pb facs="5423972_1_0198.jpg" n="5"/>do some type of work, can always find an outlet for his skill, as well as for his talents.</p>
   <p>A spiritual grip on life is also necessary. Without it a man is like a petal torn from a flower; the petal then loses its identity as a floral specie, and is of little value.</p>
   <p>Jewish parents must, therefore, bear two things in mind when they consider the future of their children who are sent to school: First, the development of the manual, as well as mental abilities [of their children] in a specific, useful branch of human endeavor; second, the inculcation of a Jewish consciousness so that the children will know their people and their past, which will help them to develop their own individuality and personality. Fortunate are they who enter life so well equipped.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
