<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1883-03-16">March 16, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Educational Society Once More</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1883-03-16">March 16, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY ONCE MORE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a preliminary meeting recently held of the directors of this society, the above subject was freely discussed. When in the years 1877-78, this organization was first found, a warm sentiment prevailed to give the children some facilities for acquiring the Hebrew language. Quite a number of our Jewish citizens freely subscribed a regular stipend of four dollars per annum. A fund of four-hundred dollars was at once realized as a nucleus and Mr. H. Felsenthal then secretary or treasurer, held that fund in trust. For some reason no other efforts were made to prosecute or make a beginning. Not only the society lacked interest therein, but the Jewish public of Chicago showed an ulter apathy in the undertaking.....Whether the society was one of policy or not, it has proved a palpable failure; not only for the lack of interest evinced on the part of the Israelites of Chicago, but even the board were passive in the matter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0276.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The greatest obstacle however, proved to be children themselves, who were not willing to submit to an exclusive Hebrew education. The difficulties in that direction were lucidly given in many articles on this theme through these columns. In fact our Sabbath school teachers knew this as well as the Synagogue Directors.....It is now freely admitted by even the moderate orthodox Israelites everywhere that the sphere of exclusive Hebrew schools is not only useless, but abortive of educational advantages to our rising Israelites in every sense.....It seems that the Board of the above society (now) proposes to aid two worthy institutions with the fund on hand and such additional subscriptions as our charitably inclined citizens will extend equally between the Industrial Society recently instituted and the Kindergarten, all under the auspices of the Jewish Ladies of this city.....The Industrial School, as now successfully in vogue every Friday afternoon at B'nai Sholon Temple, is destined to achieve a worthy name among the most charitable institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0277.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Poor children are taught, clothed and fed there under the most benigh influence of our Jewish ladies. The recently organized Kindergarten called into life by Johanna Lodge No. 9, at the suggestion of Dr. and Mrs. E. G. Hirsch, is no less one of the much needed institutions in which the poor will find a helpmeet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
