<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Executive Board, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1884-02-19">Feb. 19, 1884</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Executive Board, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1884-02-19">Feb. 19, 1884</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We read the following communication from the Superintendent (of the Sabbath School), Dr. E. G. Hirsch, to wit:</p>
   <p>The fundamental proposition, which I would advance and which is without doubt, sure of your unanimous consent, is this: The school and the pulpit must agree in their teachings. The school's main object is to prepare our children for an active and intelligent participation in the aims and ends of the congregation's life. Our congregation is liberal, but still within the lines of historical Judaism. All liberal religions agree in making morals the cardinal essence of religion; while on the other hand, a Jewish congregation is the heir of an historical movement, the main outlines of which every Jew should be acquainted with. In this double character of our congregation, are indicated most clearly the lines of instruction for our school. The child confided to our care, should leave us well equipped with moral ideas and the historical knowledge of the growth of Judaism. Happily, experience has shown that either of these two branches can well be utilized in behalf of the other. Moral ideas can be inculcated by means of Jewish <pb facs="5423972_1_0497.jpg" n="2"/>history and literature, while what is learned in the moral lesson, can easily be turned to good account for the purposes of historical instruction.</p>
   <p>The great difficulty in the way of a successful accomplishment of the work is the lack of good teachers and good manuals written from our point of view. Volunteer teachers are scarcely fitted to the task. Their zeal and enthusiasm is indeed generally of a much higher order than that of professional paid teachers. But besides pedagogical tact, knowledge of a certain kind is required.</p>
   <p>To charge the superintendent with the preparation of the volunteer teachers is unreasonable, not on account of his own personal inconvenience, but on account of the impossibility to change in a few hours into competent instructors, well meaning and more or less well informed graduates of our high-schools and so-called universities.</p>
   <p>Nor can a professional Hebrew teacher of the old style fill the requirments satisfactorily. In all probability, he is still less competent than our <pb facs="5423972_1_0498.jpg" n="3"/>paid or unpaid volunteer teachers have been. If the congregation desires to so reorganize our school as to come up to the standard, at least one competent professional teacher should be on its staff. He, in conjunction with the superintendent, might undertake to fill the other places; and train the other teachers gradually so as to adopt in their class work our methods and so carry out our designs. Besides three, or at least two, more instructors will be needed.</p>
   <p>Proper manuals are also a desideratum hard to fill. To be brief, we need a sensible Biblical history, with a Biblical reader and extracts from post-Biblical literature. 2. A post-Biblical history, 3. A compendium for instruction in Ethics, to which might be added a short history of Judaism and the beliefs of the Jews. Who is to write these books and who is to publish them, is another question which I cannot answer.</p>
   <p>The course in our school should extend over six years - from eight to fourteen. With a little interest on the part of the parents, discipline might easily be maintained. A practical plan of the division in the studies, and <pb facs="5423972_1_0499.jpg" n="4"/>for the maintenance of discipline could easily be framed, after teachers and books have been found.</p>
   <p>Emil G. Hirsch.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
