<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-19">Dec. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Our Educational Budget</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-19">Dec. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">OUR EDUCATIONAL BUDGET</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a statement issued by Rabbis and laymen, who are interested in Jewish education in the city of Chicago, our educational budget amounts to one hundred and fifty thousand dollars a year, that is to say, the Orthodox Jewish community in Chicago contributes the above mentioned sum every year toward the maintenance of Jewish educational establishments, like Talmud Torahs, Talmudic schools, etc.</p>
   <p>There are three hundred thousand Jews in the city of Chicago. The majority of these three hundred thousand Jews are either positively Orthodox or they are at least anti-radical and anti-Reform, and sympathize with the Orthodox cause. The spokesmen of Orthodoxy are perfectly right in claiming that the anti-radical and anti-Reform elements in the community belong to the Orthodox camp, and should be considered part and parcel of the Orthodox community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One may state without exaggeration, that the Orthodox Jewish community in Chicago forms the majority of the Chicago Jewry. Let us say that one hundred thousand Jews in the city of Chicago belong to the non-Orthodox camp. There still remain two hundred thousand Jews, who could be considered as in sympathy with Orthodoxy, and these two hundred thousand Jews are spending one hundred and fifty thousand dollars every year for Jewish education.</p>
   <p>Many people think this is a respectable sum, but we think that this is an inadequate sum, and that instead of being proud of ourselves we should be ashamed of ourselves for not spending more than seventy-five cents per capita on Jewish education. The least we should spend is four times as much: not a hundred and fifty thousand dollars, but six hundred thousand dollars, and even then not all our educational problems will be solved.</p>
   <p>We spend a hundred and fifty thousand dollars only because we provide for four thousand children in the City of Chicago. But there [are] some forty thousand Jewish children in Chicago, and thirty-six thousand of them <pb facs="5423972_1_0157.jpg" n="3"/>do not receive any Jewish education at all. In view of the fact that ten out of every hundred Jewish children in Chicago receive any sort of Jewish education, our annual educational budget is a tremendous one. If properly managed, this sum should be sufficient to provide not four, but six or seven thousand children with Jewish education. It seems that we have made up our mind to work with a maximum of expense [for] a minimum of results.</p>
   <p>Our education budget of a hundred and fifty thousand dollars a year for a Jewish community of two hundred thousand souls, is a joke, and the poorest Jewish community in Lithuania or Poland spends proportionately more than that. In Germany, for instance, the Jewish education is not so general as in Eastern Europe, and the German Jews spend five dollars per annum and per capita for Jewish educational purposes. The Dutch Jews spend four dollars per annum and per capita for educational purposes, and the Swiss Jews, nineteen francs per annum and per capita. But the prospering and flourishing Chicago Jewish community spends seventy-five cents only per annum and per capita for Jewish educational purposes. But still Chicago is called the Jerusalem of <pb facs="5423972_1_0158.jpg" n="4"/>America. It is a pious city, an Orthodox Jewish city, and a generous Jewish city. It is true, Chicago Jews are generous and are liberal, except when it comes to pay for Jewish education.</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that things cannot go on much further in the same way without any change, unless the present Jewish generation has decided that the coming generation shall not know the rock from which it was hewn, and shall be ignorant of everything Jewish. If this is the idea of the Chicago Jews, then every further discussion on our educational problem is unnecessary and superfluous. However, we do not believe that the Chicago Jews purposely and wilfully neglect the Jewish education of their children, so that they may grow up Jewish ignoramuses.</p>
   <p>We believe that the Orthodox Jews in Chicago, who are providing for Jewish education, must attempt to organize such an educational agency for the entire city that would enable every Jewish district to build up its own educational establishment. By building a Talmud Torah here and a Talmud Torah there, <pb facs="5423972_1_0159.jpg" n="5"/>nothing much can be done. The work must be planned in advance, and carried out according to certain policies and intentions, or there will be in one district five Talmud Torahs and none in the other. What is thus needed is a central Jewish educational agency in the city of Chicago in the form of a board of Jewish education. And this board of Jewish education must have the moral as well as the financial backing of the community to carry out its mission. True, a half million or six hundred thousand dollars for the Jewish education cannot be raised so easily. We think that such a central body as a general board of Jewish education could, in the end, find ways and means how to raise the sum, and how to spend it in a way satisfactory to the community. We cannot solve our educational problem unless we make up our mind to centralize Jewish education and to direct it from one agency. And this agency, we hope, will be able to raise all the necessary funds, and it will also organize the work of instruction in every part of the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
