<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1926-05-11">May 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Specific Jewish Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1926-05-11">May 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIFIC JEWISH ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As to the Jewishness of our institution and the extent to which we shall direct our program I have already spoken earlier in this report. I want here merely to give certain specific Jewish activities conducted during the past year. We have cooperated with the Jewish Education Committee in promoting the Circle of Jewish Children, which has participated in many club activities and holiday celebrations; assisted in registration of the Kodimah Hebrew School, which meets two days a week at the Institute. The Observer gave publicity to all Jewish education projects, such as the Hebrew School, the College of Jewish Studies, etc. Meetings of the Jewish Educational Committee were held at the Institute, also the High School Educational Society's meetings were held at the Institute, where the foundation for the organization of the High School Jewish Youth Movement was laid. The Jewish Youth, organ of the League, is sold at the Institute to students at reduced rates.</p>
   <p>I have already referred to the exhibitions of works of Jewish artists; <pb facs="5423972_1_0068.jpg" n="2"/>also to the biblical backgrounds and Jewish themes woven into the program of the Institute's Jewish Art Workshop. We cooperate with young Judea in the development of a club program. Chicago young Judea held two large affairs at the Institute, one celebrating the opening of the university in Jerusalem, the other a holiday get together. In addition to the many Institute celebrations, outside Jewish organizations used the Institute as a center for holiday festivals and pageants. The following list will indicate the extent to which the holidays were celebrated:</p>
   <p>Purim 1925.</p>
   <p>March 10. Circle of Jewish Children's Purim celebration.</p>
   <p>March 12. I. B. D. Purim party.</p>
   <p>March 14. West Side Sabbath Schools' play and entertainment.</p>
   <p>March 15. Pernix S. C. Purim dance.</p>
   <p>March 15. Winchester and Miller Streets Talmud Torahs. Resolved: That Esther was justified in not disclosing her Jewish identity.</p>
   <p>March 15. Girls' Club's Purim rally. Central Post Office for Shalach Monos.</p>
   <p>March 22. Portuguese Israelite Fraternity's annual Purim dance and entertainment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0069.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Pesach 1925. April 12.</p>
   <p>Girls' Democracy, Junior Girls' Club Council's Pesach party.</p>
   <p>Shevuoth 1925. May 31.</p>
   <p>Circle of Jewish Children's Shevuoth celebration.</p>
   <p>Rosh Hashonoh and Yom Kippur 1925.</p>
   <p>High holiday services by congregation Beth Israel. Portuguese Israelite Fraternity (Sephardic), special children's services under the supervision of the Jewish Educational Committee.</p>
   <p>Sucooth 1925. October 12.</p>
   <p>Circle of Jewish Children's Sucooth program. Simohath Torahs parties by congregation Beth Israel. Portuguese Israelite Fraternity.</p>
   <p>Chanukah 1925.</p>
   <p>Institute's Chanukah pageant and play. West Side Sabbath Schools' celebration. Adas B'nai Israel. Winchester and Miller Streets Talmud Torahs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0070.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Circle of Jewish Children.</p>
   <p>In cooperation with Jewish nationalistic and Zionist organizations, the Institute was used as a station for the following Tag Days:</p>
   <p>1. Poale Zion Palestine Workers fund.</p>
   <p>2. National Fund Flower Day.</p>
   <p>3. Zeire Zion Pioneers Fund.</p>
   <p>Jewish National Workers Alliance Culture Fund.</p>
   <p>The above activities were for the main branch only.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
