<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-13">June 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[A New Talmud-Torah]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-13">June 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[A NEW TALMUD-TORAH]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Moses Montefiore Talmud-Torah (school) the progress made in the last two years was discussed. There was a special discussion of the two new buildings recently erected which accommodate about 500 new pupils. In order that the Talmud-Torah may continue in the future to fulfill its duties, it was decided to buy another building for a Talmud-Torah near Laflin Street, about halfway between Miller Street and Winchester Avenue. As has been reported, children living in this neighborhood are being reared without knowledge of or respect for the Torah. They know nothing of "Yiddishkeit" and have never attended a Jewish school. Their mothers hesitate to send their little children a mile across car tracks, especially in winter time. We know that the poorer classes live there and that their children are not provided with adequate clothing. But now with great satisfaction we can report to the Jews of Chicago, especially to those interested in the rearing of Jewish children, that we have recently purchased a suitable house in this neighborhood [where a school will be established]. It will be remodeled - [there will be] four very pretty classrooms, light, airy, with electric light, and steam heat. We hope to be able to start the classes shortly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to achieve our aims we turn to you, the "well-to-do" of Chicago, for help and assistance. You, orthodox Jews, have supported our Holy Institution for over thirty years. You have responded at all times when the Talmud-Torah was in need. It is with your help that we now have three city Talmud-Torahs valued at over fifty thousand dollars, where Jewish Torah and ethics are taught to over thirteen hundred children, mostly poor orphans, children of divorcees, of abandoned mothers, or those whose parents are in charitable sanitariums and hospitals. In the name of these unfortunates, we call upon you again for succor. Give the children a place to study, to become good Jews, so that they will not wander in the streets [where they will meet] bad company and grow up to bring shame to our Jewish community. In the name of our children of the [poor who perpetuate the light of Israel], we appeal to you in the hope that you will [guarantee the fulfillment of] our undertaking.</p>
   <p>Send your contributions to the Building Fund [Committee] in the Talmud-Torah office, 1253 Miller Street that the Torah may be taught to the children of Ruben. Then you will be worthy of rearing your own children, thereby gaining [for yourself] much happiness and success in all your undertakings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0424.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With Zion's blessings,</p>
   <p>Ben-Zion Leizerovitz, president</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
