<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-09">Aug. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Among Newspapers and Journals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-09">Aug. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">AMONG NEWSPAPERS AND JOURNALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great deal has already been written about the question of Jewish education. The problem is so intricate and complicated that it becomes void of sense. But let us listen to Rabbi Meyer Berlin's opinion about the matter.</p>
   <p>In an article entitled "Ydshon Vchodosh" ("Old and New") in the last issue of the Hebrew, Rabbi Berlin points out that in former years there also existed diverse opinions about this question; that there were two different types of studies--religious and secular. And about Jewish education in America he says:</p>
   <p>"Jews of America are not aware of the controversy that has taken place among us concerning the religious and secular studies. All Jews in America have accepted, at first through compulsion and afterwards through their <pb facs="5423972_1_0447.jpg" n="2"/>own volition, that which had already been accepted long ago by the Jews of western Europe, and more recently by the Jews of Poland and Lithuania, viz, the principal factor in education is secular study. In these countries there is neither a father nor a pedagogue who would think of changing this course of study or of attempting to minimize the secular studies.</p>
   <p>"Yet there are differences of opinion about the educational courses in these countries. The differences of opinion are, however, centered around the religious studies alone. The old-fashioned people are of the opinion that because there remains little time for the religious studies, we should teach our children the same system as was taught our parents. Therefore, they want to introduce into their children's study courses or into the Talmud Torahs which are under their supervision, Hebrew reading, interpretation of a chapter in Pentateuch or in Prophets, and perhaps a little of the Talmud. These studies are taught in Yiddish and in English and the parents are quite satisfied. Modern people admit that the objective of <pb facs="5423972_1_0448.jpg" n="3"/>Hebrew studies is to acquire a concept of Judaism and are not against the study of the Torah, Pentateuch, Prophets, etc., but they also claim that the young generation will not be sufficiently inclined toward Judaism if it does not possess adequate knowledge of the Hebrew language. According to the opinion of modern people we should see that our children acquire a profound knowledge of the Hebrew language. In their opinion this is the only key to our national treasures".</p>
   <p>However, if the Jews in this country were as devoted to their opinions as our parents of former times, this controversy about secular and religious education would be just as difficult as it was then. But just as the Jews on this side of the Atlantic have "cooled off" in regard to many things, so has the "war of education" become a peaceful war. The result is that both the old and the new systems of education have collapsed here in America. What should we do about this?</p>
   <p>Rabbi Berlin continues: "It is hoped that eventually our civic leaders <pb facs="5423972_1_0449.jpg" n="4"/>will become interested in the problem of Jewish education. We witness many movements, which seemed to have expired, reviving here in America, and when the better elements among us begin to think of the future generation, it will be impossible to overlook the problem of Jewish education.</p>
   <p>"The question of Jewish education will have to be the first among the questions concerning the existence of the Jewish people in America, and our civic leaders will have to cope with it."</p>
   <p>This is, however, no more than a hope for the future. In the meantime, Jewish education is so neglected in America that it is impossible to look forward to such a time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
