<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-22">May 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Three Jewish Children of Marshall High School Win Scholarships</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-22">May 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THREE JEWISH CHILDREN OF MARSHALL HIGH SCHOOL WIN SCHOLARSHIPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The young hearts of Libby Shnitzer, Freeda Jacobson, and Max Newberger, Jewish students of Marshall High school, beat faster yesterday when the chairman of the Scholarship Committee made known that they were the three fortunate ones to win the scholarship prizes awarded each year by the Marshall High School to its three best scholars.</p>
   <p>Libby Shnitzer, who won first prize, consisting of a memorial scholarship valued at $150, was overwhelmed with joy.</p>
   <p>Miss Shnitzer felt as though she was in seventh heaven. Her eyes sparkled with joy when all her teachers and school-chums shook her hand to congratulate her for her victory. She bashfully thanked everyone and rushed home to her parents with the glad tidings.</p>
   <p>Likewise felt young Max Newberger when he learned he was the winner of the second prize. Max is popular in high school for his untiring work in the <pb facs="5423972_1_0095.jpg" n="2"/>Literary Club and in the Club of Science of the school. His readers like him for his quietness and seriousness. With modesty he received the news that he had won the second scholarship prize.</p>
   <p>Freeda Jacobson was the third to win a prize. The news that she had won the University of Chicago scholarship, a prize given by the Marshall High School, excited her so that she could not fine words to express her appreciation.</p>
   <p>The winners have excellent records both in elementary and high schools.</p>
   <p>Miss Freeda Jacobson's prize for good conduct and excellent work will enable her to attend the University of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
