<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-03">Aug. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Voice of the People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-03">Aug. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">VOICE OF THE PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Editor of the Jewish Courier: The article written by Harry A. Lipsky, which appeared in the Courier under the caption "The Problem of Our People's Education," and in which he sets forth plans to encourage adults to continue their studies in evening schools, has evoked intense interest among your readers.</p>
   <p>Permit me to express my opinion in your newspaper concerning this important matter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lipsky's plan of using moving pictures to illustrate various studies is superb, as well as highly original and modern. It would undoubtedly induce many adults to attend evening classes. I do not agree, however, with the writer of the article when he maintains that many immigrants discontinue their studies because the subject matter is taught to them as it is to children. I believe that this is not true.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As a former student of a public night school, I know the reason--which is that in the evening classes there are many teachers who do not correctly understand the character of newly-arrived immigrants. Not infrequently misunderstandings occur between the teacher and students because the one does not understand the language of the other, and this usually leads to the discontinuation of studies on part of the students.</p>
   <p>In my opinion the Board of Education should take this into consideration. I also believe that it is Mr. Lipsky's duty, as a member of the Board of Education, to bring this before a meeting of the Board. The Board of Education will have to engage, in the various districts, teachers who understand the language and the make-up of those immigrants who attend the schools, so that the feeling between the teachers and students may be mutual.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>M. S.</p>
   <p>906 South Lincoln Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
