<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Workmen's Circle Must Carry on Independent Worker's Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE MUST CARRY ON INDEPENDENT WORKER'S EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Workmen's Circle is first and foremost a worker's organization founded on the basis of the class struggle.</p>
   <p>Everything that the Workmen's Circle does for its members in the way of benefit, is just like the cement keeping the bricks together of a brick wall.</p>
   <p>As a worker's organization, the material benefits are as important as it is for a union to better the conditions of the work shop.</p>
   <p>A union that cannot do something for its members must sooner or later perish--and the history of the labor movement is full of such facts.</p>
   <p>It is therefore very important to discuss the question of education, from the standpoint of a worker's organization, recognizing the fact, that the good, <pb facs="5423972_1_0523.jpg" n="2"/>which they get from the Workmen's Circle is as important for the Workmen's Circle as air is for a human being.</p>
   <p>The question of an independent education for workers is more important for the Workmen's Circle, for in the branches there are quite a number of members who are not workers and their interests in the Workmen's Circle are materialistic and not idealistic or spiritual.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, doubly necessary, if we are to understand the meaning of a worker's education, that we undertake, in Chicago, a systematic, steady dissemination of propaganda for workers among the members of the branches, and among those who do not come to the meeting, but just send in their dues by mail or check. The latter constitute approximately 8 percent of our organization.</p>
   <p>What is meant by a worker's education? What do we mean by a worker's press? All workers know the answer. A worker's paper dedicated to the class struggle is as different from a capitalistic paper as night is from day. The same is true of a worker's education. When the workers leave their education to their <pb facs="5423972_1_0524.jpg" n="3"/>class enemies, they will be controlled by their class enemies.</p>
   <p>A worker's education means the inculcation in the mind of the workers the philosophy of the workers.</p>
   <p>When an industrial conflict arises, we do not go to the capitalist press to ask what stand the workers should take.</p>
   <p>A worker, in order better to understand his interest, must understand the capitalist system of today and the economic laws which guide it, and must realize the difference between the efforts, and the aims of the capitalists, and those of the workers who received a worker's education, and have the viewpoint of the workers. The philosophy of the worker is contrary to that of the capitalist. The capitalists are concerned with the preservation of the existing system. Their entire philosophy stems from this viewpoint. Their educational system is founded upon it, and they spread that education among the workers through the medium of the schools, churches, newspapers, moving pictures and colleges. The atmosphere is filled with capitalistic education <pb facs="5423972_1_0525.jpg" n="4"/>which is based on the preservation of the system of today.</p>
   <p>Properly speaking, the viewpoint of the worker on education must necessarily be contrary to that of the capitalist. The education of the worker must have for its main aim the discontinuance of the present system. The workers must strive toward a fundamental change in the existing social system.</p>
   <p>An organization like the Workmen's Circle must spread this concept among the members of all its branches. The Workmen's Circle should educate and develop all their members, and should have an apparatus to carry on worker's education, and to supply the means to reach the membership of the Workmen's Circle.</p>
   <p>Once we realize what the foundation of a worker's education is, it is very important that we make clear to those who think that we have in mind only bread and butter when we speak of the viewpoint of the worker that that is not the case.</p>
   <p>It is true that the foundation of a worker's education is the fundamental <pb facs="5423972_1_0526.jpg" n="5"/>concept of the class struggle, which gives the worker the class viewpoint, and which serves as a compass to lead the workers in a straight line of thought. But it is also true that learning other social sciences is not ruled out of the program of a worker's education; and when workers have adopted the approach of workers to all economic and social problems, they will, in learning the other phases of human life, have the viewpoint of workers as a guide.</p>
   <p>The Workmen's Circle, as a worker's organization is now the only body in the Jewish community, which is capable of carrying on this educational work. An apparatus must be created to educate out members to be not only members seeking benefits, but also class-conscious individuals in the army of workers, who have the point of view of the workers toward everything that occurs in life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
