<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-13">Dec. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Danger of Fanaticism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-13">Dec. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANGER OF FANATICISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>America is in serious danger from a new wave of fanaticism, compared to which the fanatical prohibition wave was child's play. We refer to the new movement of the clergy to make the Sunday equally holy for the one hundred and five million citizens of this country, whether Jews or Christians, whether devout churchgoers or freethinking persons. The clergy wants to prohibit everything on Sunday, theaters, restaurants, ice cream parlors, newspapers, automobile riding, and railroad traffic. They want to prohibit everything to such an extent that the citizen may have no other choice but to go to church on Sunday.</p>
   <p>An interview with prominent leaders of the Congress was published in the Courier a week ago. They unanimously declared that the project of the clergy for a blue Sunday has no chance to pass the Congress. This does not mean, <pb facs="5423972_1_0575.jpg" n="2"/>however, that the danger of such an inquisitorial law is thereby removed. If the clergy has no chance to carry out their project now they may have a chance later in some succeeding Congress. It depends on, how long it will take the clergy to revise American public opinion to create the desired atmosphere for a blue Sunday.</p>
   <p>For many years the prohibitionists did not have the slightest chance, but the opportune hour suddenly arrived and the United States became dry as the desert of Sahara. But what was very difficult for the prohibitionists, could be much easier for the new movement by the clergy. So long as one attempt was successful in curbing the personal liberty of the citizens there is no knowing how far this wave of fanaticism and reaction will reach, if something does not occur to restrain it in an effective manner.</p>
   <p>The present moment is especially favorable for the spreading of the fanatical wave. The fear of radicalism is so great that many who are outside the church and the narrow spiritual circle of the clergy consider the church as the best <pb facs="5423972_1_0576.jpg" n="3"/>means of combating the reds, and they are prepared to collaborate with the clergy. Herein lies the entire danger of fanaticism in America, which would otherwise be powerless and insignificant.</p>
   <p>It stands to reason that the Jews have, more than others, to be alarmed by the spreading of such religious fanaticism. The project of the clergy would make it impossible for the Orthodox Jews to observe the Sabbath without becoming economically ruined by two rest days in the week.</p>
   <p>The Jewish conscience must also protest against such an attempt to deprive others of religious freedom; this would be foreign to the spirit of the Jewish religion, which has, as one of its basic principles, the recognition that non-Jews are free from the doctrines of the Torah, besides the fundamental principles of morals--The Seven Precepts of The Sons Of Noah [A Hebrew book of morals]. In the entire history of the Jews we cannot find a single instance when a Jewish majority has sought to compel a non-Jewish minority to strictly observe the Sabbath. We, therefore, have a perfect right to protest against <pb facs="5423972_1_0577.jpg" n="4"/>any attempt of a Christian majority to force a Jewish minority to observe their Sabbath.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, though, our protests alone will not help to remove the danger of a drive for a blue Sunday, led by the united reactionary forces of the country. We must unite with the liberal non-Jewish elements to combat it, not only through intercession in the Congress but also by molding public opinion, which is the chief factor in such a movement, and this must be done before it is too late.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
