<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-02-06">Feb. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[The Prohibition Law]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-02-06">Feb. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[THE PROHIBITION LAW]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An amazing statement was recently made public in the American newspapers by one of the most prominent representatives of the Protestant Church of America regarding the prohibition law. This statement was made in the name of a certain temperance society, an organization which has as its purpose the combating of intoxication and which is part of the Protestant Church, having a membership of over twenty thousand people. In this statement it is openly mentioned that the prohibition law not only failed to reduce the amount of intoxication throughout the country but actually increased it, and, what is more, has spread it among the younger generation. The prohibition law, the statement reads, was a deathblow to the entire work of those who for the last few years fought against intoxication.</p>
   <p>This statement was made by no other individual than Reverend James Empinger, the national secretary of the society fighting against intoxication, after thousands of members had declared themselves as opposed to the prohibition law as it is now being practiced. It is far more surprising when we learn <pb facs="5423972_1_0559.jpg" n="2"/>that Reverend Empinger is none other than the former superintendent of the Anti-Saloon League of New York State--a man who worked heart and soul for the passage of the prohibition law in America. Now, however, the same people who as representatives of the Church, fought so strongly for prohibition in America came out openly for repeal of the prohibition law or for its modification in such a way that it will permit the drinking of wine and beer.</p>
   <p>We cannot foretell what the results of this open demand by the Church representatives will be. However, one thing is certain: as strong as the rich brewers and liquor dealers of yesteryears were against prohibition, so strong are the organized bootleggers, for whom prohibition pays, against it today. The battle to abolish prohibition in America will be just as difficult as was the battle to adopt the prohibition law.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
