<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
<date when="1918">1917-18</date>, pp. 367-395.
<title level="a">List of Rabbis and Instructors in Jewish Colleges in the United States. Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
<date when="1918">1917-18</date>, pp. 367-395.
<title level="a">LIST OF RABBIS AND INSTRUCTORS IN JEWISH COLLEGES IN THE UNITED STATES. CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Album, S. H., 1253 S. Halsted. Cardon, A. I. Congregation Shaari Torah Anshei Maariv, 1301 S. Sawyer. Chaiemovitz, B. Congregation Anshe Shavel and Yanova, 1359 W. 13th. Coffee, Rudolph I. National Director, Social Service I. O. B. B; Congregation Judaea. Cohon, Samuel S. Zion Congregation, 1507 Ogden Av. Elfenbein, Israel. Congregation B'nai David and Ohave Zedek, 1228 N. Claremont Av. Elman, Abraham. Field Secretary of Jewish Consumptive Relief Society. Epstein, Azriel. Cong. Beth Hamedrosh Hagodol U'Bnei Jacob, 3439 Douglas Blvd.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0436.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Feuerlicht, Jacob. Superintendent of Home of Jewish Friendless. Fischer, Moses. First Hungarian Congregation Agudath Ackim, corner Marshfield and Polk. Goldenson, Abraham Ber. Cong. B'Nai Reuven, 1109 S. Paulina. Hevesh, Joseph. Cong. Anshe Emeth, 627-33 Gary Place. Hirsch, Emil G., Cong. Sinai. Hirschberg, Abram. Temple Sholom, Pine Grove Av. and Grace. Klein, Israel, 2340 W. Adams St. Kuppin, Louis, 4630 Lake Park Av. Levi, Gerson Baruch, 5000 Grand Blvd. B'nai Sholom Temple Israel. Levy, Felix A. Long. Emanuel, 701 Buckingham P1. Muskin, Eleazar R. Cong. Sons of Joseph, 802 S. Claremont Av. Newberger, Joseph M. Cong. Ateres Israel, 1230 S. Millard Av. Newman, Julius Moses Montefiore Cong. 1048 N. Robey Rappaport, Julius. Cong. Beth E1. Romiransky, Samuel. First Engle-wood Congregation B'nai Israel, 6157 S. Aberdeen. Rosenstein, M. <pb facs="5423972_1_0437.jpg" n="3"/>Cong. B'nai Jehoshua. Scharfarber, Tobias. Cong. Anshe Mayrev, Indiana Av. and 33rd. Shach, Samuel. Cong. Kehillath Jacob, Douglas Blvd. and Hamlin Av. Shugan, William. Cong. Bickur Cholem, 8927 Houston Av. Silber, Saul. Cong. Anshe Sholom. Stolz, Joseph. Isaiah Temple, Vincennes Av. and 45th. Ungerleider, M. Cong. B'nai Abraham. Yudelson, Albert B., 4611 Indiana Av. Zelesnick, Judel Michael. Cong. Ohel Jacob Koono, Peoria and 14th P1. Zevin, Mordecai. Cong. Anshe Lebowitz, 1132 Washburne Av.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
