<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-09-22">September 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Jews of Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-09-22">September 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE JEWS OF CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thirty world-famed Yeshivoth in Europe and Palestine are supported by the Vaad Ha' Yeshivoth.</p>
   <p>Ten thousand students, the most brilliant minds in Israel, the very flower of Jewish youth, are being trained in these Yeshivoth to be the future leaders of our people, the standard-bearers of our faith.</p>
   <p>The people of Israel, scattered over the face of the globe, everywhere hunted, killed, deprived of every human right, for two thousand years has had but one means of preserving its identity - the Torah: The sacred Torah has been the wandering homeland of the Jews. It has truly <pb facs="5423972_1_0361.jpg" n="2"/>been the "tree of life," in fulfillment of the ancient promise that they who shall cherish it, shall have life eternal. The Yeshivoth are the unconquerable fortresses of Judaism; the great rabbis at their head are the fearless commanding officers; their students, the legions of a mighty army, and the Torah itself our arsenal and ammunition.</p>
   <p>The Vaad Ha' Yeshivoth is the only medium through which the Yeshivoth derive funds in Chicago. It conducts an annual campaign in an efficient and dignified manner, without the mediation of solicitors and collectors, and it insures distribution of all funds collected in just proportion to the needs and merits of the respective Yeshivoth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0362.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Vaad Ha' Yeshivoth, from its inception has stood guard over the "Eternal Light," the holy Torah, for whose preservation Jews in the past have given their all, lest the Light be extinguished forever.</p>
   <p>The condition of the Yeshivoth this year is an anxious one - terrible privation makes their lot harder to bear than ever before. They call to us with a clarion call for assistance!</p>
   <p>The High Holidays, days of judgment and forgiveness, are appointed by every synagogue as the occasion for the annual appeal for the Yeshivoth. When you stand before the Judgment Seat and pray to the Almighty for the benefits of health, wealth and happiness for the coming year, do not deny the earnest plea of the great "Gaonim" of this generation, the <pb facs="5423972_1_0363.jpg" n="4"/>titular heads of the Yeshivoth, and the appeal of the thousands of Yeshivoth students, whose studies are attended by the specter of want, whose hands are stretched out to you for help.</p>
   <p>When the Torah calls, can you refuse to answer? Can you refuse to fulfill your sacred duty to the holiest institutions in Jewry, on the holiest days of the year? Express your loyalty to the glorious past of Judaism, and your abiding faith in its no less brilliant future, by contributing towards the continued existence of the Yeshivoth, the repositories of the Holy Torah.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0364.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We pray that your support of Torah will invoke upon you and yours the blessings of a happy and prosperous New Year, a year which will see a more glorious flowering of the Torah and the long-awaited return of the oppressed of our people to Zion and Jerusalem.</p>
   <p>Vaad Ha' Yeshivoth</p>
   <p>3244 Grenshaw Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
