<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-03">Sept. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Letter to Jewish Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_1_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-03">Sept. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LETTER TO JEWISH CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Children: You will soon go back to school. After a ten-week vacation, you should now feel fresh and lively, and with rejuvenated energy should endeavor to continue your studies until you shall have completed all your courses.</p>
   <p>Many of you will return to school cheerfully and happily, having been promoted to higher classes, new teachers, new textbooks; you are now on a higher rung of the ladder which leads to the highest institution of universal education and science. You should feel proud of your abilities.</p>
   <p>Other children will return to school with long faces; they are in the same class, they have the same teachers and are using the same textbooks. These children should not feel defeated. If they will study more conscientiously from now on, they will certainly be successful in school.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_1_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ambition leads to success.</p>
   <p>If the same children who failed in their examinations understood that they themselves were to blame--that they neglected their studies, they would now be able, by virtue of a stronger desire, to catch up with their more successful classmates. Every child possesses talents--these talents need only to be developed.</p>
   <p>And do not forget, dear children, that you are living in a country where you can develop your talents in the field of education. Less fortunate are your schoolmates abroad, those in dark Russia which withholds education from her people in general, and from Jews in particular. Hundreds of thousands of Jewish children are rejected each year from the schools. Only a certain per cent is selected. They crave knowledge as one thirsts for water, but they are shown only an empty quart.</p>
   <p>Therefore, you can consider yourself lucky, dear children, because you live <pb facs="5423972_1_0201.jpg" n="3"/>in a country where there is no prejudice against Jewish children. The doors of all schools are open to you. Enter and sate yourselves with knowledge--to your heart's content.</p>
   <p>Tens of thousands of Jewish children really accept this invitation and study diligently.</p>
   <p>For this reason, Jewish fathers are proud when they read, in the American newspapers, about the great success of Jewish students. Every Jew is proud when he reads through a long list of the names of Jewish students who have illustriously distinguished themselves by the marks they received in examinations given in schools, colleges and other institutions of learning.</p>
   <p>With pride and courage, dear children, return to school. Study conscientiously and with determination, and success shall be yours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
