<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-03-20">Mar. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Samuel Ladanyi</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_3_0105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-03-20">Mar. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SAMUEL LADANYI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The news of the death of Samuel Ladanyi was like a thunderbolt from the sky striking into the hearts of the Chicago Hungarians. This man who a short time ago was full of vitality and great plans has left us, [and we are shocked by such a catastrophe].</p>
   <p>Samuel Ladanyi was born on Jan. 2, 1867, in Szabolcs County, Hungary. After completing his education, like many thousands of other Hungarians, he found it hard to locate himself in the industrial life of Hungary, so he decided to migrate to America.</p>
   <p>At first he settled in New York City where he suffered many hardships, as did all immigrants. But these hardships and trials only spurred his ambition to become a success.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0106.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He came to Chicago a few decades ago, and during the Chicago World's Fair introduced the Hungarian frankfurter to the American public. His frankfurters became so popular that he and his uncle organized what is known today as the Vienna Sauage Mfg. Co. In the last ten years he has been a pioneer in the development of smoked meats. His sausage factory prospered, and as the years went by it became larger and larger, until today it is one of the largest of its kind. Its yearly business amounts to more than a million dollars.</p>
   <p>Samuel Ladanyi became a wealthy man. He did not [make the same mistake which other Hungarians who acquired wealth, made--i. e. adopt a superior attitude toward their poorer brethren]. He remained the same, common, ordinary man. [His simplicity]was shown in his home and in [his method of]handling people.</p>
   <p>Although he behaved as a common, ordinary man, his thoughts, feelings and <pb facs="5422061_3_0107.jpg" n="3"/>activities made him a great man.</p>
   <p>Samuel Ladanyi was an honest man, a good Hungarian, and a loyal Jew. These three characteristics were blended so well within him that he was loved by all who came in contact with him.</p>
   <p>He glorified the Hungarian nation because regardless of whom he met, he was always proud to acknowledge his Hungarian descent.</p>
   <p>He was always willing to donate to a good cause. He never showed partiality. His activities were governed by the dictates of the Old Testament. He practiced the dictum that what his right hand did, his left hand knew nothing of. There was never a worth-while Hungarian activity which he did not support. No one left his home empty handed. He was a great supporter of all cultural activities amongst the Hungarians and gave aid to their theatrical projects.</p>
   <p>A man can be a hard worker--he can be wealthy and wise--but if he can't <pb facs="5422061_3_0108.jpg" n="4"/>gain the confidence of his fellow man, his life is one without purpose. Fame and fortune die, but the activities and the results of those activities remain [and influence the future].</p>
   <p>The fact that eight hundred businessmen were present [at the funeral] to pay their last respects to the man who had been so humanitarian, testifies to the respect which he commanded, and the love that existed for him among the Hungarians in Chicago. </p>
   <p>The educated and the uneducated, the rich and the poor, can feel that someone of great importance has passed away because a great man was lowered into his grave, to rest in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
