<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-04-16">Apr. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Correspondence from Hungary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_3_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-04-16">Apr. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CORRESPONDENCE FROM HUNGARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are few Hungarians in this country today who have not received letters from friends or relatives who have gone back to Hungary, Most of these letters are very interesting. There are some that express great dissatisfaction though this is only true in a small number of cases. There are many interesting and educational letters received by this office concerning conditions in Hungary at the present time. We will endeavor to give our readers the general ideas contained in these letters.</p>
   <p>We do not wish any one to be alarmed because of the ideas which may be disturbing after reading such letters. Most of these letters <pb facs="5422061_3_0063.jpg" n="2"/>are from people who formerly lived in the United States, but went back to Hungary after a long absence.</p>
   <p>It is true that today the Hungarian army is enlisting every man eligible for army service. But this is also true of the Czechoslovakian army and of all the neighboring countries.</p>
   <p>Here is an example of army enlistment: A young Hungarian man went back to the county in which he was born, but this county is occupied by the Czecho-Slovakians at the present time. For two days this man and his family enjoyed each other's company, but on the third day the Czecho-Slovakian government forced him to join their army. The distressed family <pb facs="5422061_3_0064.jpg" n="3"/>wrote of their plight to friends in America.</p>
   <p>There is also a letter from the county of Miskolc, where the Hungarian army officials stayed three weeks enlisting men. The writer also states that the Slovak boys living in this county were joining the Hungarian army with great enthusiasm, claiming that if they could endure the World War for five years, they surely could fight the Czecho-Slovaks for one year. These Slavish boys are showing their mettle to Czecho-Slovakia. Regardless of their relationship to the Czecho-Slovaks, they know that their Czecho-Slovak brothers are Cains, and they they do not want to be Abels.</p>
   <p>There is another letter which reports that the Czecho-Slovaks have put a barbed-wire fence and have dug a trench along the border and have guards <pb facs="5422061_3_0065.jpg" n="4"/>stationed along this fence with orders to shoot down any Hungarian who dares approach the border. It seems that the Hungarian people who emigrated from this country are farther way from their loved ones now than when they were in this country.</p>
   <p>This does not matter. The Hungarian boys have seen better barbed-wire fences than these. Whenever the time comes, it will be a very simple matter for them to hurdle these fences and cross trenches. Not even the great Wall of China can stop these brave Hungarian soldiers when the time is ripe for Hungary to fight.</p>
   <p>The most interesting incident that we have heard is related in the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0066.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A Hungarian man who was from the County of Szaboles decided he was going to return to his native land regardless of cost. The foremost thing in his mind was that he would arrive safely.</p>
   <p>He did reach the land of Hungary. He was tired from his long journey and it cost him much money to make the trip. Forgetting this, he was overjoyed that he was now on Hungarian soil. He continued his journey to that little town in which he originally lived.</p>
   <p>On his way, he reached the gently flowing waters of the Tisza River, and on the far side he saw the small white house of his own village. Looking across the river to his little village he realized that it was farther <pb facs="5422061_3_0067.jpg" n="6"/>away than ever because at that time a Hungarian was not allowed to cross this river.</p>
   <p>Through some strange coincidence, his wife found out that her beloved husband was on the far side of the river. Upon reaching the banks of the river, she saw him on the other side. They exchanged greetings and their joy knew no bounds. The husband had come from America to see his loved ones. He knew that if he dared set foot on this Hungarian soil occupied by the Czecho-Slovaks, he would be shot at once. His predicament was worse now than before he emigrated from the United States.</p>
   <p>This is the way the man on his way to Szaboles, saw his loved ones.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0068.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>That beloved Tisza River, which has seen the Huns of Atilla drink its water; Alfred the Conqueror, with the original Hungarians; the Turks, the Tartars, the Russians, and the Slavs, flowed gently on. This river will see a great deal more in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
