<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-06-10">June 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Gross' New Treachery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_3_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-06-10">June 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND GROSS' NEW TREACHERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee of Congress is now investigating facts in connection with Nazi activities in the United States.</p>
   <p>The committee wishes to shed light on whether the Nazi propaganda here is financed and directed by Germany and assisted by Dr. Hans Luther, German Ambassador at Washington.</p>
   <p>It is not probable that Dr. Luther would personally conduct such propaganda in a strange country. Diplomats, even Germans, do not make such mistakes. The charge against Dr. Luther is made by one of our countrymen, who up to now was known to be pro-Nazi. This person is Reverend Francis Gross, ex-Roman Catholic priest, of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We do not know the reason for the Father's change of faith. According to the congressional investigation, it seems that the German Ambassador was <pb facs="5422061_3_0085.jpg" n="2"/>not willing to contribute financially to the Father's activities. Because he did not succeed in selling Dr. Luther anything, Reverend Gross ran to the congressional committee and showed them a letter, which reads as follows;</p>
   <p>"The correspondence in my possession is proof that Dr. Luther is sponsoring and financially aiding the publishing of my book. If the aforementioned correspondence will be the subject of further public debate, this will have a sensational effect and will result in Dr. Luther's recall to Germany, and would even cause the United States and Germany to sever friendly relations."</p>
   <p>Because foreign ambassadors cannot be questioned by American authorities, we have to take Father Gross' word for the present.</p>
   <p>We have our doubts about the Father's allegations, because we cannot believe that he turned from the Nazis because he received money from the Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
