<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1929-04-05">Apr. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Father Stephen Soltesz</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_3_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1929-04-05">Apr. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">FATHER STEPHEN SOLTESZ</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After fifteen years of service in Burnside, Chicago, Father Soltesz, has announced his retirement. He came to Chicago from Lorain and the exertion due to intensive work underminded his health and wrecked his nervous system.</p>
   <p>Sunday, April 28, he celebrated his silver mass (25 yrs.) His congregation gave a dinner in his honor, but everyone was sad, because he repeated what he announced in church that he is leaving soon. Fifteen years ago he came, full of earnest hope, and today after fifteen years of struggle, he is a man broken in health and spirit, ready for retirement. Behind him he leaves no great edifices to remember him by, but his fanatic love of his country, honorable and straight-forward character will be remembered by the Chicago Hungarian Roman Catholics.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If Father Soltesz had any fault, it was that he wasn't diplomatic, but he hated insincerity as much as he loved his people.</p>
   <p>We were sorry to see two priests of the same blood and their congregations at odds with each other. Each listened to third parties intrigues and the two churches traveled different ways.</p>
   <p>Those who remember the years of the World War know that Father Soltesz wasn't immune to suspicion and persecution.</p>
   <p>Many other Hungarians were the victims of vicious gossip at that time. Prison and other troubles did not break his spirit but the cutting to pieces of Hungary and the discord within his church left an unhealing wound in his heart.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0091.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The tears in the eyes of his followers proved that they loved him. In his retirement his conscience may be clear, because he was a good pastor and though he may not be taking wealth, he takes with him the greatest treasure the love and respect of his fellow men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
