<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-04-23">Apr. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Time for Action Is Here</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_3_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-04-23">Apr. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE TIME FOR ACTION IS HERE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian-American press is continually bemoaning the fact that fate has seriously struck our beloved homeland, Hungary. Every day we read articles of the depressed conditions in Hungary, but no effort is made to remedy them.</p>
   <p>It is useless to cry or show signs of distress unless some concerted efforts are made to relieve the disturbing cause. We cannot save Hungary with tears; if this is to be accomplished, we must act now.</p>
   <p>We believe that the fate of Hungary is in the hands of the Hungarian-Americans. At the same time, we should not forget that the Hungarian-Americans are not organized politically. Under these circumstances the Hungarian-Americans can be of no assistance, either financially or politically, to the distressed country of Hungary.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If we earnestly desire to be of assistance to our mother country, then the paramount thing to be accomplished is to awaken the spirit of cooperation. We must prove to ourselves that we are Hungarians and that we are worthy of that name.</p>
   <p>Therefore, our first duty, primarily, is to put forth every effort to become a strong unit, and thereby receive the political recognition which we deserve.</p>
   <p>An unorganized mass is not recognized nor does it stand for anything. General Hindenburg said, when he was describing the Russian army, "I am not afraid of them because they are not an army, but an unorganized mass."</p>
   <p>Hungarian-Americans should not seek mercy for Hungary. It is their privilege to step forward boldly and demand the rights to which their mother country is entitled.</p>
   <p>The duty of the Hungarian-American at the present time is to cast aside all religious and political differences, all class hatred, and keep the interest <pb facs="5422061_3_0060.jpg" n="3"/>of their homeland in mind by organizing one strong political body, whose specific duty shall be to see that the Hungarian people receive proper recognition. As to our affiliation with any political group, we cannot say. This is left to the decision of the general membership.</p>
   <p>An organization of this kind can survive only if it keeps in mind Hungarian principles and stands firmly for them. It would also preserve the interests of the Hungarian-Americans. An organization of this kind should not be allowed to act in the interest of individuals, as some organizations of this type have done in the past. This would be detrimental to all concerned.</p>
   <p>To make such a political organization possible requires the aid of the officers and members of all existing Hungarian societies. These are the men who have trusted one another, and we feel sure that we will not find a man among this group who has selfish aims or who would cast aside his patriotic feelings toward his country, but will put forth effort in the advancement of the true purposes of the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_3_0061.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Therefore, we must not waste time; we must get started. The time for action is here!</p>
   <p>We solicit helpful suggestions and constructive criticism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
