<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Harmonien's Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">HARMONIEN'S CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Harmonien Singing Society had good attendance at its concert last Sunday. The program was well arranged, and the quintet's performance in particular deserves favorable comment. Under the direction of Mr. Joel Mossberg Harmonien's Chorus has labored hard to obtain the excellent results demonstrated throughout the concert.</p>
   <p>"The Sailors' Song" from "Capriciosa" and Kjerulf's composition, "Effect of the Sun," were beautifully performed, and "Aloha Oe" (Hawaiien Lovesong), arranged by Joel Mossberg, was received with applause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Agnete Mundt, who made her debut on this occasion, proved to possess a bright, winning voice that took the audience by storm. A critical listener would point out perchance that Mrs. Mundt's pronunciation is somewhat indistinct at times; but we trust that she will be able to improve it through <pb facs="5420780_2_0701.jpg" n="2"/>continued training. We do not have very many Danish sopranos; so we great new stars with a hearty welcome, particularly when they appear as promising as does Mrs. Mundt.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Gudrun Jacobsen and Mr. Ove Knudsen acted a little play, "Substitute," by Otto Benzon. However, that part of the program was somewhat dull, although this was not the fault of the performers. The audience had gathered to hear and to enjoy a musical performance and seemed unprepared for other kinds of entertainment.</p>
   <p>The quintet, consisting of Messrs. Verner, Carl Sorensen, Kaj Henriksen, Hans Sorensen, and Harry Larsen, was greeted with thundering applause. The new tenor, Mr. Verner, had improved his technique considerably since we heard him last. He has a natural voice of middle pitch and a notable sense of harmony, which makes him an efficient performer in a quintet.</p>
   <p>As a concluding number Director Joel Mossberg combined his chorus and the <pb facs="5420780_2_0702.jpg" n="3"/>orchestra in a marvelous performance of Riberhus Marsch by Frolich, after which the audience demonstrated its appreciation and enthusiasm in a remarkably audible manner. On this occasion the Danes once more demonstrated the interest which they feel for our singing societies and choruses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
