<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Poets Get Together</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH POETS GET TOGETHER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago countrymen, who with greater or smaller success have, in prose and verse, contributed to the preservation of our mother tongue on foreign soil, were last Saturday invited to a festive gathering, which included the visiting Danish author and poet L. C. Nielsen, in the Wahl-Henius Institute on Fullerton Avenue. The host was, of course, Dr. Max Henius, a master in arranging pleasant surprises.</p>
   <p>The representatives of Danish literary activities in Chicago numbered exactly eighteen and, besides, ten persons from other walks of life were present.</p>
   <p>After having inspected the institute, the guests enjoyed a showing of Dr. Henius' newest lantern slides, and then partook of a buffet supper in the festively decorated lecture hall.</p>
   <p>Each author or poet had been requested to read, recite or sing a sample <pb facs="5420780_2_1011.jpg" n="2"/>of their literary efforts and present a copy of the work to Mr. Mielsen, who is making a study of the cultural and spiritual accomplishments of Danish-Americans.</p>
   <p>This was done, and the following gentlemen, in alphabetical order presented their "brain-children": Librarian J. Christ Bay, of the John Crerar Library, Pastor M. F. Elichfeld, Editor C. Botker, Engineer C. C. Christensen, Pastor Adam Dan, Mail Carrier C. P. Ditlefsen, Author Carl Hansen Bookkeeper Carl Hansen, Managing Director C. H. W. Hasselriis, M. Henningsen, Ph. D., Painter C. Blinkenberg-Jensen, Director Carl Jacobsen, Editor Ivar Kirkegaard, Bricklayer Anton Kvist, Wine Merchant Albert Kear, State Senator C. M. Madsen, Manager A. M. Petersen, and Inspector Willards Sorensen.</p>
   <p>J. Roubak and A. Thomsen were prevented from being present, but the latter forwarded a poem which was read by Carl n.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1012.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We will not here discuss the merits of the many well-written and entertaining literary products which were presented during the evening, but we do want to call attention to the deep-felt and characteristic poem written and recited by State Senator C. M. Madsen, depicting the struggles and joys of the Dane making his way in a foreign land.</p>
   <p>In well-chosen words, L. C. Nielsen complimented the Danish writing man, to whom he generously referred as his "colleagues," and it was evident that he had enjoyed the affair, which was really unusually interesting and entertaining, and pervaded by good fellowship and high spirits.</p>
   <p>It was resolved to cable a greeting to the Danish King in response to the one received from him by all Danish-Americans, through Mr. Nielsen, and in conclusion the audience sang a song, written by Pastor Dan in honor of the distinguished visitor, and ending with a request that he carry a hearty greeting from Chicago Danes to old Denmark.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
