<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"Bygmester Solness"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"BYGMESTER SOLNESS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday evening, Mrs. Borgny Hammer produced Henrik Ibsen's play, "Bygmester Solness" (Master-Builder Solness). The house was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>When the Scandinavians produce a play, there are always one or two persons who take the leading roles in the play. This was also the case this time. The artists, Mr. and Mrs. Hammer, as professionals, were the only ones able to show any artistisc ability. It must be said that the rest of the cast is without mention, though everyone did his best to make the play a success.</p>
   <p>Rolf Hammer played the part of "Bygmnester Solness" with great force, and true understanding of his part.</p>
   <p>Borgny Hammer played the part of "Wilde Wangel," and her portrayal was fine and genuine.</p>
   <p>At the Same time, we had the opportunity to see Lido Lossuius as "Mrs. Aline Solness," Jacob T. Reynertson as "Doctor Herdal," Joseph Sorensen as Knut <pb facs="5420780_2_0878.jpg" n="2"/>Brovik," Bie Markussen as "Ragnar Brovik," and Helga Blichfeldt as "Kaja Fosli." When we cleared Ibsen's usual mysticism away, we understood that he wanted to show "Bygmester Solness" valuing the importance of keeping one's youth.</p>
   <p>Man must have the courage to rise as he aims, and as high as he builds. This can only be done in the flower of his youth, or if we have been able to guard our youth, beneath our gray hair.</p>
   <p>"Bygmester Solness" could do this when he saw "Hilde Wangel" for the first time. He could then rise to highest heights, because he was young. He could descend again, unhurt, because he did not become dizzy. Ten years later, he could not, because trying to become great, the greatest of all, he had lost his youth. So he had really become small, without courage or strength to ascend to higher heights. He believes he has won back his youth. He does not know it is lost, and lost youth can never be regained. When he tries to rise as high as he has <pb facs="5420780_2_0879.jpg" n="3"/>built, he falls and is destroyed. This is what Mr. Harmer portrayed in his role.</p>
   <p>"Hilde Wangel" is the personification of "Bygmester Solness'" youth. In the years that had passed, "Solness" had forgotten the embraces and kisses. When they met again, they both wanted a reunion, but they only built castles in the air, and, therefore, they tumbled down. Mrs. Hammer not only portrayed "Solness'" youth, but she was youth. Therefore, she could rise as high as she had aimed and built. That was why her portrayed was rapturous. It was admirable to note the sincerity with which she portrayed the many different sentiments of her role. And her last lines, "I will never see him again," brought out such heart felt pain over the loss of "Solness," when he went into the world where nothing more can be done because youth is gone.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lindboes' orchestra, only a violin and a piano, filled the intermissions in a manner which made us forget how long they were.</p>
   <p>The play was again produced in Bjorgvin Hall, Sunday, February 18.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
