<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-02-25">Feb. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Poul Bai</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1927-02-25">Feb. 25, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">POUL BAI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years have slipped by since Poul Bai, internationally famous baritone, stepped before an admiring public to make his debut in Copenhagen on February 17, 1917. Even then, as a young man, he was welcomed into the close fold of true musicians; that circle of artists to which a chosen few are elected, though many seek admittance.</p>
   <p>During these past years Bai has fulfilled and fulfilling the rich promise of high attainment which he made at his first appearance success has marked his work in the concert field and in teaching before his advent to America, European critics set their stamp of unquestionable approval on his work. Two years in this country have firmly established him <pb facs="5420780_2_0483.jpg" n="2"/>here as a musician and a singer of merit.</p>
   <p>Aside from his own work in concerts and recitals, Mr. Bai has a definite interest in teaching. Unusual ability to convey his knowledge and artistry to his students produces remarkable results in them. Hearing his followers speak of him, one knows that Bai's work is sincere. His students are his first consideration. He works with them, plans for them, inspires them, and encourages them.</p>
   <p>Those who love good music look forward with enthusiasm to Paul Bai's recital to be given at Kimball Hall on Wednesday, March 2. It is satisfying to hear a fine vice, rich in quality and power, singing with artistry, the best in music literature.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0484.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's Note: Mr. Bai has given More concerts than any other Danish singer in Chicago]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
