<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-02-14">Feb. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-02-14">Feb. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The society for the Danish Old People's Home held its annual general membership meeting last Wednesday in Dania Hall.</p>
   <p>The president, Mrs. William Nelson read a report on the activities of the home during the year 1913, and on its present status. Evidently everything is running smoothly, and the membership of the society increased by 86.</p>
   <p>The income from various social gatherings and entertainments arranged for money-raising purposes, amounted to $1,135.54; membership fees, $922.50; gifts, $886.62; admission fees to the home, $650; income from visitors to the home, $332.31; interest on capital $1,246.69; Altogether a net income of $5,173.66. Operating expenses amounted to $3,024.</p>
   <p>Four residents of the home died during the year and four new ones were admitted.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1690.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The president thanked everybody who in one way or the other had contributed to the welfare of the home and its residents.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the building fund committee, Lauritz Olesen, reported that so far more than $2,000 had been collected, and expressed confidence that when definite plans be formulated and construction started, more money would be forthcoming.</p>
   <p>The latest proposal of building a number of cottages instead of one large building was discussed, and arguments were presented for and against. The landscape architect Jens Jensen had prepared a sketch, showing how the cottages might be grouped around the administration building and connected with the latter by a closed-in corridor. However, since this plan is new and no definite information in regard to cost and its practical advantage <pb facs="5420780_2_1691.jpg" n="3"/>is available, it was decided to authorize the president to appoint a committee which is to obtain accurate date, blueprints, and other necessary material. When this is done, another meeting will be called, and a final decision made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
