<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-02-27">Feb. 27, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of the Danish Old Peoples' Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-02-27">Feb. 27, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF THE DANISH OLD PEOPLES' HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.5......The new addition to the Danish Old Peoples' Home will be dedicated Sunday afternoon with appropriate ceremonies. When the decision was reached a year ago to enlarge the home, many doubted the advisibility of doing this, for at that time, the times were not what they had been and money was scarce.</p>
   <p>If the building committee and its energetic president, Mr. J. C. Nielsen had been firm in their convictions regarding the undertaking it would not have succeeded. Faith always finds a way. The Danish people of Chicago, who have been behind this work for twenty-five years did not default this time either. Large and small donations all according to the ability of the donor came in, until finally the goal was reached. At times it seemed as if the work would have to be discontinued, but the work was always resumed with reneweed vigor.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0706.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is with pleasure that the Danish Old Peoples' Home Society can look back upon a well completed task.</p>
   <p>The first house was burned in June and the work progressed fast. The cornerstone was laid August 17, and now the building is ready for occupancy. Many have contributed towards this grand result.</p>
   <p>Architect Axel Teijen designed the building end the builders are Anton Christensen and Jacob Svendsen.</p>
   <p>There is room for fifty old people, who will find a quiet-pleasant home amidst beautiful surrounding during the sun-set of their lives.</p>
   <p>The society has over seven-hundred members; it is to them, first honors are due for such an undertaking. However, many others gave both of their time and money, to bring the work to a successful conclusion.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0707.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The dedication ceremonies will start Sunday at 2:00 o'clock P.M. Mr. Anton Kvist has written a Prologue and Chas. Ditlefsen and Pastor Dan have composed songs.</p>
   <p>Attorney General Oscor Carlstrom will speak as will the Danish Consul R. Bauman, Mrs. Consul Hansen, Mr. George Jensen and Pastors A.T.Dorf and A.W. Anderson.</p>
   <p>Mr. Carl Antonsen will read the Prologue and Mr.and Mrs. Holger Petersen will sing.</p>
   <p>If the weather permits, many are certain to avail themselves of the opportunity to come out and inspect the building and to rejoice with many others that a good deed is well done through united efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
