<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1891-02-02">Feb. 2, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Svenning Dahl</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1891-02-02">Feb. 2, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">DR. SVENNING DAHL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago a contractor sued Dr. Svenning Dahl for malpractice. We wanted to get the details about the case, so we interviewed Professor Christian Fenger and Dr. Merrick, who were called in after an emergency operation had been performed by Dr. Dahl on Mr. Nelson. Professor Fenger cleared Dr. Dahl of any suspicion of malpractice.</p>
   <p>In our interview with Dr. Merrick he was asked,</p>
   <p>"What do you think of the operation which Dr. Dahl performed on Nelson the contractor?"</p>
   <p>"I was called to assist Dr. Dahl on November 27 in re-dressing the patient's wound," said Dr. Merrick. "I did not see the wound when it was dressed the first time. It was a dreadful fracture, I must say, and I have never seen so many precautions taken in an operation. Dr. Dahl made me wash and scrub <pb facs="5420780_2_0323.jpg" n="2"/>my hands twice and sterilize myself before going near the patient. All science knows about asepsis was used, and I do not think that any surgeon in Chicago could do better, I don't care who he may be. I am an old practitioner, having been a surgeon for twenty-four years, and I have had quite a lot of experience; so I ought to know something about it."</p>
   <p>"Was Nelson 'bound and gagged,' as he stated, while he was being dressed?"</p>
   <p>"No; that is a lie, and you may publish that statement as coming from me."</p>
   <p>"What do you think of the case in general?"</p>
   <p>"Oh, it is all bluff, nothing else. If I were Dahl, I would not spend a penny in a legal way. A case as clear as this cannot but come out all right; there is no case at all.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0324.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We felt that because of this false accusation against Dr. Dahl and because the daily press had played the case up, not in Dahl's favor, we were in duty bound to give the true story.</p>
   <p>Dr. Dahl is a young Danish physician, who recently graduated with high honors from the College of Physicians and Surgeons here in Chicago. He is a protege of Professor Fenger's, and we are sure that this young Dane will make a name for himself.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Dr. Dahl discovered the anaesthetic called Stovane, which is considered one of the safest local anaesthetics. He has done a great deal of research in the field of anaesthesia. He has been honored time and time again.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
