<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-03-21">Mar. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Anniversary]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-03-21">Mar. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[ANNIVERSARY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian Women's Socialist Society, now a year old, observed its first anniversary with a festive gathering last Saturday in Wabansia Hall.</p>
   <p>A large number of members and friends attended, and the ladies proved to everybody's satisfaction that even though they are very active in politics and agitation, they have not forgotten the art of cooking.</p>
   <p>N. F. Holm delivered the welcoming speech and acted as toastmaster. Mrs. Lycinka Hansen had written a song for the occasion, in which she urged women to live up to their responsibilities in a world which is waiting for them to take a more active part in its affairs, and in a sincere and forceful speech she further developed this idea, reminding women that the future of humanity depends to a great extent upon the influence which they are able to exert.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our countryman, State Representative Christian M. Madsen, who so ably represents the Socialistic party in the legislature, in his speech discussed the strong socialistic undercurrent which more and more is making itself felt in our American society.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Adolph Christensen warned against the tendency among many Socialists to confine their agitation within a too narrow circle, and several others, among whom were William Petersen, Nicholls, Wipsness, and Ferd. Andersen, propounded the Socialistic cause in spirited speeches.</p>
   <p>The proceeds of the affair were donated to a Socialistic publication, which is having financial difficulties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
