<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1922-02-11">Feb. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish-American Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1922-02-11">Feb. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH-AMERICAN PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are happy to see that the Danish-American press has improved since the birth of the Danish Times. It proves that the Times has proven itself quite a competitor. The moth-eaten Danish-American was thoroughly dead and stagnant until Danish Times showed itself above the horizon. Then a few papers and periodicals slowly awakened, while others still slept on, peacefully. We have never thought that we could get all the Danish readers in America, but we do believe by giving our readers a clean, well edited, and interesting paper, it will be possible to improve other Danish papers. This has been proven in a few cases, while it is apparent that some papers will fall by the wayside.</p>
   <p>The Danish papers in America have long been a party of a press. They used their scissors a lot, cutting most of their material out of Denmark's papers, reprinted old novels, without receiving a penny for space, and called it a paper. Original <pb facs="5420780_2_1064.jpg" n="2"/>material, good or bad, was seldom seen. Illustrations belonging to modern journalism were few and far between, and the few that appeared were very bad.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is opportune that some competition be started so that the people can get better papers than before. We hope our competitors will be successful, but it is difficult to change the policy of old papers.</p>
   <p>A certain paper tries to get some interview every week, but this is not a very good policy. Another paper has uncovered a number of old cuts, with which they try to please their readers, in order to show that the paper is not asleep well, they do the best they can in the face of new competition. Very commendable, but a few new cuts would serve the purpose much better.</p>
   <p>A third paper, which can not produce much on account of old age, has increased its sentimental stories. This is a very bad policy, because the duty of a paper is to give clear, honest, and interesting news, in order to improve the contents of the reading matter, whether it is metropolitan or rural. Probably there may be a few readers that could be satisfied with material of this kind, <pb facs="5420780_2_1065.jpg" n="3"/>but the taste for good reading is in danger of being spoiled, so our press should try to do their best, even though it may be difficult. We hope that this particular paper will change its tactics so that they may become our competitor. It will make us very happy if all our competitors would try to give their readers better and better papers. It is our goal to give our Danish-American readers just as good a press here as they have in Denmark.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
