<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-06-12">June 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Way Out</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1931-06-12">June 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE WAY OUT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to Victor S. Yanos' able review, Norman Thomas in America's Way Out denounces the profit motive as incompatible with economic stability and economic or social progress. The trouble is that doing away with this motive would be tantamount to communism, which the author, in line with all good and true socialists, whether of the current European or American brand, professes to abhor and hate, while in turn being lambasted as bourgois or reactionary by the reds.</p>
   <p>A wide divergence between the old school of Marxism and contemporary socialism is strikingly illuminated by comparing the two outstanding leaders; the venerable departed fundamentalist, Eugene U. Debs, who proudly went to jail for a visionary cause, and his successor, the party's standard bearer, Norman Thomas, who typifies a bewildered mixture of professedly individualistic yearnings and efforts to <pb facs="5420780_2_0147.jpg" n="2"/>destroy or at least impair the economic social structure shaped by individualism.</p>
   <p>If the world finds itself in a blind alley and is facing difficulties of a more serious extent and nature than a passing crisis, it is exactly for the same reasons that will wreck any business concern when overhead expenses are constantly growing at a rate out of proportion to net earnings. Wars and preparations, armaments, and tariffs, displaced gold reserves, and other frequently cited causes are in no more than minor ways contributary to the paralysis created by accumulated and inherited wealth, the most definite manifestation of which are an imposing leisure and luxury class sponging upon other people's labor.</p>
   <p>This enormous and ever-growing liability upon the capitalistic world ledger having been eliminated by Soviet Russia in religious adherence to Marxian principles, evidently infuses a certain vitality into the system, but at <pb facs="5420780_2_0148.jpg" n="3"/>the same time is severely handicapped by also eliminating the profit motive and individual enterprise. The communistic level of existance, which may suffice for simpletons never used to anything better, looms rather repellent to people of more advanced views and requirements; both material and spiritual, and so it is up to the rest of the world to mend its way and demonstrate that freedom, opportunity and economic justice are realizable under a true and healthy consistent individualism, a system free from all species of unfair privileges, subsidies, bounties and artificial inequalities. It is almost certain that the alternative is moral and economic bankruptcy, the process of decay from within the system itself being accelerated by an eager army of socialists, radicals, liberals, progressives, and other confused but well-meaning propagandists and reformers with an abundance of experimental socialization, paternalism, bureaucracy, government subsidization or restriction of business, the pouring out of doles and soaring taxes which contribute to the creation of the vicious circle of distress and distemper wherein bolshevism may thrive.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0149.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Thomas' way out having already been widely tried and inevitably proven to be the way down, a better and more genuine American way out of a situation admittedly full of peril would be an enactment of an individual income surtax, reasonably and uniformly graded up to one hundred per cent. Why not try this simple and straight way to safer and saner human relations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
