<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-04-19">Apr. 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1912-04-19">Apr. 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Art lovers of Chicago, were hardly through admiring the Scandinavian paintings exhibited at the Art Institute before their attention was called to another great event.</p>
   <p>The Danish pianist and composer Thorwald Otterstrom, for many years a resident of Chicago, has won a high place in the world of music, and last Friday afternoon and Saturday evening, his new composition "Zlegi, Koral Og Fuga," was played by the Chicago Symphony Orchestra before a great enthusiastic audience.</p>
   <p>In this work, which is written for a complete orchestra, (including organ) the composer has employed the most distinguished and noble, but also the most difficult form of music. Thereby revealing a marvelous technique, yet without shadowing the pure musical aspect <pb facs="5420780_2_0536.jpg" n="2"/>of the composition. The composition carries a stamp of simplicity, modulation and thematic development throughout. It is characterized by harmony and color so often missing in modern compositions.</p>
   <p>American musical critics agree on placing Mr. Otterstrom among the greatest of modern composers.</p>
   <p>Besides the above composition, Mr. Otterstrom has contributed several compositions for piano, twenty four preludiums, forty-two fugues six concert studies, and twenty-eight melodies.</p>
   <p>Mr. Otterstrom was born in Copenhagen here he received his first musical training. Later he studied in St. Petersburg. He arrived in Chicago in 1898. Signed George Dupont-Wausen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
