<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title><date when="1925-11-06">Nov. 6, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Song and Tuxedos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title><date when="1925-11-06">Nov. 6, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SONG AND TUXEDOS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The affiliated Danish choir, which was the source of so much enjoyment during the week of Opera Singer Johs Fonss's visit should be congratulated,especially for its performance at the University of Chicago. The impression these vocalists made on their audience, particularly on the young students and the specially invited guests will constitute a cultural contribution on the part of Danes in America.</p>
   <p>The marvelous choir under the direction of Marinus Poulsen and Joel Mosberg deserves our appreciation and thanks.</p>
   <p>So much for the song, but we feel obliged to criticise their behavior a little.</p>
   <p>We would say that 95% of the singers stood erect and attentive while singing, and thus represented their nationality in a worthy manner, but a few, presumably the <pb facs="5420780_2_0699.jpg" n="2"/>last recruits, stood as if they had just alighted from an express, their eyes scanning over the audience, as though they were trying to locate somebody; some actually stood with their hands in their pockets.</p>
   <p>We hope this will never happen again. If these offenders of stage etiquette had a chance to see themselves in a mirror, they would have learned something.</p>
   <p>We would not ask for or expect too much of our obliging singers but we believe their appearance would be greatly improved if they uniformly wore tuxedos when staging their performances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
