<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-12-04">Dec. 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Peoples Home's Christmas Market</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-12-04">Dec. 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD PEOPLES HOME'S CHRISTMAS MARKET</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... An enormous crowd greeted our eyes on Sunday evening when we visited Dania Hall. Sweet young damsels selling "Chances" hung on to us until "business" was transacted. Then we were pushed over to one of the many booths, and in a short time we had a beautifully embroidered nightgown on the arm. Butcher Olsen showed us a basket overflowing with choice groceries. All for ten cents. We were foolish enough to give him half a dollar, whereupon on the butcher disappears with the whole amount leaving us with five unlucky numbers. Butchers should not be admitted to bazars. From the stage, Bank Director Hansen's young son spies us - Three for a quarter - just for you alone;, guaranteed to win - thank you! The wheel spins - but the Bank Director's son did not speak the truth.</p>
   <p>We peek curiously into the many other booths. They all have many visitors and the money rolls in. A gentleman in "Harmonien's" booth shouts so loud that he drowns out "Holy Night" from the Workingmen's Singing Society. The same <pb facs="5420780_2_1666.jpg" n="2"/>gentleman takes, without the slightest compunction,our last forty-five cents. The wheel spins again. A sixteen year old boy with a Prince of Wales sweater wins a hand-embroidered apron. The nearby ladies smile at him jealously. The apron disappears under the sweater. In front of a large blackboard G.P. Jensen is scooping up nickles. Mr. Jensen does not shout so loud, but his black sparkling eyes draw customers to his booth. "Five cents per vote - who is the colony's most popular lady or gentleman?"</p>
   <p>We look at the blackboard: Martin Meisel and Claus Jensen are leading for the moment. A couple of gentlemen from the South Side pull out their "Rolls," and Paul Wester and E.C. Bunck rise in "cold cash popularity."</p>
   <p>On the blackboard where the womens names are registered, we are not surprised to see Mrs. James Henriksen in the lead, closely followed by the Hesdames G.P.Nielsen and O. Nielsen.</p>
   <p>Finally we reach the exit; people loaded down with goods of all kinds, flowers, smoked meats, toys, electric appliances and much else are leaving, while other guests from all parts of the colony arrive.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1667.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the basement, (where on Saturday the Workingmen's Singing Society) entertained,"Harmonian", with Harry Larsen as director, is helping to entertain the crowd. Further back in the dining-hall the ladies are serving delicious sandwiches with a consoling cup of coffee to the disappointed lottery players.</p>
   <p>An animated spirit prevailed everywhere, and the guests left with the satisfaction of having contributed their share towards a worthy cause - The Danish Old Peoples Home.</p>
   <p>The committee will certainly be able to report a neat surplus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
