<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1930-07-04">July 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Freedom of Our Plutocratic or So-Called Free Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1930-07-04">July 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">FREEDOM OF OUR PLUTOCRATIC OR SO-CALLED FREE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When our visitor first entered the City Editor's office, he was pleasantly surprised at being confronted with a man who, according to his understanding of psychology, was possessed with all the qualifications that make for greatness.</p>
   <p>After a short exchange of greetings, he being offered a seat, the visitor explained to the City Editor his reason for calling.</p>
   <p>Lately, one of the big stores in town had been having trouble with their help, all due to the fact that the store owners, who already were paying their help starving wages, were trying to cut the amount down to a minimum, unacceptable even to a slave.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0157.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The City Editor, with his kind eyes and well formed forehead, sat patiently listening to the plea for justice, so eloquently expressed by the spokesman, and representative of the working girls. After the visitor had finished his plea, the editor stated that his sentiment was for the girls one hundred per cent.</p>
   <p>Yet, when asked if he would accept an article which would bring the real facts home to the public, the Editor frankly admitted the impossibility of such a thing.</p>
   <p>The spokesman left, but his first and favorable impression of the City Editor was somewhat dimmed. He asked himself the question; why such a noble head had been placed on a spineless body?</p>
   <p>After weighing the incident however, the spokesman realized that the City Editor himself was but a slave, who, for the sake of a job, had to sell his soul. Poor Editor.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0158.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dante's Inferno is but a pocket edition to man's troubled conscience, which, due to lack of a spine, and to the big appetite of his belly, fails to follow his own convictions.</p>
   <p>The human race would indeed be much better off if such men were never born, for like most religious and quack doctors, they are the real stumbling block to progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
