<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-06-21">June 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Woman's Suffrage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editiorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1913-06-21">June 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WOMAN'S SUFFRAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editiorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The granting of suffrage, even if limited, to the women of Illinois, is an historical event, which was recently celebrated at a banquet is Springfield's leading hotel, and among those at the speaker's table were the two Danish members of the legislature, Senator Niels Juul and Christian M. Madsen, state representative.</p>
   <p>Senator Juul, in his speech, explained that when he, in the past had opposed women's participation in public life, he was simply using such judgment as he had, and his position was a certainly not influenced by any lack of respect and admiration for the weaker sex. However, his experiecce as a member of the committee which was appointed to study moral and working conditions among women, had converted him, and he was now a staunch believer in and supporter of women's suffrage.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Representative Madsen recalled a similar banquet in the City Hall of Copenhagen, Denmark, where women, after having won the right to vote, did all the talking, while mere man listened, and he thanked the women of Illinois for not depriving right away the men-folks of the freedom of speech.</p>
   <p>He pointed out that the attempts made to convince the legislature that women's suffrage is identical with socialism, had not been successful, and he was glad to observe that the time has now passel when a good cause could be suppressed just by calling it socialism. (He did not, of course, make the statement, as quoted in the Tribune, that socialism would never be identified with woman's suffrage.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
