<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>Danish Times</title>, <date when="1930-09-19">Sept. 19, 1930</date></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1780</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet Archive by the University of
     Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>,
      <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus
      Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>

   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation"><bibl><title>Danish Times</title>, <date when="1930-09-19">Sept. 19, 1930</date></bibl></div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1780.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I fail to see why a few men could not come together and thrash out this difficulty in an
    honorable manner by cutting out a little on the one side and adding a little on the other
    side.</p>
   <p>We should be big enough to dominate all selfish pride and ignore all private interest in
    deciding these points in question. There appears to me to be more at stake than just the Danish
    Aid and Relief Society or the National Committee's Relief Fund. It stands out forcibly to me
    that if the National Committee expects to be a success in the future, we must have harmony; and
    if the relief funds expect to be successful we must also have harmony, and to accomplish that we
    must not be two bodies, each going our own way. I maintain that the principle of co-operation is
    bigger than the interest of any individual, and I claim that no one has the right to stand in
    the way of a successful solution of this difficulty. As matters stand now, there is a
    possibility of the Danish Aid and Relief Society losing the Tag Day and there is a possibility
    that the National Committee's Relief Fund might not <pb facs="5420780_2_1781.jpg" n="3"/>be
    granted a Tag Day. Is it difficult to see who will be the principal losers?</p>
   <p>I for one will do my utmost for a reconcilation before it ever goes that far, and to that end
    I respectfully suggest that we form an arbitration committee consisting of two members from each
    side, having full power to act. This arbitration committee should select one man as chairman;
    this man should not be a member of the National Committee, nor should he be a member of the
    Danish Aid and Relief Society.</p>
   <p>Such men as the supreme president of the Danish Brotherhood Mr. John Christensen, or Dr. Max
    Henius, or Mr. Ericksen, of the Daily News, or someone else who has no axe to grind and who
    would only look upon the question with an unbiased mind, would undoubtedly bring the much wanted
    result.</p>
   <p>But in order to accomplish this, the arbitration committee should meet with full <pb
     facs="5420780_2_1782.jpg" n="4"/>power to act and should agree to abide by the chairman's
    decisions.</p>
   <p>If we can agree on that, the problem will be solved and we will again be able to stand before
    our countrymen as an honest and harmonious unit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
