<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1915-05-22">May 22, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Socialist Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1915-05-22">May 22, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALIST ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The House of Representatives, in Springfield, recently discussed several proposals that would give women nine hours work per day, or a maximum of fifty hours per week.</p>
   <p>The employers opposed this legislation and tried in various ways to substitute jokers in order to defeat this bill. Representative Purdunn went so far as to make a motion that the bill include housemaids. Representative Butler then asked for the floor, and very soberly amended this motion to include housewives.</p>
   <p>For a moment, it looked as if this motion and amendment would be passed, amidst much joking and laughter. But then Christian Madsen arose, and shamed them for their insincerity to the people who had elected them. And closed by saying: "You make a joke out of this thing and degrade the State of Illinois before the country and in the eyes of the world. You are supposed to represent the State and you ought to be proud of it. You are unworthy of the trust the people of Illinois have placed upon you, and I hope it will not take very long before <pb facs="5420780_2_0190.jpg" n="2"/>some of the women who are demanding legislation will have seats on the floor of this House, and then you will not treat the women of the State of Illinois as a joke. I Vote No."</p>
   <p>His words turned the tide of opinion, and all the remaining votes were opposed and many of those who had already voted in favor, changed and voted no.</p>
   <p>The result of Christian Madsen's speech is that he has been recommended as a member of the Committee of Industrial Affairs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
