<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-04-07">Apr. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish Sharpshooters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-04-07">Apr. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH SHARPSHOOTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday evening, the Danish Sharpshooters celebrated their 26th anniversary at Albany Hall. Few were present, as one would know that society had just returned from the battlefronts, and many were missing in the ranks. But there was plenty courage in both the veterans and the recruits, and the delicious supper inspired many of them to show how good they were both as singers and speakers.</p>
   <p>Jacob Nielsen, president, directed the meeting, and John Pooder spoke for the society; Hjalmar Nielsen spoke for America, Jens Lundsberg spoke for Denmark, and Theo Beck spoke for the ladies.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1273.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Between the speeches, we heard the Sharpshooters' "Old Battle Song," by Anton Kvist, a song for Denmark by Lundsberg, and the "Sharpshooters' Review for 1917," with no less than twenty-five verses, written by Mrs. H. Sorensen, who also was called to make a speech. Other speakers were: Mrs. Christ Sorensen, John Olsen, who is an old sailor, and who at this time enlisted in the Marines; Soren Hansen, who holds the record of having attended all of the twenty-six anniversaries of the society; Christ Hede, H. Sorensen, who brought greetings from the champion sharpshooters; Westergard, P. Mommesen, S. Nymark, and others.</p>
   <p>The Society's shooting instructor, P. Christensen, was presented with the gold medal for marksmanship, having scored 2416 points in one hundred consecutive shots, every bulls eye scoring twenty-five points. Alfred Andersen <pb facs="5420780_2_1274.jpg" n="3"/>was presented with a gold button for good and reliable service as cashier. J. P. Jensen played both at the banquet and the dance which continued far into the morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
