<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-01-06">Jan. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas Eve at the Danish Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1917-01-06">Jan. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS EVE AT THE DANISH HOME FOR THE AGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very successful Christmas celebration was held at the Danish Home for the Aged. All the inmates, now a total of 31, were filled with a radiant Christmas spirit when the ladies of the house committee and other executives arrived to spend the evening with them. The managers, Mr. and Mrs. J. Ensen decorated the dining room and lounge, in honor of the occasion, and a small Christmas tree was placed on a table. The presents for the old people were placed around it. About 6: p. m. dinner was ready, and everyone went to the brightly lighted and beautifully decorated dining room and sat down at the well-set table. The dinner consisted of goose, turkey, Aeblekage (Danish apple-cake) and other good food, all of which was well cooked.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1681.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many pretty speeches about the home, the executives and the inmates were made. Everyone added something to the festivities, and many of the inmates spoke, sang or recited. Mrs. Erika Hansen delighted the party with her merry songs.</p>
   <p>After dinner everyone went over to the old Home, where hours were spent with music and song. Later they all gathered around the Christmas tree and presents were given to the inmates.</p>
   <p>Among those who helped to make the party a success were, Mrs. E. Holm, who played well known Danish melodies, and Miss Alpha Henriksen, who sang some beautiful songs. We want to thank our friends, who sent gifts and who, one way or another, helped make this Christmas party a success.</p>
   <p>Mrs. W. Nelson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
