<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Pamphlet: Jensen, Otto, "<title level="a">History of the Harmonien Singing Society?</title>" <title>Harmoniens Golden Jubilee Book, 1886-1936</title>. by Harmonien Singing Society Golden Jubilee Committee, Chicago,
<date when="1936-11-08">November 8, 1936</date>. pp. 4 - 12.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Pamphlet: Jensen, Otto, "<title level="a">History of the Harmonien Singing Society?</title>" <title>Harmoniens Golden Jubilee Book, 1886-1936</title>. by Harmonien Singing Society Golden Jubilee Committee, Chicago,
<date when="1936-11-08">November 8, 1936</date>. pp. 4 - 12.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Danish Singing Society "Harmonien" was started the 10th of November 1886 on the corner of Kinzie Street and Milwaukee Avenue. The first members of the Board were H. V. Rocatis, President: Otto Darn, Vice President; Marius Olsen, Secretary; R. Skovboe, Cashier. A week later Theo Elberg was elected as Leader of the Singers.</p>
   <p>The first meeting was given on the 21st of November, with entertainment under the auspices of the Harmonien. The 8th of January, 1887 the first Concert was given, but the first real Concert was given the 14th of May, 1887 in Concordia Hall. A great audience was present. In November, in the same place, the first Fall Concert was given.</p>
   <p>A Ladies Committee consisting of Mrs. Ryberg, Mrs. Carl Jensen, Miss Skovboe, and Miss Snidtker had a long time been very busy getting a Flag for Harmonien. They succeeded and presented it to the Hannoni, a beautiful large silk Flag as a gift from 150 Danish gentlemen and ladies. In 1888 Harmonien had a big concert at Aurora Turner hall, for a crowded house. The Volmer <pb facs="5420780_2_0681.jpg" n="2"/>Battle Song was sung, receiving a storming applause.</p>
   <p>In 1891 Harmonien partook in the Scandinavian Song Fest in Minneapolis with 40 singers taking part and with Prof. Nielsen as leader. The year before Theo. Elberg had resigned, his eyesight having failed entirely. Congressman Niels Juul was Harmonien's President and was elected as President for the Scandinavian Singing Society in America.</p>
   <p>In the year of 1893 Miels Juul arranged with a Committee of the Harmoniens to have a large Scandinavian Song Fest at the World's Fair. More than 700 singers took part. Two concerts were given, one in the Music Hall at the World's Fair and one in "Battery D". The great Opera Singer Herald from the Royal Theatre of Copenhagen sang a solo.</p>
   <p>In 1893. Professor Niels Petersen resigned as leader and Professor Lanzky was put in his place.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0682.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Library was erected by Harmonien in 1894 and for several years was appreciated very much. But as new books were not bought, the Library closed up and gave its 400 Volumes to the Danish Old People's Home in Norwood Park in the year of 1914.</p>
   <p>The first artist visiting Harmonien was Valborg Andersen 1896; Mrs. Elisabeth Riis 1897; Johannes W. Jensen and Johannes Fouss, 1925; and Lauritz Melchior, 1935.</p>
   <p>In 1898 Harmonien arranged a large concert in the central Music Hall for the benefit of the Danish "Children's Home." The amount taken in was $800, which went towards a new building for the Children's Home.</p>
   <p>In 1899 the first Minstrel Show played for a full house. Two weeks later by request, they played again. The originators were Edward and Valdemar Hansen.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0683.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In 1899 Professor Victor Lanzky resigned, being too busy with other work. Kristran Nielsen a Norwegian, was elected leader. He started the talk of a trip to Denmark but it never materialized. In 1900 Harmonien sang at Drachmans Feast in Music Hall." The Sunday after, a Smoker was given in Brewster Hall with Drachman as guest of honor. The "Hamlet" Singing Society from Racine was present. Theo Elberg made a speech for the guest of Honor. Drachman; Drachman answered with a speech for Harmonien.</p>
   <p>On November 10, 1901 Harmonien had its first big concert Down Town at the Studebaker Hall. The "Kings Daughter" and the "Volmer Battle" was the program. Miss Harrit Hertz and P. Marinus Paulsen was also on the program. In the month of July, Dr. Max Henius was taken in as a member of honor. He was until his death, true blue.</p>
   <p>In 1902 the 2nd Minstrel Show played again for a full house. The program was the same as the last with the exception of two songs of Charles P. Ditlefsen and one of Fred Snidtken. Edward Hansen was the instructor.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0684.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In 1904 the first trip was made to the Old People's Home on the 1st of May, entertaining the Old People with singing and all partook of a fine lunch. In front of Elbergs grave the Singers stopped and sang a few songs in his memory.</p>
   <p>In 1904 the reunion of the four leaders took place. The four men had been song leaders for the twenty years Harmonien existed and all the old songs were sung all over. Dr. Max Henius; Henry L. Hertz; Theodore Elberg; Niels Juul and Carl Antonsen were the speakers of the evening. A prolog of Aage Engel was read by Albert Kear. As soloists was Peter Boas and Oscar P. Rubardt.</p>
   <p>In 1907 Kristian Nielsen resigned as leader and Joel Mossberg was installed. He was avery likable and beloved leader. The Harmonien made great progress under Joel Mossbergs' leadership.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0685.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In 1903 Harmonien gave up its old way of doing business, and replaced it with an Advisory Board of twelve men. Their business was to take full charge of Harmonien affairs. The Advisory Board was given the name "Kancelljraadet." It lasted two years, and Harmonien went back to its old ways again, by having five men on the board and having a business meeting once a month.</p>
   <p>By invitation of Racine, Wisconsin, "Dania", a concert was given in Racine in April. 1910. It was a two day affair and a great success. In 1911 the Danish Student Singing Society of Copenhagen arrived in America; when they visited Chicago, they were received at the depot and Harmonien gave them an old Studeuter Song. In the Afternoon they were entertained at Bjorgvin Hall for a "Sexa" and in the Evening at Bismark Garden, when the Danish Student and Harmonien sang together and received great applause from the guests at the garden. The 25 years Jubilee was celebrated in the Association Auditorium at LaSalle Street. A beautiful Memorial of the history of Harmonien was written by Secretary Alfred Hansen.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0686.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In 1913 Theo Elberg died at the Old People's Home in Norwood. He was buried at the Old People's Home Cemetary. In 1917 a monument was erected by Chicago Danish Singers in his memory. In 1913 Author L. C. Nielsen was guest of honor at a Banquet. The Banquet was a great success. Dr. Max Henius-Carl Antonsen, and Ivor Kirkegaard from Bacine were the speakers. Alex Roos and Halger Pedersen sang solos.</p>
   <p>In 1915 Harmonien went to "San Francisco." Along the way stops were made at Omaha, Nebraska and Salt Lake City, Utah. In Festival Hall, San Francisco, on the Fair ground, a Concert was given very successfully. In memory of Niels W. Gades 100 year birthday, 138 Danish Singers give a concert at Consistory Hall. 1,100 people were present.</p>
   <p>In 1921 Harmonien celebrated its 35th birthday at the Garrick Theatre. Dr. Max Henius and Carl Antosen presented Harmonien with two beautiful Harps.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0687.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>In 1923 the Harmony bought Bjorgvin Hall. It was impossible to keep it up and it was sold at a great loss. In 1924 Harmoniens 38 Singers and leader, Joel Mossberg went on a trip to Denmark, stopping at different cities in Denmark and giving Concerts. The income of the Concerts amounted to 103,000.00 Kroner. The amount was given to Welfare Societies in the different cities of Denmark. Joel Mossberg; Jacob Hvass, and Charles P. Ditlefsen were Knighted by the King.</p>
   <p>Harmoniens 2nd trip to Denmark in 1930 together with Dania was a great success. In the 50 years of Harmonies existence five members have been made honorable members: Theo. Elberg, Niels Juul, Victor Lanzky, Dr. Max Henius and Helmar Hansen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
