<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-07-13">July 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1722</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1722.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 3 (Norwegian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1907-07-13">July 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Danish Old People's Home has published its 4th annual report. Accompanying this report was an appeal to support the Institution, rules for admission, etc., as well as memorials in honor of the late Mrs. Thorsen, founder of the institution, and of an elderly lady, Miss Caroline Jorgensen, who died at the Norwegian Tabitha Hospital after having donated her entire fortune, $6,000, to the Danish Old People's Home.</p>
   <p>The financial condition of the institution is steadily improving. During the past year a total of $1008.83 has been collected as net proceeds from four social affairs. Dues amounted to $966.05; admission fees, $132; donations, $92.70; collections at meetings, where coffee and lunch was served, $101.85; interest on capital, $770.04.</p>
   <p>The total amount owned by the Society [Editor's note: The funds of the institution are collected and managed by a financial committee elected by the Danish Old People's Home Society, which is back of the institution.]</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1723.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>has now reached the figure of $28,980.77. The Home has twenty inmates. There were fifteen applicants during the past year, so the proposal for expansion is justified. Plans for an addition to the buildings have been considered, but the means with which to carry such plans into effect should come from sources other than the present funds of the Society, it is thought. A Dane by the name of V. Michaelsen, president of the Illinois Paint Mfg. Co., who has been the heaviest annual contributor up to now, has donated $250 towards an addition.</p>
   <p>The executive committee elected by the Society has asked us to convey the information that, in the list of donations published in the report, the names of Madsen and Dalgaard, who donated the beautiful sign adorning the institution, have been forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
