<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-05-08">May 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Good Fellowship Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_1790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-05-08">May 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD FELLOWSHIP CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week a group of men from St. Ausgar's Church met in the home of Mr. John M. Petersen to discuss the desirability of organizing a club, the aims of which would be to extend aid to fellow country-men in various ways.</p>
   <p>It is but a matter of course that we attempt to help one another, and much is being done to that effect; but it is often impossible for the individual to help even if he would like to.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, a necessity that we collaborate our efforts and take advantage of the ways and means which are at the disposal of a group. We do not particularly have in mind financial aid although this should also be extended where it is needed. However, there are many other groups organized for that special purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_1791.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our thought is rather to be of assistance to newcomers in the way of placing them where their individual training and education may prove most advantageous, and also help them to establish suitable social connections that may prove valuable for them in the future.</p>
   <p>All those present agreed that the need for such assistance was evident and that an organization, such as the one proposed, would serve this purpose. A committee was appointed with Mr. John Petersen as chairman. The committee is to formulate a few by-laws which were thought to be absolutely necessary, and call a meeting in the near future to take up the plans of organization for final discussion. The organization will function as a branch of St. Ausgar's Church, but membership will be open to people outside the church. An arrangement which will be similar to that of the church's Ladies Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
