<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1923-04-15">Apr. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Ukrainian Woman as a Full-Fledged Member of a Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1923-04-15">Apr. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">UKRAINIAN WOMAN AS A FULL-FLEDGED MEMBER OF A COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women, whom we often think of as the weaker sex, are endowed by nature with more virtue than the male. Is not woman--as a mother, the procreator of mankind--the firm foundation on which is built the whole family, the group, and even the nation? The woman is weak in body and in spirit--that is the way they usually speak among us of women.</p>
   <p>When being reared as children, future members of communities are in the hands of women. Taking this into consideration, what do we find? We find women lacking sleep while they care for small children, working hard to carry out their obligations in rearing them. Do not women participate in that which makes the community finer and more intelligent? It is sufficient that only one woman appear at any meeting for the men to become more discreet and courteous in their speech. No one an deny this.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0135.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Is not the schoolteacher one of the important workers in the community? Always, wherever a woman appears, whether as schoolteacher or as procreator of children, these children--especially the small ones--accumulate more knowledge. They learn how to become calm and more agreeable than they would be if the woman's place were occupied by a man. Why? Because a woman knows how to approach a child easily and gently.</p>
   <p>It is a known fact that when a man becomes a widower his small children perish like bronze-colored mice; but when a poor defenseless woman becomes a widow, she manages to put the half-orphaned children on the right road in the world. It is no wonder that our Ukrainian people composed the proverb, "With a mother and no father, the child is one and one-half; but without a mother and with a father, the child is just an orphan." Therefore, we women should not hide that with which nature has endowed us so generously! It is necessary that we all stand for our rights, especially because our obligations are far more important than those of the men!</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0136.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was a time when education was unattainable for the woman, and as a result she wandered about in ignorance, profiting only from her natural endowments. That time has passed. Now every woman has to scoop in by handfuls that which not so long ago was like a dream to her. Every woman and girl should belong to some society, thereby taking part in the national work. We want our Ukrainian people to be cultured and free, so let there be no woman who feels unconcerned about her obligations. Make it come about that in the struggles of our oppressed nation, every Ukrainian woman will work together with our men in the national interest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
