<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Only Orientation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Excerpt)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE ONLY ORIENTATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Excerpt)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Here in the United States of America, the Siege Organization calls upon each and everyone of you: Give up dirty politics; wipe out even the last speck of dust that is left from the old way of traveling through roadless jungles; cast out profitless fables, and roll up your sleeves and start out some real work, some profitable activity. Our field in that direction is covered with weeds, and it will take some time to get rid of them, especially if we continue to follow the same roads.</p>
   <p>Regardless of where you are, join the Athletic Siege Organization; it is our strength, our future, and the training center of the true sons of Ukrainia. How to take it up, how to make it fit our circumstances, our present writing will teach you. It will be particularly dedicated toward this end. Let there be not a single Ukrainian who will not read this newspaper.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0502.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After all, the object of this paper is clear. In it you will not find any politics, abuse or cheating, but a sincere word of truth, a word of true counsel at this momentous time. Neither the Siege Organization nor its periodical has any aim of rivalry, disruption, or conniving for reorganization. Their aim is to care for that, which has been up to the present time not taken care of sincerely, and which is so necessary for a harmonious development of our culture. Therefore, we are trying to safeguard ourselves ahead of time from all sorts of attacks, - and it is quite hard to avoid them altogether, - on the part of eventual enemies. Whoever is an enemy of this periodical, he is also an enemy of our culture, of our progress; he is a traitor to our cause. Spread these writings everywhere, wherever the Ukrainian spirit is present: among the young and old; men and women. Join the Ukrainian Siege branches all over the United States.</p>
   <p>Remember that in a sound body a sound mind.</p>
   <p>M. D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
