<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1924-09-20">Sept. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">First Presentation of Siege before the Americans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege Herald)</title>,
<date when="1924-09-20">Sept. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST PRESENTATION OF SIEGE BEFORE THE AMERICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Siege took part in the American manifestation on September 12. The Siege, in their uniforms, made such a splendid and impressive appearance that the parade committee had the Ukrainian local Siege march ahead of the entire American manifestation. We believe that this was one of the finest affairs that the Ukrainians had ever had in Chicago. There were over 1,000 Siege members who took part in it. The Ukrainian women wore their national costumes; a group of them wore Siege uniforms. With them were also four priests, numerous businessmen, and especially laborers. The full splendor of uniforms showed their meaning. Without them the Siege would have been practically lost in the massive manifestation of the Americans, and, as a matter of fact, no one would have noticed the Ukrainians. But as it was, the Ukrainian flags were carried at the head of the parade, together with American flags.</p>
   <p>In a few months there will be a new American holiday to which our Siege will again be invited. It is imperative that those who still do not <pb facs="5425703_0534.jpg" n="2"/>as yet have their own uniforms get them as soon as possible, so that a still greater number may be able to join the American parade, and together with the already uniformed members, jointly as a Ukrainian unit, again add to the splendor of the American parade. Write-ups, on such occasions, in American newspapers about us will do us more good than if we paid for it.</p>
   <p>We also wish to add that thirty-six miles out of Chicago, in Gary, Indiana, the local Siege branch No. 12, on this same day, September 12, took part in the American parade held there. The American press made good comments about them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
