<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Professionalists of America and Canada</title>.
      <date when="1933-08">August, 1933</date>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0675</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0675.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Professionalists of America and Canada</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Ukrainsky Profesionalisty v Ameritzi e v Kanadyi), (Winnepeg, Manitoba, Canada), PP. 49-52. By Stephen Sumeyko. (Address delivered at the First Congress of the Ukrainian Professionists--held in Chicago, August, 1933.</p>
   <p>JOURNALISM AS A PROFESSION FOR OUR YOUTH.</p>
   <p>Some day when a historian writes a history of American-Ukrainian life, he will undoubtedly designate the contemporary period as a period of transition. Today we are witnessing the gradual retirement and decline of the older generation of American--Ukrainians and the continually increasing influx in its stead of a new and fresh element--American--Ukrainian youth. Yet this displacement of one generation by another is not the most important manifestation of this transitory period. What is important is the beginning of a readjustment in the class status and class consciousness of the Ukrainians in America. From being a practically pure laboring class, the Ukrainian immigration in America, under the influence of favorable local conditions, is beginning to readjust itself to a more natural and balanced social order, based upon the proportionate presence of all classes which go into the make-up of a well balanced ethnic group: The laboring, the artisan, the business and, lastly, the cultural and professional classes.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0676.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have witnessed the coming of the Ukrainian artisan, the Ukrainian business man, and now we are witnessing the arrival of the Ukrainian professional man and woman. Every year brings and ever-increasing arrivals to this class. Every year we see more lawyers, doctors, engineers, dentists, teachers, accountants, musicians, and even a literary light or two appearing in our midst. Slowly but steadily we are assuming those positions which befit an inherently cultured and talented people such as ours.</p>
   <p>It is this gradually increasing entrance of our young men and women into the various professions that has led me to notice that there is one very important field which offers fine opportunities for our youth, and yet which for some reason or other seems to have been overlooked by them. The field or profession to which I refer is--journalism.</p>
   <p>What do I mean by journalism?</p>
   <p>Omitting a highly technical and exact definition, journalism is generally regarded as the profession or occupation of publishing, writing, or conducting a journal. "Whether journalism is a profession, or an art, a science, a trade, a craft, or even a game depends," to quote one authority, upon the equipment, the <pb facs="5425703_0677.jpg" n="3"/>point of view, the outlook and the motive of the individual engaged in it. To an editor or writer it is usually a profession, to a man in the advertising department it is a business, to a printer it is a trade. "What I have in mind is that which begins with reporting and end with editing, and which, in view of present-day stringent requirements of preparation and training, may be properly called a profession.</p>
   <p>Although this profession offers fire opportunities for the individual engaged in it, as well as to the cause to which that individual may subscribe, yet as a life calling it does not seem to attract our young people, even though some of them have considerable talent for it.</p>
   <p>Here in America, journalism has reached its highest peak of development. The printed word is now more powerful than ever before. The American newspaper besides being a mirror of world-wide life is also a powerful instrument in the shaping of public opinion. It offers to the young man who seriously enters it an education in many respects greater than any college can afford; it puts him in close contact with life; it makes him broadminded and arouses a high degree of intellectual activity.</p>
   <p>Aside from these general advantages, however, there are additional benefits which <pb facs="5425703_0678.jpg" n="4"/>will insure to those young American-Ukrainians who take up this profession as their life calling.</p>
   <p>Even the more pessimistic observers among us are beginning to see that the Ukrainian cause is assuming greater importance than ever before, despite all efforts of its enemies to the contrary. This growing importance of the Ukrainian cause has its repercussions here in America too, in the form of growing stability of American-Ukrainian life. Contributing to this stability is the realization by our people that their future welfare depends mostly upon these uniting their strength. Everywhere, therefore, efforts are being made to attain this unity. And with the elimination of certain evils from our life, these is very strong likelihood that Americans of Ukrainian descent will play a definite and important role in American life and at the same time be of considerable aid to their kinsmen in their native land Ukraine.</p>
   <p>Yet the entire matter depends upon the younger generation of American-Ukrainians. The older generation has built a foundation, and it is up to the younger generation to erect the rest of the structure. That is why the really decisively critical period in American-Ukrainian life, one that will determine its future existence, is yet to arrive during the span of American-Ukrainian Youth's existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0679.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Happily for all of us, as well as for the Ukrainian cause, the American-Ukrainian youth is showing greater interest in the Ukrainian cause as well as in its own common fate than was even expected. Being gradually welded together by common descent and interests, it is beginning to show signs of living up to the hopes of the older generation and performing greater deeds than the older generation in the field of good American citizenship and in the sphere of Ukrainian National aspirations.</p>
   <p>Yet in order that these hopes be realized here in America as well as in the old country, in order that the youth may play its part in the building of American-Ukrainian life, it is absolutely necessary that the growing interest of our youth in Ukrainian affairs be never permitted to die out. It must be fanned to white heat and everlastingly kept there.</p>
   <p>And what medium other than the press, in all its manifold forms, will best succeed in keeping this interest burning brightly, in keeping alive in the future generations of American-Ukrainians the realization that they are descendents of a great race, that it is their duty besides being good American citizens to strive for the complete independence of Ukraine, and that also it is their solemn obligation to continue the works, and tasks of their parents and build them to even greater heights. There is hardly a doubt, I am sure, that in a <pb facs="5425703_0680.jpg" n="6"/>country as large as America, where our people are scattered far and wide, the press is the best fitted to cope with such a tremendous task.</p>
   <p>It is my conviction that the Ukrainian newspaper in America has a fine future. The American-Ukrainian youth is far more accustomed to newspapers and more greatly dependent upon them than were our parents. In time, when this youth comes into its own, it will demand a press of its own, one that will reflect its life and help chart its course. Whether these newspapers will appear in the Ukrainian and English language is another matter and besides the point, for the same ideals can be expressed and disseminated in either language. It's the spirit that counts! The question arises, though, will there be sufficiently talented and trained American-Ukrainian journalists to rise to this demand, young men and women who have been born and raised here in America and yet who through diligent study are well acquainted with their Ukrainian background, with Ukrainian life, history, and culture?</p>
   <p>The answer to this most vital question can be determined now. Now is the time and opportunity for a number of talented young American-Ukrainians to prepare themselves for this calling--journalism in the field of American--Ukrainian life. Start now!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
