<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-03-15">Mar. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Minutes of Siege Organization Press Purchase in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Accompanied by Three Pictures, Namely: of Michael Yavorsky, John and Andrew Bulkas Translated]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-03-15">Mar. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MINUTES OF SIEGE ORGANIZATION PRESS PURCHASE IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Accompanied by Three Pictures, Namely: of Michael Yavorsky, John and Andrew Bulkas Translated]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In May, 1920, at the Siege Organization Convention, held in Pittsburg, Pa., when it was decided that the central headquarters of the organization be moved to Chicago, the executive committee consisted, as it does yet, of the citizens of Chicago of Ukrainian descent. This new executive committee made a firm decision to buy and own a Siege press. And there a chance presented itself to realize the decision. The Ukrainian Publishing Company was bought by Messrs. Andrew and John Bulkas, and Michael Yavorsky.</p>
   <p>Therefore, on February 26, 1922, the executive committee of the Siege organization passed a resolution to buy the whole press outfit for the fixed sum of $2,300. For this reason they sent out one of the officers Peter Didyk, to other Siege branches and districts, to appeal to the members to contribute to the press fund and thereby help realize the purchase of a so much needed press for Siege organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Due to much unemployment that year, the purchase of the press was almost out of question, because from March, 1921, to the date of purchase only four hundred dollars was in the bank for that purpose.</p>
   <p>Until after New Year's 1922, after a reorganization of the executive staff in the headquarters, the resolution of buying a Siege press was renewed with more action behind it.</p>
   <p>They got in touch with the three owners of the press.</p>
   <p>The gentleman that busied himself most on this account was Dr. Stephen K. Hrynevetsky, through his organization assistant, L. Stachursky. The former, as chief executive of the organization and a sincere Siege member, who has the good of the organization at heart, proved to the owners of the press how much good they would do for Ukrainians in general and particularly the organization, if they the three owners, would only let the press go for a somewhat lower price.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0266.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Executive Staff invited the owners of the press to the meeting on January 22, 1922. It was then that Mr. Michael Yavorsky gave up his share, amounting to seven hundred dollars, in favor of the organization, and the brothers Andrew and John Bulka let eight hundred dollars off their two shares, and so on January 12, 1922, the printing machinery of the Ukrainian Publishing Co. became the property of the Siege Organization as per the agreement and contract, which is now in possession of the general financial secretary.</p>
   <p>When the time for the first payment came, on January 26, at the presentation of a note for the last four hundred dollars for the machinery. Messrs. Bulkas donated that amount to the organization and signed an acknowledgment "Paid in full." Thus all the press machinery was bought for only $400 instead of $2,300 as was originally, anticipated in 1921.</p>
   <p>No lesser recognition should go to Mr. K. Kopchynsky, linotype operator for the former Ukraina Publishing Company. He, with his cooperation, <pb facs="5425703_0267.jpg" n="4"/>helped the former three owners hold the ownership of the press machinery, and thus prevented it from going into undesirable hands. He also did everything in his power because he wanted to see it become the property of the Siege organization. Many thanks to him for this noble work.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Michael Yavorsky, John and Andrew Bulkas are members of Bohdan Chmelnitsky Siege, branch No. 15, in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Michael Yavorsky, is a Ukrainian building contractor, who not only financially, but also with activity, is helping the Ukrainian people get started.</p>
   <p>The Bulka Brothers are also sincere Ukrainian patriots, our countrymen, and businessmen, and they fully deserve our wholehearted support.</p>
   <p>Thanks, many thanks, to our benefactors: Michael Yavorsky, and John and Andrew Bulkas for their great benevolent acts. Their names will shine in the history of the Siege organization and in the history of the struggle for the independence of Ukrainia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
