<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1932-03-15">Mar. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Young Sitch Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1932-03-15">Mar. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG SITCH ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have taken pride, in the past, in boasting of the fighting deeds of our Cossacks and of other great men who have fought for their ideals, but why should we be content just to extol those who fought in the past? Why not turn a leaf of our own, and show the world that this present, young generation of Ukrainians is as capable, if not more so, of performing similar deeds or (if we may be so bold as to say) even greater ones than those of our forefathers?</p>
   <p>In order to show the world what we are and what we can do, we must have a proper place in which to demonstrate our ever-present desire and ability to do things. We must have a home of our own. All Sitch companies and Ukrainian church organizations of Chicago have pledged themselves to support any movement to build schools and athletic homes for the young Ukrainian generation in Chicago and vicinity. The members of these organizations should be <pb facs="5425703_0328.jpg" n="2"/>highly commended for the extreme interest they have taken, and we, the young generation, should forever feel deeply indebted to them.</p>
   <p>What have we to show that we are worthy of such loyal support, and how can we express our gratitude and appreciation? The least that we can do is to show our interest by pushing, pulling, dragging, and striving by every means humanly possible to support the worthy movement.</p>
   <p>Sitch Company I is very much interested in the construction of a building on the Saint Nicholas church grounds in Chicago, where space could be provided for both a school and a gymnasium. Toward this end Sitch Company I together with Central Headquarters is sponsoring an amateur championship boxing contest, the proceeds of which will be used to help furnish athletic equipment for our new gymnasium, and, at the same time the Ukrainian champions of the various boxing classes will be determined. The final winners of these contests <pb facs="5425703_0329.jpg" n="3"/>will be awarded beautiful prizes by the Reverend Father F. Tarnawsky, including a trip to Cleveland or Detroit, where the Ukrainian boxing championships of the United States of America will be decided. This boxing contest is open to all Ukrainian boys up to twenty-eight years of age, regardless of where they may reside, their standing, or whatever organization they represent. The only requisite is that they be of Ukrainian birth or descent.</p>
   <p>Let's go, you young Ukrainians, and show our fathers and mothers that we are capable of doing things. Enroll in this contest and show your ability!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
