<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
<date when="1936-10">Oct. 1936</date><title level="a">"Listopadove Sviato."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
<date when="1936-10">Oct. 1936</date><title level="a">"LISTOPADOVE SVIATO."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Eighteen years ago, on the first of November, the Ukrainian Army with the help of the Ukrainian Youth captured Lwiw, capital of western Ukraine. For the first time in six centuries the yellow and blue banner of Ukraine flew from the high tower of the city hall and proclaimed to the world the rebirth of a nation--the existence of the western Ukrainian Republic.</p>
   <p>But Polish greed for Ukrainian lands again began to show itself. Nine months of heroic fighting against Poland ensued, but the Ukrainian forces were compelled to evacuate Western Ukraine. Lack of ammunition and military equipment made impossible the continuance of their desperate struggle against a foe daily strengthened by fresh supplies of ammunition, tanks, and cannon from France; even French Officers were giving aid to Poland. Before long, Ukraine again fell under the control of her enemies.</p>
   <p>In commeration of the proclamation of independence on November 1st, and of the subsequent heroic stand of the Ukrainian soldiers, the Ukrainians throughout the world established the traditional November Holiday--Listopadove Svato.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0520.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Once a year, on or about the first of November, we pay homage to the heroes of those eventful days with church services, programs, and concerts.</p>
   <p>This manifestation of Ukrainian Independence Day has taken a strong hold on the Ukrainian-American Youth. Previously, it had been the custom for each church or association to celebrate the November Holiday independently of each other, any time during November. The gestures are meritorious; we should honor those who gave everything for their nation, but the thought is to honor them in a manner that would render greater satisfaction to the Ukrainian nation as a whole...in a manner that our heroes would wish us to do could they but rise to tell us so...and that is all together.</p>
   <p>The Ukrainian Youth believes that this historical event should be celebrated in unity--one great manifestation combining all groups. Certainly this great event is cause enough to bring together all those of us who wish to honor those who gave their lives for their nation.</p>
   <p>The November Holiday is common meeting ground for all Ukrainian people who believe in the coming of permanent independence for Ukraine. Let us ennoble with love and <pb facs="5425703_0521.jpg" n="3"/>unity the tradition that is behind the celebration of November Holiday.</p>
   <p>In Europe, in spite of tyranny and oppression, the Ukrainian people flock together to honor their national heroes. Must we in America segregate ourselves into small groups at such times? Must we have oppression to teach us unity; the older generation wants it likewise. The thing is to get together.</p>
   <p>May we once more repeat; Didn't the heroes of 1918 fight for all Ukrainians?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
