<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1925-09-01">Sept. 1, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1925-09-01">Sept. 1, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Go to school, to the higher schools, for there is nothing better than school. When on the threshold of this school say firmly to yourself: "I must finish this school, no matter how difficult it may be!" Decide on it in that way, and see it through. There is nothing worse than a school career not completed. People say justly, "A student who did not complete his studies is worse than a blockhead." It is better to go to school and complete it than to shorten your life in some factory or in washing some Chinaman's dishes. Every worker is important, but the insulting blockhead always creates rottenness, and is an abomination. They regret that they have squandered their young lives; that is why they are always insulting and throw mud on everything. Therefore, if you begin school, complete it! Do not begin that school with the idea that you want to become a master because a person who does so never learns anything. Go to school with the idea of acquiring higher knowledge, not only for yourself but also for those who stay in the factories at hard work. They <pb facs="5425703_0039.jpg" n="2"/>will provide everything needed in life, and you should prepare yourself to repay that debt by telling them the truth and caring for them. While you are attending school do not lose your faith--the faith of your mother and father--for when you lose that, even though you have completed your studies, you will not bring anyone any good because internally you will be burnt to ashes and your mind will be vacuous! Without the faith which your people have, you will be a wicked noisemaker and a ruined and poisoned fruit in a white collar, and with an overturned head. In this head will only be madness and contempt for the aching hand of the workingman who is providing your bread and butter. This is the greatest experience of true education, and whoever tells you otherwise is a blockhead, no matter how well he tries to fool you by showing you educational books.</p>
   <p>The beautiful and sweet fruit of knowledge teaches us to acknowledge laws, humane work and, above all, faith in the Supreme Power on which everything rests. Go to school, higher school. Begin it, stay in it and complete it with a firm determination that you will serve your people with <pb facs="5425703_0040.jpg" n="3"/>truth and not domineer over them. Then you will not be a stupid and wicked destroyer, but a real leader. Go, and do not forget this, for every word written here is the truth. Some day you will be convinced of the truth of this study.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
