<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
<date when="1934-07-08">July 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Cossack Chorus Makes a Big Hit at First Anniversary</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth's</title>,
<date when="1934-07-08">July 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">COSSACK CHORUS MAKES A BIG HIT AT FIRST ANNIVERSARY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the Ukrainian Cossack Chorus of Chicago celebrated their first anniversary. The chorus for the first time sang at High Mass at St. Nicholas church, and after this went to the picnic, run for this occasion, where a wonderful time was had by all. June 28, 1934 was the first birthday of the Chorus, for it was exactly a year that Mr. Sam Czuba with about fifteen (15) boys held their first rehearsal. After seven weeks of practice the chorus won second place in the Chicagoland Music Festival Contest. Three and one-half months after the contest the chorus made a trip to Detroit and ran two concerts and sang a radio program. On May 19, 1934 the chorus sang at one of the biggest concerts ever held in Chicago, that of the Ukrainian Soyuz of America, at which Mayor Kelly was present. In all the chorus made seventeen(17) appearances in Chicago and three in Detroit, which is quite a record for any one year "old" chorus to beat. The boys have made a hit with the public, but it was not done without effort and self-sacrifice. They have succeeded, but only by diligent work which climaxed by learning the whole mass during the period of two weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
