<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1924-03-10">March 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Ukrainian Opera in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1924-03-10">March 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">UKRAINIAN OPERA IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ukrainian life in Chicago becomes and more interesting. The great wrestler from Ukrainia Alexander Harkavenko has attracted the attention of other nationalities to himself as well as to Ukrainians in general.</p>
   <p>Now the Ukrainian opera, under the direction of Mr. Karalash, from Cherson, Ukrainia, ex-member of the Russian operas as well as a member of the Grand Opera in Chicago, enjoys great popularity.</p>
   <p>Sunday, February 24, a Ukrainian opera organized by him, made its first appearance on the stage and presented "The Cossack Beyond the Danube." The outcome was just wonderful in almost every way.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Cymbalist unquestionably deserves the first laurel of distinction in her part as "Daria." She surely can act and sing impressively on any stage of any city in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0183.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Svitlow, in the role of "Andrew," represented a real cossack-Zaporozets, both in acting and singing.</p>
   <p>His sweetheart in the role of "Oksana," played astonishingly well. Her melodious accentuation and enunciation of the Ukrainian language is unsurpassable.</p>
   <p>The roles of the "Sultan," and Imam," were very well-played by one and the same person.</p>
   <p>The role of the "Chinaman," bodyguard of the sultan, played by Dmitro Atamanec could not have been rendered any better.</p>
   <p>The most difficult part, that of "Ivan" was played by the organizer of this group, Mr. Nicholas Karalash. He did not portray this character as just a mere drunkard, but seemingly dizzy with drinks, yet shrewd and diplomatic to infinity with a refined soul and a cossack's daring courage.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0184.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Odarka" came out wonderfully well in every respect. All the nuances of the sulky and occasionally enraged woman, who had been disappointed in love were expressed very well both in her singing and acting, considering the fact that she is just an amateur. Just think what a grand star she would make, if she could give all of her time and attention to this artistic profession. In this role, she had one great disadvantage, her partner was suffering from a severe case of the grip. He could hardly sing at all, and most of his part he skilfully recited; yet she knew how to cover it up so deftly that it would have taken a real artist, who knows opera quite well, to notice the shortcomings of this opera. So much for the actors.</p>
   <p>The most obvious shortcoming was the fact that the orchestra and the singers had not had enough practice together in rehearsals. Regardless of how good the orchestra may be, or how excellently the players may perform, a joint practice in rehearsal in indispensable; here was the real difficulty. Even though the chorus could have been compared to a human pipe organ, and the orchestra was well selected for the occasion, they could have performed together much better if they had <pb facs="5425703_0185.jpg" n="4"/>both sacrificed more time for joint rehearsals. Fortunately, they came out quite well, but on the other hand it tells us that although we have such a capable company both of musicians and performers, there was room for improvement from the general point of view. Well, as long as there is worth-while material, and they are conscious of their shortcomings, then all that is needed is more general practice with the orchestra.</p>
   <p>Our public, above all the Siege members, I am sure will excuse them this time, and will help to support this great cultural activity of theirs in the future. We firmly hope that Mr. Karalash, together with all the Chicago Ukrainian intelligentsia, will work for the complete success of the opera in the very near future.</p>
   <p>S. H.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
