<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
Monthly Vol I, <date when="1934-05">May 1934</date>, No 1
<title level="a">At Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
Monthly Vol I, <date when="1934-05">May 1934</date>, No 1
<title level="a">AT WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago, youth is simply bubbling with effervescent energy and zest. The Ukrainian American Catholic Youth, better known as Young Ukrainia, is constantly working. In March a Ukrainian drama of five acts was enacted and sponsored solely by this organization and it was successfully done. On April 1st a concert in honor of the celebrated poet, Taras Shevchenko, was conducted by it. The organization meets every Friday for general meeting where business is performed, discussions heard and talks given by members, guests and the reverend missionaries. The group always gains unusual information and rare amusement from the lectures of Reverend missionary Markiw. The Culture Club, a division of this organization, meets after the general meeting to discuss topics of immediate interest, as poetry, education, music, heredity and behavior, or to have a debate. There are also music groups; a separate boys' chorus and girls' chorus. Both are under the direction of two organization members. The boys have been and are active in the sports division, and especially in baseball games. Socialsare held once a month in the form of short plays, concert numbers or movies. Also a sewing club for girls; another division meets weekly in order to learn the art of Ukrainian embroidery. Of this organization Walter Skoropad is the presiding officer and John Hull is the secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are a few promising future editors and reporters in Chicago - really six young boys - who by their own efforts are striving and succeeding to make their newspaper, Young Ukraina a success. They issue this paper weekly and thus far their abilities seem unlimited, for they are soaring to great heights in the publication of their news and opinions. The editor of this paper is Michael Kaninga who is to be lauded for his initiative and sincere work.</p>
   <p>A new Siege company has been formed this winter, composed of young men. They drill each week, receive excellent lectures from experienced men and participate cooperatively in every function requiring their services. John Hull is the stalwart captain of this Siege Company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
