<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1933-07-22">July 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Our Ukrainian Youth</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Under this heading we print some facts about]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1933-07-22">July 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">OUR UKRAINIAN YOUTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Under this heading we print some facts about]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Young Americans of Ukrainian descent, leaders in arts, sciences, and the social life of the younger generation, and future workers in the field of Ukrainian life who have shown their interest in the great country of their ancestors and their love for it, and who, as we hope, will render great and worthy service to the Ukrainian cause in the future.</p>
   <p>Wanda Ercha, born in Herkimer, New York, September 23, 1916, the daughter of Peter and Ann Ercha, came to Chicago in 1928. She was formerly a student of violin at the Bush Conservatory of Music in Chicago. She studied under Bruno Esbjorn [Dane] until 1930 and is now developing her musical talent under the guidance of Professor Richard Cherwonky, who has been her instructor since 1931. Professor Cherwonky is a well-known German violin soloist and <pb facs="5425703_0220.jpg" n="2"/>composer, a professor at the Lake View High School. He is recognized as the highest on the violin staff and was formerly conductor of the Boston, Minneapolis, and other symphony orchestras.</p>
   <p>Miss Ercha plays in the Lake View High School Orchestra and is a member of the All-Chicago High School Orchestra and of the Chicago Conservatory Symphony Orchestra. Excellent recitals have been given by her at the Bush Conservatory and at the Lake View High School, and in 1932 she made her first appearance among the Ukrainians. Since then Miss Ercha has been a regular performer on our stage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
