<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. I, No. 5, <date when="1930-07-11">July 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Toward Which Goal Can One Strive by Strenuous Work and Endurance?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>Ukrainian</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. I, No. 5, <date when="1930-07-11">July 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">TOWARD WHICH GOAL CAN ONE STRIVE BY STRENUOUS WORK AND ENDURANCE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Barabash, son of parents of the peasant class at Zarudia, county of Zboriv (Galicia), has attained by strenuous work and endurance a splendid position in a musical and artistic world among the Americans.</p>
   <p>The praiseworthy and remarkable quality of his character is that he always and everywhere in an artistic and musical world admits that he is an Ukrainian. He finished public school at Zarudia, county of Zboriv, and in his boyhood went to Germany for work. Over there in Germany he saved a little money and left for the United States of America in 1912. Here in this country he got a job in a furniture shop for $5 a week. In 1913 he received a job in a bakery shop, and in the evenings took instruction and lessons in music from the director of the Ukrainian band existing at that time in Chicago. In 1914 he began to learn the goldsmith's business and worked in that business till 1917, receiving wages of $12 per week.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While working at a goldsmith's shop he continued his studies in music, taking private lessons in music for two years from the German professor, Mr. Karl Brown. In 1917 in April, he enlisted voluntarily in the military band of the 131st Infantry Regiment. From the regiment to which he was enlisted he was sent out by regiment command to the military musical school, where he studied music for two years and took the examinations for band instructor and in a short time after he was promoted to the rank of sergeant and in 1918 he became concert master. In the same year ye returned to Chicago and received a scholarship.</p>
   <p>In order to get a diploma from the Musical College, the same student must have at first the diploma from high school. Therefore, John Barabash not being in possession of such a diploma from high school, started to complete a high school course and to get a required diploma. He was working for his living with a theatrical orchestra in the evenings, and at nights and by day for four and a half years he was attending the YMCA school. In 1920 he enrolled at Harrison High School, and after four years of hard studies he finished high school and musical college.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0175.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Being a student in high school and musical college, he gave instruction and lessons to the Ukrainian band and some Ukrainian students. He already, as a student at high school, was conducting the high school band and was arranging the school musical performances.</p>
   <p>After receiving a diploma from high school and musical college he became a musical teacher at the same school and in this position he remains till this day. At the end of 1924 he accomplished an examination for the director of military music, being promoted to the rank of captaincy of the 131st Infantry Regiment of the United States Army of America.</p>
   <p>Captain John Barabash is studying now a course of music at the Northwestern University, preparing himself for the highest examination of the department of music, namely, the decree of Master of Music. In 1924 he was appointed a teacher to the Ukrainian parochial band at St. Nicholas Church in Chicago, in 1926 he participated with a young Ukrainian band in the contest of the public school bands in Chicago <pb facs="5425703_0176.jpg" n="4"/>The Harrison High School band participating in that contest won the first prize, under the direction of Captain John Barabash, and in April of this year (1930) the Chicago Daily News invited Captain John Barabash with his Harrison High School band to the public music festival to take the part in a contest of all the high schools of Chicago. At that contest was present Captain Edmund Goldman, who was concert master of all the high school bands and of the band of Captain John Barabash.</p>
   <p>After the concert was at an end Captain Edmund Goldman expressed the hearty acknowledgement and congratulations before competent authority and before the whole auditorium upon the splendid success of his Harrison High School band and at the same time highly praised the ability and expertness of Captain John Barabash, and the administration of the Chicago Daily News, as a sponsor of that festival, rewarded Captain John Barabash, giving him the brass plate for successfully winning first prize.</p>
   <p>The alderman from the ward where the Harrison School is located, <pb facs="5425703_0177.jpg" n="5"/>presented to captain John Barabash a gold pin with a diamond in recognition of his splendid work. To such an achievement and career came Captain John Barabash, poor peasant boy, emigrant, by his strenuous work, without any one's protection and help, by his persistent endurance in order to attain to success and esteem.</p>
   <p>Captain Barabash serves as an excellent and vivid example, worthy to be imitated by all the young Ukrainians; for the Ukrainian nation Captain J. Barabash is achieving fame and honor in the music world.</p>
   <p>Captain John Barabash is well known to the whole colony of Ukrainians in Chicago, participating in all social, cultural and political activities. The Ukrainian colony needs more such men as Captain John Barabash.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
