<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1919-06">June 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Word from the Ukrainian Women's Alliance of America to All the Ukrainians in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1919-06">June 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WORD FROM THE UKRAINIAN WOMEN'S ALLIANCE OF AMERICA TO ALL THE UKRAINIANS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite all the hindrances on the part of our community, and also on the part of our unexperienced groups of women, the Ukrainian Women's Alliance lives and is spreading. This spreading, however, is not done as fast as we would like to see it, still, slowly but surely, it gathers strength day by day. We are not rich in number, but in work. We ask not to be judged by the number but by the work and its quality.</p>
   <p>The organized women of our society are only the enlightened ones who carry about the ideal work for the people.</p>
   <p>The organizing of women in our community is something new and unseen. Our people indeed cannot fully appreciate this innovation. New for us! Other people long ago adopted women as their models in the national work. We are only weighing, thinking over, whether it is <pb facs="5425703_0146.jpg" n="2"/>needed or not? So also our women are undecided. Our intelligentsia is keeping aloof from us. What should we expect from the lower strata of the community? Despite all these obstacles, we are going forward.</p>
   <p>He who observes our women more closely will at once notice their bigheartedness, sadly neglected self-confidence.</p>
   <p>Our women are hardly prepared for this big moment that dawns over our native land, not only to great, but also to work together for the liberty of the Ukrainian republic and for the free nation. The women of other nations are not only preparing themselves for this new life, but are already working in that direction. The Polish women of America gathered great quantities of goods, like clothing, various living articles to the sum of five million dollars, sent them to Europe to help the Polish population.</p>
   <p>Among the Jewish, Czech, Slovak, Jugo-slavs, etc., women, who work is seething for their countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0147.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our nation and our women, because of the neglect and indifference of our leaders, remained lagging in their work, at this most important time! What good did we, the Ukrainian women of America, do, what did we acquire, what did we prepare for war-ruined territories? We do not even think of what we should do and how we should do it. We are not sufficiently organized and are inexperienced! We even cannot find mutual understanding among ourselves, because we are scattered and divided.</p>
   <p>Dear sisters! How long shall we remain in this condition? Should we further sit with folded arms and look at the other nations of Europe? Let us not disgrace our nation before the whole world. Shake off the sleepiness, inexperience, and neglect! Let us unite ourselves, put ourselves to work for the service of our free, liberated nation.</p>
   <p>Let the Ukrainian Women's Alliance add the greatest number of members possible, let each and everyone roll up her sleeves and put her hands <pb facs="5425703_0148.jpg" n="4"/>to the great national work. The five hundred who are being organized is a small number from out of the thousands of our women in America. To organize such a number should not take years, in fact, not more than a week.</p>
   <p>A little more self-sacrifice, on the part of our women, our Women's Alliance will rapidly spread and cone to prominence, by doing the work commissioned to them.</p>
   <p>Let us not dissipate! To work, to action! The free Ukrainia demands of us that we Ukrainian women of America undertake with all our power the true, honorable and useful work assigned to us for the good of the free independent state of ours - Ukrainia!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
