<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovy Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1923-06-01">June 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Latest Affair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovy Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1923-06-01">June 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE LATEST AFFAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 9, for the first time in the world's musical history, and moreover in the history of Ukrainians, there will occur a most important and pleasant incident for us Ukrainians. On that date, the world's largest Ukrainian band, The Ukrainian Sitch Musical Society, will give its first concert on the radio, under the baton of John Barabash and sponsored by M. Zalizniak of Company 12 of Chicago. To enrich the program, there will be a violin solo by Miss Anna Motluk, an eleven-year-old artist and student of John Kobeliak, and a xylophone solo by Mr. F. Zelina. This concert will be an important one because, also our Ukrainian soprano, Mrs. Stephanie Tsymbalist, will sing some solos. She is known from her appearances in Detroit, Michigan, but is not known here. Thus, Americans and others will have an opportunity to hear our Ukrainian nightingale.</p>
   <p>This concert is not going to be an ordinary one; it will be a concert in which thousands, and even millions, of Americans and others will listen to the <pb facs="5425703_0305.jpg" n="2"/>melodies of our native songs, both instrumental and vocal. People especially interested in music will listen to it. That is why we appeal to all Ukrainians, not only of Chicago and its suburbs, but also of all parts of the United States and Canada, to take an interest in this concert and to inform others about it. We especially appeal to those who have radios in their homes not to forget that on Saturday, June 9, 1923, between the hours of 10 and 11 P. M., they will be able to hear the first Ukrainian concert of the famous Sitch band and the soprano soloist, Mrs. Stephanie Tsymbalist, over the Drake Hotel radio station, W P A P.</p>
   <p>The concert program is as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Overture, "Superb"... arr. by Dolby</p>
   <p>2. March, "National Emblem"</p>
   <p>The Band</p>
   <p>3. Violin solo, "Souvenir"</p>
   <p>"The Swan"</p>
   <p>Miss Motluk</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0306.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. Ukrainian Medley in honor of Alexander Koshetz....arr. by Barabash Mrs. Tsymbalist and the Band</p>
   <p>5. Solo, "Ah! Where Is That Flower?".....Nuzamovsky Mrs. Tsymbalist</p>
   <p>6. Xylophone, "Ukrainian Pearls"....arr. by Barabash Mr. Zelina</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note: This article translated because follow-up article did not appear. The issue of Sichovy Visty, July 2, 1923, is missing from the files, and may have carried the follow-up article.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
