<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
<date when="1919-06">June, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Editor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
<date when="1919-06">June, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE EDITOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The women organized into the Ukrainian Women's Alliance of America decided to issue their own monthly newspaper. The first two sample issues of the Ranna Zorya are known very well to everyone.</p>
   <p>This time we decided to issue our Zorya in a smaller size, but on account of this it will be issued monthly instead. If the circumstances permit us, we shall strive to enlarge the news section. We appeal now to all the Ukrainians to support our cause, and help us both morally and materially in this work of ours. Especially our Ukrainian women should spread our newspaper among the people of good will. We also ask them to write anything that is interesting about the work of our women in America, or anything that can be beneficial to the community.</p>
   <p>Our program remains the same as had been outlined in the past issues of the Ranna Zorya.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0272.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Wake up, women, to independent living and thinking.</p>
   <p>Wake up your self-consciousness.</p>
   <p>Let us educate our daughters and women and teach them everything that is good.</p>
   <p>Let us unite them into one strong group.</p>
   <p>Let us encourge them to national work.</p>
   <p>Let us show them the path to this work.</p>
   <p>Let us give them a sensible and sound criticism of our lives.</p>
   <p>Let us prove to them our far-reaching purpose.</p>
   <p>We anticipate that there will not be found among our loyal Ukrainians a single person opposed to this program.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0273.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So with faith in a better good will cooperation, and with hope for the progress of our work, the Ukrainian women will stand inferior to none in the ranks of other national workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
