<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title><date when="1936-03">Feb.-March, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Club's Activities</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth Magazine. (Official Organ of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League, Philadelphia, Pa.)</title><date when="1936-03">Feb.-March, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CLUB'S ACTIVITIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yearly elections have been a source of lively and competitive interest among youth organizations in Chicago. In early December the Ukrainian Red Cross Club called together all their members, re-elected their President, Kathryn Zuoinsky, and chose Jean Chuba to be their Vice-President; Jennie Lewtuch, Corresponding Secretary; Nettie Timetz, Financial Secretary, and Sophie Sweda, Treasurer.</p>
   <p>On January 10, 1936, another club held their annual elections--Moloda Ukraina. Unanimously, the members decided that their President, Walter Skorapad, be re-elected for another year of service. Then after well-mannered competition the following individuals succeeded to honorable positions: Katherine Panko, Vice-President; Ellen Hope Spikula, Secretary; Nicholas Lucia, Treasurer; Millie Kozak, Librarian; Genevieve Kocur was appointed by the newly-elected librarian to be assistant librarian; Peter Sweda, Substitute; Emily Oscil, Mike Kozak and George Onischuck, Auditors.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon of Sunday, January 12, 1936, still another club, Good-Will Society, conducted its annual elections. The President, Marie Lubas, and the Financial Secretary, Walter Skoropad, were unanimously re-elected. The newly-elected officers are: Mayme Gawaluch, Vice-President; Mildred Kozak, Recording Secretary, and Michael Kozak, Treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0649.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Elections have not been the only interest of the youth clubs. In the afternoon of December 2, 1935, the Aviation School, which is sponsored by the Hetman Organization, sponsored a successful concert in Chopin High School Auditorium.</p>
   <p>Among the features of the program were two outstanding attractions--the note-worthy young Ukrainian violinist, whose artisically rendered performances have delighted discriminating audiences, Mr. Emil Tiahnybik, and the prize-winning Ukrainian Cossack Chorus, directed by Samuel Czuba.</p>
   <p>In February 6, 1936, the Red Cross Club sponsored a dance. On February 13, the Good-Will Society conducted a Valentine Dance. On Valentine evening, Moloda Ukraina enjoyed a social, during which business was a forgotten procedure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
