<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1922-11">Nov. 1922</date>.
<title level="a">To All Ukrainian People in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1922-11">Nov. 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL UKRAINIAN PEOPLE IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Although this convention took place in Philadelphia, a number of prominent Chicago Ukrainians took an active part in it; because it is an appeal to all Ukrainians in the United States, it naturally includes Chicago. Transl.]</p>
   <p>People, at this time every living Ukrainian heart is boiling with hatred and is crying for vengeance against aggressive Poland who, like the locusts, occupied Galician-Ukraine, and with sword and fire, jails and gibbets, introduces its barbarian orders.</p>
   <p>At this time patience is exhausted; the cup of suffering and martyrdom is overflowing and all the Galician-Ukrainians rebel, and with a vengeance against the Polish occupier express their desire to be free and independent.</p>
   <p>At this time an incomparable fight of our brothers and sisters in the native <pb facs="5425703_0565.jpg" n="2"/>land is going on, a fight for freedom for Galician-Ukraine from the centuries long occupation by the Polish barbarians. You sent your Ukrainian delegates from all over the United States to the Ukrainian Convention held in Philadelphia, October 26 and 27.</p>
   <p>During these two days they spoke with determination and ardor. They all discussed business of the most grave nature; national affairs of such character that would bring the most good to all Ukrainian-American citizens as well as to those abroad. The delegates to this Ukrainian Convention gave most of their time to discussions on how to deviate the bitter fate of their Ukrainian brothers in Europe.</p>
   <p>In order to give at once a helping hand to those in extreme need, and at the same time to let the world know how dreadfully the Ukrainian nation in Galicia suffers under the Polish yoke; to assure our heroic brothers in our native country, of steady help while they are fighting in Ukrainian Galicia <pb facs="5425703_0566.jpg" n="3"/>for freedom and independence of that part of the country, the Convention unaminously decided to make a general appeal to all Ukrainian-Americans to introduce a voluntary Ukrainian national tax, whereby the fighting for freedom of Ukraine could be helped.</p>
   <p>Brothers and sisters, our native country, sprinkled with the blood of her best children, looks at us full of faith, trusting in your help. The Ukrainian Government which, amid the hardest conditions known, was holding the banner of national liberty high, is waiting for moral and material support from us. Give as long as and until its highest ideal is realized, until the Ukrainian Republic becomes free and independent.</p>
   <p>All our ideals, all our tendencies let us turn toward our native country. In order to help Ukraine let us contribute all that we can to the Fund of Immediate Help; let us join together in the voluntary national tax.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0567.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Ukrainian people, these your elected delegates, came to this decision, that it is necessary to solidly organize the Ukrainians in America; to enlighten the unenlightened; to uplift the downfallen; to unite the scattered. Through enlightenment of the political and economic organization we shall become so strong that we shall be able to give the greatest possible help to our brothers fighting in our native country.</p>
   <p>As a foundation of a systematic work there must be above all unity, harmony, and sacrifice. Only with diligent guarding of the national funds, and honest and economical management of them shall we win the confidence of the masses. Please, let us note this well: without public confidence, no work for the good of the whole could be effective.</p>
   <p>To amend the past misunderstanding, the Convention has decided to check up on the financial standing of all the political organizations now in existence that collected and managed public money. Only the past experience of <pb facs="5425703_0568.jpg" n="5"/>unclean and sad cases, and a thorough analysis of them will lead us to something better, especially to be more careful in spending public money. In short, we can profit by the mistakes of those who did not know much about financial matters.</p>
   <p>In order to assist our starving brothers and sisters in Great Ukraine the Convention has thought of a series of ways to do so.</p>
   <p>To prevent a complete annihilation of learning, and to counteract the darkness in this respect in the old country, the Convention decided to arrange in their respective localities, from time to time, a collection for the vernacular schools in Galicia.</p>
   <p>To reform our present school and enlightenment organizations in America, the Convention delegates recommended the Ukrainian National University in America to call a special educational convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0569.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Convention passed a great many important resolutions for the good of the Ukrainian people.</p>
   <p>In order to bring all these resolutions into actuality, the Convention appointed a special committee from the representatives of the outstanding Ukrainian organizations.</p>
   <p>The consolidation of the Ukrainian organizations in America comes upon the national horizon at this grave and critical moment. This is the opportune time for a national uprising. It calls us to active work for the great Ukrainian nation. Again consolidation appears to be the only source from which the most effective medicine, material help, will ensue. This, in turn, will help to bring about the realization of the great ideals, our lawful tendencies, after which the sunrise of freedom and independence of the Galician-Ukrainian Republic will follow. Consolidation of the Ukrainian organizations in America is an anvil upon which a steel hammer breaks the fetters of the Polish barbarian dungeons.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0570.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Starting this work with self-sacrifice, the chief executive of the consolidated organization, appeals to the Ukrainian colonies of the central and local organizations, societies, sodalities, and to all Ukrainians of both sexes, individually:</p>
   <p>"Brothers and sisters, an important duty was imposed upon your shoulders. Loyal to the national ideal, we want to have that duty done for the good of the whole Ukrainian nation. However, we cannot accomplish anything without your solid and zealous cooperation. United we stand and from this starts our co-operation, and in this lies our guarantee, here in America, that our stupendous aim and plan will be realized.</p>
   <p>From the consolidated work of all the Ukrainians in America lies our co-operation with, and the future of, the Ukrainian emigration all over the world." Philadelphia, November, 1922.</p>
   <p>For Consolidated Ukrainian Organization in America: Rev. Leo Levitsky, <pb facs="5425703_0571.jpg" n="8"/>president; Dr. S. K. Hrynevetsky, and M. Kotsiuk, of Chicago, assistants to the president; Dr. B. Siminovich, S. H. Skehar, W. Shabatura, of Chicago, directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
