<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1922-10">Oct., 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Minutes of the Siege Executive Staff in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Summary]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-10">Oct., 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MINUTES OF THE SIEGE EXECUTIVE STAFF IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Summary]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On September 6, the Executive Staff decided that the recording secretary should write to all district majors, who should see to it that the members of the companies in their respective districts be prompt in paying their dues, according to the decision of the last Siege Convention held in Cleveland.</p>
   <p>The money for the so-called Known Fund is to be sent directly to Dr. S. K. Hrynevetsky, chief executive, and the executive office will then be responsible for it and will sent it to the designated place, thereby having direct control over it.</p>
   <p>On September 27, a letter from Dr. Dnistryansky was read. This led them to refer the matter of helping Ukrainian students abroad, to Siege Company No. 1, <pb facs="5425703_0406.jpg" n="2"/>in Chicago.</p>
   <p>M. Kotsiuk was notified that if District No. 1 does not pay P. Nayda his travelling expenses, while he is transacting business of the organization with Company No. 5 at Wilmington, N J., the executive office in Chicago will pay him from the general fund.</p>
   <p>Chief executive Dr. Hrynevetsky has decided to attend the next Siege Convention to be held in 1924 in Philadelphia. Naturally his travelling expenses are to be paid from the general account of the organization.</p>
   <p>On October 4, the recording secretary wrote to the bookstore Umna in Vienna, and ordered, according to the smallest sample sent in, a sufficient number of badges for all the Ukrainian-American Siege members.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0407.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>O. Reviewk sent in propositions of the Obyednanya Insurance Association to which the entire executive staff agreed. They appointed M. Kotsiuk, to be present, if possible, at Obyednanyas next meeting to be held on Oct. 13, in Jersey City.</p>
   <p>With reference to the suggestion of Dr. Luke Mishuga to bring over two people from Czechoslovakia, the executive office decided to inquire of every district major as to their opinion on it before the Central Headquarters would finally decide.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
