<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1922-05-17">May 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Letter of Thanks and Further Appeal to Central Executive Office of the Siege Organization Chicago, Ill</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0340</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0340.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-05-17">May 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">LETTER OF THANKS AND FURTHER APPEAL TO CENTRAL EXECUTIVE OFFICE OF THE SIEGE ORGANIZATION CHICAGO, ILL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We beg to inform the honorable Executive Office that on April 15, 1922, we sent to you a statement and acknowledgment of your last donation as well as a further appeal.</p>
   <p>During the past heavy winter, the temperature in our living quarters was about nine degrees centigrade above zero for several days. Both we ex-officers and ex-soldiers are not so much concerned with ourselves as we are with the physical welfare of our wives, especially the wives who are pregnant. There is great anxiety over their confinements and preparations for the newborn.</p>
   <p>Up to now we had a fund of our hetman, the head of our U. M. E. A. in Czecho-Slovakia, but it happened that on April 18, 1922, we spent our last four hundred Czecho-Slovak crowns to defray the expenses of the <pb facs="5425703_0341.jpg" n="2"/>confinement of Mrs. Walter Kyprian, ex-officer's wife, who bore him a son.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, wish to appeal strongly to the honorable Executive Headquarters to be so kind as to refer this matter to the women's associations and committees in the United States, as well as to the Reverend Pastors, so that with their counsel, influence, and work they will at least partly help us meet this extreme necessity and thus help ease some of our worry.</p>
   <p>We appeal in this case to the women's committees and the Reverend Fathers because they understand the practical side of life much better than others. Nature, by the Providence itself, has thrown upon them the heaviest duty toward the new members of humanity, so that the former, as well as the latter, take care of the new life from the very beginning, especially the women, who do so with full sacrifice, and up to the very last breath of the individual.</p>
   <p>It is to you, mothers and sisters, Reverend Fathers and Reverend Sisters, who are caring for and bringing up children, that we send our ardent appeal <pb facs="5425703_0342.jpg" n="3"/>not to forget your sisters who, due to the hostile occupation of our country, were forced to give up their homes and now, in foreign countries in Europe, are not living but just existing; not in becoming homes, but in dark and uncomfortable barracks, and there they fulfill their duty to humanity, imposed upon them by the will of the Providence itself, and they expect to be delivered. Do not forget them, and instead of some small entertainment try to arrange in every one of your club groups a benefit day for newborn Ukrainian babies and send the profits you make at these enterprises to those distressed ones in Europe; thus you will help many suffering mothers.</p>
   <p>To you also little children beyond the seas we send our appeal: do not forget your little brothers and sisters here across the ocean. Remind your parents every day to give you a penny for milk for those little children far away in the old country, take this penny to school and give it to your Ukrainian school teacher and ask her to collect more pennies from other pupils to send them for the poor children of the emigrants <pb facs="5425703_0343.jpg" n="4"/>in Josefov, Czecho-Slovakia.</p>
   <p>Many thanks to all of you to whom this letter of appeal is directed, for your past and future co-operation.</p>
   <p>For the Charity Distribution Committee:</p>
   <p>K. Krushelnitsky, Chairman</p>
   <p>D. Kabarivsky, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
