<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
<date when="1930-06-13">June 13th, 1930</date>. Vol. I. No. 1.
<title level="a">(Chicago, Ill.) Weekly. Our Newspaper</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0262</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0262.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainia (Ukraine)</title>,
<date when="1930-06-13">June 13th, 1930</date>. Vol. I. No. 1.
<title level="a">(Chicago, Ill.) Weekly. OUR NEWSPAPER</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With today's issue we begine to publish a Ukrainian weekly newspaper Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>Our newspaper is not an organ of any political or financial group but it is a non-political paper published for all the Ukrainian people in America. Ukrainia, being non-partisan and at a distance from all quarrels and "fights" that poison our national life both in Europe and here and hinder us from acquiring our aim-the rebirth of a political and economic independence.</p>
   <p>Ukrainia as an independent periodical will make worth while our life, looking at the same through non-partisan glasses; it will describe the various changes in life and will give news about our national existence and struggles, exactly the way they appear in everyday life.</p>
   <p>Our newspaper will turn its special attention to the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>For many reasons, our sojourn in Chicago up to this time is found in a state of disorganization. Lack of the printed, non-partisan, Ukrainian word, that would dull the sharp ends of partisan saores and would bring the society to that order which behooves the twenty five thousand Ukrainians. As it used <pb facs="5425703_0263.jpg" n="2"/>to be formerly--a brother avoided his brother and a friend overlooked his friend. The supposedly twenty five thousand Ukrainians in Chicago, fighting among themselves, morally without any resulting good from either this or that thought. The consequences of this will be as follows: we cannot help the country from which we originate in its misfortunes, or, take part in this city life in particular and American life generally; nor can we help ourselves much. The "watchword" "support your own kind", has long ago been forgotten. The only ones who know where our places of business are with small exceptions, are probably, only the Christmas Carolers and other collectors, that do not forget to visit them regularly and remind them of the motto: "keep your national solidarity". Ukrainia will strive to introduce among its people the "modus vivendi" with the Ukrainian groups in Chicago, and will back enterprises furthermore, it will help in the economic development of the Ukrainians in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Ukrainia will faithfully adhere to our national and economic life in Chicago representing truthfully all its good and bad features.</p>
   <p>Our newspaper will go in a straight forward direction, with hope undiminished that the Ukrainian public in Chicago, and in America generally will accept it as a new and desirable co-laborer with our American immigration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
