<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1918-08-15">Aug. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Why Was the Ukrainian Siege Organization Established in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Sharowsky, Siege Secretary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1918-08-15">Aug. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHY WAS THE UKRAINIAN SIEGE ORGANIZATION ESTABLISHED IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Sharowsky, Siege Secretary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some individuals think that the Siege was established by a group seeking honors and titles as Siege officers. As a result of this it is no wonder that although it is almost two years since the Siege was established, only a comparatively small number realize its real purpose.</p>
   <p>When we look more closely into the life of the immigrant, we notice that all nationality groups have their organizations in order to get together now and then. The so-called athletic organizations draw our attention particularly. There is hardly a foreign national group in this country that won't recognize the value of physical drills and athletics. For instance, let us take the Czechs. They take particular care in training their youth. Therefore, it is no wonder that when one visits a Czech Eagle lodge one cannot help but noticing how the old mothers bring their <pb facs="5425703_0499.jpg" n="2"/>children to the drills.</p>
   <p>Why? Because they know that physical drills build a healthy body, beautifys it, develop perserverance, and add years to one's life. If children are healthy, so will be the nation, and this applies to any nation. Let us turn our attention to ourselves. Who of us ever thought of the blessings brought about by athletics? It has been over thirty years since our immigration started into this country, and nobody has ever mentioned anything seriously about athletics yet. All of us seem to look at it indifferently, although there are many who know that for us Ukrainians it is indispensably necessary; yet during all that time they did not do anything in this direction. Meanwhile, our youth, feeling the necessity of physical drill, joined clubs hostile to us, for the sake of gymnastics. This is why today we find a number of Ukrainians in the ranks of the Polish Eagle organization. They speak Polish as fluently as if they did not know their native language or neglected it. And today we complain that our Ukrainians read Polish newspapers and speak their language, but we do not try to find the cause of this evil, and even though we see it, we are ashamed to tell <pb facs="5425703_0500.jpg" n="3"/>ourselves the truth straight from the shoulder, that this is our own fault.</p>
   <p>The saying goes: Bend the tree while it is young. So, if we had undertaken that work right from the start, then today, positively we would exceed twice 500,000 immigrants, for we emigrated in a far greater number than they actually give us credit for. Alas, many foreign elements unjustly claim any number of Ukrainina immigrants. To counteract this situation at least in part, we established the Siege Organization, which has for its object the training of the Ukrainian Youth, both physically and spiritually. Everyone of us already know that in a sound body there is a sound mind.</p>
   <p>The Siege organization answers all the requirements of the Ukrainian nation. Therefore, there should not be found a single one from among us that should join an encampment hostile to us. There is among us our own organization. The officers of the Siege Organization will do everything in their power to attain this aim. From now on we cannot complain any longer that there is not any organization of this kind among ourselves. Take advantage of it, everyone of you; take advantage of this accomplishment, which is established through you, for you, and among you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
