<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. IV, No. 37, <date when="1920-10-02">October 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Important News! a New Ukrainian Astronomical Clock Invention</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>UKRAINA</title>,
Vol. IV, No. 37, <date when="1920-10-02">October 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT NEWS! A NEW UKRAINIAN ASTRONOMICAL CLOCK INVENTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the top of this clock there are three planets which represent the sun, the earth and the moon. It shows how the sun illuminates the earth. It shows how the world turns on its axis once every twenty-four hours, through which we have our night and day; how the world turns around the sun and in what way it creates four seasons of the year. It definetly shows how the moon turns around the earth and in what way the changes of the moon originate. It also shows how the earth, together with the moon, circles around the sun and why a year has twelve months. It likewise shows in what way the eclipse of the sun and the moon originate. Besides this, we can clearly see the rotations and the position of the planets. This clock has a seperate dial on which there is a calendar for the whole year, the hands on it show the hours accurately, day and months, names of the months and seasons of the year.</p>
   <p>The inventor of this Astronomical Clock is Mr. Michael Bulka, a Ukrainian from Galicia, brother of the widely known patriots A. and M. Bulka, owners of the Ukrainian Tailor factory in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0162.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This invention is already patented.</p>
   <p>The American School Council approved and acknowledged this Astronomical Clock in the first place as the best for the American Schools.</p>
   <p>We have a large order from schools. There has been no similar invention up to this time in any country.</p>
   <p>Many strangers call on the inventor offering him considerable amounts of money and propositions to induce him to sell them the patent or take them into partnership and open up a company factory. But the wishes of this inventor, as a true Ukrainian, are that the Ukrainian invention as an important technical gain should remain in the hands of the Ukrainians, also that the Ukrainian factory of Astronomical Clocks should be built with Ukrainian money, and that the Ukrainian people should take advantage of the assured profits.</p>
   <p>So fulfilling the Ukrainian national duty, and understanding very well what great profit this Ukrainian Astronomical Clock Factory will bring to the Ukrainian people, <pb facs="5425703_0163.jpg" n="3"/>we believe in the full success and undertake to work and organize a Ukrainian company under the following name: "Astronomical Clock Mfg. Co."</p>
   <p>We invite all clear thinking Ukrainians to unite with us in buying shares and becoming co-owners of our Ikrainian factory. By taking advantage of the big profits that are assured, you will assure yourself of better living in old age. Being independent with money in old age is the ideal of all clear thinking people. Our watchword and national obligation should always be, never give anything to the hands of strangers which could bring profit to ourselves.</p>
   <p>So onward to business, Ukrainians, to clear and sensible business.</p>
   <p>In a day or so we will send out our representatives to all places where Ukrainians live, to explain the cause in a broader way and to sell the shares of our company.</p>
   <p>Every Ukrainian can afford to buy one share for $50.00 and thus become a co-owner of this excellent and profitable business.</p>
   <p>We ask all Ukrainians to take part in our Ikrainian Company and to become members of it. The address of the company is as follows:</p>
   <p>Astronomical Clock Mfg. Co.</p>
   <p>1910 Wabansia Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
