<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth of America</title>,
<date when="1934-07-29">July 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association Gives Picnic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0351</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0351.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth of America</title>,
<date when="1934-07-29">July 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">UKRAINIAN PROFESSIONAL AND BUSINESSMEN'S ASSOCIATION GIVES PICNIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association is holding its first annual picnic today at the St. Nicholas Picnic Grove on Higgins Road. An interesting program is scheduled for the day.</p>
   <p>There will be competitive games for boys and girls, men and women, with prizes for the winners. There will also be a large number of prizes raffled off to the holder of the lucky number, therefore, retain the stub of your ticket, and if your number should be called, present it, and receive your prize.....</p>
   <p>The price of admission, as you probably know, is free, that is, if you have <pb facs="5425703_0352.jpg" n="2"/>one of the tickets which the professional and the businessmen have been giving away to their customers. If you do not have a ticket, the cost of admission at the gate will be thirty-five cents. But those who support the members of the Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association received their tickets free.</p>
   <p>The Association's aim is to urge Ukrainians to support the Ukrainian businessmen, instead of all others as they usually do. After all, everybody buys food, clothes, shoes, furniture, coal, beer, etc; but how many of you buy it from a Ukrainian businessman? I am sure they all have what you want, and as reasonably priced as the other fellow. Therefore, in the future when you are about to buy something, remember always to go to a member of the Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association. Give them a chance, and I am sure they will satisfy you.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0353.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Remember to come on out today and enjoy yourself. Dance to a six piece orchestra, drink, eat, and make merry, and from now on firmly resolve always to patronize the members of the Ukrainian Professional and Businessmen's Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
