<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
Vol. I, No. 2, <date when="1934-06">June 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Task for Us</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
Vol. I, No. 2, <date when="1934-06">June 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A TASK FOR US</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Historia magistra vitae (History is life's teacher) says the well known Latin adage. The Ukrainians can boast and be truly proud of their history. The first historical annals in Europe were written by an Ukrainian monk, Nestor, and remain up to our days the main source of information for the scholars of Eastern European history. Other important workers followed to be crowned by the really monumental achievement of Professor Michael Hrushewsky, of his History of Ukraine, on which he worked for 30 years. It is the most complete work on this subject in ten large volumes.</p>
   <p>But it seems that we Americans of Ukrainian descent have less interest in historical things than our brothers in Europe or even in Canada. With the exception of one volume written years before the war about the Ukrainians in America by a certain Dr. Julian Bachynsky, who at the time was visiting America, there is literally no history of us Ukrainians in America. We heard that there was some attempt to collect certain information about the first Ukrainian settlements in the United <pb facs="5425703_0300.jpg" n="2"/>States, but it remained a mere trial and a pious wish, as many other things undertaken by men from the old country.</p>
   <p>Why shall we, the young generation, only look at the helplessness of the older one? Let us show them that, although they say that we are no longer Ukrainians (according to their way of looking at things), we are still devoted to Ukrainian ideals and that patriotism consists in doing things, not merely talking about how they should have been accomplished.</p>
   <p>Let us be practical.</p>
   <p>Every member of our worthy organizations should find in every place where the Ukrainians have settled some intelligent (not necessarily intellectual) person, to whom they may go and ask a couple of questions concerning the first Ukrainian settlers in that given locality. Let the person interviewed tell you all he knows. And put it down in writing. Your father, your mother, your uncle or godfather or any one will do. Ask them from which village of the old country they come, when and how they came and to what locality. Ask the parson (if there is any church <pb facs="5425703_0301.jpg" n="3"/>in your or in the neighboring locality) when that church was built and by whom, who was the first pastor and his successors. Find out what organizations exist and by whom they were started. In a word, use your common sense and ingenuity in finding the history of your community and of the Ukrainians in it. You will be surprised how much knowledge you will derive from such an interview and how interesting it will be even for using it in your home papers. And how much fun you will have in finding things you never suspected, in your particular town.</p>
   <p>Send your findings to the editor of Ukrainian Youth. We shall publish the most interesting essays about your locality, and out of those letters you will send us we shall try to compile at least a short history of the Ukrainians in the United States. Your material will be a source of information for the future historian of our people in America.</p>
   <p>Remember that history is not written only by scholars but is made and <pb facs="5425703_0302.jpg" n="4"/>found by living ones, is gathered from letters and records, from inscriptions and even from handbills distributed in the theaters.</p>
   <p>History is a means of informing ourselves and others about Ukraine and Ukrainians. In this way we give to others to learn of us and eventually we shall gain the admiration and respect of all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
