<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 14, <date when="1919-05-10">May 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Uncle Sam Has to Aid War Ruined Europe</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>UKRAINA</title>,
Vol. III, No. 14, <date when="1919-05-10">May 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">UNCLE SAM HAS TO AID WAR RUINED EUROPE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wheat and meat, clothing and building material will have to be sent very soon to Europe in large quantities.</p>
   <p>America is always in position to carry out this work, because the United States is the richest country in the world. At any rate, America cannot further its help problems, when you will not aid her.</p>
   <p>You know that a large part of the past loan from the Svoboda went for the nourishment of needy nations. Now comes a bigger demand to help the war ruined people in the form of giving them a loan - for the purpose of feeding the hungry and bringing the shattered nations to peace and prosperity.</p>
   <p>In what way can Uncle Sam think of feeding, clothing, and in other ways helping Europe in her fearful situation resulting from the war? This help is to be given from the Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>If every one of us will loan a small amount, Uncle Sam will be able to give more.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What's more, it will speed up the securing of the Liberty Loan and prosperity will be here. Wages will go up. We will be able to help ourselves.</p>
   <p>We, Ukrainians, should not neglect the call of Uncle Sam. We know that if we loan him money, it will be returned to us dollar for dollar, and after four years there will be an interest of 4¾ per cent.</p>
   <p>By the government plan the Liberty Loan can be paid out in six installments, the last payment being on November 11th, 1919.</p>
   <p>Buy now, today! Let the badge on your chest show that you completed your obligation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
