<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth Magazine (Official Organ of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League, Philadelphia, Pa.)</title><date when="1936-03">Feb.-March, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Unity of Catholic Church in Practice</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth Magazine (Official Organ of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League, Philadelphia, Pa.)</title><date when="1936-03">Feb.-March, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">UNITY OF CATHOLIC CHURCH IN PRACTICE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An event, unusual but solemnly beautiful to the Ukrainian Catholics, took place at the St. Nicholas Church (Oakley and Rice Sts.) on January 26, 1936. From his Eminence Cardinal Mundelein's Seminary came some fifty students preparing for the priesthood of the Latin Rite, a number of whom are to be ordained in a few months. In this group were accompanying priests and deacons. They all came to attend in our Greek Catholic Church the Holy Mass and to behold the Holy Eucharist according to the Divine Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom. The sight of the tall young student priests garbed in black and white and placed around the altar and in the front pews inspired the admiration and respect of all behold us. The sermon was delivered in English by a priest representing the seminary. His sermon made the hearers feel that the Catholic Church is drawing all its followers still more closely together, even though different rites and different languages are used. He stressed the fact that languages and rites do not matter when the liturgy celebrated is the same as in Catholic Churches. He emphasized the unity found in the Catholic Church and asked that we pray for other peoples to be led to this unity--the Catholic Church, which brings light to all. The entire service seemed more beautiful that day than ever, with brilliantly lighted Christmas trees, with gleaming candles on marble altars, with the graceful altar boys aiding the Basilian Fathers at Mass, and with the choir uplifting each soul with praises of God.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
