<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
<date when="1935-03-31">March 31, 1935</date><title level="a">Sports</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
<date when="1935-03-31">March 31, 1935</date><title level="a">SPORTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year our St. Nicholas Church will be well represented in the sport world. To date we have two baseball teams, both of which have in the past years proven themselves worthy of the task of representing our church.</p>
   <p>The first which plays under the nick name of the Elks, has been for the last three years showing great promise as to a future Ukrainian Championship team of Chicago. Last year they beat the South Side Representatives (St Mary's baseball-team) three times out of a possible three. This year they intend to repeat their invasion of the South Siders and add to their lists the scalps of the Cicero baseball team. The Cossack team better take notice, for it won't be long before the Elks start going after their scalps.</p>
   <p>The second, a girl's team, which plays under the name of Zippers, has also done many great thing in the past. Last year under the managership of Stella Sweda and Anne Demetro they beat the Cicero Championship baseball team two games out of a possible four. This year with Stella Gabro (Captain of the team for the past two seasons) acting as their pilot they intend to perfect their record against the Cicero team.</p>
   <p>Among other teams which have been developed at our church, but will be representing <pb facs="5425703_0326.jpg" n="2"/>private concerns are the Cossacks who hope &amp; possess the backing of the Chi-Oak Tavern, and the St. Nicholas team who has as its backers the Ukrainian Professional Business Men's Ass'n.</p>
   <p>The Cossacks who at one time were without a doubt the Champions of Chicago three years ago, under the managership of J. Evankoe will again try and rebuild their reputation which has been broken on account of the poor showing of last year. Proof that they have started off in earnest is the fact that they have again picked Jim Evankoe as their manager.</p>
   <p>For all of the above mentioned baseball teams the staff wishes to take this opportunity in wishing each and everyone of the teams the best of luck. May this season be the most successful one of their existence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
