<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1932-07-01">July 1, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Our Prominent Ukrainian Doctor Has Passed Away</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1932-07-01">July 1, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROMINENT UKRAINIAN DOCTOR HAS PASSED AWAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 13 of this year Dr. Vladimir Sieminovich passed away; he was seventy-four years of age. He was one of the oldest Ukrainian emigrants in the United States.</p>
   <p>Dr. Sieminovich was born in the village of Monastersky, county of Buchacz, in eastern Ukraine.</p>
   <p>The notes of Dr. Sieminovich indicate that the Sieminovich family originated in Lithuania, where they are mentioned in historical documents as far back as the fifteenth century. From Lithuania the family migrated to the eastern Ukraine, where it produced a number of Ukrainian priests and patriots.</p>
   <p>The deceased Dr. Sieminovich after completing his high school and college studies in Buchacz and Berezany and serving in the Austro-Hungarian army <pb facs="5425703_0156.jpg" n="2"/>entered the university, taking up the study of law. His career at the university was soon terminated, for he was called to America by Father O. Voliansky to help organize the Ukrainian emigrants. Dr. Sieminovich came to the United States in 1887, and for some time he edited a Ukrainian Newspaper,"America"; he was also a church singer, and organized many Ukrainian churches and co-operative societies. He took an active part in cultural work among the first Ukrainian emigrants.</p>
   <p>After some time he began the study of medicine in American universities. After completing his course he became a physician. In 1898 he went to Europe to pursue his medical studies further. After returning to the United States he became a professor in the Chicago Medical University, where he lectured on childbirth and female troubles.</p>
   <p>The greater part of Dr. Sieminovich's life was sacrificed in nationalistic <pb facs="5425703_0157.jpg" n="3"/>community work. He was head of the enlightenment movement for the Ukrainian National Association, for which he wrote many cultural books; he also edited Enlightenment, a newspaper. In 1930 and 1931 he edited the newspaper Ukraina in Chicago.</p>
   <p>He had lived in Chicago for the last forty years. He was organizer of the Ukrainian Greek Catholic church here. He also took an active part in organizing the Intelligence Club. Besides all this he did work for various Ukrainian publications in Europe, especially Woman's Destiny, which he helped morally and materially.</p>
   <p>Dr. Sieminovich always participated in every movement that was promoted by Ukrainians. The deceased even during the worst circumstances of his life never fell into despair, and even up to his death he believed that the Ukrainians would have their own independent country, saying that of the Ukrainian ethnological masses a nation will be formed.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0158.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the presence of a great crowd of people the burial took place on Friday, June 17; his final resting place is the St. Nicholas Church Cemetery.</p>
   <p>Father P. Tarnawsky said a few words, full of feeling, over the grave of the deceased, pointing out the good traits of Dr. Sieminovich's character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
