<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1920-11">Nov. 1920</date><title level="a">Siege Organization Holiday in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1920-11">Nov. 1920</date><title level="a">SIEGE ORGANIZATION HOLIDAY IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, October 3, this year, there was a celebration of the Siege branches in Chicago in honor of the dead Ukrainian heroes. Under the auspices of the Chicago Siege officers the special commemoration took place at the Wicker Park Hall on North Ave.</p>
   <p>Branch No. 15, which considers itself independent is composed particularly of the Catholic St. Nicholas parishioners at Oakley Blvd. and Rice St., and acted independently with the possible intention of injuring the program of the general Siege celebration.</p>
   <p>Despite this disharmony the celebrants were very numerous in our general holiday. The majority of sincere Chicago Ukrainians remember the main Ukrainian cause and not the petty affairs of a single group whose members <pb facs="5425703_0536.jpg" n="2"/>regard the general Ukrainian business too narrowly, and look after the good of their parish only.</p>
   <p>At 3 P.M. the hall was filled with Siege members from various districts: Hammond, Gary, Cicero, Joliet, Chicago, Burnside, South Side, West Side, North Side, and even from Milwaukee, Wisconsin. There were some non-members too, who are sincere Ukrainians, and came down for a joint-celebration to honor and glorify the fallen heroes of Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>With silent, yet intense sympathy, the gathering reverently awaited the opening of the concert of the festival, and while meditating on the past beyond the ocean, in Ukrainia, they were comparing it with the present times, both over there and here, when the commencement of the concert interrupted their thoughts.</p>
   <p>With the rising of the curtain, in the middle of the stage there was a grave <pb facs="5425703_0537.jpg" n="3"/>mound covered with green and a wooden cross reminding those present of the countless fresh graves strewn throughout Ukrainian valleys, meadows, and the lonely steppes. This sight was enough to make the people's expressions grave. There were sighs of longing, and even drops of tears could have been perceived on many of those present.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened by the district colonel Mr. M. Saragun, with a short, yet sincere introductory speech after which followed music by the musical society "Free Cossacks," Directed by Mr. John Kobeliak, the national anthem, "Ukrainia Has Arisen," was played.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. Novodvorsky's lecture was next on the program. He briefly reviewed the great historical deeds from the Cossacks' period to the present time.</p>
   <p>The number following was "A Bundle of Ukrainian Songs" played by the musical club "Free Cossacks," after which followed the number, "Honor To The Heroes."</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0538.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>During the first part of the ceremony, the choir of the Young Boyan, directed by Mr. K. Pendik, sang "You Fell Through Sacrifice, after which a twelve-year old girl, Miss Stephania Motsio, dressed in a typical Ukrainian costume, recited in her ringing voice a short poem in honor of the fallen heroes, placing on the grave a wreath from the Ukrainian colony in Chicago. Also Mr. Wasylovsky placed a wreath from the Self-educating club. This ended the tribute to the fallen heroes. During the ceremony all those who were present stood up.</p>
   <p>The next number, a collection of Ukrainian songs, was sung by the Young Boyan. Then followed a well given recitation of one of Taras Shevchenko's poems, "Haydamaky" (Knights) by Stephen Musiychuk. Dr. John Smuk's Eulogy was next and suited the occasion.</p>
   <p>The choir of the Young Boyan sang "I Slanderized," with a soloist Mr. P. Dmytrash, taking the lead.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0539.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Finally Mr. Novodvorsky, in a few words appealed especially to the Siege members to contribute, during the silver collection, to defray the expenses of the day. The audience responded generously.</p>
   <p>The celebration was closed with singing of the national anthems.</p>
   <p>Note: Although the celebration was not so ostentatious due to the fact that on the program there were no famous speakers or artists, but mostly our every day workmen, still we are sure that the celebration will remain for a long time in the memory of those who were present, because whatever was given had its beauty, sincerity and simplicity.</p>
   <p>By Siege member.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
