<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 4, <date when="1919-01-23">Jan. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">To the Ukrainian Workingmen, Members, and Sympathizers of the Federation of Ukrainians in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 4, <date when="1919-01-23">Jan. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE UKRAINIAN WORKINGMEN, MEMBERS, AND SYMPATHIZERS OF THE FEDERATION OF UKRAINIANS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brother Ukrainians!</p>
   <p>As you all know it was resolved at the second Ukrainian congress in Washington, D. C., that the executives of the Federation of Ukrainians take under consideration the case of transferring the Chicago weekly, Ukraina, which is to become the organ of the Federation of Ukrainians in the United States.</p>
   <p>This resolution of the Congress is not yet carried out. We expect that the executives of the Federation will do everything in their power to take over the Ukraina and its property.</p>
   <p>Brother workingmen! You know very well that the Federation of Ukrainians was started a long time ago, and progressed slowly, not the way we should like to see it. The chief reason is that the Federation did <pb facs="5425703_0278.jpg" n="2"/>not have its own paper that would stand for the interest of the Ukrainian workingmen in America.</p>
   <p>The newspaper Ukraina, issued in Chicago, though it was altogether an independent newspaper, never committed itself against the ideals that the Federation of Ukrainians had upheld, but always sided with it in a friendly way. Sometimes it had to raise a few questions which touched the Federation of Ukrainians in their voice of criticism on certain matters.</p>
   <p>Now, when Ukraina is to become the newspaper of the Federation of Ukrainians, it is the obligation not only of the members and sympathizers, but of every conscious workingman to spread and to back up the newspaper Ukraina.</p>
   <p>A good example was set in this direction by the shareholders of the Ukrainian Publishing Company in Chicago, owners of the newspaper Ukraina, <pb facs="5425703_0279.jpg" n="3"/>who resolved to leave their shares with the Federation of Ukrainians if only the newspaper Ukraina would go to the Federation of Ukrainians.</p>
   <p>So you, too, Ukrainian workingmen, do your share for this cause!</p>
   <p>Order for yourselves the newspaper Ukraina and induce others to do this. Collect advertisements, give all kinds of printing work to the printing company of the Ukraina, sponsor concerts, dances, and other entertainments for the newspaper Ukraina.</p>
   <p>Thus we shall not only insure the existence of the needed Ukrainian newspaper for ourselves in these parts, but also we shall be able to effect the coming out of the Ukraina more often, and in the near future we shall find that our weekly Ukraina will become a daily paper.</p>
   <p>Through ardent work, and willingness, this will not be a hard thing to do. Let us keep under consideration that in Chicago alone there are a <pb facs="5425703_0280.jpg" n="4"/>few thousand copies of Polish newspapers bought by the Ukrainian people.</p>
   <p>Surely, the Ukrainians would rather find out all the world news from their own Ukrainian daily than from our Polish enemy papers.</p>
   <p>When we reach this point we can boldly bring the Ukrainian cause as well as that of the Ukrainian workingmen's cause to equal our enemies, and go to fight for our beautiful national banner, for thee, our free Ukrainia! Long live and grow the Federation of Ukrainians in the United States! Long live and grow the newspaper Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>Yours for the cause,</p>
   <p>Elias Szkwarok.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
