<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitchovi Visty (Siege Herald)</title>,
<date when="1924-05-25">May 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Order Given by the Siege Chief Executive in Matter of Speeches at Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitchovi Visty (Siege Herald)</title>,
<date when="1924-05-25">May 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ORDER GIVEN BY THE SIEGE CHIEF EXECUTIVE IN MATTER OF SPEECHES AT CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. All communications with reference to the lectures and speeches to be given out at the convention are to be addressed to the office of the Chief executive: 2406 West Chicago Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>2. Where there is no Siege branch and the people wish to have one, they choose a committee at their next gathering, which must be referred to the Committee of the nearest Siege district in the matter of sending their delegate to the Convention. For organization literature the request should be written directly to the General secretary, 2406 West Chicago Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>3. Each communication concerning sending a speaker, must be sent in, at least thirty days before the Convention meeting.</p>
   <p>4. If a given Siege district wishes to have a special delegate sent from <pb facs="5425703_0563.jpg" n="2"/>the Headquarters to any of their meetings, the district should send a full traveling coverage. Without this, the sending of a delegate to your meetings is impossible, as we cannot in this way expand our organization, which does not understand that a delegate should be paid for his work and other traveling expenses, at least as much as an average laborer.</p>
   <p>Chief Executive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
