<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1930-06-13">June 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">What News Reports the Ukrainian Conscription in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1930-06-13">June 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT NEWS REPORTS THE UKRAINIAN CONSCRIPTION IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The League of the Liberation of Ukraine, organized in Chicago, resolved to make the Ukrainian conscription here in Chicago. It was resolved and done. It must be said in advance that the planned conscription of all the Ukrainians living in Chicago was not completely successful, as the League wished. First of all, the lack of skilled men for such a special work; second, the lack of the necessary apparatus to carry on such a planned conscription. The conscription is still now not complete and not finished.</p>
   <p>It will be an advantage when we make up just now the investigation and an estimate of the conscription in a general way. From the collected lists of the Ukrainian conscription properly filled out, I have selected one hundred lists as they came to my hands and after thoughtful investigations I relate as follow:</p>
   <p>(1) The question about changed names: 98 persons answering that question <pb facs="5425703_0355.jpg" n="2"/>said they did not change their names. The full name is usually adapted to the English pronunciation sometimes not very properly, for example: the proper name, Ivan, changed to John; Mikhaylo, to Mike; Hnat, to Jim, and so on. Only three businessmen of this number (98 persons) changed their names to English names, apparently from business reasons.</p>
   <p>The question whether the children who attend school have changed their names received no attention. This question is very important because the children use all their lives the names which were given to them by their teachers. By the names it is very easy to recognize how many Ukrainian students are attending high schools, colleges and universities. It is therefore very much desired that this question be filled out in the future.</p>
   <p>(2) The second question: Married or single: 82 persons answered "yes," meaning they live in the married state, only 18 persons declared that they lead an unmarried life, out of that number three women, because they have no occasion to get married.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0356.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(3) The citizenship papers: On one hundred questionaires there are 67 men who took out the second citizenship papers, 18 men took out the first citizenship papers and 15 men have no citizenship papers at all, besides the fact that many of these men have been here in America over twenty years. In reference to the women as the members of families, the matter is worse. Out of one hundred questionaires only 75 women have filled out the petitions for citizenship papers. It is evident that 23 women have already become citizens of the United States of America through being married to citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
