<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainia, (Ukraine)</title>,
<date when="1930-06-27">June 27, 1930</date>. Vol. 1, No. 3.
<title level="a">Vote Yes for the New Traction Ordinance, July 1st</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainia, (Ukraine)</title>,
<date when="1930-06-27">June 27, 1930</date>. Vol. 1, No. 3.
<title level="a">VOTE YES FOR THE NEW TRACTION ORDINANCE, JULY 1st</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For weeks, we have endeavored to bring to the attention of our readers, the vital importance of the proposed, new, unified traction ordinance, which will be submitted to the voters of Chicago for ratification on July 1st.</p>
   <p>The ordinance provides, among many valuable, and constructive provisions, for a unified, and rapid traction system, with a free transfer from any elevated, street car, or bus line to the other, for one fare. It provides for many extensions, and new lines of elevated roads, street cars, and feeder buses, with a subway, which will make rapid transit possible, and eliminate the present loop congestion, and slow transportation.</p>
   <p>It will enable a passenger to traverse the entire city for one fare, whereas now, it takes two, and three fares to reach a given destination.</p>
   <p>The most interesting, and advantageous side of the great question is, the fact that it will give the people an adequate, and rapid modern transportation for which they have been hoping, and dreaming for the past thirty years, at a lower cost than what they are paying now. It will increase real estate values throughout the city, and suburbs.</p>
   <p>The immediate improvements, and new construction, will furnish work for the <pb facs="5425703_0105.jpg" n="2"/>thousands of unemployed. It will restore confidence in financial, industrial, and labor circles, and prosperity is bound to be re-established, and to stay with us for many years to come.</p>
   <p>After having made a comprehensive study of this ordinance, and having carefully considered this important public question, from various angles, taking into consideration, the disadvantages under which the transportation lines have operated in the past, and the advantages that the new ordinance offers to the people of Chicago, we believe, that it will serve the best interest of the community, to vote for the approval of the ordinance, and mark your ballot, Yes, on July 1st.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
