<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 3, <date when="1919-01-16">January 16, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On Entering and Leaving the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0723</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0723.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 3, <date when="1919-01-16">January 16, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON ENTERING AND LEAVING THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In certain circles there are conflicting thoughts that the immigrant's sojourn depends on his signing or failure to sign his intention to return to this country.</p>
   <p>In order to correct this disputed question, the State Department says that all the rights and privileges of foreigners for coming in and going out remain as formerly. On no occasion are the foreigners allowed either to come into or leave the United States unless they abide by these rules. It appears that these rules will be enforced until the proclamation of world peace, if no longer.</p>
   <p>No one has any right to make any plans for crossing the ocean or accepting money as a down payment for ocean tickets with any promise, clear or self-understood, nor to grant the right to leave the United States. Only the government officials, authorized by the State Department, have the right to grant such permission, and even they cannot assure <pb facs="5425703_0724.jpg" n="2"/>anyone beforehand that permission will be granted. Those wanting to depart should make application in the proper department, the one nearest to his city and not at the port from which he intends to leave. The applicant should not leave his city until he receives the department's permission to leave the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
