<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1924-01-25">Jan. 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Orders of Chief Executive on How to Conduct Sitch Meetings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1924-01-25">Jan. 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ORDERS OF CHIEF EXECUTIVE ON HOW TO CONDUCT SITCH MEETINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before the Sitch organization will be able to get regular lecturers, who at set intervals could travel and give educational lectures, stopping at every district and company of the organization, the officers of every Sitch Company are ordered to read carefully all the main articles in the past issues of the Sitch News, and choose a theme for discussion before their next meeting. The article selected from our organ, before the next meeting, must be intrusted to two members who are to carefully study and develop it so as to be ready to answer almost any question that may arise during a joint discussion at the meeting. The first one of the two appointed must read aloud the article to all those present at the meeting and take the affirmative side of the article; the second one must be prepared to take the negative side in the discussion. The discussion must be conducted rather quietly, with poise, without mutual insults or attacks. The one taking the negative side will be the first to speak after the reading of the article; the one taking the <pb facs="5425703_0379.jpg" n="2"/>affirmative, will have the last word.</p>
   <p>After the discussion, the two main persons taking part in it must summarize the entire procedure of the discussion and send it to the Executive Headquarters in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Fellow-members, this order should be complied with always. At the present time this is the only way whereby we can interest the greater masses of our people with public affairs, and thus help a number of people to develop better presentation of speeches, and clearer and to the point discussions.</p>
   <p>Order as to How to Conduct Ordinary and Mass Meetings</p>
   <p>In every Sitch Meeting conducted in its respective district, where a Sitch representative is present, sent by the Chief Executive's office, he has the preferred right over the local district head officer to conduct the meeting; however, the latter may conduct the meeting with the representative's consent.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0380.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This decision is supported by the by-laws accepted at the last convention held in Cleveland. In short, where there is a representative sent directly from the Executive Headquarters, he is responsible for all the activities of that district during his stay; therefore, he must have authority.</p>
   <p>In the districts, either the district head officer or someone appointed by him, who is conducting the district meetings, is responsible for the activities.</p>
   <p>The chairman is only to conduct meetings, and is not to be the speaker; lecturers are to be the speakers. The secretary's business is to write the minutes and keep them in good order from meeting to meeting, and from year to year. The head officers are appointed especially to conduct all the Sitch meetings, and be responsible for them and their members.</p>
   <p>Order as to Selection of Themes at Gatherings and Meetings</p>
   <p>Any business of a local nature is to be discussed and decided immediately after <pb facs="5425703_0381.jpg" n="4"/>the opening of a meeting.</p>
   <p>The next necessary point at every meeting is to discuss briefly the following things which are of general interest:</p>
   <p>(1) How to enlarge the Sitch Organization and the most efficient way of getting new members.</p>
   <p>(2) The meaning of the Sitch uniform.</p>
   <p>(3) The meaning of the Sitch press.</p>
   <p>Immediately after each meeting the collecting of monthly dues and voluntary donations to the press fund should take place. The latter especially should be sent out at once to the Executive Headquarters in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Dr. S. K. Hrynevetsky, Chief Executive.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Jan. 5, 1924.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
