<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1921-12">Nov. and Dec. 1921</date>.
<title level="a">How Long Shall We Be Servants?</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal to Sitch Members in Chicago and Abroad by John Dmytriw, Chicagoan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C (Russian)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Sitch News)</title>,
<date when="1921-12">Nov. and Dec. 1921</date>.
<title level="a">HOW LONG SHALL WE BE SERVANTS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal to Sitch Members in Chicago and Abroad by John Dmytriw, Chicagoan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three years have already passed and the wild Poles, with fire and sword are still murdering our brothers and sisters, in penitentiaries and on gibbets, pillaging and ruining everything Ukrainian, ruining villages, towns, and cities, plundering our native land.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of our people are dying under the Polish-Russian yoke: they either die of starvation, or in jail, or are killed outright.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of our youth have fallen in battles; hundreds of thousands are crippled because they went to fight for the freedom and independence of Ukraine. Today the latter are dying of cold and starvation. In Eastern <pb facs="5425703_0768.jpg" n="2"/>Galicia and all over Ukraine we see utter poverty and starvation. In Eastern Galicia as well as all over Ukraine nothing but gloom, pauperism and starvation is to be found. Who is to help them? We! Other people will not take care of our nation.</p>
   <p>We Sitch members of Chicago and abroad, should take example from our forefathers Zaporoztsi. By this time we should have already 100,000 Sitch members right here in America, but alas, we are far below this desired number.</p>
   <p>Ukrainian Cossacks Zaporoztsi advanced through water and fire, by land and sea, in order to free their countrymen from Turkish and Tartaric slavery, and what are we doing in a similar case? We must help our countrymen to drive out the enemy from our native land. Otherwise, we shall not be worthy of the name of followers of the famous Cossacks as long as we do not do our sacred duty to our brothers over there.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0769.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our brothers and sisters are dying of starvation in the Polish prisons and under the Polish yoke. Shall we look at these criminal perpetrations with indifference? If so, then we are unworthy to even belong to the Sitch organization.</p>
   <p>Ukraine is one of the richest countries, in many natural resources, in the whole world. It is our sacred duty to take our own native country out of the hands of the enemy and become ourselves masters in our homeland. To accomplish this we must solidly unite into one unbroken chain with one aim and slogan: Away with the enemy from our country. Let us get to work. Let us establish Sitch branches in every place where such as yet are not existing. By being united in Sitch organizations it will give us strength and prestige and help to drive away the enemy. This we have to bring to a successful end, and the sooner the better, because we do not intend to continue dying in agony under the Polish yoke.</p>
   <p>Look, brothers! Poland is sinking deeper and deeper every day and we are sure <pb facs="5425703_0770.jpg" n="4"/>she will fall apart. All we have to do at the present time is to give her a good swift kick, and in driving her away we must take our country into our own hands.</p>
   <p>Let us first unite into one front and the rest shall be added unto us. Therefore, let us unite and thus show the world that there is unity and strength in us, whereby they will sanction our aim, and fully recognize our freedom and independence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
