<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
<date when="1935-04-14">Apr. 14, 1935</date> Vol. 1-No. 21.
<title level="a">"U. H. O. Takes Communion."</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainian Youth</title>,
<date when="1935-04-14">Apr. 14, 1935</date> Vol. 1-No. 21.
<title level="a">"U. H. O. TAKES COMMUNION."</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the emigration of our people to this country began, there were only three Ukrainian Bishops, all in our native land. Today, however, there are six; four in Ukraine, one in United States, and the sixth, Rt. Rev. Basil Ladyka of Canada. At the present time his excellency has been visiting at our St. Nichols Church. His visit although of short duration is very helpful on account of his interesting and educational sermons.</p>
   <p>The United Hetman Organization, generally known to the youth as U. H. O., has last week proven that they not only will wear their motto "God and Our Country" inscribed on their membership pins but will also live up to it. They all on the order of Nakazne Ataman, Doctor Tarnawsky, went to communion.</p>
   <p>Seeing that Rt. Rev. Basil Ladyka was here for a brief stay, Dr. Tarnawsky (who is at the head of all the U.H.O's. in the U.S. and Canada) asked his excellency to serve mass. At this sermon he promised his excellency that the whole U.H.O. of the St. Nicholas Parish would take communion. His promise, as everyone who attended mass last Sunday at 8:00 A.M. knows, was carried out. Company 3 (the newly organized company, consisting of young <pb facs="5425703_0523.jpg" n="2"/>boys ranking from 16 to 19 years of age) was there a hundred percent. Everyone accepting communion in their uniforms. Much color was added to the scene by the Blue and Gold capes. Other companies were also represented, although the uniform representation was a trifle smaller percentage.</p>
   <p>After the mass all of the U.H.O. members went down to the church hall where refreshments were served. To this; his excellency, was also invited. While the refreshments were being served he was asked by Okruzni Ataman Nicholas Moranets to give a little talk. His excellency accepted, saying that this occassion really called for a long talk (that is if he really was to express his feeling in full) but due to the fact that the high mass was to start in a short time he would make it brief. He said that he was happy to serve mass and give communion to all the U.H.O. members. He also told of a similar case in Canada, at which everyone; doctors, lawers, engineers and communion together.</p>
   <p>Next to be asked to talk was Dr. Tarnawsky. He, in his talk, thanked his excellency for giving communion to all the U.H.O. members and also stressed <pb facs="5425703_0524.jpg" n="3"/>the point that without God, Ukraine shall never live. If every Ukrainian went to communion, it wouldn't be long before the Ukrainian Flag would be carried along by the side of others. At the present time it is carried by us but does not stand for an independent country as others do. Our's stands for a country striving for it's independence. The only way it can free itself is through God. As many of you might have read in a series of articles on the famine in Ukraine about a starving woman, when asked of what she thought, she replied, that she would want the Hetman back. As you can readily see, even though she was starving she still had God, and her country in mind. She knew that with the hetman, our country would survive.</p>
   <p>Later company 3 members were presented by Okruzni Ataman, N. Moranets with bars of merit for their services last year in guarding the Holy Sepulcher. The following received the bars of merit: Capt. N. Matviuw, Serg. M. Dytko, E. Masowick, M. Tymush, J. Prietula, and P. Wojciechowski. I am sure every one of those bars were earned by everyone and here's hoping that they will earn many more. By the way, Easter is only two weeks away and our young company 3 will again stand guard at the Holy Sepulcher.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
