<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
<date when="1930-08-08">Aug. 8, 1930</date>, Vol. 1, No. 9.
<title level="a">"Ukranian Chicago". "Ukrainian National Choir Appears in Musical Contest"</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukrainia, (Ukraine)</title>,
<date when="1930-08-08">Aug. 8, 1930</date>, Vol. 1, No. 9.
<title level="a">"UKRANIAN CHICAGO". "UKRAINIAN NATIONAL CHOIR APPEARS IN MUSICAL CONTEST"</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ukrainian National Choir, under the direction of Yuriy Benetzky, known not only to the Ukrainians, but also to American public in Chicago, through his previous musical entertainments, in concerts, and operas.</p>
   <p>This choir, for the first time in Chicago, has shown a very nice opera, "Kateryna", of M. Arcas, with a great success, which was given two times in succession during one month.</p>
   <p>The Ukrainian National Choir is composed of members, who love to sing, and are under the well-experienced direction of Mr. Benetzky; it sings with real musical accomplishment.</p>
   <p>The aim of this choir, is to get the American people acquainted with our wonderful songs, and in this way, to advertise the Ukrainian name. For this reason, the said choir has decided to appear in the musical contest, which is arranged by the largest American newspaper, The Chicago Daily Tribune.</p>
   <p>In this contest, there take part, choirs, violin orchestras, bugles, and also soloists.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0230.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All choirs must step out with one American song, selected for a choir or orchestra. The Ukrainian National Choir has decided to take part in the contest, to try its luck, and also to let the other people know that there are Ukrainians, who love singing, and who wish to get the palm in the field of song.</p>
   <p>The preliminary appearances, will be held in a Balaban and Katz theatre, (the first class theatre in Chicago), and on August 23rd, on Saturday afternoon, at Soldiers Field, which contains 100,000 seats.</p>
   <p>Other dates, on which the choir will appear, will be stated in the following numbers of Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>We feel that it is our duty, to state the names of the singers, who take part in the contest, for they deserve acknowledgment for their work in the spreading of the Ukrainian song. Also, our Ukrainians in Chicago should help this choir to maintain itself, by their subscriptions, and by so doing, they will show their good will toward the Ukrainian purpose. The Choir is holding its trials in the evening, on Mondays, and Thursdays, at 2048 West Chicago Avenue, and it is composed of the following: There are 32 members in the choir, and 8 members, who financially help to keep the choir in existence. It is necessary, that the Ukrainian business-men, <pb facs="5425703_0231.jpg" n="3"/>and profession-men, get more interested in the choir, and then our song will thunder to us in the American halls, and it will be able to get a permanent place on a radio. But it needs everybody's help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
