<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1929-05-01">May 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">[Ukrainian Director's Band Victor in Chicago High School Contest]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1929-05-01">May 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">[UKRAINIAN DIRECTOR'S BAND VICTOR IN CHICAGO HIGH SCHOOL CONTEST]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The accomplishments of John Barabash as director of the band at the Harrison High School are highly acclaimed.</p>
   <p>On Apr 12 of this year a band contest was held in the Harrison High School auditorium, at 24th Street and Marshall Boulevard, in which the bands of six of the leading high schools of Chicago participated, namely, Tilden, Fenger, Lindbloom, Harrison, Schurz and Lake View; the directors of these bands were Messrs. Burnham, Baglia, King, Bartley, Barabash, Reid, and Voltz.</p>
   <p>The contest was held under the auspices of the Chicago Public School Band Society. The Harrison High School Band, the leader of which, Captain John Barabash is one of our prominent Ukrainians, won first prize in this contest. Each of the above-mentioned bands had to play selected marches.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0179.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>overtures, and other compositions. The second prize was awarded to the Lake View High School Band, and the third to Tilden.</p>
   <p>The judges of the contest were Mr. Victor Grable, director of the Sherwood Music School, Glen C. Baynan, director of the Music School of Northwestern University, and the composer and instrumentalist Clay Smith.</p>
   <p>We take this opportunity to congratulate our countryman Captain John Barabash on his accomplishment. Captain Barabash is a loyal Ukrainian patriot and a true member of the Sitch organization. May God bless him!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
