<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 5, <date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">To the Ukrainian Women and Girls in Chicago and Suburbs</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>UKRAINA</title>,
Vol. III, No. 5, <date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE UKRAINIAN WOMEN AND GIRLS IN CHICAGO AND SUBURBS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enemy is destroying our native land. Our fathers, our husbands and our brothers are dying from bullets, fire, and in jails, and our mothers and our sisters are dying from starvation, and disease. Do we, Ukrainian women and girls have to sit still and only by crying soothe our wounded hearts.</p>
   <p>No! Once again no!</p>
   <p>It is the duty of our tender women to help our native country in its misfortunes.</p>
   <p>This we have to do with combined strength of all the women in America - then our help will be useful and effective in these times of needs.</p>
   <p>Let us take other nations into consideration, how their women work and help their native land and its nation.</p>
   <p>We see everywhere, the Czech, Slovak, Polish, womens' organizations in America. Have they not taken practically all the burdens of their native country upon <pb facs="5425703_0113.jpg" n="2"/>themselves and done it very sincerely and eagerly?</p>
   <p>The same should be done by the Ukrainian women in America for our Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>Our second obligation - which already is flowing from our womens' soul and brains - is, that with their might they strive to raise women in the eyes of civilization, so that women receive the same rights as men in their private community, and political life. When the women of all nations become experienced, educated, and will take the same part in community and political life, then surely there will be no wars, there will be none of these misfortunes and destruction, which wars bring upon us.</p>
   <p>A woman, educated, and with the same rights endowed, will ennoble the commonalty and lead it to a real human progress.</p>
   <p>We want to lead Ukrainia to true progress.</p>
   <p>In order that the Ukrainian women may fulfill these two obligations, they have to join the women's organizations and societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0114.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One person alone seldom did reach or found anything big in the world. In organization there is strength, which can surmount most difficulties in doing big things.</p>
   <p>In our immigration in the United States, there is one womens' organization, namely, "Union of the Ukrainian Women."</p>
   <p>The women's union decided in the very beginning to be profitable to everybody, in the form of a benefit organization, therefore the greatest possible number of our Ukrainian women, in the whole territory of the United States, where our immigrants live, should unite under its banner.</p>
   <p>Besides its clean human program - giving moral and material aid to its members in times of misfortune and grief,- "The Union of Ukrainian Women in America" resolved itself to carry out chief ideal undertakings:</p>
   <p>(a) To spread education among the Ukrainian women and girls;</p>
   <p>(b) To educate our women as to their obligations in their social and community rights.</p>
   <p>The task of the women's society is to put Ukrainian women and girls in America in <pb facs="5425703_0115.jpg" n="4"/>a position wherein she can carry out every phase of the national work.</p>
   <p>Dear Sisters!</p>
   <p>"Organize and unite yourselves for the big cause! " Organize womens' societies and join in throngs the "Union of Ukrainian Women in America."</p>
   <p>The opportune time has come when the women cannot sit any longer afraid, with their hands crossed, but must act as a live and worthy human being that wants to take part in the broader life of this wide world.</p>
   <p>A big and honorable reward for all the women's efforts, so also for you, Ukrainian sisters, will be this strong center, to which all the true Ukrainian women and girls in America will add their strength to the mass work of the "Union of Ukrainian Women in America".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
