<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Program the Fair of Sorotschintzi</title><title level="a">A Musical Comedy in four acts by the Ukrainian Chorus of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">George Benetsky- Conductor Maria Mashir - Stage Director Sunday, October 14th, 1934 Sabin School Auditorium Hirsch and Leavitt St</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>PROGRAM THE FAIR OF SOROTSCHINTZI</title><title level="a">A Musical Comedy in four acts by the UKRAINIAN CHORUS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">George Benetsky- Conductor Maria Mashir - Stage Director Sunday, October 14th, 1934 Sabin School Auditorium Hirsch and Leavitt St</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ukrainian Chorus of Chicago presents The Fair of Sorotschintzi, Libretto - Starytsky after Gogol; Music, Mussorgsky and Shvedoff. Characters:</p>
   <p>Cherevick, a farmer - Mr. Mazurick;</p>
   <p>Khivrya, his wife - Miss Machir;</p>
   <p>Khotyna, his daughter - Miss Winarski;</p>
   <p>Tsybula, also a farmer - Mr. Kostiv;</p>
   <p>Mokryna, his wife - Mrs. Kulpack;</p>
   <p>Panko, Khotyna's lover - Mr. Revak;</p>
   <p>Prechystynsky, a seminarian - Mr. Domanshuk;</p>
   <p>Khenko, a gypsy - Mr. Yendzeyowsky;</p>
   <p>Hrunya, his daughter - Miss Wizerkaniuk</p>
   <p>Stas, a lad - Mr. Paslowsky;</p>
   <p>also</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0214.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Girls, Boys, Gypsies, Vendors, Soloists, Gypsy and Hopak Dancers.</p>
   <p>Synopsis:</p>
   <p>A farmer comes to the Sorotschintzi Country Fair with his wife and a lovely young daughter by a former marriage, whom he intends to marry off to a priest's son. The girl's stepmother supports this plan, since the priest's son is her lover and she sees the opportunity to continue her affair after the marriage. But the girl has a sweetheart of her own choice, who, with the help of a gypsy horse-dealer, contrives to defeat this plan and to marry the girl himself. The cunning gypsy recalls a popular superstition about the Sorotschintzi Fair to the effect that the devil, who had once lost an expensive red coat in the fair grounds, returns each year to look for it in the guise of a pig on long, stilt-like legs. Taking advantage of this superstition, the gypsy and the girl's sweetheart succeed in terrorizing the people into believing that the fair grounds are haunted by the devil. In the panic which ensues, they frame the girl's father, accusing him of horse stealing, having him arrested, tied and thrown into a barn, where he remains over night. They also catch the <pb facs="5425703_0215.jpg" n="3"/>stepmother in a compromising situation with the priest's son, and treat them in a similar manner. In the morning they offer to release the prisoner and suppress the evidence of their guilt on the promise that they will consent to the girl's marriage to the sweetheart of her choice. The prisoners agree to this, are released, and the marriage takes place amid merry festivities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
