<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1922-08">Aug. 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Ukrainians to Organize a Youth Siege Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-08">Aug. 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO UKRAINIANS TO ORGANIZE A YOUTH SIEGE COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several months ago, a movement was started in Chicago to organize a Siege Company comprised of young people between eighteen and thirty-five years of age. For one reason or another, this necessary work was somehow neglected until the present time.</p>
   <p>On July 24, the youth gathered at the Oakley and Rice Street Hall, for the sole purpose of organizing the youth Siege company.</p>
   <p>The meeting was presided over by D. Zabolotsky. After a short explanation, questions and discussion followed as to the conditions and obligations required and expected of those who wished to join this new company.</p>
   <p>Dr. S. K. Hrynevetsky, chief executive of the organization ardently encouraged those present, who were within the age limit, to join the company.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0435.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Vivid discussion, which showed great enthusiasm for the movement, took so long that they did not have enough time to complete their main business. Therefore, the meeting was adjourned until next Monday.</p>
   <p>On July 31, a similiar meeting took place at the Citizens' Club. Chief executive Dr. Hrynevetsky and general financial secretary John Shkraba were present.</p>
   <p>At this time persons joined the newly organized company. After this Dr. Hrynevetsky and the general financial secretary congratulated the newly organized branch and wished them the best of luck in their future work.</p>
   <p>The following were elected as temporary officers: F. Vasilovsky, captain; N. Motliuk, general secretary.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the newly organized group should be called T. Bulba <pb facs="5425703_0436.jpg" n="3"/>[Siege] Company.</p>
   <p>Among other motions and decisions of lesser importance, they decided and encouraged every member of the company to be an organizer and thus help make it a strong company.</p>
   <p>Nicholas Motliuk</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
