<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1919-06">June, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Where We Aim</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>RANNA ZORYA, (Morning Star)</title>,
Vol. I, No. 1, <date when="1919-06">June, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE WE AIM</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Besides all the explaining on the part of the organizers of the "Ukrainian Women's Alliance of America", our Ukrainians either do not understand, or do not care to understand us. Even our women do not have a clear view as to where we are going and what are we striving for.</p>
   <p>We, the Ukrainian women, resolve, conforming to the views of the women of other civilized nations, to build our own temple, where only the women will be the masters of their own ideas and work; where amidst the clean women's atmosphere we shall raise and uncover our ways of living, our thoughts, longings and our will.</p>
   <p>Here we shall be able to learn, discuss, and share properly the needs of nature, object and character suitable for our women's mission and obligations.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of ourselves, the community and the nation, we want, for all we are worth, to have full rights.</p>
   <p>The field, on which we began our work, stood neglected for many years. No wonder, <pb facs="5425703_0142.jpg" n="2"/>therefore, that our work is going so slow. That is why we came across various obstacles; that is why there is not enough willing hands to work. Still, let us not pay attention to this, but go forward. Even though with trouble, but diligently, thoughtfully and patiently let us push aside from under our feet the obstacles, such as: prejudice, unwillingness, distrust, malice, ignorance and backing out.</p>
   <p>The means of acquiring our aim is not only the aim of ourselves but that of our women's organization, which is founded on benefit grounds. The name of this organization is "Ukrainian Women's Alliance of America".</p>
   <p>Those opposing our organization say, that our organization has its aim to disrupt the existing benefit associations, of which there are enough in America, and through this neither of them will ever be able to rise to a high financial level. They naturally give advice to back the women's organization on true educational grounds, without any benefit basis. He who knows the history of our immigration will be able to discover that among our people in America such associations grew faster, when they were backed on some financial (benefit or insurance) grounds.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is why the organizers of the women's organization decided to gather the women in this type of a society, which by experience made the best progress here in America.</p>
   <p>Money paid for insurance is not wasted but is a banked capital for a good interest.</p>
   <p>In Europe the father leaves his family land. Here in America the working class has no land to leave for their children. The lack of other assurance is substituted by insurance. In other nationalities every member of the family is insured, not only the parents. Big American rich men, even though they have enough money, in addition to it insure themselves for a large sum. If the insurance was a waste of money, as you can often-times hear among our people, then thoughtful people would not insure themselves; still they act on the contrary. The unthoughtful back out of it, as if it were an evil.</p>
   <p>We again state, that though we value the good points of insurance, the financial assurance is not the only aim of the "Ukrainian Women's Alliance of America". There is an additional aim, which is the main object of our program, namely, the enlightment <pb facs="5425703_0144.jpg" n="4"/>of our women, and the gathering our women for the national and community work. This is our main purpose, and this is the plan we are determined to follow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
