<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-03-17">Mar. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Letter of Acknowledgment to the Chief Executive's Office of the Siege Organization, Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-03-17">Mar. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">LETTER OF ACKNOWLEDGMENT TO THE CHIEF EXECUTIVE'S OFFICE OF THE SIEGE ORGANIZATION, CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I am sure that you must have received by now my letter of acknowledgment and thanks to you for the substantial donation of six hundred dollars for the unfortunate ex-soldiers, whom ill fate has cast out of their own native country, for which they fought.</p>
   <p>This, your good will donation, is constantly before my eyes, because it shows the actual fact that for the past few years how steadily you have felt an increasing sense of responsibility toward the nation as a whole. It is high time I let the world know of your noble activities, especially from the time your great Siege organization so widely developed pro-national tendencies. This activity not only woke up the old from inertia, but also the women, and even the youth became tireless workers in the direction of the national organizations. They do not spare either spiritual, moral, or physical support, in full awareness of the fact that only in this way <pb facs="5425703_0345.jpg" n="2"/>the Ukrainian nation will win its independence and free its native land from under the yoke of the enemy.</p>
   <p>My words can hardly express to you my joy in learning from your letter, wherein the donation of six hundred dollars was enclosed for our unfortunate brothers, whom ill fate has cast out of their native land to foreign lands, that this sum was collected by B. Chmelnitsky Siege Branch No. 15 alone, including its two collateral groups of older women and the youth. When our youth is already so filled with firely love toward their misfortunate brothers that they are ready to give them aid and help to defend their people and their native land then our faith becomes far greater for a better and brighter future for our Ukrainian people and thereby we are much stronger and closer to the goal of freeing our nation from under the enemy's yoke.</p>
   <p>Hail to your glorious youth! Their youthful zeal inspires us and those whose faith after a long struggle in fighting for freedom may have weakened <pb facs="5425703_0346.jpg" n="3"/>somewhat. Your youth wakes up the sleepy and commands them: "Unite into one national front and with greater determination against the cursed enemy."</p>
   <p>May these, my words, come as a further inspiration and guidance to your glorious youth to continue its splendid work through which it will win the favor and thanks of all Ukrainian people. Of course, my former letters of thanks to you also include your organized youth.</p>
   <p>Your humble servant,</p>
   <p>Dr. Small - Stotsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
