<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1933-08-12">Aug. 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Ukrainian Catholic Youth Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1933-08-12">Aug. 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">UKRAINIAN CATHOLIC YOUTH CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A throng, aged and weary, passes along a descending road. Day after day a few from this throng enter the yawning jaws of the world beyond, their tasks completed, while the duties of the others gradually come to their conclusion.</p>
   <p>Along another highway a new multitude moves uphill to a successfully-reached goal. This group is confident, cheerful, energetic, and capable in all the tasks it undertakes. These are the youths who walk with heads held high, with buoyant swinging steps, and with shining eyes gazing far into a bright future. Yet, a fear and sorrow grips us, for we see that this young group is not in one great body or unit but instead is steadily being separated as it marches along--a few constantly straying into bypaths from which they never return.</p>
   <p>This is what is happening to the young folk of Ukrainian blood, but we must not allow it, for their powers are too precious and valuable to be wasted upon <pb facs="5425703_0545.jpg" n="2"/>countries and people who do not require their aid. It is our Ukraine which needs these youths, because of the fact that the older generation is steadily passing away.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is necessary to centralize this young life lest it be forgotten that we are Ukrainians, and that a Ukrainian spirit must prevail among all. For this worthy cause a convention of Ukrainian-American and Ukrainian-Canadian Catholic youths has been called for August 19 of this year in Chicago. All organizations and clubs are requested to co-operate by sending delegates to represent their particular group. It is desired that all local groups organize into one great body and work together both now and in the future.</p>
   <p>In localities which have no youth organization, the committee of the convention asks that delegates be sent to represent the youth of each locality. The program of the convention has been printed in preceding publications, but if anyone seeks information concerning the convention or desires to volunteer his services, whether by lecturing, participating in the oratorical contest, or <pb facs="5425703_0546.jpg" n="3"/>offering suggestions, it is suggested that he write to the committee of the convention, U.-A. &amp; U.-C. C. Y. C. [Ukrainian-American and Ukrainian-Canadian Catholic Youth Convention], 2238 West Rice Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
