<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Nash Styah (Our Banner)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-13">Oct. 13, 1934</date><title level="a">Ukrainian Youth Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Appeal by the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0662</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0662.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Nash Styah (Our Banner)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-13">Oct. 13, 1934</date><title level="a">UKRAINIAN YOUTH MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Appeal by the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We address the following appeal to the young Ukrainian men and women of the United States and Canada, and to their fathers and mothers: Help us form one Ukrainian youth front in the United States and Canada; help us in our endeavor, so that every young Ukrainian may belong to some local sport, cultural, art, or professional club affiliated with the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League.</p>
   <p>This League was formed in Chicago in August 1933, and is in its second year of existence. Through the co-operation of the various member societies the League began to issue its own organ--a twenty-four page journal, 8 by 11 inches--which received great acclaim from those people who know the value of such a journal. In addition the League has communicated with the societies of the Ukrainian Youth League in our native country and with Catholic organizations of other nations, <pb facs="5425703_0663.jpg" n="2"/>The Ukrainian youth could very soom create a united front by becoming members of their local societies, and by these local societies becoming members of the Ukrainian Youth League. The Ukrainian youth of the United States and Canada would then profit from the movement on the one hand, and, on the other hand, the League would become an effective force among its own people and the people of other nations. Therefore, those societies and clubs that do not as yet belong to the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League are urged to announce their Ukrainian character by joining. We urge those young, energetic men and women who live in localities having no youth club to establish one of their own and to announce its affiliation with the League. We also urge the fathers and mothers not to regret spending a little of their time or money in helping their children in this significant and essential work, but rather to encourage them to become members of the League and at the same time to work for their fatherland and their church.</p>
   <p>Subscribe to the publication Ukrainian Youth both for yourself and your children. This journal is written in both Ukrainian and English, and <pb facs="5425703_0664.jpg" n="3"/>the subscription rate is $1.50 per year.</p>
   <p>With autumn already here and winter pressing close on our heels, the time for organizational work is at hand, Therefore, all you active and ambitious young gentlemen, work for a united front! To the League and for the League!</p>
   <p>We ask everyone of you to write us about your local community conditions and needs, and to write for further information about the League. All communications will be answered.</p>
   <p>From the Executive Committee of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League</p>
   <p>Bohdan Katemay, president</p>
   <p>August Skoropad, corresponding secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
