<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
<date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Ukraine Before, During and after the World War Interesting Sidelights on the Ukrainian Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
<date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">UKRAINE BEFORE, DURING AND AFTER THE WORLD WAR INTERESTING SIDELIGHTS ON THE UKRAINIAN QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last decades before the World War, the Ukrainian question achieved an importance in Eastern European politics which added further tension to the rocking structure of European peace. The war, and the peace that followed, altered, but did not settle this question, which remains a momentous issue in Europe.</p>
   <p>The extinction of the Ukrainian Cossack independence in the 17th and 18th centuries, and the Polonization and Russification of the Ukrainian nobility left the spark of nationalism submerged and apparently extinguished in the mass of unlettered peasants. Due largely to the efforts of the church, the sparks remained alive, to be fanned into a considerable flame when the winds of nationalism swept across Europe in the 19th century. The Guild of Saints Cyril and Methodius, founded in Kiev in 1846 by a group of Ukrainian writers to promote the movement, was suppressed within a year by the government of Nicholas I. From that time on the tsarist authorities treated the use of the Ukrainian language in literary or historical publications as a dangerous political activity, to be ruthlessly <pb facs="5425703_0727.jpg" n="2"/>suppressed.</p>
   <p>"The Ukrainian language," said Valujev, minister of interior in 1863, "never has existed, does not exist, and must not exist." How any man holding such a responsible position could make a statement such as this, in which he contradicts himself, is beyond comprehension. First he claimed that the Ukrainian language never existed, and then he had the audacity to turn right around and say that the Ukrainian language must not exist. Anyone with common sense would say either that Valujev did not know what he was talking about, or that he realized what the continuance of the Ukrainian language would mean to the peace of the Russian Empire.</p>
   <p>During the World War, the United States government was interested in establishing order in the Ukraine. Charles J. Vopicka, United States Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Rumania, Serbia and Bulgaria, saw a chance for doing this. Over 200,000 Russian soldiers and officers wanted to enlist in the American army for small pay. Vopicka cabled the American government that a force of 200,000 fighting <pb facs="5425703_0728.jpg" n="3"/>Russians could be enlisted at the front to establish order in the Ukraine and to effectually check the rising tide of Bolshevism. He begged for immediate approval of this plan, and action to finance the organization, but the approval came too late. The willing Russians had already left the front to return to their homes.</p>
   <p>Had this plan been put into operation, this large army could have been organized and thrown into the teeth of Bolshevism, and history would have been spared the frightful record of subsequent events. Ukrainia would have been saved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
