<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 33, <date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The First Ukrainian Factory in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 33, <date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST UKRAINIAN FACTORY IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This page is dedicated to the Ukrainian economic advancement in the United States.</p>
   <p>It is good to see a Ukrainian being welcomed in the technical field. The first Ukrainian factory in Chicago is the property of the Ukrainian corporation, the Endless-Graph Manufacturing Company, 4200-2 W. Adams St., Chicago. They manufacture electric phonographs combined with electric lamps. </p>
   <p>This is a real Ukrainian invention. The inventor of this phonograph is Mr. Peter R. Gonsky. Here we can say with pleasure that we are proud of this invention. The conditions of this corporation were very discouraging for a short time in 1918. During the following year it began to improve and received orders for over $150,000. Up to this time, orders came mostly from American firms which undertook the selling of these phonographs.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0165.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We urge the directors of this corporation to instruct our Ukrainians to be more interested in the economic field, for this is the only way to help indirectly the Ukrainian national cause. We ask you to turn your attention to other nations that concern themselves with technical inventions. To rank high financially and economically, and play a big role in the world's politics should be the aim of Ukrainians. We should not be content to remain behind. We should leave off quarrels and bickerings among ourselves and strive to establish clean Ukrainian enterprises, cooperatives, savings banks, etc. When we are stronger economically and industrially, should any one of us return to his native country, these enterprises could be left in the hands of our countrymen and not go into the hands of outsiders.</p>
   <p>In the end we say that capital does not make people, but people make capital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
