<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
<date when="1919-07">July, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ranna Zorya (Morning Star)</title>,
<date when="1919-07">July, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In many states of the United States, the women have become equal with the men in politics. However, this change in politics has caught many of them unprepared for this work.</p>
   <p>Many women do not profit by their citizenship rights. It is a pity! The women could add much to the welfare of the community with their votes. Every person must go hand-in-hand with modern thoughts and living, without looking back to see if he or she like it or not. One who does not wish the masses to cross his path in his daily life,must go ahead with it. The wives and mothers must, sooner or later, come out of the kitchen from which they seldom emerge.</p>
   <p>They must come out into the wide world.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They must take an interest in community affairs.</p>
   <p>They must view for themselves the ill fate and sufferings of the great masses.</p>
   <p>They must be able to distinguish the good from the bad of community life.</p>
   <p>They must sacrifice part of their lives working for their families, and part for their community and nation.</p>
   <p>The women, in time, will have to become friends of their husbands, as well as friends of their community and nation. The mother must know thoroughly the life and needs of the community, and its good and bad points, so as to uplift one and remedy the other. In view of the radical changes in the lives of the women in these extraordinary times, they must be acquainted with a wide range of thoughts. In our large communities our women do not <pb facs="5425703_0139.jpg" n="3"/>fully appreciate this important phase of life.</p>
   <p>At our public meetings, our elections, and our lectures one observes that few Ukrainian women attend. The presence of more women at these public gatherings should be the first step for them to take to become acquainted with the work they must do. A woman who can but does not care to become acquainted with affairs in the community, is a hindrance to the development of the nation.</p>
   <p>The women of other cultured nationalities take an active part in political and national life.</p>
   <p>In the state of Kansas 200 women were elected to various offices.</p>
   <p>In the state of Michigan 350,000 women voted. In the city of Chicago alone, nearly 200,000 women voted. However, these votes showed no result, <pb facs="5425703_0140.jpg" n="4"/>because the women had not as yet become educated in this field, so as to go together with the present politicians, but followed rather blindly the voting machine. It seems that the American women do not as yet realize the full advantages it brings to the community.</p>
   <p>Yet, in the near future, there will come a time when women will determine by their votes whether we must tolerate chiseling, cheating, bribing, and hoarding of money by a few, at the expense of many on the one hand, and the bartering of the very lives, health, and work of the poor on the other hand.</p>
   <p>He who wishes to correct evil, must go to its very source. And to know this, one is required to take an active part in community life, and to share the common interest in everything that the community and the nation must contend with.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
