<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1929-02-15">Feb. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Help for Our Ridna Shkola (Native School) in Europe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1929-02-15">Feb. 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HELP FOR OUR RIDNA SHKOLA (NATIVE SCHOOL) IN EUROPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The matter of helping our native schools in Europe has interested many of our Ukrainians in Chicago. Our group here always has helped our brothers and sisters across the sea. That is why we invited the delegate of the native school, Mr. Leo Yasinchuk, to stop in this city and inform our group about the conditions of Ukrainian life in the old country, particularly about the activities of our native schools. Mr. Yasinchuk accepted our invitation and delivered his lecture in the parish hall at Oakley Avenue and Rice Street, again on the South Side, and again in West Pullman.</p>
   <p>The members of these groups assembled and listened with great enthusiasm to the words which our native brothers and sisters addressed to them through the lips of their representative. After listening to the lecture our groups did not stop there but instead reached into their pockets and contributed toward the welfare of the native schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We saw every one give, not because they had to, or because they expected to receive praise; they all gave sincerely from their hearts because they understood the importance of the native school and its struggles. The amount collected at these lectures totaled two thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The Ukrainian District Committee of Chicago and Suburbs takes this opportunity to thank all the donors who so generously contributed to so worthy a cause as that of our native schools in Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
