<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 41, <date when="1919-11-15">Nov. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">To Patriots for Consideration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In Chicago and all over the United States)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0805</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0805.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 41, <date when="1919-11-15">Nov. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TO PATRIOTS FOR CONSIDERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In Chicago and all over the United States)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Ah, nobody is as happy as the young cossack is."</p>
   <p>Indeed these few words can be applied to the present circumstances, in which almost the whole Ukrainian nation finds itself. A tramp alone is expected not to make anything out of it; his heart will surely not be bleeding over the downfall of the general all-Ukrainian affairs of the Ukrainians in America. Why is it so? Because a tramp is loafing, walking aimlessly from place to place, and therefore does not look deep into the hearts of the Ukrainian "politicians" who are tools in the hands of our "leaders."</p>
   <p>At one time there appeared all sorts of articles published that called upon the nation to unity. Now one, now another political party wanted <pb facs="5425703_0806.jpg" n="2"/>us to join their ranks. Each one of them promised everything possible to help us to attain the independence of Ukrainia; to give help to our poor enslaved brothers and sisters in the old country. The slogans of one or the other party did not fall like the grain on the stone, but fell on sensitive hearts, and everyone tried to contribute as much as he possibly could.</p>
   <p>But there was nothing wrong in it. Soon the offerings were directed to purposes to which the people assigned. I shall not enlarge on that whether or not the offerings went to their destined place. I have in mind to divulge the consequences which are being felt due to not sufficiently enlightened and rather blind partisans.</p>
   <p>A good number of people, to whom the good of the Mother Ukrainia is not only at heart, but they almost can not imagine Ukrainia as an enslaved state, so they group themselves, hold meetings, and think <pb facs="5425703_0807.jpg" n="3"/>time and again and plan on what would be the most expedient way to group together all the Ukrainians under one banner, under one slogan: "Help the native country." After having made definite plans, they call together a larger number of people, they reveal their thoughts, and all of them like one agree on the proposition.</p>
   <p>To this group comes and joins another group, etc., until all of them are of the same mind. However, it would be better by far, if the partisan misunderstanding would be entirely and once for all discarded and all of them took to work for common good, and no Ukrainian should decline to act in that direction, especially to give moral and a material assistance to the native country.</p>
   <p>The heart leaped for joy in every Ukrainian, when he saw how all of them together, regardless of religious or political persuasion, attended meetings and gatherings, took part in discussions and exchanged their ideas and experiences: they united themselves in order to expand the work of good will. It seemed that from now on there peace will <pb facs="5425703_0808.jpg" n="4"/>be established among us against which no hostile force shall prevail. And indeed no hostile force could shatter us in performing our determined work. This incident will be present in our mind till our very death, and we shall glibly entertain thoughts about it and hand them over to our children, as if it were a miracle, that all the Ukrainians in Chicago and in the United States, full-heartedly tended toward the one aim.</p>
   <p>Yet, how long did it last? After several months a few political bigots, who could not see further than their party, started their irrational movement. Seeing that the people were gladly contributing, and that the sum was swelling considerably, they wanted to distribute that money, not among their enslaved brothers and sisters who beg for help, but to send it over to their party, so that the party would promulgate the names of the bigots in heavy type - for they want to be shown how big they are - and could show to the public that they <pb facs="5425703_0809.jpg" n="5"/>are the holders of the receipt from the money. And as to their brothers and sisters living in the old country - what of it - let them die of cold and starvation, let them cry for help as much as they want to, they (the bigots) do not hear the cry from across the ocean.</p>
   <p>Do not worry, however, dear brothers and sisters! Not all the people of ours are of this type! Before long those ambitious criers will stop their bigotry; their foggy heads will clear out and they will come back to themselves and see their grave mistake. Deep within their hearts they are as generous and as good as the rest of the Ukrainians, and therefore they will soon understand that we could rather stand the decline of our institutions in the United States than the downfall of our Motherland.</p>
   <p>When our Mother Ukrainia becomes a free and independent state, she will not forget us in our needs, provided we help her now, provided we support her now. She does not need our pecuniary help for political <pb facs="5425703_0810.jpg" n="6"/>purposes, either at home or abroad but she needs and expects of us her sons and daughters a moral and material support for reconstructing purposes.</p>
   <p>The finest moral support we can offer to our Mother Ukrainia is when we all group ourselves together, and leave out once for all all sorts of misunderstandings, negative criticisms, and dissensions, and stand shoulder to shoulder to fight the enemy. Thereby we shall give a living example to our brothers and sisters in the old country and thus show them what they have to do to win liberty, freedom and independence for Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>We shall help Mother Ukrainia then, when we hurry to dispatch not only money, but also clothes and food. Therewith we shall strengthen their spirits, which are weakened in them through sufferings of cold and starvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0811.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Let us leave the political field to diplomatic missions who are existing in all countries. Let us help them by sending our protests and urgent requests to state officials; everywhere let us arrange local protesting manifestations, protesting meetings, and let us promulgate this among the Americans and other nations.</p>
   <p>We think that our diplomatic mission does not need any money from us, but in case they would require of us what Ukrainian would there be but would contribute for the purpose.</p>
   <p>In unity there is strength. Therefore, let us do everything with a united front; let us not permit any dissension to creep in; let us not look around asking what does the majority want or what the minority does not want, but let us act in such a way that all unanimously would agree upon our propositions. And when we act thus, do not worry, Ukrainia! No hostile power in this world can sweep thee away; no enemy shall prevail thee, and the Ukrainian nation is assured of coming up to the very top in Europe.</p>
   <p>Yaroslaw Burlachenko.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
