<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Ukrainian Youth</title>
      <date when="1935-10">Oct. 1935</date>
      <title level="a">"Appeal to the Youth"</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Ukrainian Youth</title>
     <date when="1935-10">Oct. 1935</date>
     <title level="a">"APPEAL TO THE YOUTH"</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Fifty years have I waited for this thing to happen".</p>
   <p>Incredible as this statement seems, it is true. The Ukrainian immigration in America has waited for about fifty years for the First Congress of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth. Fifty years is a long time to wait, but the waiting was not in vein; for August 19, 1933 the Congress that can boast of the most outstanding outcome was held in Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>At the first congress of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth, the first union of Ukrainian American and Canadian Catholic Organizations was realized--the Ukrainian Catholic League was formed.</p>
   <p>Great responsibilities lie on this League, the work is enormous, but not discouraging. Two years has this league toiled, but not without results. With the help of his excellency, the most Reverend Bishop Bohachevsky, the Reverend Fathers, and all the Ukrainian Catholic people, the League has drawn many new clubs <pb facs="5425703_0656.jpg" n="2"/>into its ranks. It has organized clubs where there were none, sent forth into the world its official organ the Ukrainian Youth, and called the Second Congress which was held on the 13th and 14th of July, 1935, in New York City.</p>
   <p>It is not necessary to write about the Second Congress, as most likely all of you know all about it either from your presence, the newspaper reports, or the reports of your friends who attended it.</p>
   <p>Now the Congress is over and we are on the threshhold of a new term with new officers. The Executive Committee is doing its best for the welfare of the League; are you doing your part? The progress of the League depends upon your cooperation, upon your interest in the work of the League, upon your willingness to put your energy to work for the benefit of this great cooperative enterprise.</p>
   <p>There is much to be done, but neither is there energy lacking; all we need is the will. Are we lacking in this? Are we not willing to work for the two greatest things possible--are we not willing to work for God and for our country? Will we be left behind? Will we disappoint our parents after they have waited fifty <pb facs="5425703_0657.jpg" n="3"/>years for the organization of our great League?</p>
   <p>Let us show them what we can do. Let us answer the above questions not by words but deeds. Let us make sure that the club we belong to is a member of the League. Let us organize clubs where there are none and then ascertain that they join the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League. Gather subscriptions for the Ukrainian Youth, but before going anywhere subscribers. Write to the headquarters telling them of your work and your needs and they will act accordingly.</p>
   <p>Remember the old adage "where there's a will, there's a way". Remember the fifty years our parents have waited for this organization of ours and work so as to enable them to say at the end of the third year of the existence of the Ukrainian Catholic Youth League; "We have waited fifty years but not in vain, for now we can die knowing that our faith will live on and our country will soon be independent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
