<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1930-04-15">Apr. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Text of the Letter Sent to the Honorable Royal S. Copeland, United States Senator, by the Sitch Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1930-04-15">Apr. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">TEXT OF THE LETTER SENT TO THE HONORABLE ROYAL S. COPELAND, UNITED STATES SENATOR, BY THE SITCH ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorable Sir:</p>
   <p>Compelled to live out of our country, we Ukrainians were deeply touched by your generous intervention in behalf of our native land by your bill, introduced in the Senate of the United States of America, which recommended the recognition by the United States Government of an independent Ukraine. This bill reflects the great importance of self-determination of nations, a principle which actuated us in the year 1917-18 after the downfall of the Russian Empire, and upon which the wish of the Ukrainian nation for independence was based, as was so strikingly manifested by the voice of our people in 1917. Thus in 1917 the Ukraine became an independent country with a republican form of government, and later in 1918 it became a state under the leadership of a hetman. These achievements were later nullified by the violence of the Russian Bolsheviks, who, having conquered and subjugated <pb facs="5425703_0744.jpg" n="2"/>the country, merely granted it a fictitious independence under the nominal title of "Ukrainian Soviet Socialistic Republic", and the country became, in fact, a colony for Bolsheviks and was held in a slave-like independence under Bolshevik rule. With the country overrun and occupied by the Moscow Bolsheviks, the Ukrainian nation at once raised protests against this act of violence. The repeated peasant uprisings, general armed resistance against the oppressors, and lastly the flight of virtually the entire Ukrainian cultured class to other European countries, as well as to America and Asia, furnished proof of the Ukrainian protests against the Bolshevik occupation.</p>
   <p>Imbued with the lofty principle of independence, every Ukrainian abroad put all his energies into the effort to influence public opinion regarding the deplorable state of affairs in his country under the Bolshevik yoke. This is the reason your splendid action is of such predominant moral importance and force to the Ukrainian cause, and why we hope that it may be instrumental in bringing about important results in our struggle for <pb facs="5425703_0745.jpg" n="3"/>the liberation of our country. While we are expressing our sincere gratitude to you, permit us at the same time to draw your attention to an important fact which, it seems to us, you did not especially dwell upon in your bill. Among the Ukrainians abroad, as well as among those who live upon the Ukrainian territory, there are two different political groups which, although each seeks to achieve an independent Ukraine, differ in their views as to the ultimate political structure of that country. One group strives for an independent Ukraine under a republican form of government, while the other, with which we ourselves are affiliated, hopes for an independent Ukraine under the leadership of a hetman, in accordance with our historical and traditional form of government. This latter form of government existed during the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries and was restored by Hetman Skoropadsky. In sympathizing with and welcoming your action in behalf of the independent Ukraine, we believe that your support of the cause as expressed by your bill did not embrace the idea of any particular form of government for an independent Ukraine. However, we are fully convinced that the form of government which is most universally <pb facs="5425703_0746.jpg" n="4"/>approved, and which most nearly approaches our national principles and ideals, will be and should be selected by the Ukrainian notion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
