<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1921-12">Nov. &amp; Dec. 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Central Siege Organization in Chicago to All Members</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1921-12">Nov. &amp; Dec. 1921</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE CENTRAL SIEGE ORGANIZATION IN CHICAGO TO ALL MEMBERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The highest and the most precious ideal, the most beautiful and the happiest thought of an individual as well as that of a whole nation is freedom, that is, independence and self-government of one's nation on one's own land.</p>
   <p>Yet, for how many years did our people fight, and are still fighting, for this freedom? How many heroes died for it? How much blood was shed for it?</p>
   <p>Day after day, year after year, our nation is fighting for freedom, and is waiting for the moment of resurrection, the moment of freedom!</p>
   <p>Many summers our forefathers, fathers and even our brothers toiled at the sweat of their brows, the hottest days not excluded, on the manor fields that were not, and are not their own; many winters they froze in unheated homes or tramped around without a place to lay their heads, they were all waiting and <pb facs="5425703_0772.jpg" n="2"/>lived with the sole hope that better days were yet to come, the days of national freedom. They were and are still waiting! Their bodies are freezing with cold, while Polish bandits are beating them up, yet they suffer, and are waiting for us here beyond the seas, with their outstretched arms asking us for help!</p>
   <p>But how can we help them? Is it with our tears, by weeping over their bitter fate, without otherwise even turning a finger for a betterment of their lot, while we continue to live comfortably here in America? We must help them with something substantial! We must follow the appeal which they send us through the words of President Petrushevich and his envoys! We, one and all, should buy a National Liberty Bond, and thus help to defend the rights of Eastern <pb facs="5425703_0773.jpg" n="3"/>Galicia, i.e., Western Ukrainia. This is the only way in which we can help our fathers and mothers, brothers and sisters, who are suffering today great tortures under Polish bayonets.</p>
   <p>We must support our Ukrainian government in its struggle for independence of our Eastern Galicia, the dear land of our forefathers who shed so much blood for it and the many, many who gave their lives for it.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we appeal to you, all Siege members of both sexes: If there be anybody who still has not bought a Liberty Bond to help free Eastern Galicia from the Polish occupiers and their yoke, try to buy one for the smallest sum of money. It is the last call!</p>
   <p>Be generous, Siege members! Those few dollars that you have or will spend for the Liberty Bond, they will be paid back to you or to your children by <pb facs="5425703_0774.jpg" n="4"/>Ukrainia, when she is freed.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every Siege member to not only buy a bond, but also to help sell some to others.</p>
   <p>Christmas time is approaching. Try to recollect how you Siege members, enjoyed immensely this Christmas holiday in Ukrainia. How lovely it is just to think of it. How sweetly, how pleasantly, in a cozy home with the rest of the family we celebrated it. But how bitter it is for the one who does not have any home relatives, and sometimes not even a bite of stale bread on this great holiday. What an unwelcome thought to think of those unfortunate ones, hungry and in tatters, driven out of Ukrainia by the enemy, somewhere in Europe tramping through foreign lands, and reminding themselves on Christmas day of the grand times we all once had in Ukrainia.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0775.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Such poor tramps, hungry and ill-dressed, are our own Siege sharpshooters in Czechoslovakia and other countries. These, our brothers, once sacrificed their lives for their people, they still are more ready to fight for the ideal of freedom for our land and people. They, hungry and cold, are just awaiting the momentum, when again they will have a chance to fight for what is Ukrainian. It is our duty to help them. Let us show them materially that we are united with them in spirit, and thereby we will inspire them while they are waiting for an opportune time to fight!</p>
   <p>Therefore, on Christmas Day let us go from house to house to sing Christmas carols and the money received for it let us send to our brother fighters. Let none of the Ukrainian homes refuse Christmas carolers, for theirs is a great purpose: to help our heroes who stand in protest against the whole <pb facs="5425703_0776.jpg" n="6"/>world for the freedom of Ukrainia.</p>
   <p>Let every Siege Branch appoint a committee of Christmas carol singers, to go from house to house, and the money thus collected let them send to Czecho-Slovakia for Ukrainian soldiers.</p>
   <p>Then every Siege Branch should give a list of exactly how much it collected for that purpose and where the money was sent.</p>
   <p>We anticipate that every Siege branch will answer the appeal and do his duty as we have directed, thereby helping our brother soldiers to get ready once more to fight for Ukrainian freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0777.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>M. Kotchuk, ass't head commander,</p>
   <p>S. Museychuk, rec. secretary,</p>
   <p>N. Pashko, fin. secretary,</p>
   <p>L. B. Stachursky, colonel,</p>
   <p>I. Shkraba, cashier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
