<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Siege Ranks Grow Stronger</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SIEGE RANKS GROW STRONGER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ukrainian Siege Organization in the United States fights all obstacles to be found in its way, and with a strong step forward, it further strives for its cause. Siege ranks grow stronger. The Society of Fighters joined the Siege organization, and now they are members of the new Siege in Chicago, branch No. 15, of the Ukrainian Siege Organization in the United States.</p>
   <p>The head commander, Mr. Zadoretsky, received the following letter from Mr. Moranets, a Siege member, in which he speaks of the new Siege in Chicago:</p>
   <p>"Greetings, Father Commander! The time has come, when we, here in Chicago, are not lagging behind. I have the honor of submitting to you a list of our Siege members, whereby we beg of you to accept them as one of the branches of the Ukrainian Siege Organization in the United States. We experienced many obstacles because of our enemies, however, the victory is ours. To begin with <pb facs="5425703_0487.jpg" n="2"/>we have only eighty members.</p>
   <p>Enclosed, please find a check for $33.50: $25.00 for the press fund, and $8.50 for subscriptions for the Sichovi Visty. I have good reason to believe that in the future all the Siege members will become subscribers of the Siege organ. We really work! Health and greetings! N. Moranets."</p>
   <p>The district commander of the new Siege is Rev. Nicholas Strutynsky, the only priest who disregards his old age, and sacrifices much of his time for the spreading of the Siege organization, and for the national cause as a whole.</p>
   <p>The officers of this branch are as follows: Mr. Nicholas Moranetz, centurion; Nicholas Volkovetsky, assistant centurion; Alex Tymush, secretary; and Stanley Babily, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
