<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
p. 10, <date when="1937-04">March-April 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Prof. A. A. Granowsky Visits Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Trident</title>,
p. 10, <date when="1937-04">March-April 1937</date>.
<title level="a">PROF. A. A. GRANOWSKY VISITS CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Returning from Kansas City where he presided at the 16th annual meeting of the North Central States entomologists, Professor A. A. Granowsky stopped in Chicago, March 7, to deliver a lecture on the subject, "Why are we nationalists," before the members of all divisions in Chicago and vicinity of the organization for the re-birth of the Ukraine and the young Ukrainian nationalists.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, also on the same day, was the representative of O. U. N., who gave a long and interesting talk on the present day nationalistic movements, the possibilities of the nationalist ideal, and causes and effects.</p>
   <p>During the course of the meeting the following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>"In order to intelligently repel the various enemy and opposition attacks upon the Ukrainian nationalist movement, and in order to strengthen the pledge to O. U. N., the members will undertake to conduct a <pb facs="5425703_0367.jpg" n="2"/>campaign in which each member is to secure a contribution from outside sources of one dollar every month (Y. U. N., fifty cents) for a period of six months, starting with the month of March. The money thus raised is to be paid into the branch treasury for transmittal to the Central Office.</p>
   <p>The O. D. W. U. of Chicago commends the O. D. W. U. of other cities for initiating these resolutions, and entreats other organized nationalists to adopt similar methods, so that the introduction of this new course might confirm the nationalist call of "Our strength is our own," and serve to inspire to action the entire patriotic populations.</p>
   <p>At the close of the meeting, a banquet was given by the Daughters of the Ukraine in honor of the two distinguished guests, at which liberal contributions were made to the Nationalist Fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
