<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1925-09-01">Sept. 1, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Fathers and Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sitch</title>,
<date when="1925-09-01">Sept. 1, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO FATHERS AND MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Autumn is approaching. Millions of golden ripe products will fall from the trees to the ground to serve as the seed of the future trees. Millions of birds will get their offspring ready for the long journey to the south.</p>
   <p>Fathers and mothers! Your golden fruit, your children, have also matured to the extent of having gone to school to prepare themselves for their long journey into life. Dumb animals can teach their offspring only that which they themselves know. Human beings can educate their children to a higher level than the one on which they find themselves. That is why you should not say to your children, "Go to work, and bring me five dollars a day! I worked hard; you do the same!" This is only done by the dumb wild beasts of the woods. But the beasts are not responsible for what they are doing, because they cannot achieve progress.</p>
   <p>Progress is the accomplishment of human beings alone. Do not be an enemy <pb facs="5425703_0055.jpg" n="2"/>to your child! Do not let your children be driven in the factories like oxen. Brighten your fruitful blood for the benefit of yourself and your people! Enroll your children in the higher schools. Let it be in the future that when the green grass grows over your bones, your child will remember you as a good father and mother, and not as covetous ones who for five dollars stunted their blossoms in a factory. Perhaps some of you have children in the old country, boys or girls. Help them also to go to school. It may be difficult for you; but in any case it will be easier for you to keep them in school over there than for them to do so unaided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
