<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-11">Nov., 1922</date><title level="a">Ukrainian National Choir in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sichovi Visty (Siege News)</title>,
<date when="1922-11">Nov., 1922</date><title level="a">UKRAINIAN NATIONAL CHOIR IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As in other localities the American citizens of Ukrainian descent in Chicago, welcomed very sincerely, and acted as a generous host to the Ukrainian National Choir.</p>
   <p>Monday, October 8, at 8 A. M., the delegates from all Ukrainian societies, fraternities, etc., of Chicago, waited at the La Salle Street Station, where the choir was to arrive. All the delegates, some of them in national costumes, brought flowers to welcome the choir. Above all, the local Siege district No. 2 was best represented. Besides the delegates there were a great number of Chicago Ukrainians who came out personally to see and welcome the world's famous choir.</p>
   <p>The Choir arrived at 9 A. M. and was instantly surrounded by newspaper reporters. After this ordeal the Choir formed a semi-circle and <pb facs="5425703_0187.jpg" n="2"/>Dr. Myroslaw Siemens officially welcomed them in the name of the Chicago Ukrainians, and presented Mr. A. Koshets, choir conductor, with a huge bouquet of flowers. Mr. N. Motliuk spoke a few words of welcome to the Choir from the body of the local Ukrainian students.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. Koshets replied in a few dynamic words his appreciation of the welcome they accorded him and his choir. His finishing thought was that we should give our full support to the National Choir. After this the delegates took the Choir to the Auditorium Hotel for breakfast.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a tour through Chicago's principal streets, places, parks, and buildings of historical value.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0188.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This same evening the choir gave a concert in the Symphony Orchestra Hall. There is not enough space in this newspaper, and furthermore no words can describe the feeling, sentiment, and inspiration that filled the hearts of each and everyone present at the concert. It may be of importance to some to know that the hall containing 3,000 chairs was filled almost exclusively by Ukrainians. The Ukrainians expected the large crowd and bought their tickets ahead of time.</p>
   <p>Many other nationalities did not expect such an enormous crowd, did not secure tickets in advance, and consequently were included among those over 1,000 people who, due to the lack of space, had to return home. For this very reason, in the middle of the concert, it was announced that another concert would take place on November 5, at Medinah Temple, in a much more spacious hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0189.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The welcome committee, chosen from different societies, clubs, etc., provided presentable bouquets for Mr. Koshets and the choir soloists. There were also numerous bouquets from strangers as well as from many individual Ukrainians.</p>
   <p>After this second concert a banquet was arranged at the Congress Hotel in honor of the Ukrainian National Choir. At the banquet there were delegates from almost every society, club, fraternity, etc., and especially from the Chicago Siege Organization District No. 2.</p>
   <p>During the banquet there were many speeches in honor of Mr. A. Koshets and his famous choir.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0190.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It must not be omitted that the banquet was honored by the presence of the Ukrainian Count Archbishop Metropolitan Andrey Sheptytsky.</p>
   <p>The speakers were the following: Dr. M. Siminovich; Dr. S. K. Hrynevetsky, chief executive of the Siege Organization, who fearlessly and openly spoke his mind as to the difficult agreement between the Ukrainian National Choir and their impresario Mr. Rabinoff. Then followed the speeches of : Dr. Volodimier Siminovich, Dr. S. Yanovich, Rev. W. Stetsiuk, Count Archbishop Metropolitan A. Sheptytsky, S. Museychook, M. Tkatchuk, H. Skehar, I. Levtiuch, Rev. L. Van, Rev. I. Hundiak, P. Novodvorsky, S. Kochy, R. Smook, I. Sawchuk, and others. Prof. A. Koshets replied to all those speeches and showed himself to be not only a genius of song, but also a genius of eloquence. The banquet was concluded by singing, the Ukrainian hymn, "Ukrainia Still Lives."</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0191.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Special thanks are due Roman Smook, our young attorney, who worked hardest to make the welcome of the Choir successful.</p>
   <p>Because the Choir remained in Chicago for a whole week, the Chicago Ukrainians were given an opportunity to talk to its members individually and learn many things from our native nightingales about the conditions in the old country.</p>
   <p>On Tuesday the Choir had a reception and supper at the residence of Rev. W. Stetsiuk, where Count Archbishop Metropolitan Sheptytsky also resided during his stay in Chicago. The latter was now given the opportunity to become better acquainted with the conductor Prof. Alexander Koshets and his Choir. Here the singers were more free to express and enjoy themselves. They sang a few church and national songs which will long remain in the memory of the venerable old Archbishop and the others present.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0192.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Rev. Wasyl Stetsiuk truly is an exceptionally generous person and sincere worker; he never spares himself nor money for a good cause. He showed those excellent traits particularly at the funeral of the late Perehowsky, during the sickness of Archbishop Sheptytsky, and during the reception of the Choir at his residence. Three cheers for him for that!</p>
   <p>On Friday, Nov. 3, the Ukrainian Orthodox people prepared a welcome supper for the choir, at 1944 West Erie Street, Chicago. Many speakers had a chance to express themselves at this banquet, but they unanimously had words of cordial welcome and sincere gratefulness for A. Koshets and the Choir. Mr. Koshets thanked the speakers for their warm words of appreciation as well as for the presents received. Here he described and related with more detail the Ukrainian <pb facs="5425703_0193.jpg" n="8"/>National Choir and its traveling mission all over the world. The Choir did its part and sang a few songs which satisfied very well those present.</p>
   <p>During the banquet the well-known orchestra of John Barabash played.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, Mr. A. Koshets and his assistant Prof. Harry Tuchapsky were present at Mass at the St. Nicholas Church, the corner of Oakley Blvd. and Rice St. Dr. Joseph Nazaruk, special representative from Ukrainia, was also present.</p>
   <p>The same afternoon Mr. A Koshets was invited to a huge meeting called by Dr. Jos. Nazaruk. Invited by the latter as well as by the entire Meeting Committee, Prof. A. Koshets made an exceptional impression upon the audience with his speech. He showed himself to be a master of <pb facs="5425703_0194.jpg" n="9"/>eloquence.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the meeting, the Ukrainians went to hear the Ukrainian National Choir at the Medinah Temple. Due to the fact that the Ukrainians attended the mass meeting in the afternoon, not many of them attended the Choir concert; nevertheless, the spacious hall was filled to its capacity by the American public.</p>
   <p>The program of the concert was different from the former ones. Even the regular attendants of all the concerts of the Choir, as well as the entire audience were much pleased, because these numbers and the presentation of them were something entirely new to the audience. Miss Nina Koshets sang some of the solos, such as, "Oh, Mother," and "Tra-la-la!" May I add that this hall is twice as large as the former.</p>
   <p>It is next to impossible to describe every singer of the Choir <pb facs="5425703_0195.jpg" n="10"/>individually, or every number separately. Let the heart in its higher aspect alone judge what an impression each and every number left on the audience. Self-praise gets no one anywhere; therefore, let me cite from some of the local American newspapers about the Choir:</p>
   <p>"Hail and sincere thanks to you, great conductor A. Koshets, and to your choir. You seem to us like our native nightingales."</p>
   <p>"Hail to you! By singing about the freedom of Ukrainia, you are strengthening her aims and endeavors."</p>
   <p>"We salute you for your divine and melodious way of telling us who you are and who your ancestry is!"</p>
   <p>Sing, therefore, for us and for others! Sing about the famous Siege of the past and their dauntless heroes, who with their very breasts <pb facs="5425703_0196.jpg" n="11"/>like bulwarks, protected for centuries not only Ukrainia, but also the whole Western civilization against the savage hordes of Turks and Tartars and other migrating Asiatic tribes. Tell the world through the medium of songs, what Ukrainia is: that she is one of the richest countries in the world; that for many centuries her cossacks have done far more than their share for the preservation of the whole Western civilization and culture. Through the medium of our song make the world recognize the immortal fame and glory of the Ukrainian cossacks, saviors of European culture.</p>
   <p>The Observer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
