<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 34, <date when="1919-09-27">Sept. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Ten Thousand Ukrainians Protest against the Poles for Taking Ukrainian Territory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5425703_0822</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5425703_0822.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>UKRAINIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Ukraina</title>,
Vol. III, No. 34, <date when="1919-09-27">Sept. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TEN THOUSAND UKRAINIANS PROTEST AGAINST THE POLES FOR TAKING UKRAINIAN TERRITORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the manifestation! To the manifestation! Let us protest against the Poles for taking our Ukrainian soil! Let us gain freedom and the liberty of our dear Ukrainia!</p>
   <p>These and similar calls were heard in Chicago and suburbs within the past few weeks. Not a small group of people, but thousands of men, women and children hastened to answer this call, so that with their presence the holiday of the Chicago Ukrainians could be exalted.</p>
   <p>Ever so often news comes from the suburbs that the Ukrainians are preparing themselves for this holiday, calling meetings among themselves, collecting money for the expense and wherever possible they rehearse parading in their localities so as to come already prepared to the gathering place.</p>
   <pb facs="5425703_0823.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The manifestation parade began at Oakley and Rice Streets, by the St. Nicholas Ukrainian Catholic church. Our young Ukrainian men, who served in the United States Army, were put at the head of the parade where, with their presence, they reminded the Poles that they are not afraid of their Haller army anymore than they feared the Germans should the time come for this. After them followed the Siege from Chicago and suburbs, numbering nearly a thousand. Siege banners, alongside the American flag, which glittered in the rays of the sun, reminded everyone of the value of our holiday, and added to the spirit of those standing in the ranks of fighters who, though here in America, have their spirits there in Ukrainia and (are ready) to defend the rights of the Fatherland, for which the Ukrainians sacrificed their lives under the azure and gold banner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
