<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-07">Jan. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">On the Matter of National Mourning for the Year 1893</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_1024</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_1024.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-07">Jan. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE MATTER OF NATIONAL MOURNING FOR THE YEAR 1893</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of national mourning, which was so hotly debated last year, has become a matter of fresh interest in Poland and even here in America. It gathered new impetus with the coming of the year 1893, the centenary anniversary of the second Polish partition. Already at the end of last November, the youth from various educational centers of Lwow decided upon a whole year's national mourning, calling for a general cessation of entertainment activities and increased effort in public enlightenment. This initiative, though it came from a source scarcely competent to decide the behavior of a whole adult society, found certain echoes in Galicia. At the same time, a sweeping appeal was addressed to European emigrants to observe mourning by prohibiting entertainment activity, and redoubling efforts for individual and collective advancement. It called also for general organization and for the establishment of a National Fund. Just as last year, opposition to this project arose. In Lwow, the influential association of handicraftsmen, <pb facs="5423968_11_1025.jpg" n="2"/>"Gwiazda" [Star], declared itself definitely against a whole year's mourning, as did the Businessmen's Association of Lwow. Many newspapers in Poland recognize and support this opposition to the proposed mourning period. It is superfluous to repeat here all the arguments in favor of mourning, and against it. A year ago, this newspaper treated the subject more fully. A year ago too, this newspaper declared itself in favor of mourning--only if all of the Poles agreed to put it into effect. A partisan "mourning", favored by the more fervent elements would only substantiate the fears of those who believe that practical harm will result.</p>
   <p>In Polish-American circles, it is impossible to consider such an observance, in the face of the various party differences and internal dissensions which attack us so pitilessly. In any case, since we cannot observe it any other way, let us demonstrate our mourning by redoubling our national and social work. Let us work for education and for society--and first of all, for the unification of our Polish groups, torn apart today by scandalous quarrels and irrational hatred.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_1026.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This will be the best observance of the year 1893!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
