<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 23,
<date when="1916-06-07">June 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Manifestation at the Foot of Kosciuszko Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 23,
<date when="1916-06-07">June 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH MANIFESTATION AT THE FOOT OF KOSCIUSZKO MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Poles in Chicago celebrated two holidays on the 28th day of May, namely, the 125th anniversary of the May 3rd Constitution (Polish Constitution Day), and the tribute to Thaddeus Kosciuszko. The celebrations were composed of two parts. There was a huge parade to the foot of the Kosciuszko monument in Humboldt Park and a banquet, which was held in the evening in the Auditorium Hotel, where speeches were rendered by various prominent Americans and Poles.</p>
   <p>The parade to the Kosciuszko monument included over thirty thousand people. During the manifestation at the foot of the Kosciuszko monument a talk was rendered by Senator John W. Kern from the state of Indiana, who spoke on the theme of carrying help to the hungry Poles in Poland. He made the following statement:</p>
   <p>"Within three weeks grain and other food products will be on their way to Poland. During this month the outlook for the independence of Poland is better than it has been at any time during the past century.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0522.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"When the time comes for peace the United States will be one of the most powerful factors in these negotiations. I know the United States will insist that Poland should have the freedom which it so sincerely deserves."</p>
   <p>Judge Olson from the municipal court spoke about the country's preparedness for war, and pointed out the need of such preparedness, using Poland as an example. If Poland was prepared in a military way, it would not have been partitioned by. its neighbors. The United States must be better prepared defensively in regards to war, if it does not want a similar misfortune to fall upon it.</p>
   <p>Other speakers were Judge Michael Blenski from Milwaukee, censor of the Polish National Alliance, Mr. Adam Majewski, T. M. Helinski, Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, and Attorney N. L. Piotrowski.</p>
   <p>During the celebration at the Kosciuszko monument resolutions were read, the more important paragraphs(of which)were as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0523.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We, Poles, citizens of the United States, gathered this 28th day of May at the foot of Kosciuzsko monument, address ourselves with a mighty voice, in order to spread our principles by word and act, in order to carry help to the persecuted nations. The United States must be strong and rich not only in worldly goods, but must also be prepared in a military way, because we are living during such times when might is oppressing justice and right. For that reason we propagate the country's preparedness for war, so that its voice would have a meaning and influence not only in the region of idealism but also in practical life.</p>
   <p>"Free America should not look indifferently on the fall and sufferings of other nations; it should not allow the powerful nations to oppress and persecute the weaker ones. We American citizens, having in sight a terrible war, which will decide the future of Europe and civilization, demand from the whole world freedom for all persecuted nations, freedom for Poland, the greatest martyr among the nations; we demand the union of all parts of Poland under one government. Let live free America! Let live free and united Poland!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0524.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The banquet in the Hotel Auditorium was held that same evening. The most impressive speech was rendered by Senator Aitchcock. We have placed it in another column.</p>
   <p>The speakers during the banquet were Senator James Hamilton Lewis, John F. Smulski, Archbishop Mundelein, City Attorney Harry C. Miller, and others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
