<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-17">Dec. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Enemies of Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-17">Dec. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ENEMIES OF IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enemies of immigration have not repudiated their principles. They discover the most diverse excuses for rendering difficult the entry of new arrivals from Europe or other parts of the world. We have learned through telegraphic reports that the immigration rules in the port of New York are to be made considerably more stringent. As a result of this many a poor man leaving his native land with the hope of arriving here will be doomed to disappointment. The immigration authorities here would be able to return him to the place from which he came for even the most insignificant reason. As a pretext for making the immigration laws more stringent Commissioner Williams takes the fact that a native of Wales, a certain Thornton, being allowed entrance here with five of his children by the intervention of the President himself, has left debts in his native land and suffers want here. Thornton complains in his letter to local authorities that he is unable to find proper <pb facs="5423968_11_0056.jpg" n="2"/>employment, that he is of weak health, and that he greatly regrets his migration to America because he was far better off in his native land. This complaint of one immigrant, therefore, is to be sufficient reason for denying admission to thousands who would willingly work and would not utter a word of complaint.....</p>
   <p>It is a fact that at first no immigrant likes to be here. Many immigrants long for the lands that they have left. They long for their families and their friends. They are sad because they find themselves in strange surroundings and do not know the language. In addition to that, if they do not find employment immediately, having no reserve and no friends to aid them in the first moments of their struggle with fate in a foreign country, it is natural that immigrants should complain and regret their arrival here. That, however. does not constitute a sufficient reason to close the barriers in our ports to hundreds of thousands of immigrants who will not complain. They will gradually grow accustomed to conditions and in time will become the best citizens of this country. Moreover, it should seem that this native of Wales, <pb facs="5423968_11_0057.jpg" n="3"/>Thornton, has no cause to complain of his fate. As his own sister, a wealthy lady of Pittsburgh, informs us, he has employment as a driver, and two of his children have found work. Consequently conditions are not so bad for this family. Such insignificant things as the letter of an immigrant stating that he is not satisfied here, and things of like nature, are enlarged upon by immigration authorities and are used by American chauvinists to promote their anti-immigration activities.</p>
   <p>The mere fact that this immigrant had left debts behind him in his native land does not constitute sufficient reason for not allowing entrance to immigrants. As long as a person is not a thief, a cheat, a criminal, or a murderer, he need not be ashamed of debts if he has the sincere intention of earning money and paying them, which he can easily do here. Very few immigrants arriving in America are without debts. Some have incurred debts by borrowing of their neighbors in order to purchase passage to America; others, again, have some obligations on their meager estates; still others have had to borrow because of some dire need or misfortune. Debtors of that type, therefore, are not <pb facs="5423968_11_0058.jpg" n="4"/>in the least criminals. Moreover, the immigration authorities cannot foretell what type of debtor an immigrant will turn out to be--whether or not he will pay off his financial obligations. This native of Wales, if he had remained in his native land, might never have had an opportunity to clear up his debts. Here in America that opportunity can be found sooner because he will earn more, and if he is an honest man, he will meet his obligations. Poor and inadequate indeed are the reasons grasped at by the local immigration authorities in order to make entrance more difficult for immigrants. If they apply these restrictions to their full extent, the chances are that they will not give admission even to a tenth part of the best immigrants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
