<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-30">Mar. 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Enterprise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0733</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0733.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-30">Mar. 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH ENTERPRISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Sigmund Slupski has conceived a novel project for the year 1894. His plan is to arrange for a tour of American Poles through Poland. The reason why he has chosen 1894 is that that year is the hundredth anniversary of the Kosciuszko Insurrection. At such a time it should be especially a pleasure for every Pole to visit places of historical importance. At the same time, it will give American Poles an opportunity to visit the Lwow Exposition. The tour will pass through the cities of Poznan, Gniezno, Danzig, Torun, Krakow, Lwow, some of the larger towns in Galicia, as well as Zakopane and Morskie Oko in the Tatra Mountains. Along the way the tourists will stop at London, Paris, Berlin, Dresden, Prague, and Vienna. Individuals who wish to do so may leave the party to visit Warsaw. Mr. Slupski estimates that the cost of the trip (second class) will be $250. This seems to us to be definitely too low a figure. In reality, we feel reasonably sure that a trip of this sort would cost <pb facs="5423968_11_0734.jpg" n="2"/>at least twice as much. Mr. Slupski expects that many Poles who were born here, or who came to America as children, will take advantage of this tour.</p>
   <p>We will not estimate the possible success of Mr. Slupski's enterprise. We wish only to add that a tour of this sort would indeed be educational to our younger generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
