<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-27">Feb. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">National Security League Will Honor Polish Nation through its Representatives</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-27">Feb. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL SECURITY LEAGUE WILL HONOR POLISH NATION THROUGH ITS REPRESENTATIVES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third of March will be a day forever to be remembered not only by the Poles of Chicago but by those of the whole country. On this day, the Polish nation will be taken off the list of foreign countries and grouped with the Allies by the American Security League. The League, which held its convention in Chicago a few days ago and under the honorary leadership and with the active participation of former president Taft considered ways and means of assuring victory for the United States in the World War, desires to honor our heroic nation for its readiness to support the American cause and the cause of freedom for all nations with its own Polish army. A group of the most prominent members of the National Security League, with the participation of the governor of Illinois, wishes to express publicly its high esteem of the Poles, and at the same time to reaffirm its inseparable union with that people in the holy war for the triumph of the ideals of Washington, Kosciusko, Lincoln, and Wilson. It will be a demonstration in honor of the oldest and most faithful ally of the United States which, during <pb facs="5423968_11_0440.jpg" n="2"/>the war for independence in this country, inflexibly served the cause of liberty. For a hundred and twenty years Poland has fought against the autocracy and tyranny of its conquerors in a series of insurrections; with ceaseless and limitless sacrifice, with strong and unswerving faith, and with a perennial perseverance, it has defended the liberty established at the Oder and the Sala and at the gates of Kiev by Boleslaus the Brave, strengthened by the defeat of the Teutonic Knights of the Cross by Jagiello [in 1410], and made sacred by the Union of Lublin [with Lithuania]. During the spread of the tyranny of the conquerors, their expansion of power took place in territories unlawfully oppressed; the war between the nations of Europe has now disclosed this mortal wounds inflicted upon humanity by this evil system, and has disclosed Poland as a fortress standing in defense of the national welfare of all oppressed peoples. President Wilson has rendered Poland an immortal service, in that through the smoke of the conflagration, through the barbaric indifference [to humanity] of the advancing Germans, he has heard that faithful echo which for a hundred and twenty-five years has proclaimed the battle for liberty, and in the annals of that fight has written down the names of Poland as the oldest ally of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0441.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The National Security League moves along the path appointed by our president, and with ardor hastens to honor that Polish name for its faithfully rendered and recognized services. Poland will be honored through its representatives.</p>
   <p>Among those representatives, our beloved Ignacy Paderewski occupies the first place. It can rightfully be said of him that he gained fame in foreign lands and brightened the name of Poland with that fame throughout the world, in order to serve Poland at its most critical hour amid the Polish people of America--amid that people who so ably represent the ideals of liberty, and who so effectively defend the precepts of freedom and the inalienable rights of our [Polish] nation. Ignacy J. Paderewski has come here to us, to the Polish element in America, which, with all its freedom, nobility, sacrifice, and strong faith, represents a full realization of the principles of the Constitution of the Third of May, for it represents such a widespread and complete ennoblement of our people that class and party distinctions are destroyed, while instead there has arisen the collective force of a unified people. Toward completing this solidarity and turning it toward the inflexible defense of the Polish cause, <pb facs="5423968_11_0442.jpg" n="4"/>Paderewski has labored since the outbreak of the war, and from the first moment that he arrived here he co-operated with us in this; at the same time, he has never ceased to work for a wholehearted union with the nationalist element in Poland and with our people in France. He was the first and most idealistic representative of our nation's principles of freedom; and even before the Polish National Committee was created in France and he was entrusted with its representation with the government of this country he held high the standard of Polish independence. This faithful heroism of a great man who has given himself heart and soul to his country, this all-inspiring fire of real desire for liberty, this insistence that everything possible be gained for the Polish cause to raise Poland and make her happy, to make the whole world wonder at her, awakens for Paderewski a general esteem and admiration, and for this reason the National Security League desires to honor him first.</p>
   <p>Our Polish Army, our pride and joy, is sending three other representatives to participate in the reception. The National Security League will receive these delegates from the Polish Army as representatives of united forces of the Polish nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
