<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Reception for Polish Military Commission from France Held in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">RECEPTION FOR POLISH MILITARY COMMISSION FROM FRANCE HELD IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday can easily be said to have been one of the greatest days ever celebrated in South Chicago. The parade staged on this occasion was, in the words of Americans, one of the greatest, one of the most magnificent parades ever witnessed here. Americans were impressed not only with the parade but with the patriotism of the Poles of South Chicago, who showed yesterday that the cause of their homeland is a cause that is sacred to them, and that the Polish Army now being formed is a necessity if Poland is to be freed from its persecutors, the Germans. It seems that the general public is coming to under-stand more and more that without a Polish Army there is no future for Poland, because the Polish Army is the only means by which we can be assured of a free, united, and independent Poland with an outlet to the sea. Only our own army can win freedom for us, for if the Allies see that our intentions are good, they will see to it that Poland will be given all the territories that right-fully belong within its boundaries. But we, for our part, must show the Allies <pb facs="5423968_11_0309.jpg" n="2"/>that we are personally concerned and that this is our sole aim, our sole desire. In order to prove that this is so, we must create the strongest possible army, so that our allies will be convinced that we are serious and that there are no sacrifices we are not willing to make for our beloved Poland. In line with this spirit, let there be no one among us who is unwilling to enlist in the Polish Army. Let everyone who can bear arms enlist as a volunteer, for it is a free and autonomous army. Let there be none who, seeing the present need of our country, will wait until he is taken by force. We Poles ought not to be drafted; we should all go as volunteers, for it is our duty to our homeland. The eyes of the whole world are upon us; we are the heroes of the present hour; let us strengthen in their thoughts these convictions; let the world be convinced of our great love of our country and of freedom, and our willingness to sacrifice to attain our goal. Let the world learn that what history says of our forefathers can be said about us, also.</p>
   <p>Major J. Kozlowski, chief of the Polish Military Commission in France, and Captain kleczkowski did not come to America to place themselves on exhibit or <pb facs="5423968_11_0310.jpg" n="3"/>to play at oratory. They are tried soldiers who have already earned glory in the French army. They are Poles who, upon learning that a Polish Army was being created in France, enlisted in it in order that they might give it the benefit of their experience. They have families, but they sacrificed everything for the sacred cause, leaving behind their wives and children in order to tell us what is happening in France and that the matter of forming a Polish Army can brook no delay. It is they who are appealing to you, to your consciences, pointing out that the duty of every Pole is to join the ranks of the Polish Army and fight for the freedom of Poland. It is the duty of those who cannot bear arms to support that army financially.</p>
   <p>Let our discords come to an end, let there be no more division among us. Today, because of our mutual aim and duty, without regard to our personal convictions, we should work together. Let our motto be, "For Poland!" And if we work together with this one thought in mind, there is no doubt that we will win back our homeland, and that Poland of the people and for the people will again be great and free and united.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0311.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Parade Formation</p>
   <p>The parade began to form in Russell Square at St. Michael Archangel Church. The marshal of the parade was F. X. Rydzewski. Various organizational representatives and societies began to arrive at about noon. It should be added here that many societies and organizations from outside of South Chicago participated. All factories closed at two o'clock in the afternoon because of the celebration, paying their employees for the full day. Moreover, nearly all of the American places of business and the public schools were closed. It is doubtful whether anyone stayed at home, for great throngs of people participating in the parade filled the streets. Factories sent their bands, and children of the upper and lower grades of the public schools marched in the parade with their teachers and with the American Businessmen's Association.</p>
   <p>When everyone who was to participate in the parade had arrived, it was formed in the following order: At the head rode F. X. Rydzewski, grand marshal of <pb facs="5423968_11_0312.jpg" n="5"/>the parade, on horseback, followed by a company of thirty mounted policemen. Behind them marched the marshal's adjutants, the honorary marshals, Aldermen Woodhill and Furman, the Great Lakes Naval Training Station Band, and the Citizens' Committees from South Bend, Michigan City, Pullman, East Chicago, and Kensington. Following, came Mrs. K. Obarski, honorary vice-president of the Polish National Alliance, the Reverend Sudzinski, vicar of Immaculate Conception Parish, the Camp Kosciusko Polish Army Military Band from Niagara-on-the-Lake, led by their Conductor, Wasilewski, and Lieutenant Sulewski, and the automobile bearing the members of the Polish Military Commission. In the automobile were Major Kozlowski, Captain Kleczewski, the Reverend Kowalewski, A. Bloch, president of the Central Citizens' Committee, and Polish Army Inspector [John] Przyprawa. Following these came the volunteers to the Polish Army from South Chicago, with the organizers and recruiting officers and recruiting sergeants from local and outside stations, the Illinois National Guard, the Falcon men's and women's societies, the Polish and American Red Cross, the American n Association, including a great number <pb facs="5423968_11_0313.jpg" n="6"/>of prominent local businessmen, the children from the public schools, followed by a division of civil and military [Polish] societies and a division consisting of societies from St. Michaels' and St. Mary Magdalene Parishes, and many others. Bringing up the rear were special automobiles carrying floats representing Poland in chains....,Poland arising...., Columbia....,and others. About 160 private automobiles completed the parade.</p>
   <p>Seven bands participated in the parade, but none surpassed the Camp Kosciusko Band, not even the Great Lakes Naval Training Station Band, although its members are all good musicians and have good instruments.</p>
   <p>After being formed properly, the parade started at about three thirty in the afternoon, moving toward Bessemer Park down 83rd Street to Marquette, to 87th, to Commercial, to 91st, to Baltimore Avenue, to Exchange, to South Chicago Avenue. At this point the parade stopped in front of the Federal Building, where the Polish flag waved beneath the American flag, and the Polish Army <pb facs="5423968_11_0314.jpg" n="7"/>Band played "The Star-Spangled Banner". The procession then proceeded down South Chicago Avenue back to 91st Street, to Exchange, to 90th, thence to Bessmer Park. It was necessary to wait a full hour after the first divisions had arrived at the park for all the societies participating to enter. The actual length of the parade was more than twenty city blocks. One of the most pleasurable effects for those participating was the fact that on all of the streets thorough which the parade passed, not only all of the stores and office buildings, but nearly every private home was decorated from foundation to rooftop. It should also be mentioned here that the participating women's groups of the Polish National Alliance presented a very good appearance, as did the Helen Paderewski Red Cross Society, and the Red Cross Ambulance containing Mrs. Zajac and Mrs. J. Sadowski.</p>
   <p>Exercises at Bessemer Park</p>
   <p>After everybody had arrived at the park, the Polish Military Band played the American, French, and Polish national anthems.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0315.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>An address was then delivered by the Reverend Francis Wojtalewicz, pastor of Immaculate Conception Parish of South Chicago, which was often interrupted with great bursts of applause. The second address was made by A. Bloch, president of the Citizens' Committee of Center 42 and chairman of the days' proceedings. It must be admitted that Bloch spoke very well, and it could readily be seen that he was a true Polish patriot.</p>
   <p>The next number was a choral presentation by the united parish choirs and the Dembinski Chorus, singing "The Star-Spangled Banner".</p>
   <p>The Reverend E. Kowalewski followed with an address. It is unfortunate that we cannot give this address in full, for it was a splendid one, each word carrying national significance. If those who were not present to hear it could read this address, it would awaken the Polish spirit in many a heretofore cold heart. The able priest urged everyone to co-operation, to use our united strength in the rebuilding of Poland, placing the greatest emphasis <pb facs="5423968_11_0316.jpg" n="9"/>upon the necessity for all able-bodied men to enlist in the Polish Army as volunteers....</p>
   <p>Following the address, the mixed choirs, under the direction of K. Kowalski, organist of St. Michaels' Church, sang "Oath of Allegiance," after which followed an address by Alderman Woodhill. He spoke in English, and it is a pity that there were perhaps many people in the audience who did not under-stand him. He spoke very well, however, giving the Poles credit for their work and their patriotism. He could not find words enough for praise of the merits of the Poles. Only a good American patriot would speak thus.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was chief of the Polish Military Commission, Major Kozlowski. At the sight of this distinguished guest and able soldier, whose chest was decorated with a great many medals for bravery, everyone arose to his feet and cheered for him, for the Polish Army, and for the Military Commission. Major Kozlowski is evidently studying the English language and is making great <pb facs="5423968_11_0317.jpg" n="10"/>progress, for he spoke first to the American representatives and guests, thanking them for their support of the Polish cause and for their participation in this demonstration. He assured them of the loyalty of the Poles to America and to the Allies, after which he raised a cheer for the United States and its great President, Wilson, the friend of the Poles. The audience repeated his cheer three times. Major Kozlowski then spoke in Polish, with typical military conciseness, stressing one point in particular, namely, the need for the largest possible Polish Army. His reason for coming to America was to do all in his power personally to accomplish this, in the belief that American Polonia would support him in this as becomes good Poles. He concluded his address with a cheer for the United States, for France, for Poland, and for the Polish Army.</p>
   <p>Captain Kleczkowski, also of the Polish Military Commission, was the next speaker. It was enough to take one look at Captain Kleczkowski to see that here was a real soldier and able Pole such as is rarely found. He said that <pb facs="5423968_11_0318.jpg" n="11"/>the main task and purpose of the Commission is to convince American Polonia of the need for a Polish Army and the purpose for which it is being created. He said also that, as a soldier, he may not say how large that army is at present, for that is a military secret, but, he added, that army must be of considerable size, since its numbers are kept secret so that enemy will not know the extent of Polish strength. He also said that the Polish Army consists of infantry, cavalry, an artillery division which has amazed the French officers, an air corps, and an engineers' corps, or "sappers". These sappers, Kleczkowski added, have been assigned by the French high command to train American soldiers. He placed the greatest emphasis upon the fact that the Poles ought not to wait for better terms, but, seeing the present crisis, ought to volunteer now, in order to make the Polish Army as large as possible. "Would any of you," said Captain Kleczkowski, "being on the bank of a river in which your mother was drowning, permit her to drown? Or would you throw yourself to her rescue without hesitation? Such is now the case with our homeland. This is no time to dicker for terms. We <pb facs="5423968_11_0319.jpg" n="12"/>must all throw ourselves to the rescue of our beloved Poland by volunteering for the Polish Army." The applause at the conclusion of this address seemed endless.</p>
   <p>The final speaker was J. Przyprawa, inspector for the Polish Army, The audience then sang "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland). During Kleczkowski's address, Major Kozlowski shook hands with each of the thirty volunteers present and with the ladies of the Red Cross.</p>
   <p>On the platform were representatives of the local and outside Citizens' Committees, citizens of South Chicago, and the Reverend Wojtalewicz, B. K. Szudzinski, Osadnik, of Laporte, Indiana, Gadalz, and E. Kowalewski. We failed to see the local pastors, Reverends Lange and Walczak, however.</p>
   <p>The Polish Army Bank was greeted everywhere with great enthusiasm, both on its way to South Chicago and on its way back. American listeners could not <pb facs="5423968_11_0320.jpg" n="13"/>find words enough to praise these boys, who drew crowds into their car from all the other cars in the train with their playing. The stations were also thronged with people who wanted to hear our boys play.</p>
   <p>[Translators note: Comment on neglect of the local Citizens' Committee to provide refreshment for the bands has been omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
