<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-12">July 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Two National Holidays in Cracow</title><title level="a" type="sub">(News from the Homeland)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-12">July 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">TWO NATIONAL HOLIDAYS IN CRACOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(News From The Homeland)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The feasts of "Konik Zwierzyniecki" (The Zoological Horse) and "Wianki" (The Garlands) came on June 23. Both of these national holidays enjoy great popularity and their success seems to increase with each year. Holding to the chronological order, it is proper to first say a few words about "The Horse".</p>
   <p>Immediately after the Maryan procession, a Tartar left from Zwierzniecki Street to go to the public market and on his way he performed his first skirmish before the Episcopal (bishop's) palace, surrounded by the massed rows of the curious who scattered before his massive scepter. This year the "Horse" was equipped: An adequate number of pearls, naturally paste, were set here and there on his turban, his crimson cloth was evidently new. His procession was also newly equipped. The Magistrate's subsidy helped the renewal as well as the retention of the festivity which, despite everything, has beautiful traditional background.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_1034.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before dawn of that enchanted June evening, tens of thousands of people had gathered at the shores of the Vistula to celebrate the feast of "Wianki" (Garlands), conducted at present by the gymnastic association of "Falcons" (Sokol). Before the eyes of the spectators there moved in succession the races of the members of the nautical group of the Falcons held on boats and kayaks. This sport should be held more often. A further point of the program pertained to the dropping of garlands: hundreds appeared upon the waves of the Vistula in varicolored light. The scene at times was rather beautiful and picturesque. Following this the Falcon Choir arrived by water upon floats lit up with Bengal torches and sang several national hymns and Mr. Madrzykowski burned the artificial fires which, now as ever, bring him pride. The aerial fires, as well as those won the water, especially the latter, have gained general recognition; loud applause rewarded Mr. Madrzykowski. With a portrait (appropriate to the significance of the day), "The Battle For The Fern," the exercises were concluded.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
