<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-29">Jan. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Bill</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-29">Jan. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION BILL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Immigration Bill that was passed recently by the House is aimed, in part, at those immigrants who would come to this country and cause additional competition for American labor.</p>
   <p>The bill is also aimed at prospective immigrants who have not been instructed in the rudiments of learning. This element is not considered worthy of enjoying the full rights of free American citizens.</p>
   <p>This bill also obligates all immigrants to take an oath that they will become American citizens. They must also know how to read and write in their native language.</p>
   <p>Nothing can be said against the enactment of such a bill. It is aimed against <pb facs="5423968_11_0140.jpg" n="2"/>these newcomers from Canada and Europe who come to the United States for the sole purpose of getting work so as to accumulate enough money to return to their native country, where the living is cheap and where they can live on the money they made over here. Such people are not desired in this country. They take away the bread from the mouths of American workers, and also take away a portion of the capital of the country, thereby depleting the wealth of the country.</p>
   <p>Nothing can be said against the portion of that bill which tries to raise the intellectual level of the citizens of America. A person not versed in the "three R's," no matter what his nationality or language may be, has not learned how to think properly. That type of individual is not worthy of becoming a citizen of this country, as he is not capable of fulfilling the duties of a free American citizen.</p>
   <p>The bill as a whole cannot possibly fulfill the aims intended by its sponsors. By it certain classes of immigrants from Europe are directly exposed to <pb facs="5423968_11_0141.jpg" n="3"/>chicanery on the part of the American "Know-nothing party". The immigrant questioned by an official on his arrival in New York, as to whether or not he wishes to become a citizen, will say "Yes". However, this immigrant, after a few years, may desire to return to his native country. Who or what is going to prevent him? Would it be right to withhold his passport or take over his possessions? This section of the immigration bill is void of practical meaning.</p>
   <p>Other portions of the bill state that the immigrant must know how to read and write in his native tongue. To us Poles this section has a great meaning, for all of us know that we have come from Poland, but the majority of American officials are not aware of this, since Poland to them does not exist as a country. They are familiar with and recognize Russia, Austria, and Prussia, and if this bill demands of the immigrant Pole, who hails from Polish territory occupied by Russia, Prussia, or Austria, that he must be able to speak and write the language of the country by which he is ruled, he will be denied entrance to America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0142.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Such an interpretation of the bill by the "Know-nothing party" endangers the interests of our nation. Even today the American enemies of the Poles are triumphant, not wishing to distinguish between a Polish Jew and a Pole; so that the influx of Poles to this country will be curtailed.</p>
   <p>We are not against the bill as a whole, but in the best interests of the Washington lawmakers, it is hoped that the form of the new bill [when it has finally passed both Houses] will have sense, and that the Poles, who consider themselves equal to the European and American peoples, will not be treated worse than the Cuban plantation settlers by the grandsons of Kosciusko and Pulaski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
