<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-18">Dec. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-18">Dec. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From Washington we have been informed by Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, a Chicagoan, that the immigration question is again encountering stormy seas. The opponents of immigration, the dyed-in-the-wool chauvinists, are not neglecting this matter, but continue to work toward stopping the flow of immigration. To accomplish this purpose they use all possible means.</p>
   <p>On September 6 the Farmers Educational and Co-operative Union of America held a conference at Shawnee, Oklahoma, at which a resolution was passed, by a tremendous majority, demanding the cessation of immigration. Many such resolutions are now being received by congressmen, all demanding that the necessary steps be taken to close the borders to foreigners.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath is an ardent defender of the immigrants and has had <pb facs="5423968_11_0037.jpg" n="2"/>several battles on their behalf with American chauvinists in Congress. He has been able, upon several occasions, with the help of other congressmen, to postpone action on the immigration question, but his opponents are not sleeping on the job. Congressman Sabath has gone to Panama, as a member of a congressional committee, to inspect work on the canal, and will not return until January 4 of next year. He has, however, received the assurance of the Committee on Immigration that it will not take up the immigration question until his return, when he can again enter the battle. We must, therefore, again be prepared to support Congressman Sabath and his favorable disposed colleagues in this battle. It may be that again we will have to send a counter-resolution to various congressmen from Polish electoral districts urging them to defend the immigrants, as we have already done several times in the past. We must be on guard, because the devil does not slumber, but tempts the enemies of the poor immigrants who come here bringing their strength, health, and willingness to work.</p>
   <p>The House Committee on Immigration, in the recommendations which it submitted <pb facs="5423968_11_0038.jpg" n="3"/>to Congress, expressed itself definitely against immigration, asserting that the majority of the immigrants constitute an undesirable and criminal element, and that many such "criminals" get in who are only a burden and a menace to the country. The Committee recommends the placing of a higher head tax upon immigrants, and the definite barring of adult illiterate immigrants. According to the wishes of the Committee, steamship companies which bring such immigrants here would be fined, and would have to deport these immigrants at their own expense.</p>
   <p>With these recommendations the farmers' society is wholeheartedly in accord, and urges Congress to bring them into effect as soon as possible. A frenzied chauvinism has made inroads even among the farmers who until now were peaceful and well disposed toward immigrants. Alone, these farmers are unable to cultivate the tremendous fields which they own, but still they feel an aversion to the poor but hard-working immigrant, who, if he were directed to the farms by Federal or civic agencies, would surely raise the level of agriculture, would cease being a burden in industrial centers, and would assure the farmers an adequate supply of labor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0039.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These furious chauvinists do not want to understand this; instead, they invent laws making the entry of immigrants more difficult, under the silly pretext that most immigrants are criminals. In truth, native Yankees have among their ranks more actual criminals in one of their larger cities than the immigrants from Europe have in the entire country. This is a fact which the police records prove.</p>
   <p>We are prepared in every way for a new battle in defense of the immigrants, and we will be backed by legions of intelligent people who are not prejudiced and blinded, even though they were born and raised in this country. Many congressmen, also, are on our side. We must not allow ourselves to be bested by the enemies of immigration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
