<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Restriction of Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-07">Dec. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">RESTRICTION OF IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American nationalistic fanatics have again declared a war against immigration from Europe and other parts of the world. A Congressional committee established some three years ago for the purpose of investigating immigration conditions, and finding means of regulating immigration into America, has recently issued a report of its work, observations, and recommendations. This report is contained in forty printed volumes and embodies many interesting things. A considerable amount of space in this report is devoted to the recommendations of this committee. Some of the most outstanding intellectuals and civic leaders of the time were members of this commission. These gentlemen arrived at the conclusion that people were not emigrating for political reasons, because persecutions of people of opposite political convictions had already ceased (we doubt it), and the only intention of immigrants to America was to gain <pb facs="5423968_11_0060.jpg" n="2"/>employment here and to send out their earnings to their native land.</p>
   <p>We cannot understand what prompted these gentlemen to come to a conclusion that immigrants to the United States in these days are not fleeing from polical enslavement and oppression. Their argument is only a clumsy excuse, their sole aim is to stem the flow of immigration. Everyone knows that Poles, as well as Bohemians, Slavs, Irish, and other oppressed people, come here primarily for political reasons; they cannot breathe freely or develop nationally under strange governments. It is true that a considerable number of them come to America for economic reasons as well, but these people create more things here with their labor than they get paid for in return. They create wealth here, not for themselves, but for the local magnates, who exploit immigrants.</p>
   <p>The type of report submitted by the committee on immigration affairs is not at all surprising; on the contrary, it could have been expected, especially <pb facs="5423968_11_0061.jpg" n="3"/>since a person of Senator Lodge's viewpoint was a member of that committee. It required a great amount of difficult and tireless work of organizations and the influence of voters of various nationalities, naturalized citizens, to combat the recommendations of Lodge's famous anti-immigration bill. This bill was presented at a time previous to his appointment on the immigration committee. It will be necessary for us to be on the alert and to extend this watchfulness, because the recommendation of this committee will come under consideration during the coming session of Congress. No one knows what the result would have been, had not organizations and the electorate of various nationalities raised a protest against the intended severe restrictions on immigration.</p>
   <p>The commission recommends the placing of a tax on every new arrival. Other suggestions are that every new arrival should show a larger amount of money; that ordinary workers should be denied entry and only craftsmen and professionals be admitted, and that every immigrant should know how to read and write <pb facs="5423968_11_0062.jpg" n="4"/>at least in his own language.</p>
   <p>If these recommendations were to pass, it would mean that only every tenth immigrant would be permitted to enter the United States. It is a known fact that a majority of the new arrivals of this country are ordinary workers and that only a few are tradesmen. It is also known that many immigrants are totally illiterate or know how to read but not how to write. The most hardy laboring people would be held back and immigration from Poland, Italy, Hungary, Spain, and many other nations would be limited to a minimum. There is but one thing on which the immigration commission is correct: that is, that immigrants do not have the same proportion of criminals as citizens born here. And yet, for some inexplicable reason, this commission is opposed to immigration.</p>
   <p>The recommendations of this commission go even further; they suggest a limitation on the number of immigrants to be admitted at a given port. This means that if <pb facs="5423968_11_0063.jpg" n="5"/>it were decreed that the number of immigrants for the port of New York was not to exceed one thousand persons a month and it happened that two thousand arrived there, one half of the unfortunates would be returned, even if they satisfied all of the rules and regulations of immigration.</p>
   <p>It is therefore necessary for all right thinking people to make preparations in defense of immigration if we do not wish to have the gates of freedom closed to our brethren who wish to search here for a haven and livelihood.</p>
   <p>One thing for which the immigration commission can be praised is its recommendation that governmental bureaus be established whose duty it would be to find employment for the new arrivals or to put them on farms. The commission admits that arrivals from Europe are the best and most capable farmers and that they can be depended upon to develop our agriculture. Consequently, <pb facs="5423968_11_0064.jpg" n="6"/>they contend, immigrants must necessarily be settled on farms and not permitted to congregate and kill themselves in large cities. There is a great deal of truth in that statement, but by it the commission contradicts its first recommendations, which would graciously allow entry only to tradesmen and those who know how to read and write. Evidently they do not know that a tradesman will never be a farmer or, again, that a majority of capable farm workers did not have the opportunity to learn how to read and write. Whom, therefore, will they settle upon farms, since they forbid entry to hard-working farmers? This matter will be considered more thoroughly in subsequent articles, as it will soon become very widely publicized in the House and the Senate. We shall then be able to elucidate it more adequately. Our people, as well as those of other nationalities, should, and will, know of what attempts are made to hinder their progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
