<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>- Vol. VIII No.28.
<date when="1904-07-13">July 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chronicle Dr. Adam Szwajkart Named Park Commissioner</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>NAROD POLSKI</title>- Vol. VIII No.28.
<date when="1904-07-13">July 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chronicle DR. ADAM SZWAJKART NAMED PARK COMMISSIONER</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are informing our readers that Dr. A Szwajkart, our head physician <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Chicago, and especially among the Poles in the northwestern part of the city, has been named West Parks Commissioner by Governor Yates.</p>
   <p>This news come as a surprise to the people of other nationalities. Customarily there are many persons seeking this office, because it is an office of high honor and does not bring material benefits to the individual, but rather high esteem. It does not happen to be (as often happens in political circles) some sort of recompense or favor given for services rendered to some political party, but an honor given to persons highly deserving.</p>
   <p>Dr. Adam Szwajkart, whose portrait was shown in the local English dailies has been known for many years to his own countrymen in Chicago; he is the head physician of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, is a member of the staff of physicians at the Sisters of Nazareth Hospital, physician to the Austrian Consulate, physician at the Home for Orphans, etc. He has always been and <pb facs="5423968_11_0983.jpg" n="2"/>and still is very active in matters concerning the Poles in general, regardless of party affiliations in a way such as real patriot should be.</p>
   <p>Therefore, our hearts are filled with joy at this new distinction of our head physician, which is also delightful and honorable to us. We offer heartiest congratulations in the name of the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
