<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-23">May 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish National Alliance Gives Banquet for Polish Army Military Band</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-23">May 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE GIVES BANQUET FOR POLISH ARMY MILITARY BAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, at two o'clock, a banquet was held at the Wawell Restaurant for the Polish Army Military Band from Camp Kosciusko at Niagara-on-the-Lake. The banquet was under the sponsorship of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Our capable musicians, with Wasilewski, their conductor, and Lieutenant Sulewski, sat down to well-laden tables. The Polish National Alliance was represented by Casimir Zychlinski, president, J. Magdziarz, treasurer, and Mrs. M. Milewski, J. Singer, and W. Pijenowski, directors. W. Grabewski represented Dziennik Zwiazkowy. Just as the banquet was about to begin, Major Joseph Kozlowski, chief of the Polish Military Commission in France, accompanied by W. Rezanski, organizer for Recruiting Center II, arrived at the restaurant. Major Kozlowski was greeted with a storm of applause. After greeting Zychlinski, he was introduced to the officers and directors of the Polish National Alliance, the members of the military band, and the volunteers for the Polish Army who had just arrived from <pb facs="5423968_11_0322.jpg" n="2"/>Omaha and Texas, and who were also present at the banquet.</p>
   <p>The first after-dinner address was delivered by Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance. His words had the same effect upon the boys of the band as dew has on wilted plants, for when he had finished speaking, new confidence showed in their faces, and they were convinced that Chicago Polonia would take care of them as Polish volunteers deserved. Of this the Polish National Alliance gave the first evidence. Zychlinski assured the members of the band and Major Kozlowski that the Polish National Alliance, the aim of which it has always been to aid the Polish cause, will in the future, also, do everything in its power to help build up the Polish Army. He then placed two hundred dollars in the hands of Lieutenant Sulewski as a gift from the Polish National Alliance, to be used for the immediate needs of the Polish Army Band. At the sight of this, the boys arose and gave a cheer for the Polish National Alliance, and thanked Zychlinski for so generous a gift and for the wonderful reception they were accorded.</p>
   <p>Zychlinski then said: "Remember, boys, that if you are ever in need, you can <pb facs="5423968_11_0323.jpg" n="3"/>turn to the Polish National Alliance, and it will always help you."</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Sulewski spoke on behalf of the band, thanking the Alliance and its president for so splendid a gift and reception. He recommended that the boys give three cheers for the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The next address was delivered by Major Kozlowski, chief of the Polish Military Commission in France. Speaking in truly military fashion, he greeted the boys as comrades in arms, adding that in a short time his mission will be over and he will return to France. He expected, too, that shortly after his arrival there, he would be moved to the battle front with the Polish Army, to give the Germans proof that the Poles are fighting. He mentioned also that the boys should not complain if they do not get some of the things to eat to which they were accustomed at home, such as roast chicken, for example. He assured them, however, that the food would be good, nutritious, and healthful, and that they would lack nothing that a soldier needs. Anyone who is acquainted with a soldier's life, continued the major, envies him; for a soldier's life is athletic <pb facs="5423968_11_0324.jpg" n="4"/>and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, such as people paid good money for before the war.</p>
   <p>Zychlinski then asked one of the recruits to volunteer a few words. One of the volunteers, Leon Pachowski, of San Antonio, Texas, arose. En route to the training camp with a number of other recruits, he had stopped at Recruiting Center XI. He spoke very well, urging these present to agitate for more recruits to fight the Germans. He added that he would not forget what he had seen; namely, hew the Polish National Alliance received the military band and how Chicago Polonia in general aids the volunteers to the Polish Army.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, Zychlinski arose to say that he must leave the hall to attend a meeting of the [Polish] National Department. He said that he hoped something would be done at this meeting about uniforms for the Polish Army Band. When the boys heard this, they arose and cheered again, for the question of uniforms is one of their most pressing problems. Their enthusiasm was such that when they played "Jeszeze Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland is not yet lost) and the "Alliance March," it seemed as if the walls of the restaurant must burst. One cannot <pb facs="5423968_11_0325.jpg" n="5"/>help mentioning on every occasion that these boys play uncommonly well. On all sides one hears: "My, but they play! You can feel immediately that it is a military band." And we feel that they will play still better when they are dressed in new Polish uniforms and when they have better instruments.</p>
   <p>As the band played later in front of the Polish Women's Alliance building, W. Helezer, president of a real-estate association, gave the boys ten dollars for cigarettes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
