<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-06">Sept. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Hold Reception for Dr. C. Lewakowski and S. Balicki at Pulaski Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-06">Sept. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">HOLD RECEPTION FOR DR. C. LEWAKOWSKI AND S. BALICKI AT PULASKI HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Polish National Alliance paid tribute last night at Pulaski Hall to two distinguished Poles from Europe, Dr. C. Lewakowski, minister of the Austrian government, and Sigmund Balicki of Geneva [Switzerland], president of the Polish Immigrants' Alliance of Europe. When the guests entered the gaily decorated hall they were greeted with shouts, music, and applause from capacity audience.</p>
   <p>Various groups from the Second Corps of the Polish Army of America and members of the Polish Sokols were on hand to welcome the two visitors.</p>
   <p>After the two prominent Poles had been escorted to the stage the following leading Polish citizens took chairs beside them: Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, pastor of Holy Trinity Church; S. F. Adalia Satalecki, Mr. Slominski, Judge M. A. LaBuy, Mr. Majewski, J. F. Smulski, Smietanki, Bardonski, S. Schmidt, Przymorski, H. F. Jablonski, A. Chmielinski, and many others. The reception <pb facs="5423968_11_0677.jpg" n="2"/>was opened by Mr. Smulski, who introduced the two guests.</p>
   <p>The initial speech was made by Dr. Lewakowski. His speech, primarily one of greeting to Polish-Americans, was as follows:</p>
   <p>"We came to this country from the fatherland imbued with the feeling of love and friendship for our fellow Poles. I greet you sincerely in your native tongue. I greet you in the name of my birthplace, the city of Lwow. The citizens of that city send you their best regards. I greet you in the name of the Democratic Society of which I am president and founder. This organization gives succor to the poor and oppressed.</p>
   <p>"By special recommendation I greet you in the name of the Polish peasantry of Galicia, which I have learned to love and which I serve. I salute you in the name of the Polish Immigrants' Alliance, which I visited before embarking for the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0678.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I also paid a visit to the city of Rapperschwil, where the Polish National Museum is located, with many books and memoirs of the Polish spirit. In the name of this institution and the Commission of the Polish National Fund, I bring you salutations. The citizens of Warsaw, the Polish capital which is now covered in mourning, salute you. The representatives of that city delegated me to present you with soil form the graves of five Polish heroes, so that you may use it to grow the seed for the freedom of Poland. In the name of Warsaw I salute you!</p>
   <p>I embrace you all and draw you to my heart. This reception you have prepared for us, is a beautiful one, but I want you to know that I am no better than you. I want you to know that it is my firm belief that a slave is not the one that is shackled but the one who licks the hand of the enemy! Therefore, I am grateful for this welcome not because of my status, but because I come from the partitioned fatherland. Long live Polonia in Chicago! Long live the Poles!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0679.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The speaker's words were received with loud applause and cheers.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lewakowski was followed by Mr. Balicki, who supplemented to his associates remarks:</p>
   <p>"I bring you greetings from the Polish people of Europe, from secret forces which are working under cover for the liberation of our country in Russian-occupied Poland. To this I should like to add more; however, silence is more golden than words."</p>
   <p>The speaker then pointed out that the purpose of his visit was "the union of forces, the tying of knots of unity, and the creation of one soul which will ring with one voice".</p>
   <p>Later on Mr. Balicki spoke about the Polish national movements in this country. Mr. Balicki was in great favor of working and acting for the right of existence of the Polish nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0680.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"The voice of the struggle for life, the voice of protest," averred the speaker, "is the true voice of the Polish nation. Without this struggle the land that is now divided by our three enemies cannot be united. This struggle also takes on a greater meaning. It is a secret organ which is the keystone to the secret work which is being conducted for the liberation of Poland. This work should be continued with an iron hand and an iron will, for only in this way will it be accomplished.</p>
   <p>"One of the programs being carried out to bring about the Freedom of our nation," Mr. Balicki continued, "is the establishment and the maintenance of the Polish National Fund [founded by Polish Societies about 1870]."</p>
   <p>He urged that more work be done in this direction and more contributions be made.</p>
   <p>Although this was a short speech, Mr. Balicki's words were very impressive, and won the applause of the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0681.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This was followed by a medley of songs by the combined Moniuszko and Halka Choirs. The band of the Second Corps also played a number of Polish national airs.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lewakowski was called again to take the stand. He said that the work for the Polish cause should be conducted as follows:</p>
   <p>"The principle of this work is the idea of freedom for Poland. This idea existed during the days of old Poland, but later it was forgotten. John Casimir revived this idea. The Constitution of the Third of May [1791] gave the nation now liberties, but, unfortunately, even this met its doom. Kesciusko, Staszyc, and Mickiewicz devoted their lives for the propagation of this idea. The Polish gentry demanded: "Make the laboring class citizens," continued the speaker.</p>
   <p>"The Insurrection of 1863 [uprising against Russian oppression] renewed the idea of brotherhood and national freedom. As a youth I helped to spread this <pb facs="5423968_11_0682.jpg" n="7"/>idea of freedom through the villages of Podole [eastern part of Poland under Russian occupation]. And today as a graying man I still help to sow the seeds of this ideal. After all, there is only one truth. The mother places this truth before her child in the cradle as a guiding star, and this star should act as a guide until the grave. The truth is that a nation cannot exist without people, and the people should have their future assured. Beside the national ideals should stand religion, the Holy Faith of the Roman Catholic Church. It is our duty to safeguard our faith, for it teaches us our obligations to God and mankind.</p>
   <p>"Our second duty should be toward the fatherland. This is not only being propagated here but practiced here," concluded Dr. Lewakowski.</p>
   <p>The doctor promised to return to Chicago after attending the Polish National Alliance Convention at Cleveland.</p>
   <p>After the singing by the Moniuszko and Halka Choirs, Mr. Satalecki said a few <pb facs="5423968_11_0683.jpg" n="8"/>words. The reception was concluded by singing "God Save Poland".</p>
   <p>Many outstanding Polish citizens of Chicago were present at this reception.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
