<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1918-02-13">Feb. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">N. L. Piotrowski, Our New President</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0908</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0908.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1918-02-13">Feb. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">N. L. PIOTROWSKI, OUR NEW PRESIDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Roman-Catholic Union of America has elected its new president, on whom Narod Polski, weekly newspaper, commented in various publications. About him is printed a long article, but very truly, consciously, without mixture of his political activities. Any member of the Roman-Catholic Union would be very curious to know a brief story from his lifetime activities, in order to make a true judgment about the new leader of the Roman-Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>Mr. M. L. Piotrowski was born at Bnina, province of Poxen. He came here to America as a 19 year old boy. His first education received in Notre Dame, later in Valparaiso, where he received academical degree, with title of doctor of both laws.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0909.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before he started his practice of law, he was professor of mathematics and grammer in St. Thomas College, St. Paul, Minn.</p>
   <p>Since 1892 Mr. N. L. Piotrowski has been permanent resident of the city of Chicago as a lawyer conducting his professional duty with great success. For four years he was city attorney in Chicago. To the Roman-Catholic Union he already belonged and was twice a managing officer of this institution. In a short time after assuming duty as a manager of this organization in 1910, there was discovered a large embezzlement in this institution. The executive officers during that administration of said institution in a full agreement with two conventions have given instructions to him to prefer charges in the Criminal Court against all the embezzlers. On account of this criminal charge two criminal processes were started and both were conducted by him, and were successfully finished for the Roman-Catholic Union. Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, as a lawyer acting and conducting, won both processes and saved over $50,000 for the R. C. U., <pb facs="5423968_11_0910.jpg" n="3"/>money which would otherwise have been lost. In all national Polish affairs he has been very active. He published articles in local American newspapers in defense of his countrymen living here in emigration.</p>
   <p>Two years ago he was selected and sent to Europe as a reporter, delegate, and representative of the Herald and Examiner and seven other big newspapers from here to investigate the existing conditions of Polish affairs and its relations to other states of Europe. This trip lasted over seven months, during which time he visited all the countries of Europe, except Germany, and conferred with leaders and politicians. His remarkable reflections and observations have been published and printed in English newspapers.</p>
   <p>Mr. N. L. Piotrowski visited the White House in Washington, D. C., and conferred with the Presidents of the United States of America; once with <pb facs="5423968_11_0911.jpg" n="4"/>Taft and the second time with Mr. Wilson.</p>
   <p>Few months ago Mr. N. L. Piotrowski organized and established a Polish institution on a firm basis; a unique institution of its kind among Polish people here, and its name is The Great Lakes Insurance Company.</p>
   <p>Without doubt Piotrowski can do very much more helping our institutions and defending our country against unfriendly attacks in the foreign and domestic press.</p>
   <p>When President Wilson announced for the first time his candidacy for presidency, and before his campaign, Mr. N. L. Piotrowski was among the first Polish citizens who offered to support Mr. Wilson; Piotrowski was strongly critized for this. Today all Polish people are convinced that President Wilson is the best friend the Polish people have.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
