<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-12">Jan. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Vilna Is Ours</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-12">Jan. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">VILNA IS OURS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago the telegraph brought very happy news for Poland of the results of the results of the plebiscite, or as they call it the consultation of the people, on the question of the Vilna territory. The plebiscite was held on January 8, and the result of it is clear and incontrovertible proof of the correctness of Poland's stand in regard to the Vilna question. The population of the territory voted overwhelmingly to be incorporated in the Polish state and against joining Lithuania.</p>
   <p>So far we have not received the final results of the voting in the entire Vilna territory. We must remind our readers that lately several counties were added to this territory which formerly were part of Poland. The votes are being counted in Vilna, Troki, and Oszmiona and in others of the larger towns and settlements. The Polish press will publish in the near future the result <pb facs="5423968_11_0249.jpg" n="2"/>of the voting. Initial information received seems to indicate that the great majority of the population voted for Poland.</p>
   <p>News from England adds that the final decision rests with the League of Nations and will be announced within the next few days, perhaps today or tomorrow. We do not know what the League will have to say in this matter, but we imagine that it will consist of formal acknowledgment of the results of the voting, since it could not go against the wishes of the population, which voted for annexation to Poland. After all, the League cannot separate Polish land from Poland and join it to a foreign country against the expressed desire of the people. In view of these facts we need not worry in the least about the final decision of the League of Nations in this matter.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that now, after the consultation of the people of Vilna, we shall also find some modus vivendi with the Lithuanians beyond the borders of Vilna territory. The world is convinced, and so the Lithuanians <pb facs="5423968_11_0250.jpg" n="3"/>should also be convinced that Poland was right in demanding Vilna for herself and in refusing it to the Lithuanians. Historic traditions are unimportant when faced with present realities. We have experienced it ourselves, and we make no apologies to any one in this matter. We all know that Poland's former territory was at least three times as extensive as the present area of the newly reconstituted independent state. But Poland had to agree with [the League's] decision and to renounce large areas on all her borders. We are all aware that Breslau, in Silesia, was once a Polish city, but the present boundary in this part runs near Bytom, and even this was gained only with great difficulty because of the intrigues and the greed of our enemies; and on the east we used to drive our boundary posts in the river Dnieper, but today how far west of this river is our border! And so it does not matter that once upon a time Lithuanians owned the territory where Vilna now is because Vilna was built by Polish initiative and remained Polish through centuries to such an extent that in its territory Lithuanians form the smaller percentage of the total population.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0251.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Lithuanians should at last come to the conclusion that this is the best way out, and that it is to their highest interest to live in understanding and agreement with Poland. It is hard to fight windmills or to swim against a strong current. Today it is known that the people of the Vilna territory do not desire to live under the Lithuanian government. Would they, then, endeavor to keep this people in subjection against their expressed desire? It is silly even to think of it. We say, therefore, that Lithuanians ought, at long last, to open their eyes and set out on the way of rapprochement and understanding with Poland. If the Vilna plebiscite brings this about, it will be the first step toward the elimination of differences between these two neighboring peoples, and in time it may become a mustard seed, a tiny insignificant seed, from which, in the future, the strong and magnificent tree of Polish-Lithuanian alliance will grow; there may even be a rebirth in the hearts of our children of the eagle and the knight of ancient glorious Jagellonian tradition. [Translator's note: During the Jagellonian dynasty Poland and Lithuania formed a federation, somewhat like that of England and Scotland today. They had two separate diets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0252.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The eagle is the Polish national emblem, and the knight is the emblem of Lithuania.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
