<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-19">Dec. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Proposals Restricting Immigration to America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Voices of the Press--What are the Results to Be? (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-12-19">Dec. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PROPOSALS RESTRICTING IMMIGRATION TO AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Voices of the Press--What are the Results to Be? (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the legislative realms, under the initiative of Republican leaders, a movement started sometime ago to greatly curtail the flow of immigrants from Europe. This movement reached a climax recently when a committee presented to the Senate its proposals relative to the immigration problem. According to its suggestions, only those immigrants coming to America will be accepted who can read and write in their native tongue, who possess a hundred dollars or mere, etc. Senator Chandler proposes more: as a protective measure against Cholera, he suggests that immigration be stopped completely for one year be-ginning March 1, 1893.</p>
   <p>Beth of these proposals were covered by the Dziennik Chicagoski, which has also mentioned the strong opposition voiced by the steamship companies against these proposals. Last week these companies stopped the issuance of prepaid third-class <pb facs="5423968_11_0172.jpg" n="2"/>tickets, and beginning the first of the year third-class passenger fares are to be discontinued and rates on first and second-class travel are to be doubled. A delegation representing the leading steamship lines came before the Senate to voice its grievances. Discussion of the immigration proposals is to begin this week.</p>
   <p>This problem, which involves the vital economic interests of the United States, is arousing considerable interest, and a wide divergence of opinion is reflected in the general press. The voices of the press are very interesting. The American press in general is in favor of curtailing immigration. Opinions to that effect are found not only in the Republican papers but also in a large number of Independent papers, and even in some of the Democratic journals.</p>
   <p>The newspapers, however, go further than the proposals which are now before the Senate. Not only do they demand a curtailment of immigration, but often they suggest closing the immigration gates for two or more years. Others propose different measures for checking the flow of immigrants to America. The following are characteristic opinions of the press at large.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0173.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The influential New York Herald (Independent) plainly states that it favors the discontinuance of immigration for one year, and unceremoniously says: "This will safeguard us for twelve months against Cholera, paupers, and ten-dollar immigrants." The New York Times (Independent-Republican), Indianapolis Journal, Minneapolis Tribune, Philadelphia Republican, Denver Leader, and Cincinnati Commercial, all Republican papers, are in accord with the Herald. The Commercial goes so far as to recommend banning immigration for two years. The Republican Kansas City Journal goes a step further by asking that immigration be banned for an indefinite period in order to prevent the influx of the ignorant, criminal and degenerate elements which have arisen during a century of decadence in Europe. The Boston Traveler plainly asks: "Why not repeat the same steps as were taken against the Chinese?" And the Baltimore News (Democratic) states that the present day flow of immigrants is not only detrimental to the "Anglo-Saxon ambition and industrialism, but the lower classes of Russians, Poles, Italians, etc., are often afflicted by disease, are wanted by law or are poor." Perhaps the most severe opinion was issued by the Oregonian, a Republican paper published in Portland, Oregon. The Oregonian demands a flat ten year stoppage of immigration, and states: "We want pure <pb facs="5423968_11_0174.jpg" n="4"/>Americans--not half-breed citizens."</p>
   <p>Other papers have different proposals for the curtailment of immigration. The New York Herald, for example, suggests a hundred-dollar tax on each immigrant coming into the United States. This proposition, similar to those of medieval times finds, however, little support. The Pittsburgh Gazette (Republican) is the only paper that favors it. On the other hand, the Milwaukee Sentinel (Republican) is of the opinion that this idea would be a failure. The St. Paul Globe (Independent-Democratic) very justly claims that the hundred-dollar tax would not decrease the flow of immigration but would increase the number of paupers in the United States, since the immigrant after arriving here would be shorn of his savings and would undoubtedly become a pauper.</p>
   <p>From this cross section of the American press it can be seen that a majority of papers are in favor of stemming the flow of immigration. This is especially true of the Republican newspapers. The Democratic papers, however, and some of the Republican ones, do not favor the proposals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0175.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For instance, the Nashville American contends that free America ought to open its doors wide and become a haven for all oppressed peoples. The Pioneer Press (Independent) of St. Paul is of the opinion that the ban on immigration would be unjust to all those thousands of honest people who have a desire to settle in America. The Republican Detroit Tribune is opposed to the curtailment or complete ban on immigration and does not suggest any radical changes. The Buffalo Evening News (Independent-Democratic) says that it is not necessary to revert to any "Chinese restrictions." The Arkansas Democrat remarks that the present immigration laws are sufficient. According to the Colorado Sun, America ought to be always a haven for the oppressed. The most convincing commentary on this subject is given by the Brooklyn Citizen, which speaks out as follows:</p>
   <p>"The wealth of the people is represented by work and not capital. Work produces wealth, and the greater the productivity the greater the prosperity, because every producer makes more than he can use. Such idle talk about the dangers of the mixture of races is asinine; they will not assimilate us, but we will assimilate them. There is room in America for more people than the millions the <pb facs="5423968_11_0176.jpg" n="6"/>white race of Europe can send; therefore, we ought to prepare a better welcome for all those who come to live among us with honorable intentions."</p>
   <p>Most of the other Democratic papers express similar opinions, and their attitude encourages us to hope that the proposals curtailing or completely forbidding immigration without any apparent reason will fall to pieces against the sound judgment of the American people.</p>
   <p>The establishment of these proposals as law would not only bring to ruin the plans for the Columbian Exposition in 1893 but, in general, would bring about an upheaval in the economic balance of power in the United States. Assuming that immigration was stopped for a certain period of time, the value of property would, as a result, drop from twenty-five to fifty per cent. This would in turn place the brunt of the consequences on business at large in America.</p>
   <p>This is why we once more express the hope that the Democratic party, whose recent victory is the triumph of the true idea of freedom against the various Republican obstacles and limitations, will not permit the capable and civilized <pb facs="5423968_11_0177.jpg" n="7"/>immigrants from Europe to be placed on the same level as the Chinese barbarians. Otherwise, the United States will be threatened with a great disaster.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
