<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Few More Remarks about the Inefficiency of the Polish Diplomatic Service Abroad</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A FEW MORE REMARKS ABOUT THE INEFFICIENCY OF THE POLISH DIPLOMATIC SERVICE ABROAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reader will no doubt recall our recent two articles devoted to observation on the inefficiency of Polish diplomacy and the poor quality of the diplomatic officials representing the Polish republic abroad. We want to remind you that we severely criticized the ineptitude of this service, its outmoded and antiquated system, wholly inadequate for our modern times, and that we cited some individual cases deserving not only of criticism but of downright condemnation. We discussed the ideas and the circumstances obtaining in Poland and referred to our experience with Polish diplomatic service in Chicago, which greatly needs improvement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In writing about these matters we did not fail to mention that we did not desire to discuss the Polish diplomats in Europe, since the information that we had about them was insufficient, although about the activities of some diplomats there we were quite well informed, as for instance about the Polish legation at the Vatican at the time of the notorious "Ambassador" Kowalski, but about others we could not say very much.</p>
   <p>Today we add an interesting item to our previous remarks and complaints which concerns the Polish legation in Paris. We quote below a few paragraphs from the Polish newspaper in Paris, Polonia, from an article discussing the Polish diplomatic service criticized by us in Dziennik Chicagoski, which seems to prove that even over there the shortcomings of our diplomatic service are clearly recognized, and that even there the people are beginning to realize that Polish interests and Polish prestige are being represented abroad superficially and insufficiently, in a way <pb facs="5423968_11_0237.jpg" n="3"/>detrimental to the dignity of the Polish state in France, a country very closely allied with Poland. The Polish public, evidently realizing the importance of this matter, is beginning to discuss it and to criticize [the diplomatic service]. This is what the Paris Polonia writes:</p>
   <p>"And again, as always, we were not there."</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
   <p>The above quotation is the title of an article in Polonia discussing the absence of Polish representatives at the ceremonies at the Sorbonne, conducted by the Friends of Science in France, at which the president of that society, M. Raymond Poincare, delivered the principal address, followed by the speeches of the representatives of sixteen countries. There was also <pb facs="5423968_11_0238.jpg" n="4"/>another instance [of such neglect] in the ceremonies at the Soldiers' Home, at which all the nationalities that fought under the French flag were represented except the Polish. A similar article was published in the Dziennik Poznanski (Posen Daily News).</p>
   <p>(Translation Continued)</p>
   <p>We will help Polonia and Dziennik Poznanski, so that their complaints may reach Warsaw, even though they have to go via Chicago. This is the reason why we have reprinted the articles quoted above. Many copies of our paper go to Warsaw, and besides, our former articles on this subject were especially marked for delivery to official circles and to persons whose job it is to be well informed in these matters. Today's article with the above-mentioned quotations will follow the same route. It proves, among other things, that <pb facs="5423968_11_0239.jpg" n="5"/>our observations were not erroneous, nor are there only a few isolated cases; on the contrary, it seems that this defective service is general and widespread, and that our diplomacy suffers with chronic debility and is in urgent need of a thorough overhauling. This corroboration of our opinion on this matter by circles closer to Poland than we are is highly gratifying. Perhaps those voices will call the attention [of the Polish government] to this matter, and it will begin to think seriously about radical changes and improvements in the Polish diplomatic service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
