<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Last Rites for the Late Walter Malinowski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennki Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-23">Sept. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LAST RITES FOR THE LATE WALTER MALINOWSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Funeral rites for the late Walter Malinowski, a well-known member of the Polish National Alliance and a popular figure in civic affairs, were held on Monday, September 23, 1918.</p>
   <p>The funeral cortege was led by a band. Immediately following the band were floral wreaths from the many societies to which the deceased belonged. His closest friends acted as pallbearers, headed by Mr. Charles Konarski.</p>
   <p>Following the hearse were the children of the deceased, his bereaved widow, escorted by Mr. Bernard Matz, who was recently appointed legal adviser for the draft board, Mr. S. Opalinski, Mr. and Mrs. J. Sobolewski, Mr. and Mrs. T. Hofman, and many other prominent Polish leaders. A long line of automobiles were in the funeral procession.</p>
   <p>The cortege halted momentarily before the Polish National Alliance building.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0901.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All Alliance office employees and members of the press who, due to the pressure of their work, could not be present at the funeral, paid their respects to their comrade by meeting outside of the Polish National Alliance building.</p>
   <p>A rather sympathetic figure passes into the grave: a figure which could not be readily replaced. His absence will be felt, not only by those with whom he had lived intimately and to whom he was wholeheartedly attached, but also by the Polish youth to whom he was a true leader.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
