<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-23">Sept. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Steczynski's Trip to Poland] (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-23">Sept. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[STECZYNSKI'S TRIP TO POLAND] (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sincerity and the festive mood of the fellow-members of the Polish National Alliance must have filled with joy the hearts of all those present at the testimonial dinner given in honor of Mr. M. B. Steczynski, president of the Polish National Alliance. The distinguished guest had returned from a brief sojourn in Poland, where he had gone in order to attend the celebration of the historic battle of Grunwald. Members of various groups of the Alliance gathered at this banquet. The old and the young, businessmen, doctors, and lawyers, factory workers and office workers, all were at the home of the Alliance; yet, in spite of this mixed aggregation, everyone felt at ease and Pleased. A fraternal spirit predominated throughout--a feeling that a great happy family was holding a reunion. All those present had come for a common purpose--to welcome their leader, to hear from his lips of our beloved Poland, <pb facs="5423968_11_0613.jpg" n="2"/>to hear how he fulfilled the mission entrusted to him by the Eighteenth Convention of the Polish National Alliance. This large aggregation of members of the Alliance had not come to the hall simply to honor a member of the Alliance, whose members are legion, but, as Mr. Steczynski rightly said, to show their fealty and sincere adherence to the Alliance. Mr. Steczynski, whom the people greeted as the leader of an alliance with eighty thousand members, was thanked for his excellent work as a representative of all our Polish immigrants.</p>
   <p>Those who congregated at Walsh's Hall to pay homage to their president, did not do so simply to partake of food and drink. There are other occasions and places for festivities of that type. In this instance, our brethren had only one purpose in mind--to honor the great Polish National Alliance and its supreme ideals by honoring its president. They gathered there to express their feeling of joy and satisfaction in the fact that, after so many years of efforts, today the Polish National Alliance stands morally and materially upon such a <pb facs="5423968_11_0614.jpg" n="3"/>firm foundation as to be in a position to present the results of its efforts to the motherland. A proof of the success of the Alliance is that it sends its representatives to Poland in order to renew the filial ties of attachment with the motherland. Feelings of this type were manifested at this testimonial dinner. When the president spoke about our brethren in Europe--pointing out their undaunted faith in the future, their attachment to the land and the national ideals, the gigantic efforts made in the direction of rejuvenating our people and the results that would evolve therefrom--the enthusiasm grew among his listeners. An unfathomed devotion toward this beloved Poland and her heroic defenders was apparent even among the young people born and educated in America, who know Poland only through narratives or descriptions. When the representative of the Alliance continued in his description of the fervor and enthusiasm with which our brethren in Europe greeted the representatives of the Alliance, how they expressed their sincerity at every occasion, how they thanked them for their hardships in coming to them and for their efforts exerted toward Poland, a feeling of profound emotion <pb facs="5423968_11_0615.jpg" n="4"/>grasped the audience and a tear of yearning could be found in the eyes of many--a tear of joy as well as pride.</p>
   <p>We believe firmly that the same feelings of emotion play in the hearts of every brother and sister under the banner of the Polish National Alliance. Were it not for the long distances they would have to travel and the difficulties resulting therefrom, it is certain that hundreds of thousands would have come to receive their president, to hear from his own lips about the life, development, and work of our brethren abroad, as well as about what they think of our own efforts. Those who were not present when the president spoke, will read of his report with certain satisfaction. Later on, the president will submit a complete report before all the members of the Alliance, which, through its representatives, delegated him to leave our soil and homage, personally, to Poland. He was delegated also to send greetings to our brethren who remain under the triple annexation. Our honored president accomplished his mission worthily. He represented our organization everywhere, attending <pb facs="5423968_11_0616.jpg" n="5"/>large meetings, visiting newspapers and other publications, and interviewing our more prominent compatriots. In this work he was ably aided by another representative of the Alliance, Mr. R. Abczynski, the assistant censor. Both have brought honor not only to the Polish National Alliance but to all the Poles in America as well, whom they presented to Europe in the proper light. The representatives of the Alliance were greeted rather cordially and hospitably wherever they chanced to be. They were welcomed, not as individuals, but as representatives of the greatest national organization in the world, of which a great deal was already known.</p>
   <p>The evening of the reception will always remain a memorable one in the minds of those present. There were several speeches which, although delivered by people born and educated here in America, were permeated with the purest and most sincere love for the oppressed motherland. Homage was being paid this subjected Poland, and various methods were suggested wherein one might serve her best. Words of mutual encouragement were expressed, and a feeling of <pb facs="5423968_11_0617.jpg" n="6"/>attachment to everything Polish was the dominant characteristic of the entire affair. The people were encouraged to exert their most vigorous efforts in behalf of the Polish National Alliance and the Polish Falcons Organization. They vowed perseverance in their endeavors to perfect and elevate our people in America, resolving that our motherland can rely upon our assistance in case of need. Many members of the Alliance who were present at this festivity expressed the wish that such fraternal evenings occur at more frequent intervals. Their contention was that affairs of this type bring the Poles closer to one another, strengthen our faith, enlighten, elevate, and unite, giving encouragement to a more energetic work in the realm of national solidarity. This idea was taken up by the Polish Falcons Alliance, which was numerously represented at this meeting. It was then resolved that evening affairs should be held occasionally, not only for recreational purposes, but also for purposes of elevating the spirit, of assisting ourselves mutually in times of hardship, and of educating the people by pointing out to them ways and means whereby they can best attain their goal. This is an excellent idea that we hope will be put <pb facs="5423968_11_0618.jpg" n="7"/>into practice. It is time that our people become more closely acquainted with one another, not superficially, but in giving counsel for our mutual welfare. We have an undying faith that our Falcons will occasionally prepare such spiritual banquets for our people as will result in a gain for all concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
