<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-21">Jan. 21, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">About the Galician Emigration to North America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-21">Jan. 21, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE GALICIAN EMIGRATION TO NORTH AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The emigration of Polish population from Galicia to America is the object of a lengthy report made by the Galician National Department to the Sejm.</p>
   <p>We are reprinting some of the more important paragraphs of this interesting document, which has been widely published in all the Galician newspapers.</p>
   <p>"Instances of permanent settlement by emigrants in America are rare, and occur only when the emigrant seeking employment finds an exceptionally prosperous condition and, deciding to settle down permanently, sends for his family.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Only Jewish skilled laborers emigrate to North America with the advance intention of settling there permanently.</p>
   <p>"Our Polish emigrants are employed in North America as plain laborers for ditches, or for the simplest but hardest work in factories and mines, earning one to three dollars a day, which, in spite of the high prices of foods, will permit a considerable saving to those satisfied with a simple form of living.</p>
   <p>"Statistics of money sent to Galician post-office branches in various towns are very interesting and prove that certain counties in Galicia receive quite a large amount of money in money orders.</p>
   <p>"A detailed daily report, supplied by the post-office authorities, will soon be published by the bureau of statistics.</p>
   <p>"The total sum of money orders sent from North America to Galicia in 1894 <pb facs="5423968_11_0157.jpg" n="3"/>amounted to 2,656,953 zlotys [monetary unit of Poland--111/4 cents].</p>
   <p>"The largest amount was received by the Jasielski county (329,547 zlotys), then Gorlicki (288,873 zlotys), Sanocki (221,335 zlotys), Rohatynski (178,730 zlotys), Mielecki (140,531 zlotys), Pilznenski (129,748 zlotys), Krosnienski (113,289 zlotys), etc.</p>
   <p>"Due to the universal method of using banks as exchange intermediaries, we must understand that the gross amounts are considerably greater.</p>
   <p>"This kind of emigration has a permanent and mild form.</p>
   <p>"The emigrants travel through Hamburg or Bremen; some buy their steamship tickets from local agencies, and a greater number of them have them sent by relatives already residing in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0158.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Taking advantage of these emigrants, in view of the widely publicized ways and means of travel to Hamburg, is very rare; in Hamburg and Bremen this is considerably more difficult.</p>
   <p>"Yet, in Galicia proper, an emigrant loses a lot of money, for, to get across the boundary line without a passport, he is forced to have the help of smugglers and underworld agents."</p>
   <p>This is part of the official report on the question of emigration to America, which, as we can see, even in these hard times is responsible for the three million zlotys received in Poland, earned by the Polish Galician laborers in America.</p>
   <p>This emigration is very beneficial to the old country.</p>
   <p>But a different situation confronts us on the Brazilian emigrant question, which brings the Poles in Galicia only extortion, failure, and ruin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
