<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV. No.12,
<date when="1904-01-15">Jan. 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Is the Emigration Home a Business?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV. No.12,
<date when="1904-01-15">Jan. 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">IS THE EMIGRATION HOME A BUSINESS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspaper scandal about the Immigrants' Home, is constantly ruining the good work and record of this institution. They claim that it is not a home for the needy immigrants but an enterprising business; and should be able to keep this institution in good standing without any government help.</p>
   <p>But this is not so, because this institution is a charity home, to help the needy, and not a money making enterprise. This home takes donations, but does not compel the needy immigrants to pay. This institution has to abide by its laws, and stay within these bounds, if it wants to exist.</p>
   <p>The main object of this institution is to place these immigrants at work, and do their utmost for them at all times, while in their care. A short time back this institution was closed by the government, pending an investigation because false statements in the newspapers claimed this institution placed young ladies in bad homes, and did not take much interest in this matter. But after a through investigation, it was reopened, due to the fact that the government found all these statements about this institution untrue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0113.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This institution is opened to all Polish and Slavic immigrants. It also has a separate section for beggars; where there is enough space in one room for three or four to sleep at one time and they are treated with the utmost care and given the best food.</p>
   <p>A few of these immigrants pay for their lodging as a donation to this institution but some stay for two or three weeks and, when they are working and able to take care of themselves and their families, they leave; they promise that as soon as they are able they will send a donation.</p>
   <p>Many of these people are soon making a good living, but they never mention a word about this institution helping them when they were hungry and penniless. This is gratitude and the thanks this home receives for its gallant work. How can this immigration home exist, if these people do not help it?</p>
   <p>This is true in many Catholic churches; the priest has the same trouble trying to make the people donate for the upkeep of the church.</p>
   <p>Under such circumstances, the emigration home as well as the churches should charge a small fee for their services. In the case of the immigrants' home, they should <pb facs="5423968_11_0114.jpg" n="3"/>charge a small entrance fee, and then an additional daily fee; this is the only answer the manager of this institution has to avoid being so hard pressed financially. The church should also charge a yearly fee, and then receive the regular Sunday and holiday donations.</p>
   <p>If the immigrants would stop to think, what the cost of upkeeping this institution amounts to yearly, they would no doubt donate gladly for so good a cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
