<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-30">Sept. 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Poland and the American Press]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-30">Sept. 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[POLAND AND THE AMERICAN PRESS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English newspapers are becoming more and more interested in Polish affairs. Favorable articles concerning Poland and Poles can be found at frequent intervals in these papers. These articles are not written by Poles but by people of some other nationality. Newspapers which, until recently, were antagonistically inclined, and at times even persecuted our people by referring to us as barbarians, are now favoring our people. Not only have they ceased their mockery, but they are printing every article they can obtain pertaining to Polish affairs, past or present. The New York American, a newspaper which had always spoken of our people in contemptuous terms, has now changed its attitude and is beginning to write favorably of Polish matters. Recently this paper published an article entitled "The Partition of Poland" written by the Reverend Thomas B. Gregory, a Protestant pastor. The author of this work condemns the crime of partition in no uncertain terms. He refers to those <pb facs="5423968_11_0610.jpg" n="2"/>instrumental in the partition, the Russian Czarina Catherine, the Austrian Empress Maria Theresa, and the Prussian King Frederick as the three crowned thieves. The author further states that the partition of Poland--the nation which produced such men as Sobieski, Kosciusko, and many other prominent leaders--is a crime so great that nothing will be able to efface it. Every self-respecting person must abhor such action and sympathize with the unfortunate but brave nation of Poland.</p>
   <p>The author recalls the merits and sacrifices of Kosciusko, a man who rendered priceless service in behalf of American freedom. He adds that every freedom-loving citizen must feel the highest esteem and respect for this hero, who sacrificed his life, not for honors or money, but for freedom. "Poland as a nation does not exist, but her free spirit lives amongst us. It will continue to live thus as a symbol of endearment, of freedom, and of humanity, with disdain for the thievery and tyranny of the partitioners."</p>
   <p>Thus it is evident that the historic merits of our great leaders are now <pb facs="5423968_11_0611.jpg" n="3"/>beginning to be recognized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
