<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-26">Sept. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Death of a Well-Known Civic Leader in Avondale</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0898</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0898.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-26">Sept. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DEATH OF A WELL-KNOWN CIVIC LEADER IN AVONDALE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Francis Rutkowski, of 2898 Milwaukee Avenue, a popular figure in Polish circles in Avondale, is dead. He was accidently asphyxiated by carbon monoxide while starting his automobile in the garage. Before his death the victim called for help, but, unfortunately, when help did come it was too late. All possible methods of resuscitation were applied but to no avail. It was impossible to bring him back to life.</p>
   <p>The victim was in the prime of life, since he was but forty-two years of age. He conducted his tavern business decently and had a wide circle of friends and acquaintances. He was a well-known sportsman and was constantly surrounded by a group of professional hunters.</p>
   <p>He always took an active part in furthering the interests of Polish organizations. Everything Polish interested him exceedingly. The sincere grief of many will accompany him to his grave.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0899.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He leaves a wife, Valeria, and two young sons, Edward, eleven, and Francis, eight years old.</p>
   <p>Funeral rites will be held on Saturday, September 28, 1918, at his late residence and also at St. Hyacinth Church. The body will be interred in St. Adalbert's Cemetery, in Niles, Illinois. In recognition of the accomplishments of the late Francis Rutkowski, and grief stricken over his passing, the Dziennik Zwiazkowy wishes to take this opportunity to extend its condolences to the bereaved family of the deceased.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
