<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-04-26">April 26, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">St. Wenceslaus Youth Bids Farewell to Father Przbylski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0875</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0875.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-04-26">April 26, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ST. WENCESLAUS YOUTH BIDS FAREWELL TO FATHER PRZBYLSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mere than five-hundred friends and parishioners of Father Przybylski participated in the farewell dinner and entertainment given in his honor in the Red Room of the Hotel La Salle last Sunday evening. More than five-hundred voiced their regrets in losing this splendid Catholic priest. Father Edward, as he was affectionately called in the environs of the parish church, spent five years at Saint Wenceslaus. During this time he accomplished wonders with the youth of the district, promoting their movements till they reached the high degree they now hold. He was an untiring worker, where young people were concerned, and the mass turnout at Sunday's banquet was an indication of the high regard the people had for him.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thaddeus New, master of ceremonies, called upon Brother Peter, C.S.C., to pronounce the invocation; after the benediction, members of the Young People's Club of Saint Wenceslaus parish sang the club's official anthem, "Purple and Orange" in Polish and English. The master of ceremonies then called upon Mr. Albert Danisch to speak. in view of the fact, that many of those present were not of Polish extraction, and did not understand the Polish language, Mr. Danish spoke in English. He spoke of the innumerable services rendered by Father Przybylski, and wished the priest good luck in his new office, - that of pastor at Saint Ladislaus Parish, West Irving Park and Portage districts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0876.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Danisch, was followed by Mr. Joseph Zlotow, tenor, who sang "Roses of Picardy". Next inorder was Mr. Bartosz, president of the Saint Wenceslaus Holy Name Society, who spoke at length on the departing Vicar's organization ability. Miss Mildred Roschman, representing the society of the Little Flower of Jesus, delivered a beautiful eulogy; and the silvery voice of Mrs. J. Koskiewicz further beautified the program. Miss P. Scibiorska accompanied on the piano.</p>
   <p>One of the finest bits of oratory ever heard at a banquet or gathering of this kind, was delivered by Brother Peter, C.S.C., instructor at the Holy Trinity School. Brother Peter, emphatically declared that he doubts whether a man could be found, who is better suited to the needs of the younger element of the parish, than is Father Przybylski. Brother Peter, indulged in reminiscences of only a few years ago, when he was Father Edward Przybylski's teacher. He recalled with pride that in all his forty years of tutoring he found no better pupil and scholar than this priest. He then stated needless as it was, that the Young Peoples' Club will find it difficult to replace its organizer and guiding mind with another man of equal qualities. In conclusion, the venerable Brother Peter said, "This is not good-bye, but an revoir".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0877.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After a fine rendition of several compositions by Joseph LaRosa, violinist, to the accompaniment of Adalbert Tadelski, pianist, Mr. J. O'Reilly, one of the host of friends of Father Przybylski, admitted that he respects Father Ed. as perhaps no other personage with whom he has similarly come in contact. Mr. Stephen Kolanowski represented the Young Men's Club of Saint Wenceslaus parish; he too spoke in English, briefly but with almost unquenchable enthusiasm. Father Edward Przybylski, was moved deeply by this display of loyalty and fealty; words, however, failed him in his attempt to express what was in his heart. And when the chairman of the banquet committee presented the guest of honor with a check for five-hundred dollars. Father Przybylski, declined to accept it; upon the insistence of brother Peter and the insistent urging of all those present, he could do nothing but accept the gift. When the guests were about to disband, the Chairman announced that additional contributions made it possible to purchase a handsome "Reflex" camera and the receipted invoice for the apparatus was presented to the beloved organizer of the youth movement in Saint Wenceslaus Parish.</p>
   <p>The banquet concluded with the singing of the Polish Anthem by the assembly. Dancing to the strains of Tadelski's band followed the banquet and was continued into the small hours of the morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
