<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Happening There?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS HAPPENING THERE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The news that emanates from Poland and reaches this country is so contradictory that when a poorly informed reader reads it, he becomes dizzy hefore he can come to any conclusion. Which is better, to go there or not, to make plans for a future trip or to let the entire matter drop; would it be better to invest some money in a Polish enterprise or to leave it in the banks in this country where it will accumulate interest without endangering the capital?</p>
   <p>Those that leave for Europe return with varied opinions. One group says that Poland has become a virtual El Dorado and that prices are the lowest in the world. Part of this may be true. When American money is exchanged for marks and the visitor pays for goods with them, he is under the impression that he is paying very little for his purchases. He forgets that the American dollar is quoted at a high premium on the Foreign Exchange. There are an equally large number who say that conditions are so bad that one could not find worse.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0277.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are also those that pack up their things, liquidate their interests here and return to Poland. Some of these stay, while others cannot pack quickly enough to return.</p>
   <p>The accusers declare that unemployment, exploitation and profiteering, graft, low production laziness and the destruction of ambition are spreading throughout the nation. Some go to the extreme and say that conditions are even worse than during the Tsar's regime! The government departments are filled with inactivity, laziness, graft, and intrigue--to such an extent that it is undermining the morale of the country. To this is added political intrigue and the introduction of methods which have been copied from the Prussian police and from Russian spies.</p>
   <p>Such publicity is not very complimentary to Poland.</p>
   <p>In reality, there is very little truth in these stories. A majority of these rumors is nothing but propaganda. We can only say that people who live <pb facs="5423968_11_0278.jpg" n="3"/>in glass houses should not throw stones.</p>
   <p>After all it must be remembered that Poland at the present time is a young country, that it is trying to bring order out of chaos, that the introduction of methods and systems must be begun from scratch. It is no easy task to get peace and order when the neighboring enemies must be handled. Furthermore weak political parties, infected with egotism, selfishness, greed and very little intelligence and patriotism, took over the controlling reins of government and in order to keep them, had to grant favors. Ordinary people could probably have managed better and things would be different.</p>
   <p>But it also must be remembered that the present conditions in Poland will not last. Patience, patience--elections for the new Diet are approaching. Better people will be elected and conditions in Poland will take on a brighter outlook. This can be expected soon. Krakow was not built in one day. It is unfortunate that some people expect the Polish spirit to awaken, become strong and united to such an extent that immediately all disorder <pb facs="5423968_11_0279.jpg" n="4"/>and thievery will be wiped out. Other countries have the same conditions. What have they done about it? What can we do? The long period of bondage has disaccustomed us to self-government. The alien rulers have brought us great deprivation and have left many scars. The Muscovites left graft and corruption, the Austrians defiled us with their bureaucracy and mechanical formality, superficiality and empty-headedness remained after the Prussian departure. All of this helped to instill such selfishness in our nation that altruistic impulses were practically wiped out.</p>
   <p>It will be impossible to remedy all these undesirable conditions in a short time. The important thing for the present is to restore general order. Only this is possible at present. Time and patience will do the rest. The remainder of the work will have to be carried out by those who have been born free of the shackles of oppression and the memories of its aftermath. After this newly born generation grows up to take over the helm, they will restore patriotic citizenship and bring order into the government. Although <pb facs="5423968_11_0280.jpg" n="5"/>absolute perfection will not be reached, we are certain that we will attain such high standards of government that they will be a shining example to other nations. A country and a government that will be the pride of all the Polish people.</p>
   <p>Some of the above statements have been formulated after reading a letter recently received from Poland. This letter contains the usual complaints about the conditions and the people. From it we drew certain conclusions. The envelope was sealed, it did not bear any marks of having been opened, nor was there a censor's stamp on it. Yet an important passage of the letter was cut out and it is apparent that this was not done by the writer.</p>
   <p>What does this mean? It is evident that some kind of censorship exists in Poland. However there is no official statement to bear out this fact. The last batch of news from Poland did not inform us of any such action. There is no reason for it. And if there were, the same methods should be put into <pb facs="5423968_11_0281.jpg" n="6"/>practice as are used by other countries--that is, a censor's stamp should be used to indicate that the letter was opened. The question is, What is happening there? It does look as though some spying is being done on a small scale. It is unpleasant to form such a critical opinion for it awakens a desire to discontinue the work that is being done here for Poland.</p>
   <p>Once again we wish to point out that these conditions will end very shortly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
