<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-20">July 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">In Defence of Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-20">July 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENCE OF IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The readers of Dziennik Zwiazkowy are aware of the fact that Mr. Wm. Sulzer, a congressman from New York submitted a resolution last May, by which he demands that an investigation should be made at Ellis Island by a commission appointed by the U. S. Congress. The purpose of this investigation is to find out how the immigration laws are enforced and whether the immigrants suffer any hardships on account of these laws. Also how to eliminate these hardships.</p>
   <p>This resolution was sent by the U. S. Congress to the Resolution Committee for revision and was discussed by the Committee at two meetings. The Congress is divided into two factions in respect to immigration. One faction favors immigration, the other is against it. The congressmen who favor immigration are of the opinion that the new element will enrich the country and should be admitted. Congressman Sulzer belongs to the second group, and may be considered <pb facs="5423968_11_0047.jpg" n="2"/>the staunchest defender of immigrants in the U. S. Congress.</p>
   <p>It is well known that Poles always have been, and are now, opposed to any unreasonable restrictions against immigration.</p>
   <p>We do not wish an invasion by an undesirable element that is bad or unable to work, but still less do we desire a drastic restriction against immigration just to please some American chauvinists, and we will check such attempts of theirs. The Polish National Alliance has always protested through its Board of Directors, and its groups, against any restrictions presented to the Congress, and these protests brought about the desired effect.</p>
   <p>In this case, however, the Polish National Alliance did not protest against the resolution of Congressman Sulzer because it is not necessary to do so. The resolution is in the hands of the Committee and it will receive proper attention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0048.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Such investigation may result in some changes at Ellis Island which will benefit the immigrants.</p>
   <p>We have been informed that the regulations at Ellis Island are very drastic and inhuman. Sometimes families are broken up; husbands and wives, children and parents are separated; even the officials performing these unpleasant duties are against these regulations. President Taft has condemned them. We hope that this investigating committee will perform its humanitarian duty faithfully and thereby eliminate unnecessary suffering.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
