<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-02-10">Feb. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Pioneer Polish Journalist Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0878</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0878.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-02-10">Feb. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">PIONEER POLISH JOURNALIST DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning we received the news of the death of Ladislaus Dyniewicz, who was one of Chicago's oldest settlers of Polish extraction; he was also one of the most outstanding pioneers of Polish journalisim; and was always considered a leader of the Polish-American element in Chicago, even when the Polish settlement was but a mere handful of Polish immigrants. He was editor of the oldest Polish newspaper in Chicago, a publication called the Polish Gazette. As an editor of the paper and at the same time the author of many Polish books he won the esteem and gratitude of all the Polish people in America. He well understood the urgent need of education and cultural development which he passed on to the many thousands of Polish immigrants through the medium of his newspaper and many of his books. With this thought in mind he established the first Polish book store in Chicago; he also operated a printing press, from which, sprung forth many thousand volumes of dictionaries, Novels, literature and historical text books, aiding in a great measure, to prepare the Polish immigrant in the fundamentals of good citizenship.</p>
   <p>Because of the many years Mr. Dyniewicz has spent in this honorable enterprise, he can justly be called the Pioneer Polish journalist of America. Just prior to the first issue of his paper, the Polish Gazette, he made the following appeal to the Polish people in America: "It is not sufficient that the Polish element in America limit itself to the reading and distribution of newspapers and other reading matter edited and published in Europe."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0879.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The urgent need for a local, Polish publication in America is very apparent; one, which shall in the future, become a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in which the Polish People of America can join hands in exchanging their views, and opinions; and where they can discuss in harmony, the problems of the day. "This was definitely his most important objective when introducing this newspaper service.</p>
   <p>The late Ladislaus Dyniewicz was born on January 13, 1843 in a small town of Chalkew, which was at that time a Russian Province but is now Poland; after attending the elementary school in Poland, he left for Germany, where he attended a technical school and college, to become, a mechanical engineer. Upon completing his education he returned to his native Poland, where, with a heavy heart he sought in vain the freedom of speech and religion; and the possibility of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> national independence for his native land. Thus, in February 1866, he embarked for America on an old whaling ship, which voyage took three months over rough seas. He landed in New York, where he stayed but a short time when he left for Chatsworth, Illinois, which also was but a brief stay, and finally in 1867 arriving in Chicago where he found employment in a supervisory capacity, for a railroad, until the year of 1871, when he purchased a bookstore from Peter Kiolbasa, (who very often was referred to as "Honest Pete;" then treasurer of the City of Chicago) which was located on Noble street, directly opposite the Holy Trinity Church. This location became the home of the Polish Gazette, a weekly, which, under the capable guidance of the late Ladislaus <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, reached, at that time, the very commendable circulation of 26,000 copies <pb facs="5423968_11_0880.jpg" n="3"/>a week.</p>
   <p>The funeral service will be held February 13, 1928, from the late residence, 4533 North Albany Ave., then at the Holy Trinity Church. Interment at St. Adalbert's Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
