<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-10">May 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet in Honor of Peter Kiolbassa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0995</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0995.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-05-10">May 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET IN HONOR OF PETER KIOLBASSA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A banquet was held yesterday in the Polish Restaurant at the World's Fair in honor of Peter Kiolbassa, former city treasurer. By this banquet, the Poles of Chicago acknowledged the honesty and the untiring energy of their countryman, who had succeeded in rising to so high a station in American life. Nearly all of the more important members of Chicago's Polish community were present. This proved that Mr. Kiolbassa has a great many friends who appreciate the services he has rendered.</p>
   <p>About eighty persons took their places at the beautifully decorated tables. Mr. Kiolbassa occupied the place of honor at the head of a horseshoe arrangement of tables. On either side of him sat W. Jedrzejek and W. Dyniewicz; the rest of the places were occupied by representatives of the Polish clergy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0996.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Toasts and speeches began after the main courses had been served. As master of ceremonies, the Reverend Vincent Barzynski called Mr. E. Z. Brodowski as the first speaker. Mr. Brodowski spoke in English, praising Mr. Kiolbassa's service and pointing to him as an example of rectitude. He closed his remarks with the cry: "Long live Peter Kiolbassa!"</p>
   <p>After a short speech by Mr. Kiolbassa himself, in which he thanked those who had gathered to honor him, Mr. Dyniewicz, one of the older Polish residents of Chicage, rese to speak. In speaking of "Peter," as he is so often called, Mr. Dyniewicz, declared that Kiolbassa is and always had been a source of pride to the Polish community.</p>
   <p>Father Barzynski spoke next in Polish, since his was a long and intimate association with Mr. Kiolbassa, he gave an outline of his life and activities in the Polish community of Chicago. He said that Mr. Kiolbassa had given his support to everything that was good and honorable; his brethren in need could always <pb facs="5423968_11_0997.jpg" n="3"/>depend upon him for help. His services to the Poles of America were invaluable. In conclusion, Father Barzynski said, "In truth, the Bible teaches us not to praise a man until after his death, but in this case, we are justified in making an exception of Mr. Kiolbassa. May he live long and continue to bring honor to the Poles in America."</p>
   <p>After another English speech by the lawyer Mr. Drzemala, Mr. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz spoke of the former treasurer's early life. Starting as a farm hand, Mr. Kiolbassa, by virtue of hard work and perseverance, climbed the ladder of success rung by rung until he reached the heights that he now occupies. He was not ashamed of the most menial employment; any job that he put his hand to was thereby ennobled. When his adopted country called, he took up arms without hesitation. The life of this man should serve as an example to all of us.</p>
   <p>Following this address, a toast was proposed by Mr. Jedrzejek, who, with inimitable humor, expressed the wish that Mr. Kiolbassa be elected governor of the <pb facs="5423968_11_0998.jpg" n="4"/>State. To the Poles in general, he predicted that the State of Illinois would in time be a "new Poland".</p>
   <p>Speeches by Mr. P. Ligman, president of the Patriotic Organization, and Mr. Corkery, one of the former treasurer's guarantors, followed.The latter, in a short English address, expressed the warmest regard for Mr. Kiolbassa and the Poles.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Sosnowski, representative of the Polish artists, who arrived from Warsaw recently, toasted Mr. Kiolbassa in the name of the people of Poland.</p>
   <p>The incumbent city treasurer, Mr. Bransfield, was the next speaker. Following him, Mr. A.J. Kowalski proposed a toast in Polish, and Judge [J.] La Buy in English. These toasts, sincere, replete with humor, were applauded vigorously.</p>
   <p>A long address by Dr. Charles Midowicz followed. With his usual ease, the honorable doctor spoke of Mr. Kiolbassa's noble gesture in paying to the city <pb facs="5423968_11_0999.jpg" n="5"/>treasury the money which could legally have gone into his own pocket. The doctor described Mr. Kiolbassa as a man of unshaken integrity, who does not worship at the shrine of the all-powerful dollar, who, instead, acts according to standards of honor, who is incapable of breaking his pledged word or of falsehood.</p>
   <p>A merry German toast by the architect Druiding was followed by one more Polish speech by the Reverend A. Nowicki, who thanked Mr. Kiolbassa for his services in the name of American Polonia. A few humorous remarks by Mr. H. Nagiel, ending in a cheer for Mr. Kiolbassa, preceded the final address of the evening--the ex-treasurer's thanks to those present. Mr. Kiolbassa spoke in Polish with great emotion. Habitually modest, he insisted that he had done nothing unusual; he had acted according to the dictates of his own conscience; he could not have done otherwise. He repeated his words of thanks in English.</p>
   <p>A Polish orchestra played intermittently during the banquet. When the speeches had ended, the gathering broke up into individual groups where, as becomes Poles, the guests fraternized with complete disregard for partisanship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
