<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-29">May 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Patriotic Exercise Held at Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0684</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0684.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-29">May 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTIC EXERCISE HELD AT TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A patriotic exercise and ball was held at Town of Lake on Sunday, May 26, in memory of the Constitution of the Third of May. The celebration was staged by the societies connected with the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The affair started at 4 P.M. Mr. Nuszkowski, president of the entertainment committee, opened the program and called upon Count P. Wodzicki to act as chairman and appointed C. Zurawski recording secretary. Count Wodzicki called upon F. H. Jablonski to present the first speech of the day.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jablonski spoke about the Constitution of the Third of May, pointing out its meaning, and compared conditions in Poland with those in other countries of Europe. He contended that Poland will arise only when it is governed by Poles for the benefit of the Polish people.</p>
   <p>The next speakers to take the stand were F. Gryglaszewski and J. Rudzinski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0685.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Both spoke about the former state of affairs in Poland and the cause of the discord which divides us even in America, bringing many troubles in our struggle for the national cause.</p>
   <p>To complete the program Miss Julia Sniegocka, of Bridgeport, presented a declamation on "The Reign of Napoleon I". Various recitations were given by children of local families. Two school children from the adjoining community, Bridgeport, also gave recitations.</p>
   <p>The newly organized Zorza (Morning Star) Choir, of Bridgeport, added color to the entertainment with its beautiful singing of Polish airs. Mr. Gackowski of the Chopin Choir was soloist.</p>
   <p>Count Wodzicki appropriately closed the program with a talk on the faults of Poland, alluding to the two last speakers. In conclusions he pointed out the duties of the Polish people to our former country which have been laid down by <pb facs="5423968_11_0686.jpg" n="3"/>the proponents of the Constitution of the Third of May and those who have not regretted making the supreme sacrifice for Poland.</p>
   <p>After this a skit was presented by M. Wleklinski and L. Czeslawski entitled "Patriots". Both executed their parts like professional artists.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a ball in which the Polish youth of Town of Lake took part. Hensel's orchestra supplied the music.</p>
   <p>The program committee wishes to extend hearty thanks to all speakers, performers and participants for their support.</p>
   <p>A collection for the National Fund of Rapperschwil (City in Switzerland) [started by Polish National Alliance about 1889] netted $10.85. Ten dollars from the proceeds of the dance were contributed to the building of the new St. Joseph Church.</p>
   <p>C. Zurawski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
