<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">Mar. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Army Rally Held in Holy Trinity Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">Mar. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ARMY RALLY HELD IN HOLY TRINITY PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A rally was held yesterday in the Holy Trinity Parochial School hall for the benefit of the Polish Army, but the attendance was disappointing, for only about a hundred persons were present.</p>
   <p>At eight o'clock in the evening, Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, pastor of the parish, opened the meeting and invited the parish committee and representatives of societies of Holy Trinity Parish to the platform. He explained the purpose of the meeting, which he said was twofold: first, to decide upon a tax for nationalistic purposes, and second, to hear from the representatives of the Polish Army. Since the meeting was not strictly parochial but was to deal with nationalistic matters, Father Sztuczko suggested that a chairman and a secretary be chosen from among those present.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kempczynski was elected chairman and Mr. Makarski secretary. After the <pb facs="5423968_11_0383.jpg" n="2"/>elections were over, Father Sztuczko said a short prayer, and discussions began on the matters for which the meeting was called.</p>
   <p>The first speaker was Mr. Kempczynski, the chairman, who explained the purposes of the meeting, one of the first of which was to decide upon a tax for the national cause, as almost all of the parishes in Chicago had already done.</p>
   <p>The matter of a national tax was then explained by Reverend Sztuczko. He said that this question had been broached at the Polish Priests' Convention in Chicago a few weeks ago by Ignace Paderewski, who pointed out that only a certain percentage of the Poles in America are members of Polish organizations, while the entire Polish population of America is estimated at about four million souls. The purpose of the tax is not only to help the Polish Army, but to help the Polish nation, dying of hunger and misery. Reverend Sztuczko pointed out that while we live here in comparative well-being, the people in Poland are actually starving. The reverend speaker said that Paderewski is not asking alms of us, but a voluntary tax through which every <pb facs="5423968_11_0384.jpg" n="3"/>person can pay for this cause. Each should pay what he can, but the lowest monthly payment should not be less than fifty cents per family, or for a single man. The tax will be collected from now until the end of the war. The speaker proposed that a committee be chosen to collect the tax, as has been done in other Polish parishes in Chicago, and he urged his parishioners to make Holy Trinity Parish an example of what should be done for the national cause, as it has always been before.</p>
   <p>After Reverend Sztuczko's speech, a general discussion began, in which a number of citizens took part. After the discussion, which lasted nearly an hour, it was unanimously decided that a national tax should be collected in Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
   <p>A short debate was held on the manner in which this tax should be collected, and a committee was finally chosen to direct the whole matter. The following persons were unanimously elected to the committee: C. Duzewski, Kempczynski, <pb facs="5423968_11_0385.jpg" n="4"/>A. Plucinski, Markarski, Mrs. Lisewski, Janiszewski, and Prusinowski.</p>
   <p>A number of persons volunteered as collectors of the tax.</p>
   <p>[List of tax collectors and their addresses omitted by translator].</p>
   <p>These collectors, with account booklets and the addresses of all members of the parish, with specified districts for each collector, will have the right to call regularly upon every family that belongs to the parish. All contributions collected in this manner will be listed in the parish bulletin so that each person will know to what purpose his money has been used.</p>
   <p>Representatives of Polish Army Speak</p>
   <p>An address was delivered by [Stanislaus] Krzywonos, who had just returned <pb facs="5423968_11_0386.jpg" n="5"/>from the Polish Army training camp. The speaker called attention to the fact that there are hundreds of Polish young men in the camp, young men who have been educated here in American schools as well as young men who have been educated abroad. These young men are giving everything they have to their motherland, without even thinking now of establishing homes of their own. The speaker said that he believes that the time will come when we will all get to work for our homeland, and that Holy Trinity Parish will accomplish miracles.</p>
   <p>Following this speech, [L.] Haduch, one of the organizers of the Polish Army, said a few words.</p>
   <p>Nicodemus Kornajzer was the first one to pay the entire year's tax--six dollars.</p>
   <p>The meeting ended a little after ten o'clock with a short prayer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0387.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Holy Trinity Parish will hold another such meeting for the benefit of the Polish Army, the date of which will be advertised in the Polish papers at the proper time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
