<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-22">Nov. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-22">Nov. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Federation of Labor, during its convention at St. Louis, Missouri, made a clear and definite statement directed against workers from Europe and Asia. Through its speakers, the Federation called upon the American people, and especially the working class, to refuse the right of permanent residence in this country to all people coming into America from other parts of the world. Sons and grandchildren of former immigrants condemned immigration and insultingly called immigrants criminals. A labor union of longshoremen declared itself against the steel trust of the United States Steel Corporation, but on this occasion the union attacked the immigrants, whom it considered an undesirable element, responsible for lowering the pay of local workers. One of the speakers of this union made a public statement to the effect that the steel company imported workers from Europe--most of whom were criminally inclined,--and employed them here at starvation wages. These union officials <pb facs="5423968_11_0071.jpg" n="2"/>therefore demanded that the borders be closed to arrivals from other parts of the universe, with the hope that conditions would become better and the workingman would benefit.</p>
   <p>Every word stated at the convention was either a lie, or an evidence of great ignorance of social conditions, on the part of those embittered American chauvinists who, after all, are of immigrant parentage. The statement that a company could import criminals from Europe is a lie; there are not as many criminals in Europe as there are here in America. Those who are there either are imprisoned or are fugitives from the law. They are not in the least anxious to leave for America to work hard, and for a meager remuneration, here in the steel mills. If a criminal should succeed in gaining entrance in spite of the watchful immigration officials, he would not come here to search for work; his primary interest would be to find a field for more extensive criminal activity. The percentage of such undesirable arrivals, however, is very small. In a city like Chicago or New York there are more criminals--bandits, murderers, <pb facs="5423968_11_0072.jpg" n="3"/>pickpockets, white slavers, falsifiers of checks, and counterfeiters of money--than there are in the whole immigrant population of this country, both from Europe and from other parts of the world.</p>
   <p>To call honest, thrifty, hard-working people organized criminals indicates a high degree of intolerance and an ill-concealed hatred of immigrants among local workers; they give the impression of bulldogs that will not themselves eat the bones and will not share them with others.....</p>
   <p>A European worker does not in the least lower wages in mines or factories; wages are lowered by the native-born loafers and hoboes--people who go from place to place and work for a few hours a month at meager remuneration or take as their occupation robbery and thievery. Wherever a strike breaks out, one will find Poles, Czechs, Slovaks, Hungarians, Italians, Lithuanians, Swedes, and other foreign-born people among the first to walk out of factories and, although they and their families are dying of hunger and suffering with cold, they do not return to work but continue to fight. But what, on the other hand, <pb facs="5423968_11_0073.jpg" n="4"/>do the native-born workers do during a strike? Most frequently they act as strikebreakers or hire themselves as undercover men and deputy sheriffs, or enter the lines of the militia and with great abandon murder their fellow workers because these, after all, are abominable "foreigners" and the act of slaying them is considered commendable. This was proved frequently during the numerous and various strikes of the past where a foreign-born worker struck and tried to better his existence, while in the meantime the American-born worked as "scabs" or took up arms against the strikers. It would seem that nothing is known of this by the chauvinists congregated at the St. Louis convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
