<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 145,
<date when="1908-06-20">June 20, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">First Polish Bishop in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 145,
<date when="1908-06-20">June 20, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST POLISH BISHOP IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, alas! it was too late to inform the people through the Polish paper which was on press, we received the information by telephone that the pontificial office nominated Rev. Father Paul Rhode bishop of the Chicago archdiocese. We can congratulate the Most Rev. Father Paul Rhode wholeheartedly that of all the Polish priests in the United States he was the first one to be ordained a bishop.</p>
   <p>We wholeheartedly call this the greatest and happiest moment of our lives, as in Bishop Rhode we have the most dignified representative of the Polish clergy in the Catholic hierarchy in the United States, one who, among all Polish priests in Chicago, is the most understanding and reasonable. The thing that is most important is that after all these years that the Polish people have worked hard and undertaken every step to build and uphold the Roman-Catholic religion, they have at last received their reward by having a Polish bishop at the Chicago archdiocese, and they should have more than one bishop, considering <pb facs="5423968_11_0941.jpg" n="2"/>the number of Polish churches, schools and Polish Catholics in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We cannot hold back our true feelings and the happiness that is in our heart, without first thanking his Excellency J. E. Archbishop Quigley, through whose efforts we now have in Chicago the first Polish bishop.</p>
   <p>At last our knocking on the door of the Pope's palace has been answered and fulfilled. The delegates who made the trip to Rome to assist the efforts of Archbishop Quigley in nominating a Polish priest as bishop of Chicago instead of a priest from some other nationality, met with plenty of opposition in Rome. The Pope consented to the request of Archbishop Quigley, who sternly stated that in order to quiet the demands of thousands of Polish Catholics in Chicago as well as in the United States, their effort and faith in the Roman-Catholic religion must be repaid and "I demand that Father Rhode be made bishop of Chicago's archdiocese."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0942.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The people know that Archbishop Quigley sent a list of all priests in Chicago that had the qualifications required for the position of bishop. He carefully studied this list and at last came to the conclusion that Father Rhode had the best qualifications and underlined his name, which was sent to the Pope to receive the final signature.</p>
   <p>The Polish people feel sure that if Archbishop Quigley remains as the head of Chicago's archdiocese, we will have many more Polish bishops here.</p>
   <p>We offer our congratulations to Rev. Bishop Rhode and wish him happiness and success in his new undertaking.</p>
   <p>There are alas! everlasting malcontents, everlasting pessimists, everlasting critics who can never be satisfied, but always find some mistake with other people's promotions. People should not feel that way, they are only one against the majority; in other words, it is only a loss of time and results in hard feelings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0943.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We are sure that almost all the Polish Catholics are the happiest group of people in America when they hear this good news. Polish people from all parts of the United States are planning to take an active part in the procession in Chicago preceding the ordaining of Father Rhode as the first Polish bishop of Chicago and the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
