<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-05-27">May 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal of the Polish Immigrants to European Nations</title><title level="a" type="sub">On the Hundredth Anniversary of the Declaration of the Polish Constitution (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0827</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0827.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-05-27">May 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL OF THE POLISH IMMIGRANTS TO EUROPEAN NATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">On the Hundredth Anniversary of the Declaration of the Polish Constitution (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A hundred years ago, on May 3, 1791, Poland, after the first partition, threatened by the second, surrounded by enemies eager to crush her, arose and proved to the world by a memorable act that she was still alive.</p>
   <p>This memorable act was the declaration of the new constitution, which was in reality the first firm step leading to urgent reforms. These reforms were to remedy all faults and inefficiencies of the social and political organization of the country.</p>
   <p>Alone, betrayed by perfidious Prussia, Poland fell once more a prey to the combined forces of Prussian and Russian monarchs. Prussian armies could not <pb facs="5423968_11_0828.jpg" n="2"/>move to France for the purpose of suppressing the rise of freedom before helping Russia to quarter Poland again. France refused and defeated the Prussians, and it is said that this defeat was due to the weakening of the Prussian army in a fight with Kosciuszko. Poland, however, was too weak, and in spite of the heroic efforts of the leader of the nation, she was removed from the map of Europe by the third partition in 1795.</p>
   <p>Poland was not restored after that fateful date. The crime of the partition of Poland was not expiated either by the creation of the Duchy of Warsaw by Napoleon or by the short existence of the Congressional Poland. On the contrary, the act of the Congress of Vienna, which was held in 1815, ratified the partition of Poland under a liberal form. The conscience of Europe is still burdened with this crime of the murder of a country as an offender or as an accessory [to the commission of an offense]; and this crime still stands in the way of a permanent peace in Europe.</p>
   <p>Although Europe has not fulfilled her duty toward Poland and herself, Poland <pb facs="5423968_11_0829.jpg" n="3"/>may rightfully say that she has remained loyal to her historic mission. Europe was either unable or did not care to resurrect a country which was indispensable for her own safety. She did not even care to remove the black blot created by the political bondage of a nation numbering twenty millions, a bondage which obstructs the tendency of the modern world toward progress and freedom and constitutes at the same time an invincible obstacle to their realization. On the other hand, Poland, after her partition, has proved her solidarity with civilized nations and has produced undeniable evidence of her vitality and her desire to be independent.</p>
   <p>Sons of Poland have fought on all battlefields of both hemispheres in the ranks of the defenders of freedom. In our native land Poles raised their national banners three times in the attempt to regain independence--in 1830, in 1846-1848, and in 1863. At each insurrection they encouraged the reforms adopted by the Constitution, confirming the principles of civil and political freedom for all classes and also freedom of religion. Besides this they not only proclaimed the emancipation of the peasants but also granted to them the right to own property.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0830.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Poles were conquered by superior forces and only for a short time. They never lost hope in the future and are trying to develop their nation, in spite of difficulties, by taking active part in the mental activities of European civilization.</p>
   <p>Even today, after a hundred years of oppression and in spite of being torn into three parts, Poles constitute one nation united by language, literature, tradition, and the hope of a better future. As on May 3, 1791, of which we celebrate the hundredth anniversary, either publicly or secretly throughout entire Poland and in foreign lands, so at this moment they are united in a common thought, as if they wished to say to Europe and to the rest of the world:</p>
   <p>"Poland is not lost and shall not be lost."</p>
   <p>Polish immigration should become an audible echo of this silent call of our countrymen who are compelled to hold their tongues. For this reason the <pb facs="5423968_11_0831.jpg" n="5"/>Polish immigrants declare solemnly, peaceably, and with dignity befitting the cause which will be triumphant because it is eternally right, in the presence of independent nations and conquering countries, that the Polish nation will not renounce any of its rights; that it protests very vigorously against all the injustices of which it has been the victim since 1772, and which it still suffers; and that in its own interest and in the interest of all Europe the Polish nation will endeavor with all its might to precipitate the moment in which it will gain freedom and independence, when it will be able to resume anew and continue further the reformative work of its ancestors interrupted a century ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
