<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-03-24">Mar. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Polish National Alliance and the Anti-Immigration Bill]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-03-24">Mar. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE AND THE ANTI-IMMIGRATION BILL]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Here are some of the replies received by the various groups of the Polish National Alliance from several representatives and senators, who acknowledge the receipt of resolutions adopted by the groups against the proposed Anti-immigration Bill.</p>
   <p>"Mr. W. Lipinski,</p>
   <p>"President of Group 904 of the Polish National Alliance,</p>
   <p>"Bessemer, Michigan</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I have just received a copy of the resolution adopted by your organization on February 19, 1910. Even though I have not had as yet an opportunity <pb facs="5423968_11_0095.jpg" n="2"/>to study this bill, I do not believe that any bill containing the provisions you bring to my attention, could pass in this session of Congress.</p>
   <p>"I am very glad to have received this information, and I assure you that I am in perfect accord with your opinion that this bill should not be passed in its present form.....</p>
   <p>"H. O. Young"</p>
   <p>Mr. F. Czaporowski, financial secretary of Group 525, Holyoke, Massachusetts, received two replies. The one from Senator W. M. Crane reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I received your letter of the 24th, and it is pleasant to know that your organization is interested in matters pertaining to immigration legislation. I assure you that this matter shall receive my undivided attention, and I shall also at all times keep your interests uppermost in my mind.</p>
   <p>"W. M. Crane"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0096.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The second letter, from Congressman Lawrence, reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I have received the resolution adopted by the St. Cazimir's Lodge No. 525 of the Polish National Alliance, and it will be a pleasure to give this matter prompt attention. I will immediately present this resolution to the House of Representatives.</p>
   <p>"George P. Lawrence"</p>
   <p>The contents of a letter received by Group 1033 of the Polish National Alliance, are as follows:</p>
   <p>"Mr. J. Rogowski</p>
   <p>"South St. Paul, Minnesota</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I received your letter containing the resolution adopted by your organization, pertaining to the Hayes Anti-immigration Bill. I will present <pb facs="5423968_11_0097.jpg" n="4"/>this resolution to the Senate, and will then turn it over to the proper commission.</p>
   <p>"Knute Nelson"</p>
   <p>We are continually receiving letters from various groups of the Polish National Alliance, letters which include replies from senators and representatives to the resolutions adopted by the groups against the Hayes Anti-immigration Bill.</p>
   <p>It is a great pleasure to publish proof of the sincere interest taken in American politics by our brother members--an interest in questions that affect vitally the lives and welfare of all citizens.</p>
   <p>This is only a beginning. In the future the Polish National Alliance will surely grow strong enough, so that its voice and opinion on important questions of the day will be heeded and heard by people who today are hardly aware of its existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0098.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Polish Falcons Nest Number 157, Group 1122 of the Polish National Alliance, Holyoke, Massachusetts, received a reply from Senator Lodge, who is an enemy of immigration: Senator Lodge's letter reads:</p>
   <p>"Mr. J. T. Strobel</p>
   <p>"Holyoke, Massachusetts</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I am in possession of a resolution adopted by your organization, opposing the Hayes Anti-immigration Bill. I am satisfied to become acquainted with the opinion of your organization on this proposed legislation. When it finally reaches the Senate, I will thoroughly scrutinize it.</p>
   <p>"H. C. Lodge"</p>
   <p>That Senator Lodge promises to look into this proposed bill to restrict immigration, keeping the resolution uppermost in his mind, is really something.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0099.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The old sinner is constantly harrassing the immigrants with his bills, but now he is compelled to discuss immigration more gently with its defenders.</p>
   <p>Mr. Strobel also received a short letter from Congressman Gillet, Chairman of the Civil Service Commission, who also promises to give the resolution his full attention and consideration.</p>
   <p>The Polish Falcons Nest Number 157, Group 1122 of the Polish National Alliance, put some pressure on the legislators in Washington also, as the contents of a letter received from another congressman of Massachusetts will attest.</p>
   <p>"The Senate of the United States.</p>
   <p>"Mr. J. R. Kurnik, president of the Polish Athletic Organization, Group 1122, Holyoke, Massachusetts.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: I received a letter signed by you and Mr. Strobel, together with <pb facs="5423968_11_0100.jpg" n="7"/>your organization's resolution, voicing its opinion on the question of immigration restriction. I will take it upon myself, to give this matter my undivided attention, keeping uppermost in mind your organization's opinion, which I was very glad to receive.</p>
   <p>"W. M. Crane"</p>
   <p>The American legislators are in this way becoming aware of the existence of the Polish people in the United States. These people, who are mostly workers belonging to various unions, are not as egoistical as the American workers, who are also members of these unions but are strongly in favor of placing restrictions on immigration.</p>
   <p>The Polish people, on the contrary, are in favor of leaving the door to this American paradise wide open, so that all decent and deserving people who are seeking employment, freedom, and security for their families can enter here and become good American citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
