<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-11-19">Nov. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Lies of Bismarck about the Poles</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0762</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0762.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-11-19">Nov. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE LIES OF BISMARCK ABOUT THE POLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During his lifetime, Bismarck accomplished a great deal, not only in his country but also throughout Europe--perhaps a great deal of good for the Germans, but much evil for the Poles.</p>
   <p>During recent years, however, Bismarck has not been able to accomplish anything. What is worse, he has not been able to do much with the Polish people, for when he came to power there were one million Poles, while now there are three and a half million....</p>
   <p>It is no wonder then that during recent months Bismarck has been searching for some means of pouring out all his hatred against the Poles.</p>
   <p>In an interview with a certain Mr. Harden, which took place a few days ago, Bismarck informed the interviewer that Germany since 1848 had always been <pb facs="5423968_11_0763.jpg" n="2"/>favorable toward the Polish people; however, the Polish worker, wherever he appears, begins scuffles and brawls (wird gewaltthaetig)!</p>
   <p>He further claims that the Poles, as early as the fifteenth century, were agitating in Prussia....and were obtruding Catholicism.</p>
   <p>Every word spoken by Bismarck was a lie! History shows that the first German entered Mazowia in 1228 under the guise of a monk--like a wolf in sheep's clothing. When such wolves threatened the Polish king Jagello at Grunwald in 1410, the king was sent swords for defense and the rabble was wiped out; the Polish territory was once more restored.</p>
   <p>Bismarck further claims that whenever the Poles came in contact with German countrymen they would start an agitation about the gentry. On the other hand, it is well known that the Prussian-German towns were warring with the German crusaders and were appealing for help from Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0764.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>According to Bismarck's assertions, the Poles are creating all kinds of pretenses to have the Germans go to war against the Muscovites and return Poland to the Polish people, of which there are only seven and one half million.</p>
   <p>This figure by Bismarck is another lie! We know only too well how many there are of us Polish people: Prussia has three and one half million, Austria has three and one half million, and Russia has thirteen million.</p>
   <p>These numbers total twenty million Poles. However, this total does not include the number in Lithuania and White Russia.</p>
   <p>"The Poles divided Russia," Bismarck states further in his absurd interview... It is sad indeed that such ignorant statements, such lies, should be imparted by him to the world! The Ruthenians were taken over by Russia during the downfall of Casimir the Great, and White Russia was taken over when Lithuania fell.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0765.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Bismarck is at least gracious to the extent that he calls the Polish man "gewaltthaetig," and praises his bravery. But this same Bismarck, in his gratitude for the physical hardships endured by the Poles and for the blood they spilt for the Germans, denied to the children of these same men the culture and education which can only be obtained in the mother tongue. He also throw out the relatives of these brave men beyond the borders of Prussia and caused them to lose hundreds of thousands of dollars. Is this not "gewaltthaetig?"</p>
   <p>Listen, Polish men, dear compatriots! Prince Bismarck expelled from Prussia over thirty-five thousand peaceful, trustworthy and industrious Polish persons who were struggling under trying conditions to earn a few pennies. These men were your relations, dear compatriots! Let us assume that each one of this large number lost ten marks; this would bring the total to 350,000 marks. It can be safely stated, as a matter of fact, that the figure exceeded a million marks.</p>
   <p>Handsome indeed is this blessing, brought about by the valuable gift of German culture!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0766.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If the Polish individual was so content under the canopy of this renowned German culture, surely all these other peoples from the German villages would not have come to America!</p>
   <p>These are the kinds of "truths" our "most beloved" has spoken about us to the world! Such statements are shameless, as always is barbarism, as always is--Bismarck.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
