<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-27">July 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Pole for Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0904</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0904.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-27">July 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A POLE FOR CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter was received with a request for publication in Dziennik Zwiazkowy:</p>
   <p>"First allow me to thank you, gentlemen, for the faith you have placed in me, as capable of representing the Poles in Congress. I want to express my deep appreciation of the noble intentions that prompted your suggesting my candidacy for this high office. I am deeply moved, for I understand fully the responsibilities that fall to the man who will be called upon for this high office, especially in the most changeable times in the history of the world, at a moment when the fate of Europe and America is being weighed, at a moment when Poland, tortured and suffering, is arising from her grave, her arms outstretched to us for help.</p>
   <p>"Guided by this feeling alone, that is, by the desire to serve the course and not by personal ambition, I allowed myself to be persuaded two years ago to <pb facs="5423968_11_0905.jpg" n="2"/>accept the candidacy for this office, with a sacrifice on my part of much time and money. My election was assured, but the underhand work of a few ward politicians, motivated by jealousy and selfishness, caused my defeat.</p>
   <p>"Yes-- as was the case two years ago, so this year there cannot be the slightest doubt that I would be elected if the Poles of the Eighth Congressional District stand behind me as one man, if there would be none of that underhand work. Whoever says otherwise is not telling the truth--he does not want a Polish Congressman. Unfortunately, without the unananimous and harmonious effort of all the Poles in the Eighth District, all endeavors and sacrifices on the part of myself and my friends can be of no avail. Even supposing I could devote all of my time to the campaign, and could spend $10,000, I would still be taking a risk. I would try to convince every Pole in the Eighth District, and I know that I could-- but this would entail a great amount of work and sacrifice on my part. Neither my financial resources nor my physical condition permits this.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0906.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Once more, I thank the Polish press and the citizenry, but for the foregoing reasons, I am forced to decline the candidacy for United States Congressman.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>"N. L. Piotrowski."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
