<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-01-17">Jan. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Golden Wedding Anniversary]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0931</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0931.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiakowy</title>,
<date when="1913-01-17">Jan. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[GOLDEN WEDDING ANNIVERSARY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow, January 18th, will the 50th anniversary of the matrimonial union of Ladislas Dyniewicz, one of the first Polish pioneers, who, with Albertine Krygier-Dyniewicz rendered great services in developing the Polish settlement in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Ladislas Dyniewicz, now retired, resides in Cragin, raising flowers as a hobby.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dyniewicz was born near Gniezno, where his father was the superintendent of a large estate.</p>
   <p>After the failure of the January insurrection, in 1831, the Prussia Government persecuted all Poles living in the Polish section taken by Prussia. Young Dyniewicz was seized and recruited into the Prussian Army from which he later escaped. He and his young wife then emigrated to America landing in New York on May 12th, 1866, penniless and without a job. A short time later he came to Chicago and secured employment at the McCormick Harvester Works.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0932.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1872, Dyniewicz purchased a small book store from Peter Kiolbasa, who at that time was city treasurer. The following year he published the first Polish newspaper in Chicago; the Gazeta Polska (Polish Gazette), which met with remarkable succees. The first editors of his paper were such noted writers as: Agaton Giller, Vladislaus Mikowski, Gregory Smolski, Domejko, Henry Kalusowski and Ladislas Plater.</p>
   <p>Many articles appearing in the Gazeta Polska, written by Agaton Giller and Andrzejkowicz, created the idea to organize the Polish element in Chicago which resulted in the birth of the Polish National Alliance. Dyniewicz was the organizer and secretary of the first group of the P.N.A., and a member of the committee for the building of St. Stanislaus church, the oldest Polish Catholic church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow, Mr. Dyniewicz, the oldest Polish pioneer of Chicago, will celebrate his 50th wedding anniversary in the midst of his family circle of sons, daughters, grandchildren and great-grandchildren-48 altogether.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
