<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-02">Feb. 2, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Representatives of Polish Organizations and the Polish-American Press Protest against the New Immigration Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-02">Feb. 2, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">REPRESENTATIVES OF POLISH ORGANIZATIONS AND THE POLISH-AMERICAN PRESS PROTEST AGAINST THE NEW IMMIGRATION BILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the honorable members of the United States Senate, Washington, D. C.:</p>
   <p>The undersigned, as American citizens, as officers of Polish-American organizations, and as representatives of the Polish-American press, beseech the honorable Senate to change the immigration bill, passed by the House of Representatives on January 27, 1897 (which has as its aim the regulation of immigration to this country) so that it will not exclude Polish immigrants--people whose country was torn apart by Russia, Prussia, and Austria over a hundred years ago--from the United States. Although the Poles might know how to read and write in their native tongue, they would not be permitted to enter the United States, because the new bill states that immigrants must write and read either the English language or in the language of the country of their birth, or in that of the country in which they lived prior to their decision <pb facs="5423968_11_0131.jpg" n="2"/>to leave. This excludes the Poles, for now they unfortunately have no "native" country. Although they were born on what once was Polish land, they are now absorbed by Russia, Prussia, and Austria, where the tongues of the respective countries prevail, while the Polish language is forbidden, or at least is not recognized by the powers.</p>
   <p>It is our express desire to present to the honorable Senate the fact that the Poles know how to write and read in Polish, and we, as representatives of an honorable and law-abiding nation, trust that you gentlemen will hear our petition and fulfill our wishes. It is hoped that the honorable Senate will not support the immigration bill which will exclude such peoples of "free and great countries," especially those whose forebears fought for the freedom of this country.</p>
   <p>We have taken it upon ourselves to cite a few historical facts about Poland, and trust that the honorable Senate will consider this plea, and will not permit the passage of a bill which, because of its double meaning, could be construed <pb facs="5423968_11_0132.jpg" n="3"/>as being opposed to immigrants who are not only qualified but who deserve recognition from the people of the United States.</p>
   <p>Poland, a Slavic country, located in central Europe, voluntarily accepted the Christian faith during the year 965, and for eight centuries has not only recognized the principles of freedom, but has defended freedom and religious tolerance. For many centuries, Poland defended western civilization from the constant attacks of the wild hordes of Mongols, Tatars, Muscovites, and Turks, who often threatened the destruction of Europe. She was justly called "the bulwark of Christianity and European civilization". Although Poland took part in many wars, they were always carried on to safeguard Polish frontiers, and never for the purpose of gaining territory. All her battles were fought for the protection of her boundaries, as well as the boundaries of neighboring countries. For the defense of Christianity, the young Polish knight, King Ladislas Warneczyk, gave his life at Varna in 1444, and the great warrior, King Stephen Batory, warded off the wild armies of Ivan the Terrible and forced them to return to the wilds of Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0133.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In order not to permit the penetration and dominance of the fanatical Mussulmen of Turkey into Europe, John [III] Sobieski led his army against the Turkish army and defeated them at the gates of Vienna, and forever assured the dominance of the Cross over the crescent moon.</p>
   <p>The valiant accomplishments of the Polish nation did not defer it in more noble deeds of peace. It founded one of the oldest Polish institutions of learning, the University of Cracow. Poland produced Copernicus, great astronomer and founder of the theory of the solar system. The literature of this nation was already marked with such famous names as Sarbiewski, the Polish Petrarch, and John Kochanowski, the first of the Polish poets, in the fifteenth century. During the Reformation, religious freedom was guaranteed to all believers. The Jews, who were persecuted by other nations, were given protection. In 1413, without the slightest spilling of blood, through the influence of the Polish people, the pagan people of Lithuania were converted to Christianity, and in 1567 Lithuania joined with Poland on the principle of "free with the free" and "equal with the equal."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0134.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Poland at no time recognized absolute slavery. In 1347, on the strength of the historical statute of Wislicki, an effort was made to better the circumstances of the Italians. The government bodies of Italy were patterned after the form of the republican (sic). One of the first principles was the assurance of the greatest personal freedom to the Polish nation. The kings of Italy were elected by diets representing the people, the House of Representatives, and the Senate, and the kings possessed very limited authority.</p>
   <p>The people of Poland never followed the despotic politics of its autocratic neighbors, and never maintained a large army during times of peace. On May 3, 1791, the Polish nation unanimously adopted a constitution which remedied the various shortcomings and abuses of the previous constitution, and placed the government upon a firm foundation. In many respects, this constitution was comparable to that of the United States. It guaranteed civil and religious freedom to all its citizens, as well as all its inhabitants. The people accepted this change for the better with great enthusiasm, without bloodshed or rioting, as compared, for example, to the French Revolution. It was greeted <pb facs="5423968_11_0135.jpg" n="6"/>everywhere as one of the greatest acts of a free people.</p>
   <p>However, it was not favorable to the despotic neighbors, who determined that no other form of government should exist in Eruope than that of an absolute government. Without the slightest provocation, the despotic neighbors condemned the laws of the free people of Poland, marched in with their armies, and destroyed the masterpiece of democratic government, and divided the land among themselves. Thaddeus Kosciusko, great friend and aide to George Washington, rose twice against these belligerent powers to protect the principles of the Polish Constitution.</p>
   <p>With the help of intrigue, the tyrants were able to subdue Poland, but not until Poland made a noble and honorable attempt to restore her freedom.</p>
   <p>During the course of the past century, the Polish nation withstood the onslaught of the worst kind of persecution conceived by the tyrannical powers [Russia, Prussia, and Austria]. Thousands of her sons were sacrificed in the uprisings <pb facs="5423968_11_0136.jpg" n="7"/>of 1831, 1848, and 1863 for the freedom of Poland. Thousands of Polish sons and daughters are now suffering in exile on the cold Siberian steppes for their love for Poland. Thousands of the greatest Polish estates were confiseated, and ownership of land was forbidden to the Poles. The treasures of the old Polish libraries, museums, and galleries were destroyed. This was carried out to such an extent that the Poles are even forbidden to pursue the religious beliefs of their forefathers. During the course of the past few years, Poland and Lithuania witnessed one of the most brutal massacres of innocent people by the Russians, because they refused to renounce the religious beliefs of their forebears.</p>
   <p>The despotic powers used extreme measures to ;uproot the Polish tongue. Despite the various brutal obstacles, the nationalistic feeling in the Poles is growing greater with each measure placed upon them to eradicate it. Polish literature, science, and art today give evidence that the spirit of the Poles is not subdued. They create an incessant protest against the existing cruelties perpetrated by Russia, Prussia, and Austria against the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0137.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>In view of the above facts, the Polish-American citizens of this country who are under the protection of the Stars and Stripes and believe in the principles of freedom, equality, and brotherhood (for they are the same principles that were adopted by their forefathers more than a century ago in Poland) are making an appeal to the honorable gentlemen of the United States Congress, and are presenting this protest for just consideration. Trusting in your sound sense of justice, we have the greatest hope that you gentlemen will not permit an injustice to be committed against the sons and daughters of a nation to which the Christian world owes a debt of gratitude for stemming the pogrom of the Mussulmen in 1685, at the gates of Vienna; the world owes thanks to the immortal Polish sons, Pulaski and Kosciusko, and their associates, for their part in the American Revolutionary War.</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa, honorary president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>Casimir Neuman, editor of Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0138.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Leon Szopinski, editor of Gazeta Katolicka (Catholic Gazette).</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Szwajkart, editor of Wiara I Ojczyzna (Faith and the Fatherland).</p>
   <p>Thomas Skaryszewski, editor of Narod Polski (Polish Nation).</p>
   <p>E. Z. Brodowski, president of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>F. H. Jablonski, editor of Zgoda  (Harmony).</p>
   <p>M. J. Sadowski, editor of Echo.</p>
   <p>Anthony Mallek, president of the Polish Singers' Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
