<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-24">Mar. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Fate of Polish Emigrants in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-24">Mar. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">THE FATE OF POLISH EMIGRANTS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Gazeta Koscielna (Church Gazette), published in Galicia, has printed some very interesting data on the emigrants from the village of Miejsce. These data throw light on what has happened to the Polish emigrants who left this village for America; they were gathered by the village pastor, and if more persons would assemble similar data and investigate the emigration movement, very important statistical material could be amassed from which important conclusions might be drawn.</p>
   <p>The article on emigration reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Miejsce, Galicia, Austria-Hungary</p>
   <p>"A few days ago, I visited all the families in my parish, as prescribed by church authority, with the book Status Animarum [census record book] in my hand, and I gathered the following statistics on emigration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0164.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The village of Miejsce, located in the county of Krosno, has 1009 Christians and 12 Jews. Emigration began in the year 1883, and during the ensuing years 118 Christians and 3 Jews emigrated from Miejsce to America, most of them to Pennsylvania. Among them were seven families and thirty-three married men who left their wives in the village, the remaining emigrants being single. Among the latter were six girls and two widows. Of these single persons, eleven married in America. Most of them married persons of their own nationalty who had come from western Galicia. One emigrant married a Pole who came from Prussia; one girl married a Ruthenian; another emigrant married a Bohemian girl; and one girl married a Pole born in America. Of these emigrants, five died in America: three died natural deaths, and two met with violent deaths. Of the latter, one was killed in a coal mine by falling dirt, and the other met his death during a strike. One girl disappeared on the way to America; her relatives in Miejsce and in America know nothing of her whereabouts.</p>
   <p>"Fifty-eight emigrants have returned from America to Miejsce, among them <pb facs="5423968_11_0165.jpg" n="3"/>being three families. Two peasants have already been to America three times, and five have been over there twice. Whenever there is a chance to buy a piece of land, a man leaves his wife at home and goes to America. Almost all of the emigrants consider themselves my parishioners, and send me contributions. Up to now, they have sent seven hundred Austrian guldens [$280] for the remodeling of the interior of the church. In addition to these emigrants to America, two men went to Rumania for a long period, and thirty-seven left the village on contract work.</p>
   <p>"These conditions exist in all the neighboring villages. If we take it for granted that these conditions exist more or less throughout the whole of Galicia, we must conclude that Polish emigration to America is not a loss but a gain for this province. But the fate of emigrants from other localities presents itself in a different light. Other localities should also be investigated in the manner discussed above."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
