<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 1, No. 18,
<date when="1897-04-30">April 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Adam Mickiewicz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 1, No. 18,
<date when="1897-04-30">April 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ADAM MICKIEWICZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next year will be a century since our great poet first saw light in an obscure corner of Lithuania. All Poland is preparing to celebrate the day of his birth and also to honor his deep religious feeling, love for his country and willingness to suffer for her.</p>
   <p>Polish-Americans probably would not wish to lag, although this seems to be the time when we would wish to leave a lasting remembrance of that day.</p>
   <p>There are several ways in which we can commemorate the memory of our immortal prophet. We can have a solemn gathering, erect a monument, found a Polish library or build a Polish National University or something similar. All these plans seem to hold some difficulties or are not appropriate to the conditions of the Polish people in America.</p>
   <p>We would probably find that most people are in favor of a University, but in going deeper into the subject, the time may not be ripe for such an undertaking. We can discuss the various projects at length later. Our suggestion, on this hundredth anniversary of the birth of Adam Mickiewicz is to erect an immigration building in New York city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0123.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mickiewicz, himself the greatest of Polish emigrants, went through a great deal of hardships and suffering associated with such a life, not for a year or two, but for the greater part of his life in Paris, as an immigrant. In building an Immigration Home in remembrance of Adam, we would also commemorate his sentence of suffering on foreign soil. With good will, the Home in a year from today could be under roof.</p>
   <p>After all, we are Poles no matter to which faction we belong, Mickiewicz belongs to us all and a home for immigrants, would serve all Poles regardless of our viewpoints. Therefore, we are setting our proposition before all Poles. It seems to us that a good way to get funds would be to publish a list of donors and amounts offered. Our newspaper, not wanting to delay the matter, is donating a modest sum to-day.</p>
   <p>On building the "Polish Home for Immigrants," on deciding on its rules, on conditions under which immigrants are to be accepted, what length of time they are to remain, and what care should be given them, we submit the Home to the direction of the "Brother of St. Francis" (Groups of Brother Albert) who have under their direction public homes for travelers in Krakow, or to some other organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0124.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is our idea and we offer it to our respected clergy, colleagues, editors, without thought of personal interest, and to our readers, and all Poles in general, living in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
