<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-12">Sept. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Countrymen by Commune Three of the Polish National Alliance of Holy Trinity Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-12">Sept. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO COUNTRYMEN BY COMMUNE THREE OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF HOLY TRINITY PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers and countrymen! Above all political idealogies and desperate plans for saving the homeland even at the sacrifice of one's life, and above the noble enthusiasm of those who hastened to stand at the side of one or another of the fighting countries in Europe, is raised the powerful voice of men of the greatest spirit and of all civilized peoples, for a free Poland as a bulwark and guardian of peace in northwestern Europe.</p>
   <p>Russia, hitherto our relentless enemy, has herself stated our most insistent postulate, that free Poland must include all of our annexed territory.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, events on the battleground--which is our native land--have so confused all of our plans and calculations that only one thing remains for us to do. Our good countryman John F. Smulski pointed it out in his telegram <pb facs="5423968_11_0567.jpg" n="2"/>to the convention of the Falcons at Buffalo: we must unite our strength and hasten to the aid of the old country with contributions of money.</p>
   <p>Since an American citizen (R. Crane) felt Mr. Smulski's appeal so deeply that he voluntarily pledged one thousand dollars a month for our cause, I am sure that our Polish generosity will keep step with the desire of our hearts to free the homeland.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in accordance with the unanimous vote of the delegates of the commune, we call upon all groups of the Polish National Alliance and all Alliance members of our district and we appeal to the brotherly affection of those citizens not members of the Alliance, that through taxing themselves voluntarily and through giving larger contributions they may manifest their sincere desire for a free Poland.</p>
   <p>In a patriotic spirit, the central department of independence exerts a specific and responsible control over all contributions. This board is composed of the <pb facs="5423968_11_0568.jpg" n="3"/>censor, the vice-censor, the advisory board, the central board of directors, and the presidents of all the groups of the P. N. A. The chief treasurer is Mr. Joseph Magdziarz, well-known and respected member of the Alliance. Under such control not a single penny can be lost.</p>
   <p>Our commune has appointed Mr. Peter I. Latwis chief collector for our district, and recommends to the Alliance groups belonging to our commune that they likewise place upon their financial secretaries the duties of collector. On receiving assessments from various members they should record the items, total them monthly for the Independence Fund, and, together with the contributions of groups, societies, and private individuals, send them without delay to Mr. Joseph Magdziarz, treasurer of the P. N. A., at the Alliance building.</p>
   <p>Reports of the contributions and voluntary pledges in our district will be read at the meetings of the delegates and announced in the papers.</p>
   <p>May unity in the desire to liberate our homeland be joined by universal generosity in giving to this sacred cause. Not being able to fight for our homeland, let <pb facs="5423968_11_0569.jpg" n="4"/>us contribute as much as we can afford with a feeling of sincere and deep devotion. Let the size of the contributions and the speed with which they are offered be proof that we really desire a free Poland.</p>
   <p>In the name of the commune of the Polish National Alliance of Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Joseph P. Szymanski, president</p>
   <p>Dr. J. K. Orlowski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
