<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-15">Dec. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Our Representative Individuals</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half tone, one column - eight of a page, bust of Edmund K. Jarecki.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-15">Dec. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">OUR REPRESENTATIVE INDIVIDUALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half tone, one column - eight of a page, bust of Edmund K. Jarecki.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Edmund K. Jarecki was born in Posen. He came to the United States in 1874 at the age of four. He received his early educational training at St. Hedwig's parochial school. After completing an elementary course, he entered St. Stanislaus high school.</p>
   <p>When he completed his secondary schooling he was engaged as a technical designer for a number of years. Then he enrolled at Northwestern University and studied law. During 1908 he earned his diploma, which qualified him to practice law.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jarecki became alderman of the 16th Ward during 1911-1912. Two years later this aspiring Polish gentleman was appointed municipal judge by the Governor of Illinois. He held this chair for seven months. After the expiration of his term E. K. Jarecki was elected Municipal judge for a six year term.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0891.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since 1920, Mr. Jarecki has been practicing law. He has his own office at 30 North La Salle Street, room 623. During the evenings he stays at his office at 1946 Armitage Avenue.</p>
   <p>Edmund K. Jarecki is known as one of the Polish individuals in national and local affairs. He took an active part in the campaign for obtaining loans for Poland. He was president of the campaign committee. For his active work in this field he deserves honor and recognition. Besides this, he has been active in many other Polish affairs which have won him many friends. This great popularity among the Polish people in Chicago is one of the best guarantees of his future career.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
