<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-12">Oct. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">What They Write about Us in the Old Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-12">Oct. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THEY WRITE ABOUT US IN THE OLD COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without question our readers should be interested in what the papers in the old country write about us. The Polish papers have devoted little space to our activities. At present, however, this situation is changing for the better.</p>
   <p>In occupied Poland there is an increase of interest in the brothers who have been flung far across the ocean because of oppression, and Dr. Dunikowski's visit to America, it is hoped, will bring about an even more marked interest.</p>
   <p>Recent numbers of the Lwow paper Przeglad (Review) have included favorable articles, under the title "Poles in America", which deal with our accomplishments. These articles are worthy of appearance in our papers. A recapitulation <pb facs="5423968_11_0768.jpg" n="2"/>of them will appear in a few numbers of the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>The anonymous author of these articles asserts that he spent some time in America and tried "not only to become acquainted with the life of the Polish immigrants but also to discover the reason for the misunderstandings among them which tend to weaken the reputation and the good name of the Poles in America."</p>
   <p>The work gives an interesting outlook on the situation of the Poles in America. The author of "Poles in America" is not a pessimist. He writes about the Polish colony in Chicago as follows:</p>
   <p>"One of the largest Polish centers is Chicago, Illinois, in the United States. This is the same Chicago which has risen almost overnight, like an enchanted city of old fable.....The number of Poles residing here is over 100,000. They <pb facs="5423968_11_0769.jpg" n="3"/>are well concentrated in two sections: the west and south sides. Chicago has six Polish churches, the largest being St. Stanislaus Kostka. It also harbors the three largest Polish organizations. In the two so-called Polish parts of Chicago, especially on the west side, one comes across cleanliness and many beautiful homes. The Polish tongue is continually heard on the streets. The only bad feature of the Polish language as spoken there is that many English words tend to be mixed with it. At times this is so marked that a new Polish arrival from Europe cannot understand what is being spoken."</p>
   <p>This is sad but true. The author in this instance, as in others, speaks advisedly. Another article of the same series will appear in tomorrow's issue of the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
