<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1921-12-29">Dec. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Honourable Distinction of J. F. Smulski. the French Government Decorates with the Cross of the Legion of Honor the President of the Polish National Department</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1921-12-29">Dec. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">HONOURABLE DISTINCTION OF J. F. SMULSKI. THE FRENCH GOVERNMENT DECORATES WITH THE CROSS OF THE LEGION OF HONOR THE PRESIDENT OF THE POLISH NATIONAL DEPARTMENT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president of the Polish National Department, Mr. John F. Smulski, was yesterday informed that the French Government presented him for his services given in the Polish-French affairs with the Lwgion of Honor Cross. This is a great honor for us Poles here in America, to have our countryman honored with such a mark of distinction. The activities of Mr. J. F. Smulski, as a true son of our Fatherland, is known everywhere. Especially France, our ally, is very grateful, to J. F. Smulski for the efforts he had made in the aim of uniting these two nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0887.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The presentation ceremony of the Cross of the Legion of Honor will take place Friday in the Union League Club, at 12:30, during which time the French consul, A. Barthelemy, will eulogize J. F. Smulski on behalf of the French Government, and bestow upon our recognized citizen the Cross of the French Legion of Honor.</p>
   <p>The committee, which is arranging this banquet, is composed of the following: The General Consul, A. Barthelemy, Colonel G. T. Buckingham, General Ch. G. Dawes, H. H. Merrick, J. R. Palendech, the president of the Z. P. R. K., Mr. N. L. Pictrowski, G. M. Reynolds and Dr. G. Taylor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
