<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-23">Jan. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Patriotic Exercises on January 22 at Bradley Street Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-23">Jan. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE PATRIOTIC EXERCISES ON JANUARY 22 AT BRADLEY STREET HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thirtieth anniversary of the January insurrection was celebrated solemnly at Bradley Street Hall on Saturday, at eight o'clock, through the efforts of Organizacya Patriotyczna (The Patriotic Organization) of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish in Chicago. The exercises were opened by a girls' choir with a prayer, after which the Reverend John Piechowski delivered a patriotic and religious address. He stated that the Poles were being punished for their sins by their present misery, and that they ought to awaken within themselves a spirit of humility and penance; since, for the successful uprising of the future, we need to remember the tears, the chains, and the graves in Siberia. He said that we must inspire ourselves with love for our country, with charity and sacrifice.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peter Kiolbassa was then named chairman of the exercises. After a beautiful song by a women's choir, Mr. Boleslaus Klarkowski delivered a historical <pb facs="5423968_11_0749.jpg" n="2"/>lecture. Mr. Klarkowski spoke of the origin and course of the insurrection, and showed how intolerable oppression and a desire for liberty combined to produce a national uprising. He declared that another cause for the revolt was that the Russians endeavored, often by violent means, to transport the youth of Poland into the depths of Russia, thus depriving Poland of its freshest strength. He spoke on the inequality of the fight, in which one Pole often faced forty Russians, and of the enormous losses suffered. But nevertheless, in the opinion of Mr. Klarkowski, the revolt was not without certain favorable results, namely, the consolidation of all classes of people, certain privileges to the peasants, etc.</p>
   <p>Following this address, the male chorus under the direction of Mr. A. Kwasigroch sang beautifully a number entitled "Badly Wounded."</p>
   <p>The Falcons of St. Stanislaus parish, organized only a few weeks ago, performed gymnastic exercises. The precision of their performance called forth considerable <pb facs="5423968_11_0750.jpg" n="3"/>applause.</p>
   <p>After a song by a girls' choir, a patriotic address was delivered by Mr. Zbigniew Brodowski. The speaker declared that in spite of the fact that the revolts were crushed, they had had important results. During the course of these insurrections, at times of most dire defeat, heroic man arose like Israel's prophets to keep alive the spirit, crush doubt, and carry forward the national standard. Kosciuszko was such; such was Kraszewski in 1863 and later, working in a different field. The fruit of these defeats was always a rebirth, an encouragement to new strength and greater effort. Here on American soil we have become a power which should, by its acts, demonstrate its nationality. [Translator's Note. The word is "Polskosc", meaning "Polishness," or, if I may coin a word, "Polonism."] One such act is the erection of a monument to Kosciuszke. The speaker appealed to the representatives of organizations to support the erection of the monument and to contribute to the fund for this purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0751.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The final address was delivered by Reverend W. Barzynski. The speaker emphasized that deep and sincere patriotism is not manifested by loud demonstrations, boastfulness, and orgies, but by work, deeds, and sacrifice. Lack of effort and sacrifice caused our downfall once and produced today's grave wrongs. There were too few schools, and the rich spent their time amusing themselves abroad until everything collapsed. This should be a lesson to us. Today's quiet labor over faith, enlightenment, civilization, and the union of the nation into a whole, should be our chief occupation. Not arms and money, but faith, religion, and love will restore our homeland. Thus, we should try again and again to create something new that will strengthen us in our faith and nationality. As one such institution that should be established in America, the parson cited the Polish Brotherhood of the Queen's Crown recently formed in Galicia and approved by Cardinal Dunajewski.</p>
   <p>The parson was warmly applauded, as were the speakers who preceded him. The exercises closed with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" by the audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
