<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1920-04-28">April 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Polish War Veterans Who Served under General Haller in France Are Back in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1920-04-28">April 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WAR VETERANS WHO SERVED UNDER GENERAL HALLER IN FRANCE ARE BACK IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first contingent of Polish troops who served in France arrived in Chicago on April 23, 1920, at 11 P.M. The Union Station was filled with throngs of Polish people since noon time. The sidewalks in front of the Union Station were also filled with friends and relatives of the war heroes. Many religious and national societies took part in the welcome.</p>
   <p>The Citizens' Committee from Town of Lake, headed by Mr. Bronislaw Koralewski, supplied the automobiles for the returning heroes. Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, president of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, invited all the returning soldiers to the hall of the Union for a dinner given by the Polish National Council. The speeches at the dinner were made by <pb facs="5423968_11_0288.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, who spoke for the Polish National Council and the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, and by Mr. J. Magdziarz, who spoke for the Polish National Alliance. The representative of the Polish Falcons spoke also. Other speakers were Mr. Chodzinskas and Mr. Milewska.</p>
   <p>Besides the dinner the Polish heroes were also presented with flowers and other gifts. The meeting was very enthusiastic. Thw wives, brothers, sisters, sweethearts and friends of the returning soldiers were there. There was great joy for it brought tears to the eyes of the greeters! Reporters of the American papers took pictures at the station and in the street.</p>
   <p>The returning Polish soldiers who served under General Haller in France are looking fine; in fact they look better now than at the time they were leaving for France.</p>
   <p>In the same high spirits the soldiers from the Haller's Army are being greeted in Milwaukee, Detroit, Buffalo and other cities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
