<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-23">Jan. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Wilson's Address to the Senate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-23">Jan. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WILSON'S ADDRESS TO THE SENATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"A free, independent, autonomous Poland"--these are the words which yesterday fell from the lips of the chief executive of this country.</p>
   <p>This is our watchword. This is the watchword of the entire Polish nation, which understands and believes that this war must bring about the realization of this watchword.</p>
   <p>For more than a hundred years we have lived in the greatest chaos and the most demoralizing conditions, constantly waiting for the time when these words would be uttered by the rulers of the world or by the mighty representatives of the will of the people of some nation, because we have believed in the power of justice.</p>
   <p>And thus unexpectedly, at a time when the entire world is absorbed in seeking <pb facs="5423968_11_0505.jpg" n="2"/>means of ending for everyone this horrible murder of people, the President of the United States has uttered these words, repaying in a way a debt of gratitude earned by our heroes who fought for the independence of the now mighty States.</p>
   <p>President Wilson has understood the wants and desires of the entire Polish nation, and in his speech, in which he pointed only at Poland, with which Europe should begin restoring the rights of smaller nations, he demanded from the world--in accordance with the already-established opinion of all statesmen--the return to us of all Polish lands, and the uniting of Poland, giving us independence, i. e., throwing off all foreign protectorates from over Poland, and giving us complete autonomy.</p>
   <p>This is what all of us desire. We will never cease striving for this.</p>
   <p>By expressing himself in the Polish matter, President Wilson raised our beloved cause very high. He placed it among the most important matters which must be definitely settled after the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0506.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Without the restoration of Poland there can be no talk of peace in Europe, just as there can be no talk of peace without the restoration of rights and freedom to other nations.</p>
   <p>Perhaps now the tongues of the Western statesmen will be loosened; perhaps now the idea of separating the Polish matter from the Russian ministry will carry weight, because the voice of the President is not only the voice of the United States, but it is the voice of the entire world, with the exception perhaps of those of our invaders who will be very sorry to give up Polish lands as a delicious tidbit which has been bitten into but not yet completely consumed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
