<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">Mar. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Recruiting Rally Held in St. Mary of the Angels Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-13">Mar. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITING RALLY HELD IN ST. MARY OF THE ANGELS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A recruiting rally for the Polish Army was held yesterday at the St. Mary of the Angels Parish Hall, at which more than a thousand people were present. The hall was decorated in Polish and American colors.</p>
   <p>The rally was opened by the Reverend Francis Gordon, pastor of the parish, with a short prayer. After addressing a few words to the gathering, he named as chairman, Judge E. Jarecki, who appointed Ruszkowiak as secretary. In his address, Jarecki thanked the gathering for its numerous attendance which, he said, proved that the Polish cause is sacred to every one; it is a cause that brooks no delay and all Poles realize that the freedom of Poland is a cause for which there can never be enough sacrifice; upon this rests our whole future, and our country's independence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0375.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the address by Chairman Jarecki, the program was begun. At this time, Sigmund Wisniewski, a veteran of the Spanish-American War, carried the Polish flag with its white eagle to the platform. At the sight of the flag, the audience leaped to its feet with long-sustained applause. When the applause was over, the audience sang "Jeszcze Polska Nic Zginela" (Poland is not yet lost). The flag remained on the stage during the whole course of the program. Wisniewski was relieved as standard bearer by Stephen Babecki, a volunteer to the Polish Army, who is enjoying a few weeks furlough in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The program was carried out as follows:</p>
   <p>The St. Cecelia young people's choir, directed by Kosobocki, organist of St. Mary of Angels Church, and E. Wiedeman, organist of St. Hedwig's Church, sang a Polish folk song, for which the audience applauded so much that it was forced to return for an encore.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0376.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The second number on the program was a recitation, "Spartan Girl", by Miss Josephine Jaworski. She was rewarded with a storm of applause. This was followed by a dialogue by two children of the St. Mary of Angels' Parochial School, John Kwiatkowski, thirteen, and Frances Taraski, also thirteen. These children deserve sincere recognition, for their performance was faultless. It was done so well that there are not words enough for praise, and consequently, the audience was unsparing with its applause.</p>
   <p>The next number was a dance, a Mazur by eight couples.</p>
   <p>[List of names of boys and girls who danced omitted by translator.]</p>
   <p>It should be added that all those who participated in the dance were born here in this country, and yet, they danced so well that it is doubtful whether native-born Mazurs could have done better. And this time too, the public was unsparing in the applause so well deserved by the dancers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0377.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The chairman then introduced the representative of the Polish Army, W. L. Ruzycki, organizer of Recruiting Center II, who has already spoken on many such an occasion as this as becomes a soldier of the Polish Army. He described the whole horror of this war, and how much our homeland has suffered and is still suffering because of it. He spoke of the people in Poland who are living in such awful misery, that they are begging with out-stretched arms that we in America help them not only materially, but that we create a powerful army that will march through Berlin to Poland and free it from the aggressors who since the war began, have been oppressing it, and at the same time, have been giving vent to their anger on our mothers, sisters, fathers, and brothers. Naturally, his words brought tears to more than one eye, for who can keep from weeping at the thought that our brethren who are suffering not only from cold and hunger but from the cruelest oppression in the world; for there are no means which the Prussian would not use to torture the innocent populace. The speech was tremendously applauded.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the Reverend John Sobieszczak, Vicar of St. Mary of <pb facs="5423968_11_0378.jpg" n="5"/>the Angels Church, who appealed to the gathering as only a priest-patriot can. The Reverend Sobieszczak probably reached every heart in which any Polish spirit exists. Justly, he called those that hide behind aprons cowards. He said that today is no time for tenderness, for our duties to our motherland are sacred and demand sacrifice and self-denial. He called upon the youth to join the Polish Army and upon the elders to contribute both for the army and for the relief of our countrymen in Poland.</p>
   <p>"Contributions," he said, "should be sincere and as large as possible, not as alms, but as the duty of every Pole who loves his homeland and wants to see Poland free, great, and independent." There can be no doubt that the words of this capable priest reached the hearts of his hearers, and it is to be expected that his splendid address will bring the proper results.</p>
   <p>A collection for the Polish Army was taken up after the Reverend Sobieszczak <pb facs="5423968_11_0379.jpg" n="6"/>had finished speaking. It netted $169.46. May God bless those who gave, but let it be remembered that contributions must keep flowing in, for without money, our army can do nothing. Remember that the Polish Army is a vital necessity and that money is indispensible to it.</p>
   <p>After the collection, the elder St. Cecelia choir sang "The Call to Battle", and after a storm of applause sang "A Rose".</p>
   <p>The next address was delivered by that indefatigable worker in the nationalistic field, the Reverend F. Gordon. He did not speak long, for the hour was already late, but in a few words, he reached the hearts of his hearers, who, after all, were all good Poles. What good Pole could remain deaf to the sincere, dignified words of the worshipful pastor: "Believe me, I would not remain here with you for one moment if I were younger but would hasten there where it is the duty of every Polish young man to be. A man who is afraid of war," continued the pastor, "is not a man, but a coward, for he does not <pb facs="5423968_11_0380.jpg" n="7"/>know how to defend the rights of mankind, and would like to have others fight for him while he sits in comparative ease, just so long as he need not expose himself." The speaker went on to say that today is no time for dissension and quarrels. We should remember only one thing; namely, that we are Poles and that it is our duty to win freedom and independence for Poland.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the American and Polish National anthems, "The Star-Spangled Banner" and "Boze Cos Polske" (God save Poland) were sung.</p>
   <p>In spite of the fact that recruiting was unsuccessful, for not one man volunteered, we are sure that the Polish spirit will awaken within us, that duty will call every Pole to action, and when the recruiting station is opened, the youth will hasten to fill out the ranks of the Polish Army so that it will be strong enough to win back that which was taken from us by force--a Poland from sea to sea.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0381.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Poles! Do not forget that the Polish Army needs youth for its ranks and elders to contribute money for its maintenance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
