<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-14">Jan. 14, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Our Present Political Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0673</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0673.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-14">Jan. 14, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PRESENT POLITICAL DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Discussing various happenings in Europe, the Cracow Nowa Reforma (New Reform) has this to say regarding the stand the Poles sould take in connection with them:</p>
   <p>"We the Polish people are merely unimportant spectators of the terrible things happening on a wide arena of international conflict.</p>
   <p>"We have been relieved of all imaginary hopes that our idea of freedom and justice will be realized on foreign soil, that the armed forces of foreign nations will resurrect our independence, in this manner repaying just debts.</p>
   <p>"Today we are seeking a future with our own strength; in civilized work, in the propagation of national education among the greatest number, and in implanting <pb facs="5423968_11_0674.jpg" n="2"/>with it simultaneously a fervent patriotism, thus we should and can discern the embryo of our national existence.</p>
   <p>"Let us be a nation alive, conscious of our historical task, respecting our past, nurturing all groups and spheres in a patriotic observance of citizens' laws and duties, and we can patiently await--although we may suffer still more and be time and again bitterly disillusioned: the time when our own political independence will be realized.</p>
   <p>"We must not permit ourselves to renounce our heartfelt desires; and our labors under this banner do not stop being a duty, regardless of what happens in Europe, what diplomatic alliances are formed, and what intrigues triumph thereby.</p>
   <p>"These words, although published by a paper of a viewpoint different from ours, are gladly reprinted by us, and we advise all our countrymen to remember them well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0675.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This article, in our estimation, contains wise political advice for us to follow today.</p>
   <p>No hopeless despair, no quarrelsome combinations or immature planning; only internal work, patriotic and civilized--such is a sensible program that is proper at this time under our present conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
