<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-20">Sept. 20, 1905</date>, pp. 1-5.
<title level="a">Polish Patriot Dies at Age of 101 Years. Mathias Rewandowski Who Fought in Three Revolutions Passes Away</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-20">Sept. 20, 1905</date>, pp. 1-5.
<title level="a">POLISH PATRIOT DIES AT AGE OF 101 YEARS. MATHIAS REWANDOWSKI WHO FOUGHT IN THREE REVOLUTIONS PASSES AWAY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the coffin borne by six of his grandchildren, the body of Mathias Rewandowski, 101 years old, was taken, yesterday, to its last resting place. His widow, 97 years old, six sons and forty-two grandchildren and great-grandchildren survive him. Gathered about his bedside, Saturday when he died, were more than fifty of his descendants. The funeral took place from the home, 468 Elston Avenue.</p>
   <p>Thirty-four years of Rewandowski's earlier life were spent in fighting for the freedom of his native land, and it is believed that he was the sole surviving participant of the first three revolutions in Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0956.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was in 1830 that Rewandowski enlisted as a private in the Polish army. General Koseinszko was his commander, and for valor performed in the first battle of the revolution, he was promoted.</p>
   <p>The second attempt on the part of Poland to throw off the yoke of her oppressor found Rewandowaki one of the first volunteers, and in the contest of 1844, he was an active participant. After the suppression of the movement, Rewandowski spent years traveling through Poland in the interests of the revolutionary party. The uprising of 1863 found Rewandowski in the ranks, and in the last battle of the revolution, he was wounded while leading a charge and was left on the field.</p>
   <p>Captured by the Russians, Rewandowski was held until his wounds had healed, and he then was sent to the mines in Siberia. After three years of servitude, he was liberated through the efforts of the Roman Catholic Church in his native land.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No sooner had he returned to Poland than he set about the forming of another revolution. He was seized by the Russians and banished to Siberia for life. It was in 1874 that the dreary march to the mines began. The party of prisoners and guards had gone but a short distance when Rewandowski escaped while the guards were asleep, and, with his wife, came to America, settling soon after in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
