<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-20">Dec. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">What the Chelm Case Is About</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Anna Wyczolkowska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-20">Dec. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE CHELM CASE IS ABOUT</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Anna Wyczolkowska</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because many people ask what is this Chelm case, we submit for the time being the following explanation.</p>
   <p>As everyone knows, the Kingdom of Poland was created by the decree of the Congress of Vienna of the 1815. This political decree was signed, with the exception of the three annexer countries, by all the countries of Europe, among them England, France, Sweden, Spain, Portugal, and Switzerland. In the decree of the Congress of Vienna, the boundaries and the indivisibility of the Kingdom of Poland are definitely guaranteed. The boundaries may be extended, but they may not be curtailed. Now the Russian government has decided to take, out of the very center of Poland, six counties belonging to the states of Lublin and Siedlce, with a population of 800,000, and annex them to Russia or make a Muscovite and Greek Orthodox province out of them. This act is being discussed <pb facs="5423968_11_0602.jpg" n="2"/>at present in the Russian Duma. It is for this reason that efforts are being made, especially by the Polish women, to prevent Russia from annexing this Polish soil. Furthermore, there is a project afoot to annex and Russianize Suwalki after the annexation of Chelm. Therefore, an appeal was sent to all the European countries which signed the decree of the Congress of Vienna, asking them to protest against this robbery, since they are authorized to do this. His appeal has even reached the Polish immigrants in Chicago but, for reasons not yet known, they have done nothing about it.</p>
   <p>This horrible blow, which is aimed at Poland's very heart, should not only be met with indignation and protest but should also be resisted with our closest co-operation with the action begun in the homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
