<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Heal the Wounds</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">HEAL THE WOUNDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past few months the nationalism of the Poles in America has been strangely and sometimes unintelligibly feverish.</p>
   <p>From all sides accusations have been hurled at even the most deserving individuals who are working for the Polish cause. They are accused because they hold opinions different from those of others and because they do not conceal these differences of opinion and hypocritically give the impression of universal agreement on national issues.</p>
   <p>Accusations of betrayal, of denying the ideals of love for the homeland, of provocations, and of selling themselves to the annexer governments, would never have been made, had not our orientation toward world affairs today been hammered out, and our plans for future action developed, in this feverish atmosphere. Like a <pb facs="5423968_11_0584.jpg" n="2"/>wild horse, unrestrained Polish nationalism has run rampant, trampling on all considerations of decent and ethical treatment of one's opponents.</p>
   <p>Today this crazy feverishness is beginning to subside under the effects of the fire of war, which is running wild over all of Europe. Today, fortunately still in time, our hands are unconsciously seeking the hands of our opponents to exchange brotherly greetings and to begin working for the common good.</p>
   <p>Let us not allow this attempt at harmony to die out, let us not allow ourselves to be pulled apart by further battles, but sincerely, as befits true Poles, let us forget our hurt feelings and think about the future. This future is knocking at our door. We all agree that Poland may arise after the present war. We, also, all desire this ardently, Then let us put aside all personal injuries and petty ambitions for leadership.</p>
   <p>It is now a matter or utter indifference who suggests a happy idea, who does this or that service, or whether this or that motion is passed. But it is decisively <pb facs="5423968_11_0585.jpg" n="3"/>important that there be people to make motions, that each person understand the will of the majority--in a word, that each do his work. We need action to-day more than ever before.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time the opinion was held that the best thing in the world was that which a Pole invented and a Czech made. This sentence should be erased from our thoughts when we are concerned with the best of all good things, a free and independent Poland, because both the idea and its accomplishment must be ours. We shall see that it will not be difficult for us to accomplish this, when we consider the scope of our action. This scope has narrowed in regard to ideas and initiative and has broadened in regard to the difficulty and the size of the undertaking.</p>
   <p>The homeland does not need our ideas and motions now, first, because we are not in a position to propound them, since we do not know what the present political orientation in the homeland is, and second, because we could by no means "expert" them to the homeland.</p>
   <p>The homeland asks of us sacrifice, money, and a whole mass of laborers who will <pb facs="5423968_11_0586.jpg" n="4"/>return to the homeland to fill the vacancies left by the war.</p>
   <p>It is a shame to waste time--we repeat--on the forming of a political orientation. News from the homeland, when any does come, is scanty and distorted by the respective governments. The Prussians want to call the Poles to armed resistance against Russia; Russia wants to do the exact reverse; and both of these powers, in accordance with their political designs, color the news which comes to us. Poland at present represents for the annexers a delicate, porcelain toy which must not be broken and which they dare not let go.</p>
   <p>Since such is the case, let us leave all political orientation and ideas to our brothers in the homeland. They can attend to those things better than we because they have more political experience than we have. We will have no influence on the victory of this or that political party in the homeland, so why should we use up our strength and energy and wear out our tongues, Better that we should prepare the Polish "granary" in order to feed the hungry and emaciated.</p>
   <p>There remains for us only one type of action--one task: to collect as much money <pb facs="5423968_11_0587.jpg" n="5"/>as possible and to encourage as many people as possible who are capable of hard work to return to Poland.</p>
   <p>Let us suppose that historical necessity will be fulfilled and Poland will arise. Then the Polish treasury will be empty, because for 120 years foreign powers have been misappropriating its funds. There will be a lack of laborers because Polish workers will have been murdered in the war or left unfit for work. There will be no system of government because for generations the Poles have been brought up under three different governments and each group will want to govern in its fashion.</p>
   <p>Cannot the Polish emigrants do much toward supplying these needs? Yes: There is enough money among us, if only each of us wanted to remember that Poland is closer to his person than his shirt, that Poland means more than the future wealth of his children. If all of us marching together should contribute generously to the treasury of the homeland, we could very easily collect many millions of dollars. Also, workmen to fill the vacancies left by the victims of <pb facs="5423968_11_0588.jpg" n="6"/>the war in the homeland could be found in large numbers among us.</p>
   <p>Although not so many of us will go back as could be desired, those of us who do go back will be such that each one will be equal to many. A Pole schooled in America will take back to the homeland with him better ideas of agriculture and economy, a knowledge of the unequaled commercial system of the United States, and a spirit thoroughly imbued with republican and democratic ideas.</p>
   <p>Let us not forget that the Poles in the homeland are threatened not only by the war but also by the equally great danger of Jewish expansion. The Jews will not rest but will immediately endeavor to get control of the commerce, industry, and handicraft of free Poland. These we must displace.</p>
   <p>Let the Polish emigrants furnish only two hundred people who understand American business methods, who know on what the good attributes of the American businessman are based, and we can be sure that these will control all of the markets in the larger Polish cities in a short time, and will thus increase their own welfare as well as that of the homeland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0589.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>These are our problems and our duties. Now we must heal our wounds, forget our injuries, and harmoniously get to work. Now we must begin collecting money and supplementing our knowledge of business. Now we must begin to think about returning to the homeland. Tomorrow we must return to Poland and begin work on the soil dear to us, begin to live the life of a climbing plant instead of that of a dwarfed weed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
