<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-04">Mar. 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A True Democrat</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-04">Mar. 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A TRUE DEMOCRAT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today Grover Cleveland steps down from the high office of President of the United States and his place will be taken over by his Republican successor, McKinley.</p>
   <p>What service the new President is going to render the country remains for the future to tell. What has been accomplished by his predecessor we will eleborate in full. Today, however, we will deal with his courage, intelligence and true patriotism, for only yesterday he vetoed the Immigration Bill, sponsored by Senator Lodge, an adherent of the American Protective Association.</p>
   <p>By such action President Cleveland has definitely demonstrated his just <pb facs="5423968_11_0126.jpg" n="2"/>displeasure with the intolerances contained in the Immigration Bill and with the unreasonableness of its proponents who desired to create an unhealthy condition in American society by letting out from its organism the new healthy blood that has been its life, instead of trying to cure the existing evils.</p>
   <p>Of what help will be the curtailment of healthy, industrious, reserved, and pious peoples who, because of conditioned circumstances, are unable to read or write, if everyone of us sees definite proof as to where we are being led by reading the American papers?</p>
   <p>Of what help will the knowledge of reading and writing be to those whose children do not have the opportunity to hear about God and the Ten Commandments in the public schools?</p>
   <p>An ignorant citizen, reared along religious lines, making an honest living by <pb facs="5423968_11_0127.jpg" n="3"/>the sweat of his brow, although unable to read or write, always fulfilled his duties to God, to his country, and to his family whether abroad or in America, provided his superiors were understanding individuals who believed in the Almighty and were enveloped with true patriotism.</p>
   <p>There are not many of such people in the United States, because a majority of the intelligentsia are but career-seekers whose only guiding light is the dollar. They do not harbor any ideals, they are unaware of the good of man, and they hold no consideration for the words: God, fatherland, humanity, and conscience.</p>
   <p>As to the desire of cleansing the country of the present evil elements, it is not necessary to turn to the immigrants in order to right the wrong, but it is necessary to cross the reins of the present subversive element which tends to abuse the privileges of freedom and liberty for the sole purpose <pb facs="5423968_11_0128.jpg" n="4"/>of bringing America to moral and material ruin.</p>
   <p>Only the blind do not see in what direction the "educated" masons, members of the American Protective Association, anarchists, and other apostles of false progress are leading us.</p>
   <p>Such unhealthy elements should be weeded out and the ignorant, unfamiliar with the art of reading and writing, unable to distinguish between right and wrong, who give a willing ear to the leaders of evil, should be given the proper training, the ability to recognize the rights of God, the opportunity to improve themselves, and the privilege of entering upon the road of life's grave responsibilities. Such is the duty of our lawmakers and men of state.</p>
   <p>Our present-day Congressmen at Washington are not such lawmakers. The <pb facs="5423968_11_0129.jpg" n="5"/>The only true man of the government is the Democrat, Cleveland, who as yet has not been called a backward Conservative.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
