<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-13">May 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Home's Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-13">May 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION HOME'S PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter has been received from Rev. J. Zlotorzynski, secretary of Immigration Home:</p>
   <p>"At the present time there is no greater need among the Polish people in America, and those coming into this country, than the formulation of an institution that will look after the interest of newcomers. The need for such an institution is growing greater every day.</p>
   <p>"My duties as a priest, especially during the Lenten season, have compelled me to set aside the question of the Polish Immigration Home, although it is close to my heart. Now, with the Easter duties at an end, I have taken up this important problem again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Providence has been kind to us, for we were able to set up such a Home in New York City. The generous contributions of our people in America have made this possible. Because of a slump in business conditions, the frequency of the visits to the Home have surpassed the quota for accommodations. The facilities of this Immigration Home are too small. It is impossible to give shelter to all that come here for help. It is a pity that they who have come to the land of plenty, should be turned away.</p>
   <p>"The readers of the press in America are familiar with figures of the ever-increasing influx of immigrants to this country. Yet the contributions for the upkeep of the Home are very meager. Why is this? It is beyond my comprehension! Despite this urgent need, donations for the starving Russians are made by the most mercenary people in America. Offerings for other causes, such as the Kosciuszko Monument Fund, are flowing from all parts of the United States and Canada. But funds for the ever-in-creasing need of the Immigration Home have become a scarcity. Is the <pb facs="5423968_11_0198.jpg" n="3"/>care of the unfortunate immigrant who is trying to make a niche for himself in the American scheme of things unimportant? Is the drive for the Russians abroad or the monument fund so vastly important? It is true that every person is our brother. But a brother on this soil is more closely related than one abroad, and bread by far exceeds the need for a monument.</p>
   <p>"I, for one, heartily support the unity of the Poles in America, but to build a monument somewhere in a park misses the mark of unity. It would be a greater and more beneficial deed to divert the funds toward the erection of a bigger and better home for the Polish immigrants who seek help. Although the monument will be built at the cost of thousands of dollars, it will never make a great impression to the spectators at the Columbian Exposition. After the termination of the World's Fair, it will be of lesser importance, although it will represent a noble cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0199.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"There is nothing radically wrong with statues and obelisks. Many can be erected. But along with them, let there be more concern placed upon the dire wants of the Polish immigrant. As it happens, because of the regulations, many of them are sent back to Europe where conditions are a hundred times worse. These pitiful returns could be averted with the proper means.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, let us make a strong attempt to have the funds gathered in Chicago for the Kosciuszko Monument diverted toward the building of a greater Polish Immigration Home in New York City. This, indeed, will be a pride and a comfort to our people. This will be the salvation of the destitute and a succor to the faithful.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely,</p>
   <p>"Rev. Joseph J. Zlotorzynski,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
   <p>"N. B. It will be greatly appreciated if this letter is repeated in other papers."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
