<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-29">Jan. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Excursion to Poland a Great Opportunity for Children and Parents Alike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-29">Jan. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">EXCURSION TO POLAND A GREAT OPPORTUNITY FOR CHILDREN AND PARENTS ALIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An unusual opportunity for our children as well as for ourselves is presented in the excursion to Poland, on July 2nd, from New York directly to Gdynia, via the Gdynia-America steamship line, under the auspices of the Polish National Alliance, Educational Department.</p>
   <p>That excursion will prove to be of invaluable benefit to our maturing youth, as well as to parents; in fact, to the entire Polish-American community. It affords the best means for presenting to our children that great country of our forefathers, with its glorious past, its monuments testifying to its great culture, and its inestimable memorials of our most recent battles for freedom. It will be the true sight of that glorious Republic of Poland in all her splendor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We cannot demand or expect of a child that it love parents whom it has never seen; neither can we request an unconditional love for Poland of those who do not know her.</p>
   <p>Therefore, with the knowledge and understanding of its true national and educational mission toward Polish immigrants, the Polish National Alliance Educational Department desires to sent to Poland the largest possible number of our native youth, and to show that youth why Poland should be glorified, loved and esteemed; why a Pole is proud of his native country; and why a child born in this country should not forget the country of its parents and forefathers.</p>
   <p>For parents, too, it is an unheard of opportunity to instill in the minds of their children a general view of the world. In schools of this country children are impregnated with the belief that only America is the sum of all perfection. It is, therefore, not surprising that the child disdains its parents who came from some part of Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0223.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Poland, they visualize as a country of poverty and misery, of ignorance and disorder; and it is with a feeling of shame that they admit their Polish descent.</p>
   <p>If, then, the child be sent to Poland, it will enrich its knowledge with a store of facts gleaned from the various spheres of life and science, and will return with an unquestionably different attitude.</p>
   <p>To begin with, these children will be cultured, and have higher, more idealistic and cleaner views; they will learn to appreciate and honor great things; and will have awakened in them higher thoughts and ambitions.</p>
   <p>Such an excursion is of paramount value, as it lends prestige to the Polish community of America. It makes the young Polish people more ambitious, more far-sighted and broadminded; it makes them embrace the Polish cause with greater enthusiasm. And it is from such a young generation that the Polish-American community will select its future leaders, intercessors and directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
