<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-12">Jan. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Results of Doctor Dunikowski's Mission to America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-12">Jan. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESULTS OF DOCTOR DUNIKOWSKI'S MISSION TO AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Catholic Gazette brings us the following results of Dr. Dunikowski's visit to America as given in a letter from Lwow:</p>
   <p>"Delegates to the Assembly and the National Council met on December 21. Dr. Dunikowski, a member of this group, had at its request visited America and studied Polish-American conditions.....The group listened with interest to Dr. Dunikowski's report, after which followed a general discussion. While the final decision rests with the Galician Assembly, here are some of the projects outlined:</p>
   <p>"1. In the near future, a secondary or high school will be established in Chicago with the purpose of developing a patriotic and Catholic spirit <pb facs="5423968_11_0755.jpg" n="2"/>in candidates for the priesthood. These candidates will receive a sound education intended to prepare them for entrance to a theological seminary. Count Rey told the gathering that he had already a million and a half francs to use for this purpose.</p>
   <p>"2. The establishment of an organization to maintain connections between Poland and the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish National Alliance, and all other Polish organizations. The object of this organization is simply to keep up the Polish national spirit in America and to raise, if possible, the intellectual level [of the Poles].</p>
   <p>"3. Polish libraries and reading rooms in America are to be supplied with books.</p>
   <p>"4. A Polish Insurance Association and a Polish Bank are to be established in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0756.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"5. A system of national colonization, designed to discourage concentration of immigrants in large cities, as such concentration produces a proletariat.</p>
   <p>"6. An appeal will be sent to Rome requesting greater attention to the needs of the Polish Church--especially the appointment of at least one Polish bishop in America."</p>
   <p>Doubtless, these are very interesting and noble projects. One point is objectionable, however, namely, that our brethren across the ocean propose without consulting us, things which can be accomplished only upon an understanding with American Polonia, and with its cooperation and support. It may be that we are mistaken--that this impression is the result of too hurried a letter bringing the news to the editorial office. At any rate, it is logical that nothing concerning us can be definitely achieved without us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
