<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Evening Post</title>,
<date when="1929-11-30">Nov. 30, 1929</date>, p. 6.
<title level="a">John Pelka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0869</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0869.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Evening Post</title>,
<date when="1929-11-30">Nov. 30, 1929</date>, p. 6.
<title level="a">JOHN PELKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John A. Pelka was born in Chicago in 1881, and has resided in the same locality practically all his life. He received his early education at the grammer schools in the vicinity, and later attended Valparaiso University, Ind.</p>
   <p>He has always taken an active part in the civic affairs of his neighborhood, and is one of the most energetic workers in promoting enterprises which are of benefit to his people. Notable among these is the Charles V. Barrett Athletic Club, which was organized to promote amateur athletics for the young boys and girls of the neighborhood, and is known as one of the most flourishing organizations of its kind in the city. Mr. Pelka is one of its organizers. He is held in the highest esteem by both the priests and parishioners of St. Adalbert's parish, of which he is a member, for the unassuming manner in which he is ever ready and willing to devote his personal attention and means in aiding those who are in need of assistance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pelka rendered invaluable service while a member of Exemption Board, Local No. 25, during the world war, and made quite a record at that time selling liberty bonds. He was appointed Secretary of the West Chicago Park Commissioners by Gov. Frank H. Lowden, and subsequently Civil Service Commissioner by <pb facs="5423968_11_0870.jpg" n="2"/>Mayor William E. Dever. He served as County Commissioner until Dec. 1, 1926, and in April, 1927 was appointed to his present position as Commissioner of Compensation, by Mayor Wm. Hale Thompson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
