<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-04">June 4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting in Behalf of Polish National Fund at Rapperschwyl, Switzerland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-04">June 4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING IN BEHALF OF POLISH NATIONAL FUND AT RAPPERSCHWYL, SWITZERLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last two weeks there has been agitation for supporting the plan of establishing an American section of the Polish National Fund at Rapperschwyl, Switzerland. The plan was initiated by Francis Jablonski, editor of Zgoda and a delegate of the Polish Emigrants' Alliance in Europe.</p>
   <p>A second meeting was held yesterday at Pulaski Hall in behalf of this cause. K. Zychlinski was chairman of the meeting, and S. Barszczewski was secretary. An outline of the plan of the new organization was read, revealing that the name will be, "Skarb Narodowy Polski Pod Opieka Muzeum w Rapperswylu, Oddzial Polnocne-Amerykanski Pod Kontrola Zwiazku Narodowego Polskiego" (Polish National Fund under the Guardianship of the Museum of Rapperschwyl, North American Section controlled by the Polish National Alliance). The purpose of the organization will be to collect money for the Polish National Fund at Rapperschwyl, Switzerland. The members of the Polish National Alliance will <pb facs="5423968_11_0717.jpg" n="2"/>donate voluntarily not less than one cent a month for this purpose. The organization will have central administration and circuit departments. The central administration will be located in Chicago, and will consist of a chairman, two assistants (of whom the first will be in charge of the circuit in which the main office is located), secretary, treasurer, and two members of the administrative staff.</p>
   <p>This plan, of which we have presented only the most important parts, was accepted almost without changes.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected: Andrzejkiewic, of Philadelphia, chairman; Dr. R. Lande, first assistant; Casmir Zychlinski, second assistant; S. Barszczewski, secretary; Michael Majewski, treasurer; L. Terczewski and J. I. Migdalski, members of the administrative staff.</p>
   <p>A collection was taken at the close of the meeting; it brought in a few dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
