<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-29">Nov. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish-American Participation in the Kosciusko Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-29">Nov. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH-AMERICAN PARTICIPATION IN THE KOSCIUSKO EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Participation by Polish-Americans in the Kosciusko Exposition, to be held in 1894 in Lwow, is gaining ever greater momentum here. Preparations are being made on all sides to send exhibits over there.</p>
   <p>Reverend Szukalski of Milwaukee decided to gather a complete set of photographics of all the Polish priests in America and send them to the Lwow Exposition. Our Polish priests are sending in their portraits and the collection should be completed shortly. It will, no doubt, be examined at the Exposition with great interest. We are informed that a set of portraits of all the Polish editors in America is also being collected to be sent to the Exposition; this is net a bad idea.</p>
   <p>The banner being sent for exhibition by the St. Stanislaus Kostka Society is one of the most interesting souvenirs the Poles possess in America. It was, undoubtedly, the first Polish banner to be used in the United States. It is not <pb facs="5423968_11_0721.jpg" n="2"/>seventeen but twenty-seven years old and should therefore be considered a valuable keepsake. The St. Stanislaus Kostka Society is the oldest Polish church society in Chicago, if not the oldest in all America. It was organized in 1866, before the first Polish church was built, and the banner was purchased in Paris immediately after the Society was founded.</p>
   <p>Various propositions are being submitted every day by Poles to the Polish Central Committee. In a letter to the Committee, Anthony Buszkiewiez of Chicago offers to erect a model American steam laundry in the Polish-American Pavilion, which would be a practical novelty. A Polish confectioner in Chicago wants to make candies on the American style and sell them in the pavilion. Mr. J. R., an artist, suggests that instead of sending displays of the actual uniforms of the various military societies to the exposition, a set of yard-square portraits of the various types of Polish-American soldiers in uniform be sent. Mr. R. is willing to paint these pictures for a nominal sum.</p>
   <p>The Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance is taking a keen <pb facs="5423968_11_0722.jpg" n="3"/>interest in the Lwow Exposition. At the last meeting of the Alliance a special committee was appointed for the purpose of furthering participation in the Exposition. The Committee is composed of the following members Mr. S. F. Adalia Satalecki, Mr. John F. Smulski, Mr. A. Greenwald and Mr. Anthony Mallek.</p>
   <p>The Polish photographers, Niklas and Pietrewski, who are making the Chicago photographs to be sent to the Lwow Exposition, are energetically performing their task despite the bad weather. They have already photographed the home of the Sisters of Nazareth on West Division Street, the interior and the furnishings of the Sisters' Chapel, groups of school girls, etc., as well as the school children attending Holy Trinity Parish School. All of the photographs are very clear. In a few days they expect to take photographs in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish and in St. Michael Archangel Parish (in South Chicago), and also photographs of the Polish Orphanage. Photographs of other Chicago and out-of-town parishes will follow in order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
