<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-29">Mar. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Protest of the Poles against the American Extradition Treaty with Russia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0735</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0735.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-29">Mar. 29, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST OF THE POLES AGAINST THE AMERICAN EXTRADITION TREATY WITH RUSSIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The protest against the American-Russian extradition treaty, decided upon at the mass meeting of Chicago Poles on March 19, has already brought results--important results. We are convinced of this by the telegram from Washington which appeared in yesterday's Dziennik [Chicagoski]. This telegram stated that final ratification of the treaty has been postponed because of protests coming from the Poles. It adds that very likely the treaty will not be ratified. The telegram was published in newspapers all over the United States.</p>
   <p>We can say with pride that our voices carried some weight with an honest government. Our cry has been taken under consideration. President Cleveland told Mr. Peter Kiolbassa, who represented the Poles, that he <pb facs="5423968_11_0736.jpg" n="2"/>recognized and would defend the rights of Polish-American citizens. We have succeeded in moving American public opinion--which has voiced itself for freedom--against persecutors. Whatever course the matter follows from this point, we can safely say that the battle is already won for us.</p>
   <p>Naturally, since the proposed treaty was diplomatically a secret one, it is difficult to know its details. It is certain, however, that we have awakened the vigilance of the government and of public opinion. Even if the treaty should be concluded, it will be rewritten in such a form that the Russian government will be unable to use it as an instrument with which to destroy the liberty of those who have come to America to escape oppression. Should the treaty in such a form be objectionable to Russia, we can be sure that the matter will be dropped altogether by the American government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0737.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The credit for the success of this enterprise must be given to the energy and solidarity with which the Poles acted. The meeting, called together rather hurriedly, was attended by members of both factions, who, instead of quarreling as is usual with us, worked side by side for the common good. The committee assigned to formulating the protest did its part, proof of which we have in the telegram dispatched the day after the meeting and the extensive memorial prepared on the same day. The Patriotic Organization very nobly came forward to cover all expenses incurred by the protest. Even the newspapers, which ordinarily condemn every move that is not originated by their "clique," have been silent, or have even lent their support. In a word, everything proceeded with perfect harmony. Thus, every one deserves acknowledgment. Most of all, however, acknowledgment is due to Father Vincent Barzynski, author of the movement, and Mr. Peter Kiolbassa, our delegate to Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0738.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Kiolbassa has already returned to Chicago. According to newspaper accounts and his own report, Mr. Kiolbassa lost no time in carrying out his mission. At the request of the committee, he readily dropped his own affairs, which, of course, are very urgent on the eve of elections, and left for Washington. All the American newspapers carried accounts of Mr. Kiolbassa's activities in the Capitol, but the best proof of his conscientiousness lies in the results he has produced. We must add, however, that Mr. Kiolbassa's conversation with President Cleverland was longer and more extensive than the American newspapers reported. Among other things, in answering the President's questions, Mr. Kiolbassa said that he has complete faith in the present administration. He added, however, that he never has had nor can ever have faith in the treacherous government of Russia, which has never hesitated to break a treaty. We think that these words, boldly spoken to the highest executive of the land, are worthy of mention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
