<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-05">Oct. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Plan for New Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (This article appeared in the Chicago News Record relative to Dr. Dunikowski's mission.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0770</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0770.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-05">Oct. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PLAN FOR NEW POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (This article appeared in the Chicago News Record relative to Dr. Dunikowski's mission.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Monday (October 3) issue of the Chicago News Record an article, entitled "Plan for New Poland," appeared which in every respect should interest all Poles. This article, besides giving a good picture of Dr. E. H. Dunikowski's visit to America, also touches upon the future of Polish politics in Europe and its relations to American Poles.</p>
   <p>The Chicago News Record is of the opinion that, besides Dr. Dunikowski's educational and cultural mission, there is also a hidden political mission. This secret errand, according to the paper, is closely connected with the political affairs in Europe. Its contentions are based on the assertions of a certain <pb facs="5423968_11_0771.jpg" n="2"/>"prominent Pole of Chicago's West Side," who, with farfetched fantasy, stated that the rebuilding of Poland is near, that Austria and Prussia will gladly return their Polish holdings to found a new Poland, which will be in sharp opposition to Russia, etc., etc.</p>
   <p>No matter how pleasant it is to read about such possibilities and to imagine that some day a situation will arise in European political affairs that will make this supposition a reality, conditions today make it impossible. At present, however, for the sake of truth and sobriety, it must be said that the above fantastic assertions are harmful, for they may lead us away from the closer and more easily attainable aims which Dr. Dunikowski presented to us. It is a very good thing that the author of this "fantasia," who is quoted as a "prominent Pole," did not permit his name to be used, for he would have been made a laughing stock among his own people. Despite his ardor for Poland, this would harm his status.</p>
   <p>To verify the "fantasia" of this "prominent Pole," the reporter of the Chicago <pb facs="5423968_11_0772.jpg" n="3"/>News Record went to other competent individuals to get their opinions relative to this matter. Verily, he received something different.</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa, city treasurer, gave a true picture of Dr. Dunikowski's visit to America. This errand was primarily for educational and cultural purposes. According to Mr. Kiolbassa, the primary aim of this visit was to establish moral and perhaps material unity between the European and American Pole, without the combined investment of Polish capital from Europe with Polish-American enterprises Mr. Kiolbassa said in an interview with many reporters: "The Professor told me that he feels fortunate and privileged to see among the Polish-Americans the heartfelt attachment to the Fatherland. Dr. Dunikowski contends that the Poles in America could do as much for Poland in the present circumstances as did the Irish for Ireland. I am of the same opinion."</p>
   <p>City Treasurer Kiolbassa was not in agreement with the opinion of the "prominent Pole" that the character of Dr. Dunikowski's visit is also political. This was <pb facs="5423968_11_0773.jpg" n="4"/>also true of the Bohemian attorney, A. Kraus, who recently returned from Europe, when he was questioned by the same reporter. Mr. Kraus told the reporter that the present political situation in Europe does not suggest any immediate rebuilding of Poland.</p>
   <p>In closing, from our point of view, the article "Plan for New Poland" in the News Record presents both sides of the issue. This paper acknowledges the fact that a general protest supported by Mr. Kiolbassa against the fantasy of the "prominent Pole" would be beneficial, for his assertions can only cause harm to the visit of the Polish delegate. In every respect we feel that recognition is due to this Chicago paper for supporting our cause, for the full sympathy it expressed for Poland, and for giving both sides of the purpose of the visit in its article, "Plan For New Poland." Such articles printed from time to time for general reading will always be beneficial to us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
