<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Necessity for Holding a Council (Sejm)</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NECESSITY FOR HOLDING A COUNCIL (SEJM)</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two weeks ago the [Polish] National Department notified the Polish communities in the United States that among the Polish-American organizations there had arisen a plan to call a general council in order that, with the participation of the largest possible Polish representation, all of the more important Polish questions of the day could be discussed. Just when this council will be called, where and in what form, will depend upon agreement between the organizations. In the same way, a program has not been developed, although certain basic points have been touched upon. Moreover, there has been no formulation of basic rules which would give everyone participating in such a council equal rights, and insure the largest possible representation.</p>
   <p>Up to this time only the plan exists which, perhaps, is just beginning to take shape in one or two instances. It will be a long time before it can crystallize <pb facs="5423968_11_0327.jpg" n="2"/>into its proper form. In the meantime, some people are growing impatient, while others are expressing themselves on the plan with more or less approval.</p>
   <p>The Polish press, in general, has already taken up the plan for a council. The predominating journalistic opinion is that such a council is a necessity, except that one paper would like to see it "red" (socialistic), another papist, a third nationalistic--in short, partisanship is rampant, for it sees a perfect field [for spreading its propaganda] in the calling of such a council.</p>
   <p>As to us, we have tried not to express any opinion in this matter, preferring to give others a chance to speak first. And today we withhold our remarks on all of the commitments in this matter for another time. For ourselves, we merely say that we consider such a council not only necessary but imperative. The Polish army questions, the [Polish] National Tax, the May contributions, and dozens of other lesser tasks preoccupy the sincere, patriotic Polish element here. It is only right that this element, through its representatives, <pb facs="5423968_11_0328.jpg" n="3"/>should decide on many questions on which for certain reasons the National Department itself cannot decide. It is also necessary that this element, through its special delegates, express itself on the work of the National Department up to the present, and its work in the future, and at the same time, be informed of many things of which it knows nothing today. Not everything appears in the papers, and in many cases, matters are deliberately withheld from the press. Some of the strongest rumors are circulating among the people, sometimes monstrous suspicions; the public in general may only conjecture, often arriving at most contradictory conclusions.</p>
   <p>It is high time, then, to remove the difficulties which, no matter in what form they appear, only harm the Polish cause. It is time to pick up the bushel basket under which many an act is hiding which needs as much air as possible, the greatest possible publicity, the widest possible scope. Only a council can do this, and for this reason we regard the council as imperative.</p>
   <p>But in addition to our own Polish questions, there are other matters, general <pb facs="5423968_11_0329.jpg" n="4"/>Slavic matters in which we Poles, especially here in America, ought to be the first to voice our opinions. After all, it is in America today that the strongest watchwords, carrying rebirth to crumbling Europe, originate. After all, it is on America today that all eyes are turned, both in a general sense, that is, concerning all nations and peoples, and in a particular sense, as in the case of our own nation.</p>
   <p>This is not enough. The eyes of the whole Slavic race in Europe are now upon the Slavs in America. And certainly, of the Slavs in America, we Poles are the most powerful group in influence, in significance, and in numbers. Our voice then, if it is a collective voice, the voice of a Polish council, for example, will re-echo in all of the Slavic countries of Europe.</p>
   <p>In all of the Slavic nations, especially in those which border upon each other, the idea of a Slavic Federation has been growing for a great many years, and at present it shows signs of ripening. Under the strict discipline imposed by <pb facs="5423968_11_0330.jpg" n="5"/>the war and the Teutonic mailed fist, this idea has continued--though timidly--to live in the hearts and minds of the Slavic leaders and representatives of the most politically enlightened classes. Let then the expression of a Polish council fan this spark into a flame that will envelop all of the Slavic lands and peoples. Let us contribute to the winning of this war by organizing all of the Slavic nations into one block against the Teutonic onslaught, awakening thereby the faith of all of the Slavs in us and assuring mutual aid. Let us make a great gesture at least once, let us show our good intentions, let us show our political insight at least, although it is impossible to make that federation a reality in the immediate future. Let us at least give it a beginning; with one sincere and just appeal let us destroy the "Chinese Wall" that separates the Poles, Czechs, Ruthenians, and others. Let us remove the first obstacle--mutual indifference--and action will come later of itself. And although we may have to wait a long time, this federalization will take place, for a great and noble idea can never die; sooner or later it assumes its proper shape as a reality.</p>
   <p>For these reasons, we are for the calling of a council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
