<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-12">Aug. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting in Brighton Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-12">Aug. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING IN BRIGHTON PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish people of Brighton Park showed yesterday that no one can dispose them against the Polish Army, not even the local pastor who, prohibited by federal authorities from working publicly against the Polish Army, tried to do so privately. Going from house to house, he talked against the Army, urging that the [Polish] national tax collectors be driven from the door, and so on.</p>
   <p>The mass meeting, arranged yesterday in front of the church in Brighton Park by S. Krzywonos, Polish Army organizer, was not the first to be arranged there; at every one of the mass meetings held, the Polish people of this community not only stopped, on leaving church, to hear what was being said about the Polish Army, but in addition contributed generously to the fund for the Army.</p>
   <p>Whoever did not attend yesterday's meeting will not believe what happened there. Although no collection was taken up, the people gave dollar, two-dollar, and <pb facs="5423968_11_0291.jpg" n="2"/>even five-dollar bills as contributions to the Polish Army's fund. Without any mention of a collection, these people realized their duty, and that our boys need care, and gave their hard-earned money so that, by mutual effort and mutual sacrifice, we can again stand as a free and independent nation. Can there be found a person who could tear from the hearts of these Polish people this desire to restore our beloved homeland? Certainly not! These people will not allow themselves to be "led by the noses" by a priest who cannot see beyond his own personal interests, and who, just so long as he himself is comfortable, cares nothing about Poland or the Polish Army, or anything else, for that matter. His selfishness reaches such a degree that he does not even care for the Polish clergy who, with but very few exceptions, favor the Polish Army, and spare neither effort nor money for the restoration of Poland.</p>
   <p>Fortunately the people see this, and understand that their pastor is a great opponent of the Polish Army and of the Polish cause in general; for what is Poland or the Polish Army to him as long as he has enough money? As a matter of fact, what does he care about those honest Polish people who support him <pb facs="5423968_11_0292.jpg" n="3"/>with their hard-earned money? Not only does he not care for these people--he would willingly give them back to German slavery.</p>
   <p>In his address, Polish Army organizer S. Krzywonos justly said that the Kaiser in Berlin is waiting for this priest, and that it is time to send him there, for there is no place for him here amongst good patriots. He said further that, after the first mass meeting held in Brighton Park, this priest came to Recruiting Center II and begged that his "business" be not spoiled, and said that he would not again speak against the Polish Army. The priest further explained that the Federal authorities had warned him to say nothing more against that Army. The speaker also raised the fact that this same priest had proclaimed that if he (Krzywonos) should appear once more in Brighton Park, he would have him arrested. After mentioning this, Krzywonos cried, "Here I am, have me arrested, worthy pastor, and then we shall see who will be the first to find himself behind bars!"</p>
   <p>In his whole address, Krzywonos did not spare words of contempt for the pastor, <pb facs="5423968_11_0293.jpg" n="4"/>who deserved it all because of his dirty work against a cause so sacred to all Poles as the Polish Army, which is already shedding its blood for our freedom. Whoever dares work against these brave boys who volunteered to fight for "your freedom and ours" is a traitor; he is unworthy of being called a Pole, and ought to look for company suited to himself amongst the friends of the Kaiser.</p>
   <p>Before Krzywonos had finished his address, there was $119.27 in his cap--exactly one hundred nineteen dollars and twenty-seven cents--as a contribution to the Polish Army. Thus the Polish people of Brighton Park, by making so generous a contribution, showed what they think of the work of their pastor, for whom they did not spare jeers during Organizer Krzywonos's address.</p>
   <p>The road to freedom has been shown to the Polish people today, and they will travel this road to a free and independent Poland; no individual can stop them, even if he "loves" Poland as much as the Kaiser himself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
