<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-20">Mar. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Poles of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-20">Mar. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE POLES OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Countrymen!</p>
   <p>The month of May is approaching, and with it, our great national holiday, the Third of May. This year, the year of the rebirth, the resurrection from ashes of our homeland, Poland, in the year of the formation of a great, autonomous Polish Army which will fight for the freedom and equality of nations at the Allies' side, we ought to observe this month with especially great deeds for our Poland.</p>
   <p>With the consent of the [Polish] National Committee of America and the [Polish] National Committee in Paris, a special committee of three, consisting of the wife of our tireless leader of the Polish nation, Mrs. Helen Paderewski, John F. Smulski, and Thaddeus Wronski.</p>
   <p>This committee's task is to conduct a campaign under the motto: "American Poles for Poland on the Third of May." The purpose of the campaign is to <pb facs="5423968_11_0358.jpg" n="2"/>raise a million-dollar fund for safeguarding the Polish soldiers, to equip a Polish hospital for them, and for various other national needs related to the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>With intentions of conducting this campaign throughout the United States, the executive committee has divided the country into circuits. Every circuit, in proportion to its number of Polish communities, will receive so-called "Golden Lists", into which it will place, throughout the month of May, the signatures of all contributors who give two dollars or more to the abovementioned fund. After the war, these "Golden Lists", signed by the local pastor and Citizens' Committee, will be turned over to our official representative, the great master, Ignace Paderewski, as proof of the patriotism and generosity of American Polonia.</p>
   <p>Everyone who contributes at least two dollars will receive as a souvenir, a beautiful picture painted by the famous Polish artist, Ladislaus Benda, showing the Holy Virgin of Czestochowa uniting under her cloak all of our Polish provinces, and blessing the Polish Army as it goes to battle against <pb facs="5423968_11_0359.jpg" n="3"/>the Germans. The name of the contributor who receives the souvenir will be written at the bottom of each picture, and a receipt for the money will be given, signed by the Citizens' Committee. In addition to the picture, each contributor will receive a button inscribed with the motto: "American Poles for Poland on the Third of May."</p>
   <p>The successful conduct of this patriotic campaign in May will demand great preparation of ground and much agitation, and it cannot succeed without the aid of all Polish elements in America.</p>
   <p>With the purpose, then, of preparing the ground for this activity, a few of our special messengers are leaving in the course of the next few days for a tour of [the Polish communities in] America. Their task will be to explain the whole campaign under the motto: "American Poles for Poland", and the aims and plans of our executive committee. A detailed itinerary of these agitators, showing when and where each one will arrive, will be published in the Polish papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0360.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In addition to this, a special weekly, entitled "Third of May", will appear on March 19; it will keep American Polonia informed on the plans and the progress being made in this matter.</p>
   <p>The address of the Executive Committee for the "American Poles for Poland Compaign" is: 12-14 West 37th Street, New York City. The headquarters will supply any desired information promptly and accurately, and the Polish press of America, useful as always on occasions such as this, will undoubtedly agree to publish our communications, so that they will appear in the columns of all our Polish daily and weekly newspapers.</p>
   <p>To action then, countrymen! Let us show that we understand the task and duties of every good Pole and that we can, by united action, raise a fund this May amounting not to one, but two million dollars for our Polish Army and the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>Let us make the month of May of this year a real Polish, patriotic month.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee: Helen Paderewski, John F. Smulski, Thaddeus Wronski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
