<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-25">Apr. 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Moral Lesson for the Poles</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-25">Apr. 25, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A MORAL LESSON FOR THE POLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Late proposals in the United States Congress to restrict immigration to the United States, and the attacks on our nationality in connection with it--even though they are unjust and unfounded--should serve us Poles as a powerful lesson.</p>
   <p>They should convince our brethren that no country desires new arrivals that are illiterate, uncivilized, immoral, or criminals.</p>
   <p>This should urge us to seek greater enlightment and a greater understanding of our moral obligations.</p>
   <p>We can see now with our own eyes that an ignorant person not only suffers because of his ignorance all his life, but is also unwillingly accepted among educated strangers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0150.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So let us educate ourselves and, above all, our children! Let us study, read, and improve ourselves! And let us warn our brethren in the old country, who desire to come here, to America, that there is no room here for ignorant and stubborn fools. Let them know this, and before they leave to come here, advise them to learn some writing and reading.</p>
   <p>There is still another lesson we should derive from this whole matter.</p>
   <p>Here in America, we are not the worst element in point of transgressors of the law or even in the matter of morality. Not at all! Statistics prove this plainly Our people, on the contrary, are distinguished by many points which place them on a higher level than peoples of other nationality, and are a very desirable material for citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>Our only fault is that we are a trifle too noisy.</p>
   <p>This is apparent to everybody. It attracts immediate attention from other peoples <pb facs="5423968_11_0151.jpg" n="3"/>and gives us a bad reputation. Drunkenness, quarrels, fights, and disorderliness at social affairs, disturbances in parishes and societies--those are the mortal sins which have made many a good-wishing American think that we are a bad, dishonest, and unnecessary element here in America.</p>
   <p>Others commit many crimes in secrecy, we commit small transgressions with a great deal of noise.... And thus they consider us a hundred times worse than the others.</p>
   <p>One way or the other, it is high time to put an end to this state of affairs.</p>
   <p>Let us heartily and sincerely renounce drunkenness, fights, quarrels, disorderly conduct, and other similar evils, and we will benefit thereby.</p>
   <p>May our social affairs be happy but respectable; may our Polish boys desist from reaching for knives at the least opportunity and our women and girls stop attending forbidden dances; may our manners become gentler--and then the Americans will judge us more favorably.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0152.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We will gain the most thereby.</p>
   <p>We will gain a higher degree of civilization and morality; we will become better citizens; and, above all, we will close the mouths of those who would like to consider us wild barbarians, something like the Chinese or cannibals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
