<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-13">June 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Prominent Priest-Patriot Feted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-13">June 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PROMINENT PRIEST-PATRIOT FETED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A modest but extremely high-spirited reception was held yesterday at the St. Stanislaus Kostka Auditorium by a group of friends in honor of the well-known and universally respected Reverend Rector W. Zapala, on occasion of the twentieth anniversary of his ordination as a priest.</p>
   <p>At the hall we noticed representatives and delegates from various elements of Polonia. No one was missing, except perhaps those whose duties called them elsewhere, or those who could not come because of work or of great distance. It would be difficult to name everyone, and so we shall not name anyone; thus no one will be slighted.</p>
   <p>A very large group of friends of Rector Zapala was seated at the long tables, with himself in the place of honor, always merry and hearty, drawing everyone to himself, so that every one can say of him, "He is ours, he is the favorite and the representative of all of us."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0921.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the benediction, and after an extremely modest supper, consisting merely of "Aesop's tongues" and white coffee, had been consumed, F. Barc, editor of The Nation and secretary of the committee of citizens that had arranged the reception, arose to explain the purpose of the gathering and describe, in heartfelt words, the services of the celebrant, calling upon S. Adamkiewicz, president of the committee, to act as toastmaster. Then flowed a series of sincere addresses by various persons, which formed, more or less, a colorful mosaic of their feelings toward the well-beloved celebrant, a sort of wreath of sweet-scented flowers bestowed upon him who, by his wholehearted efforts and sacrifice for the Polish cause, had justly earned them.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Stanislaus Sobieniowski, pastor of St. Mary's church of Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania, who had come to Chicago especially for this occasion, spoke sincerely and from the heart, expressing best wishes in behalf of the Polish Union, which has its headquarters in Wilkes Barre. Peter Rostenkowski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, presented Reverend Zapala with <pb facs="5423968_11_0922.jpg" n="3"/>the receipt for a seven-passenger automobile of considerable value, that had been purchased for him from a voluntary collection taken up among his friends.</p>
   <p>The Polish leader, John F. Smulski, a close friend of the celebrant, spoke ardently and patriotically as usual. He perhaps, knows Zapala best from his efforts in behalf of the Polish cause, which makes one see, in the celebrant, one of those Poles upon whom the eyes, not only of American Polonia, but of all Poland, are turned today.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Francis Gordon, pastor of St. Mary of the Angels Church, and the one most intimately acquainted with the work of the rector, spoke, as did Stanislaus Szwajkart, editor-in-chief of Dziennik Chicagoski, Reverend Pyterek, pastor of St. Helen's Church, and J. Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy. Lack of time prevented the calling of other speakers, who would undoubtedly have uttered further words of sincere enthusiasm and encouragement <pb facs="5423968_11_0923.jpg" n="4"/>to the celebrant in his happy work.</p>
   <p>Finally, Reverend Zapala himself spoke, thanking the gathering in words choked by emotion for the expressions of good will and the wonderful gift that had been bestowed upon him. In his address, he spoke of the influences that directed him in his spiritual work years ago, and in his nationalistic work today, and having before him always as examples, such men of his order as Kajsiewicz, Semenenko, Kalinka, and Pawlicki, he solemnly vowed not to deviate from his chosen path and to continue, so long as his strength lasts, to work for the cause that is dear to us all. He praised the services of the Polish press which, through its great influence, imbues in the people the convictions that we all believe in today, and called for greater effort, which is the sweeter because of the results which we can already see.</p>
   <p>The ardent and enthusiastic address of the celebrant was applauded frequently and his strong and commanding words touched the souls of everyone, awakening <pb facs="5423968_11_0924.jpg" n="5"/>wonder and admiration.</p>
   <p>During the course of the program, the Filaret Choir, under the direction of Professor B. Rybowiak, appeared several times, making still more pleasant, with the beautiful tones of its singing, the already pleasant evening. In addition to the Filaret Choir, a quartet, consisting of the Barwig and Kondziorski brothers of St. Stanislaus Parish, sang.</p>
   <p>During the intermission, Secretary Barc read telegrams from many individuals, among which were sincere good wishes from Paderewski, Dr. F. F. Fronczak of Buffalo, the Polish Union, of Wilkes Barre, and others.</p>
   <p>It is unfortunate that we must cut short the description of the pleasant time we spent last evening. Truly, one never forgets such moments. They serve to spur one on, for it can be seen that, today, the public recognizes the efforts of men while they still live, instead of later placing wreaths upon their monuments. It can be seen that those are spurred on who "did fall amid <pb facs="5423968_11_0925.jpg" n="6"/>disappointments," but went forward and succeeded. Such a man is our celebrant, and the honor paid him yesterday is ample reward for the labor, difficulties, and disappointments of his life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
