<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Dziennik Zwiazkowy's Future</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DZIENNIK ZWIAZKOWY'S FUTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At first glance, the future of Dziennik Zwiazkowy seems to depend upon an ever-increasing membership [in the Alliance], as a result of which the newspaper's influence will grow and increase. In reality, it depends also upon an adequate and properly equipped editorial staff. As to this second point, so powerful a publisher as the Polish National Alliance will not begrudge the necessary funds, nor will it miss any opportunity, as it never has in the past, to obtain the foremost talent for its newspaper. It can readily be seen that this has been practiced during the first ten years of Dziennik Zwiazkowy's existence, for the paper can boast of a whole constellation of literary stars who were fired with a desire to serve Dziennik Zwiazkowy and Poland.</p>
   <p>Since conditions are changing, and should they change to such a degree as to be most profitable for Poland, the conditions under which Dziennik Zwiazkowy will operate will also be changed completely. The World War <pb facs="5423968_11_0459.jpg" n="2"/>and American participation therein has already awakened a feeling of mutual friendship between various [national] groups in this country, and has hastened considerably the formation of a homogeneous American nation; this greatly affects our Polish "fourth partition." If, however, our greatest hopes are realized and an independent Poland arises in Europe, then our tendency to lose the characteristics peculiar to Poles will be still greater. It might even be feared that the process of Americanization of the Polish element here would be quite swift, if it was not for the fact that national groups having independent homelands can look to those governments for support, and thus strengthen their resistance [against denationalization].</p>
   <p>After an independent Poland has arisen in Europe, the Polish element in America will represent a reserve force necessary to Poland, and will have a tendency to move spiritually closer to it in order to become better acquainted with new trends in every field of creative endeavor. This frantic struggle for a mere livelihood will cease, and we will no longer spend our <pb facs="5423968_11_0460.jpg" n="3"/>energy in trying to find our places on the beaten path. It will drive deeper, however, the desire to achieve the highest degree of progress, for it is only in this measure that the Poles of America can give effective aid in the development of Poland. The progress that we will work for here, retaining always our faith and national spirit, will not uphold itself on points of faith and nationality alone. Rather will it have to adapt itself to the tactics of the Irish, the Germans, and the Jews, who seem to be submerging themselves in the sea of Americanism, and who are accepting all of the characteristics of American society foreign to them, in order to become equal to that society, and thereby share in its progress and in the benefits derived therefrom.</p>
   <p>Even so strong an organization as the Polish National Alliance will have to take this into consideration, and will have to raise itself to the standards of Irish alliances, of which every [Irish-] American considers it an honor and a privilege to be a member. In this task, Dziennik Zwiazkowy will have a new and very noble duty. In order to fulfill it, we must accept the <pb facs="5423968_11_0461.jpg" n="4"/>principles of the new progress to such an extent that those principles will serve as a core, beside which will burn the undying flame of nationalism; so deeply imbedded in the hearts--as is said of the Irish and the Jews--as to be undiscernible on the surface but impossible to uproot.</p>
   <p>With our present system of continuous manifestation of the Polish spirit, supported by the constant struggle for the freedom of our motherland, retaining still its spiritual bond with the homeland, it seems impossible that the Polish element here will ever be assimilated completely. Nations can thus be assimilated and yet retain the spiritual union with the homeland only through the deepest patriotism, or after they have reached the highest degree of their own national culture.</p>
   <p>Under these conditions, the forces that will aid Dziennik Zwiazkowy in its task will undoubtedly draw from both sources; just as at the close of the first ten-year period of pioneering work we can now see a perfect framework <pb facs="5423968_11_0462.jpg" n="5"/>of nationalistic endeavor in the collective effect of those very noble efforts; so in the next period, a new era will open, under the leadership of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, in which our national progress will blend into one great wave, so the speak, with modern currents and trends, but drawing always upon Poland as its source of life.</p>
   <p>We have passed through a period of quarrels in religious matters, our domestic struggles are dying out, while party relations have taken a more neighborly direction; the whole mass of personal differences is finally disappearing from view, and in the splendor of a Poland reborn great problems in the field of universal progress will enter into the lives of Polish-Americans, and especially into the sphere of activity of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Over all of this hovers the White Eagle on its field of amaranth. Let it mark the successful development of Dziennik Zwiazkowy.</p>
   <p>J. K. Orlowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
