<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-30">Mar. 30, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Modrzejewski's Daughter in Danger</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0989</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0989.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-30">Mar. 30, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">MODRZEJEWSKI'S DAUGHTER IN DANGER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several times lately attempts have been made to kidnap the three-year-old daughter of Mr. &amp; Mrs. Ralph Modrzejewski, and detectives are tracing these criminals.</p>
   <p>Mr. Modrzejewski, is as everybody knows, the son of the famous Polish actress, Helen Modrzejewski: he is a civil engineer and has an office in the Monadnock Block. He lives with his family at 1780 Wrightwood Avenue.</p>
   <p>On March 9, Mr. Modrzejewski found an unstamped post card in his mail box addressed to his wife. The fact that the card did not bear a stamp showed that it was not delivered by the postman, but must have been dropped in the box by some one else. The card, written in poor English, demanded that Mrs. Modrzejewski leave the country within three months, otherwise <pb facs="5423968_11_0990.jpg" n="2"/>the children and their nurse would die suddenly.</p>
   <p>On March 13, the nurse, Jessie, was standing in front of a drugstore at the corner of Clark Street and Wrightwood Avenue with the daughter Marylla, when an unknown man approached her, and, after asking her if she was the nurse at the Modrzejewski home, snatched the little girl from her hands and began to run. Shouting, Jessie ran after him; then this stranger released the child and ran into the basement of a near-by building and escaped through a rear exit.</p>
   <p>That same day another postal card was found in the mail box, addressed to the nurse, on which she was notified that she and the child would be blinded if the Modrzejewski family did not leave Chicago.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Modrzejewski employed a detective to guard his home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0991.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On March 21, during the absence of the detective for a few minutes, again somebody left a postal card bearing more threats. On Monday evening, March 23, Jessie was hanging the wash in the yard when she heard a knocking at the gate door. When she opened the door somebody threw carbolic acid on her, severely burning her face.</p>
   <p>Since then this strange person has not appeared. Jessie's face may be disfigured for life. She described the man as being about thirty years of age, of medium height, with blue eyes, a large nose, and a blond mustache. He was dressed well, even elegantly.</p>
   <p>The Modrzejewski family moved into this home in May of last year; previously they had resided at 1117 North Clark Street, where they were robbed twice by thieves. Their dog was poisoned there also.</p>
   <p>Who is persecuting them and why? Mr. Modrzejewski cannot imagine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
