<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-10">Aug. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[The Emigration Review on Polish Emigration to America]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_11_0187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-10">Aug. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[THE EMIGRATION REVIEW ON POLISH EMIGRATION TO AMERICA]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have, at hand, the first two issues of the Emigration Review, published in Lwow since last July. Mention of the articles therein was made the other day; today we attempt to convey the contents of them.</p>
   <p>It is natural, of course, that our attention should be focused on those items pertaining to Polish emigration to the United States. There are a number of them and we must admit that all are interesting.</p>
   <p>The most interesting of all, is the one entitled, "Concerning the Polish Element in the United States of America." Despite his efforts, the author is somewhat prejudiced; he could not be otherwise since there is no source from which authentic information may be obtained. Because some of the <pb facs="5423968_11_0188.jpg" n="2"/>conclusions are based on incomplete information, it is therefore the duty of every newspaper in America to rectify these details, if only from an individual standpoint. The editors of the Review are not to be reproached for their faults since they have no evidence to the contrary of their conclusions; for this reason, all rectifications should be forwarded to the Emigration Review, and thereby present to outsiders as honest and unbiased estimates of our conditions in America.</p>
   <p>It is difficult, if not impossible, for a person who has not spent some time here among us to form a genuine opinion on our state of affairs. Apart from a keen sense of observation, a wholly natural desire to make comparisons of our conditions of life and those of Europeans, as well as to make computations of the terms in which the life of the emigrants progresses, it is imperative to restrain bias and beliefs based on different ways of life if we wish to orientate ourselves properly in the conditions here, and judge our emigration fairly. The author would perhaps change his point of view, if he could read more of our newspapers, thereby becoming more familiar with the degree of our development and progress.</p>
   <p>In the first part of the article, the author outlines a general history of <pb facs="5423968_11_0189.jpg" n="3"/>the emigration to the United States. He says justly that at the beginning there was a lack of intellectuals among the emigrants--that the emigrating throngs were essentially peasants and laborers. According to him, the priests were the first organizers among these people after they arrived in America; they were the propagators of culture and the founders of parishes, as well as of associations.</p>
   <p>In spite of a desire to be fair and the information at hand, he later omits an important point when he says, "Only recently, there has been some culture appearing among the masses of manual laborers, and more of the intellectuals are coming from Europe." He further states that "there was disagreement among the spiritual and secular intelligentsia," that the people "adhered and still adhere to the cassock of the clergy in excessive measure; alas, they have a rooted distrust of the gentry and the "Danowie frakowcy' [those who spread dissension], and therefore of the elite."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_11_0190.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If the author were well aware of the types in the secular intelligentsia arriving here after the clerical intelligentsia had installed itself here, so to speak, he would not have made such a statement. In order to realize that this distrust on the part of the masses for the elite was inevitable--even a person who is not particularly interested but who has an ordinary sense of reasoning must come to this conclusion--we must take into consideration just what is meant in the old country by the word "elite". For many years--and even now, with but few exceptions--they could not leave Europe, because our true intelligentsia class consists of people who, having chosen a certain profession and having completed their academic studies in preparation for it, have in spite of a lack of opportunities privately attained their goal. They have, thereby, a right to consider themselves members of the intelligentsia. These include the clergy, doctors of medicine, teachers in higher educational institutions, and men of letters.</p>
   <p>In the early years, besides, the clergy and the doctors and the others had no reason to come to America, because they would have been unable to give full scope to their activities, and would have certainly perished in misery <pb facs="5423968_11_0191.jpg" n="5"/>or else, have taken any manual labor job at which the ordinary common laborer could have excelled. Even priests and doctors emigrated in small numbers out of fear of the "wilderness"; if they did so, they usually settled in the more densely populated areas in order to accumulate wealth.</p>
   <p>Then another part of the so-called intelligentsia began to arrive in America. At first, these were adventurers, somewhat polished in a worldly way, with a gift of speech and the ability to write; then, there were those who, having completed about two Gymnasium classes and suffering from maladjustment, sustained themselves by any means available with their unfinished schooling, and upon landing here, strove to bluff their way impressively. Also, there were artisans, some commercial clerks, and others who had had a "lick" of schooling and pretended to be highly educated. Later on came postal officers, telegraph operators, and even army officers.</p>
   <p>Finally, the true academicians began to come to America, forced to leave <pb facs="5423968_11_0192.jpg" n="6"/>Europe for some unknown reasons. These comprise the genuine intelligentsia. They were the first to begin the struggle between the spiritual and secular intelligentsia. In time we shall see the results of this dissension now that the real secular intelligentsia is appearing here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
