<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Task of the Educational Committee of the Workmen's Circle?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE TASK OF THE EDUCATIONAL COMMITTEE OF THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the task of the educational committee of the Workmen's Circle? Is it only to conduct children's classes, or is it obliged to do general educational work within the branches and for the membership at large? This question was discussed at a meeting of the educational committee, and the answer given was that the children's schools are only a part of the educational program; and that the Workmen's Circle must become interested in the education of their members, within, and outside of, the branches, in order to accomplish its task as a worker's organization.</p>
   <p>The cause of this discussion was the fact that the educational committee for the past two years or more, did not participate in any general educational work, with the exception of children's classes, because it was occupied with the financial problems of supporting the schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1363.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From a financial standpoint, the educational committee is, at present, in no position to do anything. The financial resources of the children's schools are in a horrible condition due to the fact that many branches are unable to pay their taxes. The problems connected with the schools, and the problem of paying the overdue salaries to the teachers and other employees tie the hands of the educational committee to such an extent that there remains no energy to indulge in the work of carrying on wider educational activities.</p>
   <p>In connection with the new general educational activities, Mr. Louis Schalffer of Branch 226 introduced a plan, whereby the work of the educational committee can be reorganized in such a manner that general educational work can begin within, and outside of, the branches. He proposed that the work of the educational committee be divided into two parts: a committee of ten be appointed to act as the school committee, and a committee of five to carry on general educational work.</p>
   <p>The plan was accepted, and the educational committee was divided into two parts: a committee of ten for the schools, and a committee of five for general educational work. The latter committee organized a program which it will attempt to <pb facs="5423972_5_1364.jpg" n="3"/>carry through in the month of November. The committee hopes that the branches and the active members will support the program in every possible way, so that it may be successfully carried out.</p>
   <p>The members of the Workmen's Circle own a beautiful building--The Labor Lyceum. Until now, no one was interested in developing our activities in the lyceum, and the building did not appear to represent an educational institution. The reason [for this situation] was that the entire energy of the labor lyceum committee was spent in meeting the financial expenses of the building. It seemed as though nothing could be done to further our educational work in our lyceum in order that the building should become a cultural and social center, not only for meetings, but also for various social activities, which would attract the thinking and active members to participate in the educational work of the Workmen's Circle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
