<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-11">June 11, 1906</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0342</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0342.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-11">June 11, 1906</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Crazed One." (Dramatic Review).</p>
   <p>Drama in four acts by Jacob Gorden. Produced by Grand Theater Company at Academy of Music.</p>
   <p>"The Crazed One" is a play whose content and tendencies are even far more actuated than in any of Gorden's works for the stage. "The Crazed One" is not a play wherein action thunders across the stage and thereby detracts appreciativeness from the audience. "The Crazed One" is a play which causes the audience to forget its day to day affairs and completely absorb itself in the production.</p>
   <p>Is the purpose of life to better the well-being of man or is it a needless and tiresome process, void of a goal? The architectural structure of the play has many draw-backs; it is not arranged in accordance with rules of modern drama, and as such would not be accepted as an artistic work worthy <pb facs="5423972_5_0343.jpg" n="2"/>of inclusion in the Jewish theater repertoire. Lacking a good many things it does, however, have its share of Jewish sweetness, witty remarks and humor.</p>
   <p>The following is the story of the play:</p>
   <p>Melech Gerber is a rich business man of Soroko, Russia, who cares not a damn about the rest of the world so long as he gets his in the way of profits. He deals in cow-hides, making leather, selling and swindling whoever crosses his path. He loans money at abortive interest rates, and even causes arrests of fellow Jews on false accusations just so his business be safe from harm. Gerber has two children, Harry and Ben Zion. The first is an ignoramous, unable to even sign his name, but adept at making money and therefore finds favor in the eyes of his father. The second son is educated, but branded as "The Crazed One" for studying science and the philosophy of the Rambom(Mai-monides). He admonishes his father for his dealings and is caused to flee from his father's home and go live with his uncle, Israel Jacob. Ben Zion invents a remarkable machine, but it is destroyed by his enemies whom he has <pb facs="5423972_5_0344.jpg" n="3"/>exposed in his writings. Eventually he commits suicide saying, "This world and its false people are not for me, I have nothing to live for among them."</p>
   <p>Everything considered, the audience enjoyed the play immensely.</p>
   <p>J. Leibner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
