<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-09">June 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jottings
by
H. L. M.
Non-Jews to Aid Jewish Day Fete</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0481</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0481.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-09">June 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JOTTINGS
by
H. L. M.
NON-JEWS TO AID JEWISH DAY FETE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A significant step in furtherance of inter-creed good will was announced today in the formation of the Chicago Committee of Christian Friends cooperating with Jewish groups in the presentation of "A Romance of a People."</p>
   <p>Judge John M. McGoorty, has accepted the chairmanship of the Chicago Committee of Christian Friends cooperating in the event. Among the others, who have accepted appointment to the committee, are Robert Maynard Hutchins, president of the University of Chicago; Walter Dill Scott, president of Northwestern University; Dr. John Timothy Stone;</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0482.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Shailer Matthews; Henry P. Chandler; Charles W. Gilkey, dean of the University of Chicago Chapel; D. F.Kelly; Bishop George Craig Stewart; Dr. William J. Parker; Rev. Walter Mee; William J. Bogan, superintendent of schools; Miss Jane Addams; Bishop Ernest L. Waldorf of the Methodist Episcopal Metropolitan area; Rev. Ernest Fremont Little; Dr. Ella May Horan; and the Rev. Paul Rader.</p>
   <p>In a letter to Meyer W. Weisgal, executive director of the Jewish Day Committee in charge of the mammoth spectacle, Dr. Artman said:</p>
   <p>"We have noted, with much interest, the progress you have been making in the promotion of the pageant 'A Romance of a People.' Several leaders in the Christian groups have wondered how they might aid in the promition of this extraordinary event.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0483.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In the light of this wide-spread interest, our Executive Committee unanimously voted, May 31, to appoint a Chicago Committee of Christian Friends, sponsoring Jewish Day and the pageant, 'A Romance of a People.'</p>
   <p>"Already a significant start has been made, and wide-spread interest among leaders of Christian organizations has been created. Men of all shades of religious opinion have enthusiastically endorsed the work which the committee has proposed to do."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
