<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">February 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Exhibition of Morris Weissenberg's Paintings</title><title level="a" type="sub">by K. Marmer</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">February 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE EXHIBITION OF MORRIS WEISSENBERG'S PAINTINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by K. Marmer</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The odd life of Morris Weissenberg is an example of the remarkable power of the artistic soul, that cannot be suppressed despite misery and want.</p>
   <p>Weissenberg has loved art, since his childhood. He did not have the opportunity, as a child, to be given an artistic education. Remaining an orphan at an early age, no one rendered enough attention to his affectations, caprices, and "crazes." The artistically inclined child had no interest for anything that existed in his father's house. He was attracted to the solitude of nature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0396.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Conditions compelled him to follow the path of his father and brother, to adopt a business career, but he was more poet than merchant and his dreams of strange beauties had more influence upon him than realities, with its accounts and profits.</p>
   <p>His quest for beauty destroyed his interest in physical well being; he turned away from the material life and began to seek the will for which his soul thirsted. He entered an art school and expected great results. He then married and acquired new obligations to fulfill.</p>
   <p>This set him on his travels. He thought he could better himself in America, but he was bitterly disappointed. He found out that here in the "land of unheard of opportunities" there is a smaller place for dreams than in the country, in which he was born.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0397.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Life was very difficult for the dreaming-artist in America. His finest dreams withered and disperesed into dust. Yet, he did not give up his fight. Through pricking thorns and sharp stones, he broke his way and later became acquainted with the Art Institute. Aside from his heavy physical labor in a factory, he also did some janitor work in the Art Institute, and in the Art School in order to be close to the source for which his artistic soul pined.</p>
   <p>In this condition of hard factory and janitor work, he turned, two years ago, to the "Jewish Art Friend," which I, at that time, edited. Upon my request, he brought some of his work......sketches on paper because he had no money for canvas and paint. My first impression was, that here stands an artist of the most intimate opinion; an artist who possesses, within his power, the discovery of the mysterious movement of the soul.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0398.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Unfortunate by The Jewish Art Friend dissolved. Yet, the artist's struggles did not cease, Later, Morris Weissenberg had the opportunity, for a few months, to live for his art and the result was an exhibition of his works.</p>
   <p>Not all his paintings and sketches are the product of a few "honey months." A great part of them were made during a two year period, when the artist still worked physically and used to do his paintings before he want to work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0399.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The exhibition of Morris Weissenberg's paintings is arranged by a group of Jewish and non-Jewish art friends, who are convinced, that they have discovered a God-blessed artist, who will possibly be a blessing to the race that bare him.</p>
   <p>The noted Chicago painter, Edward Tunan, expressed himself most clearly by picturing Morris Weissenberg with the following words:</p>
   <p>"No other thing touched me so, in the modern art world, as the sketches and paintings of Mr. Morris Weissenberg. They give me complete satisfaction, because they arouse in me, thoughts, actual thoughts, sentiment, deep sentiment. This artist is not interested in photographic genuiness of form, color, and so forth, but with the reality of God's nature, may it be a human being or a tree.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0400.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"He is a dreamer and the world would certainly cease to exist if there would be no dreamers. Such persons as Triner, the English; Wilhelm Moss, of Holland; Mile, of France; and Whestler, of America; these very persons have given the world such, that makes life worth living.</p>
   <p>"This artist endows us with inspiration, strong sentiment and promises us a golden future."</p>
   <p>The exhibition of Morris Weissenberg's painting will open, February 18, in the art gallery of Moulton and Rickerts, 71 W. Van Buren St., and will contain the following pieces:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0401.jpg" n="7"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1. Lonely Hours.</cell>
     <cell>8. My Museum.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2. Darkness.</cell>
     <cell>9. A Son of Israel.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3. The Peaceful Summer.</cell>
     <cell>10. The Disappearance.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4. Drama.</cell>
     <cell>11. Elegy.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>5. Those Who Are Hurt.</cell>
     <cell>12. Darkness. (Sketch)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6. Silence.</cell>
     <cell>13. A Pencil Study.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>7. Favorable.</cell>
     <cell>14. Elegy (Arrangement).</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0402.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>From the above list, we can see that Morris Weissenberg is a poet, a poet of strokes and colors, and a visit to his art exhibition will surely be an unusual artistic enjoyment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
