<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">October 13, 1920</date><title level="a">Again a Strike at the Courier an Explanation from the Jewish Printers of Local #16</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0905</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0905.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">October 13, 1920</date><title level="a">AGAIN A STRIKE AT THE COURIER AN EXPLANATION FROM THE JEWISH PRINTERS OF LOCAL #16</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish printers today distributed circulars, which read as follows:</p>
   <p>On the 20th of September, the Jewish printers signed a new agreement with The Forward and The Labor World. The Courier, on the other hand, resorted to legal procedure and the process protracted itself for so long a time that the printers became tired and stopped work.</p>
   <p>The Courier announced, that the president of Local #16 is against the printers upon which Mr. Kaan, the president of Local #16, answered as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0906.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>An article of The Courier draws my attention to the fact, that I warned the printers of The Courier that their dealings are contrary to the laws of Local #16. I never made any such statement. It is not my view, and I'm absolutely in sympathy with the Jewish printers in the Courier difficulties.</p>
   <p>In my possession may be a wage scale agreement signed by a representative of The Courier. The president of Chicago Typographical Local #16, and also by Mardson N. Scott, president of the International Typographical Union. This agreement contains the following clause:</p>
   <p>It is agreed that, at no time shall the weekly wage scale be lower, than the wages that are being paid by the English daily newspapers of Chicago. Since the 22nd of May, 1920, the printers of the English newspapers have been receiving $55.20 a week for day work, and $60 per week for night work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0907.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As the president of the Chicago Typographical Union Local #16, I demanded that the Courier should follow the terms of the agreement and pay $55 per week to the printers, starting September 20, 1920.</p>
   <p>My demand met with all kinds of answers, and protests from the owner, who is looking after his own interest. It is my earnest desire, that the Courier agree to the demands of the existing wage scale agreement.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. N. Kaan,</p>
   <p>President Chicago Typographical Union Local #16.</p>
   <p>This letter speaks for itself. The fact is, that all the printers of The Courier left their work, and The Courier is printed now by several scales, who are practicing scabbery twice a year, every six months, when they must sign a a new agreement. The Jewish readers of the Courier who have always showed their disgust for scales, will this time surely notify the Courier they're meaning about scales.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Printers of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
