<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-01-01">January 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Ten Years of the Forward in Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-01-01">January 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">TEN YEARS OF THE FORWARD IN CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years ago today the Forward, came to Chicago. It was in the year of 1918, when the members of the Forward Association granted the request of the Chicago Socialists and labor movement, to come to Chicago and establish a plant here and publish the daily Forward, in the same manner and the same form as the Forward is being published in New York.</p>
   <p>The first issue of the Chicago Forward appeared January 1, 1919, and that day was transformed into a great folk celebration, participated in not only by Chicago's labor movement, but by all other Jewish organizations to whom the Forward was the great and powerful people's newspaper, and who already for the last twenty years, has been the most significant factor in their spiritual and cultural life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0812.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The coming of the Forward to Chicago ten years ago marked a new epoch in the social life of the Jews in the Middle West.</p>
   <p>Publishing the Forward in Chicago which is the center point between the East and West, made it possible for such Jewish centers as Detroit, Milwaukee, Cleveland and St. Louis to receive the Forward the same day, with all their important local news and occurences of the day.</p>
   <p>Therefore, this day the tenth anniversary of the Forward in Chicago is a jubilee not only for Chicago, but for the Jewish masses in the Middle West, and especially organized labor in the Jewish centers of the West.</p>
   <p>And just because of its interest in the labor movement in the various parts of the West and Middle West, the Forward was inveigled in to installing another plant in Chicago with a line of special editions for the various cities in the West. With this step the Forward had no profits <pb facs="5423972_5_0813.jpg" n="3"/>in mind whatsoever, as at that time the Forward was too financially strong and powerful, to consider this undertaking of publishing the Forward in Chicago a source of increased income.</p>
   <p>And what is more, that time in 1919, was the most unfavorable time for such a great undertaking, this was a year after the World War, had ended. The entire country awaited an economic crisis, which came soon enough and hit with such powers that it was felt in 1920, and 1921 - so, that from a natural business viewpoint, it did not pay the Forward to make such an expensive move.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0814.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But on this, depended the need of serving in the best manner, a great part of the labor movement throughout the country, and the comrades of New York at that time demonstrated the true Socialistic spirit. They took it for granted that if Chicago and the Middle West must have the Forward, in order to strengthen the Jewish labor movement, then there was no question of how much such a move will cost. If the Jewish unions of Chicago, and the West, will gain, in the Workmen's Circle, will, by this move, become stronger and more powerful, if all the other parts of the Jewish social life in the West will start blooming, then that alone, is the greatest impetus for the Forward to take this step.</p>
   <p>At the present celebration of the tenth anniversary of the Forward of Chicago we can proudly say that the step we took ten years ago has provided a great success according to all indications.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0815.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Forward has for the last three years been in their own beautiful and magnificent home that stands out like a bright star in the heart of Chicago's Jewish center. The machinery setting and printing the Forward is the last word in modern presses.</p>
   <p>The people engaged in all departments, from the girl at the switchboard to the manager, are all loyal and devoted to the Forward and feel as members of one large family. The home of the Chicago Forward is in the center of all branches of the Chicago labor movement that are organically connected with the Forward.</p>
   <p>Today, the first day of the new year, let that be the beginning of a new and peaceful life, let the new year bring more luck and peace into the world and a more fortunate life for those who create all the wealth in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0816.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The new year shall awaken, in the workers of America, their needy political consciousness and lead them to a great victory in their struggle for a better life.</p>
   <p>Stronger and mightier may become the labor movement of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
