<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-03-05">March 5, 1886</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1886-03-05">March 5, 1886</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Slavonic citizens of Chicago met on Sunday last at 569 Canal St., for the purpose of organizing more fully their society, entitled...... "Developers of Hebrew Literature." Among the more notable persons present who addressed the meeting were:- Mr. A. Paradise, Dr. Albert Kadison, H. Eliasof, Dr. B. Felsenthal, Rabbi T. G. Lesser, Rabbi Abraham A. Alperstein, Elieser Anixter and others. With other citizens who were present were:- Mr. E. Rubovits, F. Kiss and Julius Silversmith, editor of the Occident.</p>
   <p>After calling the meeting to order, Mr. Paradise welcomed the invited guests to whom he explained the object of the meeting. He stated that the society had been formed to give the young element an opportunity of improving their time for purpose of education, and social position; that the society had already a nucleus of some five-hundred Hebrew volumes, ten newspapers and were now endeavoring to raise sufficient means to enlarge this library.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0639.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Kadison then made a stirring appeal to his countrymen to aid the society in their venture for the improvement of the Slavonic Jews in Chicago. In his endeavor to scientifically show that only through atomism were societies formed, he stated in brief that the object of the association was the education of its copatriots, that every Sunday evening there would be a business meeting, other evenings during the week would be devoted to the reading of papers and the delivery of lectures, and at stated meetings instructions in Hebrew would be given; thirdly general dissertations upon science would be held. Dr. Felsenthal followed with an able address in which he strenously advocated the furtherance of this project, and was vociferously applauded.</p>
   <p>After Dr. Felsenthal, Mr. Eliasof, delivered a lengthy Hebrew essay from manuscript, upon the progress made by the Jews throughout the Unites States; <pb facs="5423972_5_0640.jpg" n="3"/>he elucidated the necessity existing for their banding together for the purpose of preserving the literature of their ancestors; he stated that this country offers the grandest field for the development of a pure Judaism, consistent with the duties of American citizenship. The essay was listened to with marked attention throughout, and warmly applauded.</p>
   <p>Next followed the Rabbis of the orthodox congregations, who addressed their countrymen intheir own vernacular. During an interim a subscription list was circulated, and one hundred dollars were contributed by the audience, a transcript of which will hereafter appear in these columns.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
