<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-30">June 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Kaleidoscope</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-30">June 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE KALEIDOSCOPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is Jewish Gala Week in Chicago.....What with the Zionist convention, the B'nai B'rith conclave. The annual meeting of the Histadruth Ivrith and many other important conferences and conventions, Chicago will be turned into quite a representative Jewish community overnight. The Zionists have many important problems that are pressing the movement for action and from all indications it will be a hot and interesting convention, especially with Dr. Chaim Weitzman as the guest of honor. His presence at the convention more than symbolic, with the Congress being held in August.</p>
   <p>At any rate, it was a clever bit of political strategy and we suspect that some very active and sincere Zionist is responsible for his presence. Will this mean a return of Weitzman to leadership and to the presidency of the agency?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This week Chicago becomes the center of American Jewry. All eyes will be focused here. And many hearts will beat faster in anticipation of the great success that Jewish Day will turn out to be. It will be a glorious ending to a great week-end. The culmination of many months of hard and strenuous work, and the realization of a perfect dream.</p>
   <p>"THE ROMANCE OF A PEOPLE."</p>
   <p>The greatest dramatic spectacle portrayed by Israel at any time on any stage, with the exception of its own history. But the pageant will be portrayal of our history and the greatest single educational interpretation we have ever witnessed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0480.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Gentile friend of ours in our building was so enthused about Jewish Day that he ventured to prophesy that it will surpass a thousand-fold the gathering at Soldier Field during the Eucharistic Congress held here a couple of years ago. The non-Jewish population of this and other cities are as enthused about Jewish Day as any of us are. And it will remain as one of the outstanding events of the World's Fair long after the Century of Progress has ceased to function.</p>
   <p>To the delegates arriving for the Zionist and the Histadruth Conventions, we say: "Shalom! Bruchim Habaim." And hope that their deliberations will result in the revival of the militant spirit which actuated the birth of the Zionist movement. And that the convention will become the means of making Zionism a mass movement in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
