<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">April 23, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">April 23, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The History of the Jewish Theater in Chicago. by Yonah Spivak.</p>
   <p>The Jewish theater of Chicago is as old as the Jewish migration from eastern European countries to this city. It has developed on the same basis as the Jewish theater of New York. The Jewish theater of Chicago also had a prehistoric period leaving no posters or evidence of it.</p>
   <p>The old Jewish inhabitants of Chicago tell us that in 1882 the Jewish theater occupied a "prominent" place in Jewish life, - in a garret of the Turner Hall on Dekoven street near Canal. At that time, all the Jewish stores, shops, Hebrew schools and synagogues were centered in that neighborhood. The Turner Hall had catered mostly to weddings and dances and whenever it was vacant, the Jewish actors of that time took advantage of the opportunity and rented it for a performance. The manager of that company was Mr. Golubak. Mr. Golubak's company consisted of men only, because women, of that time, did not have any access to the Jewish stage.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0080.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although this was only a prelude to the real performance, when, in December 1885, the curtain rose in Turner Hall before a large audience of Jews, Boris Thomashefsky, who came from New York with the repute of a great actor, appeared. Boris Thomashefsky was then managed by L. and Hyman Rubenstein. The plays, Rothchild's Biography written by Thomashefsky's father, The Orphan In Peril, that was performed by the actor Rudolph Marks (who is now a prominent lawyer in Philadelphia) and the Pintele Yid by Goldfodem, were dramatized.</p>
   <p>But the German proprietor of the Turner Hall became obstinate after the first five performances and did not rent his place for Jewish theaters any more, because of the Jews wanting to enter the hall before the janitor opened the doors.</p>
   <p>With this, we close the first chapter of the Jewish "garret-art" in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0081.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Later Jacob Adler came to Chicago from London, with his company, consisting of Madame Kenny Liptzin and her husband, Mr. Gold, Mr. Shankman and Mr. Hannah, who is now practicing law in Chicago. Mr. Adler was financed by a Chicago Jew named Drazdowitz and the first performance was given at "Sam T. Jack's Opera House" between Dearborn and State streets.</p>
   <p>Under Adler's regime a new chapter of Jewish art began in Chicago. Jack's Opera House adopted the name of Adlers Opera House. But after the first performance which was a great success, Madame Liptzin departed from Adler as a result of a quarrel and appeared under the new management of Attorney Joseph Epstein, at the 12th Street Theater.</p>
   <p>The battle between the two stars caused a catastrophe and the competition ruined both theaters financially. Adler paid little attention to his financial condition and introduced as his leading lady his wife Dinah. In a short time, his business dissolved and he went to New York and from there back to London.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0082.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In 1884 he returned to Chicago, where he united with Boris Thomashefsky. In the month of August of that year they played at the Standard Theater, Halsted and Jackson Blvd., together with Madame Sonya Hymowitz, Bessie Thomashefsky, Madame Epstein, P. Glikon, M. H. Tiplitzky, H. Harber, H. Shankman and several others.</p>
   <p>Hyman Rubenstien named the Standard Theater, "Adler's Opera House." The building was, perhaps, constructed in the covered wagon days, when the pioneers of Chicago entered it with guns in order to protect themselves from the Indians. It was dilapidated, and its interior was particularly neglected.</p>
   <p>Boris Thomashefsky and Adler were very busy preparing for the opening performance. They decided to paint the chairs themselves. Madame Thomashefsky bought the paint on Maxwell street and they proceeded the process of painting the chairs. Large throngs flocked to the theater that evening, filling the house to the corridors. The curtain rose and the first act began. Suddenly a woman of the audience, attired in white, yelled out "WET PAINT." Similar remarks by the attendants were soon heard. This was the climax of the melodrama, and when <pb facs="5423972_5_0083.jpg" n="5"/>the curtain fell, in the midst of the first act, anarchy prevailed and the police were compelled to signal a "riot call," in fear of a tragic "wind-up."</p>
   <p>The Jews of Chicago boycotted their remaining performances and in a short time the existence of "Adler's Opera House" ceased.</p>
   <p>The Lyceum Theater, Desplaines and Madison, opened under the management of Glickman, on February 3, 1901, as a permanent Jewish theater, with the following stars: Alice Rothstein, Madame Fanny Reinhardt, Mr. Schneir, Mr. and Mrs. Frank, Mr. and Mrs. Morganbesser, Mr. Goldberg, Mr. Teplitzky, Mr. David Shoenholtz, Mr. Michowitz and Miss Eva Katz: Later were added to the theater: Mr. and Mrs. Simon, Mr. Ginzberg, Madame Danceman, Mrs. Lowitz, Mr. and Mrs. Shapiro and Mr. Hochstein.</p>
   <p>At the first performance, Glickman's Lyceum Theater proved to be very successful. All classes in the Jewish population became interested in Jewish plays. Glickman's <pb facs="5423972_5_0084.jpg" n="6"/>Lyceum Theater blossomed for three consecutive years. After that it terminated as a result of new fire ordinances which became effective.</p>
   <p>In May 1903, Mr. Adolph Gartner came to Chicago, as a member of the German Opera Company. He immediately turned to Pinchas Thomashefsky who was director of a troupe at the 12th Street Theater. Mr. Gartner's audition met with Thomashefsky's approval and Gartner was placed in the play The Son of a Baron. The company refused to play with him because he was not a union man. Thomashefsky and the union actors carried on a great fight, and finally the actors returned to the theater. Upon approaching the theater which was locked, they viewed a sign (written by Thomashefsky) reading, "Tonight will be played 'The Closed Theater' in 5 acts, with a cast of 14 hungry actors."</p>
   <p>Then Gartner took over the management of the Apollo Theater, at 12th and Blue Island Ave., and united with the "striking" actors, who played on a percentage basis.</p>
   <p>A few years later several small companies began playing at the Pavilion Theater <pb facs="5423972_5_0085.jpg" n="7"/>on Roosevelt Road near Halsted street. This theater was for several years, under the management of Muni Weisenfreund (now Paul Muni) and in this theater the great talent of Muni was first exposed. Gartner, at that time, managed a Jewish theater, the Metropolitan, and when Weisenfreund left, eight years later, he took over the management of the Pavilion Theater. Then the Jews began entering the Lawndale district, and he opened the Independence Theater, Independence and Roosevelt Road.</p>
   <p>The opening of the Palace Theater, Blue Island and 12th street, created a new epoch in the history of Jewish theater, although it did not meet with great success at first. At that time Mr. Pollay opened the Empire Theater under his management. He directed it for two seasons with great actors, but met with no success and was forced to close.</p>
   <p>Then, Bernard Beinstein, well known comedian, attempted to establish a second Jewish theater on Madison street and Western avenue, the Imperial, but was <pb facs="5423972_5_0086.jpg" n="8"/>not successful and the theater was closed in the middle of the season.</p>
   <p>Thus, the Palace Theater again remains alone on the Jewish theatrical field in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
