<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-26">Feb. 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Membership Drive for Hebrew Theological College]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-26">Feb. 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[MEMBERSHIP DRIVE FOR HEBREW THEOLOGICAL COLLEGE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The season of community activities now opens in earnest in Chicago. There is a membership drive going on now for the Hebrew Theological College. The Zionist membership drive will soon end, and in a few weeks the big Keren Hayesol ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] drive, which is expected to raise three hundred thousand dollars, will begin. Many little drives also take place between one big drive and another. Soon the drive for Ma-oth Hitim [practice of giving Passover food supplies to the needy] will begin, and other drives of a purely local character. Various committees are functioning in every synagogue. Every committee is working seriously and conscientiously. Jewish Chicago is alive and active now.</p>
   <p>The most important local undertaking now is the membership drive of the Hebrew Theological College. The College now has a yearly expense of seventy thousand <pb facs="5423972_5_1252.jpg" n="2"/>dollars and the more students enroll, the greater will be the expense. It is obvious that such an institution must have a large membership, if it is to be financially solid. The present membership is not large enough to assure the continued existence of the institution. The Hebrew Theological College must have at least five thousand members in good standing, which means that during the drive it must enroll two thousand five hundred additional members. This can be done easily if every synagogue president does his duty. There are seven thousand Jews in Chicago who are members of Orthodox synagogues; these can easily be persuaded to become members of the Hebrew Theological College because the Jew who realizes the importance of belonging to a synagogue, will also realize the importance of being a member of such an educational institution as the Hebrew Theological College. If I had been a representative of the Hebrew Theological College, I would have called all the synagogue presidents before the Rabbinical Council, which would have issued the following decision: "You must contribute to the treasury of the Hebrew Theological College as many five dollar bills as there are members in your synagogue. No excuses will be accepted." Synagogue presidents, who take their <pb facs="5423972_5_1253.jpg" n="3"/>office seriously and who respect the decision of a Rabbinical Council, would certainly accept this responsibility. If the Rabbinical Council has not yet rendered such a decision, it can and should do so. It is the guardian of the Torah in Chicago, and, therefore, has the right and the duty of issuing such a decision. I should like to see any synagogue president refuse to carry out such a decision by the Rabbinical Council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
