<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-12-08">December 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago's Cook Pot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-12-08">December 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago's Cook Pot</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Hebrew Institute, Women's Club, a Hanukah Festival for Jewish children will be given, in which all Sabbath school children will participate. This program will consist of several musical numbers, living pictures of Hanukah History, etc., all under the supervision of Miss Rose Bloom. The Committee for the Entertainment consists of the following ladies:</p>
   <p>Mrs. I.G. Grossberg, Mrs. I. Ginsberg, Mrs. I. Lasker, Mrs. Rabiner, Mrs. Gold, Mrs. Mendel Shur, Mrs. J. Wienberg, Mrs. G.M. Glazer, Mrs. Chas. Levy, and Mrs. Benjamin Davis.</p>
   <p>The Hebrew Institute will have a general discussion next Sunday, for the Young Men's Club of the Institute. Mr. Harry A. Lipsky will act as Chairman, and Messrs. B. Hurovitz, Nathan D. Kaplan, and Jacob Lerbosky will address the <pb facs="5423972_5_0529.jpg" n="2"/>audience. The musical-program will be rendered by the following players: Miss Jennie Liebson, Piano Solo; Miss Kate Berkman, Vocal Solo;</p>
   <p>Miss Rose Vito, Violin Solo; and Mr. Otto Millard, Vocal Solo.</p>
   <p>The Lawndale Club, 3322 Douglas Blvd., is giving a most enjoyable musical entertainment this evening, for its members and friends.</p>
   <p>The Resettlement Committee to which several Jewish women were appointed last Spring, became a permanent institution. Its main activities will be: Assisting the immigrants with their night-schools, wages, businesses, etc. This committee will also advise them how to bring their families from other countries to the United States, and look after their welfare and comfort, after they arrive here.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0530.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There will be an office in the Hebrew Institute for this project, which will be open every Sunday from 10 AM, to 12-Noon. Headquarters will be open every Tuesday evening at 743 Plymouth Court.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Julius Stone is Chairman of this Committee, and Miss Julia Felsenthal, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
