<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-29">May 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Concerning the Courier]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-29">May 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[CONCERNING THE COURIER]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another statement that the Courier has no more than about 8,000 circulation in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Charles Roeske, under oath, swore that he had full charge in the circulation department of the Courier in Chicago, with the exception of the South Side. Therefore, he knows that the Courier circulation in the districts where he was in charge, was no more than 7,400. The Courier denied that Mr. Roeske had charge of this entire circulation. Last week we printed the affidavit of a driver, Hyman Goldman, in which he swore that he worked for Roeske almost a year, delivering the Courier. Today, we present another affidavit of a second driver who worked for the same Roeske about a year and a half, delivering the Courier after Goldman left. He quit his job this 10th of May.</p>
   <p>Read the following affidavit:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0875.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>State of Illinois)</p>
   <p>County of Cook) SS</p>
   <p>Harry Greenberg, being first duly sworn, on oath deposes and swears that he resides in the City of Chicago, and that he is working as a newspaper delivery driver; that he was employed by Charles Roeske to deliver the Jewish Daily Courier on the so-called West Side Route, comprising the vicinity from Jefferson St. on the east to Western Avenue on the west, and from Madison Street to and including 14th Street on the South.</p>
   <p>Affiant further states that he remained in the employ of the said Charles Roeske, doing the delivery of the Courier on this route from December 1920 to March 8, 1922, and after that, when Charles Roeske left the Courier's Service he continued to do the same work for Jake Lichten, who is in charge of the Courier delivery now, up to May 10, 1922, when he resigned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0876.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Affiant further states that during the time of his employ by Charles Roeske, he has made all accounts of collections weekly to the said Charles Roeske and that his pay for his work he also received from the said Charles Roeske, and that the same is true of the other men who were working on the other routes of which the said Charles Roeske has had full charge.</p>
   <p>Affiant further states that the average copies of the Daily Jewish Courier which he distributed were 2400 daily.</p>
   <p>Further affiant sayeth not.</p>
   <p>Harry Greenberg</p>
   <p>Witness:</p>
   <p>Howard M. Fox</p>
   <p>Edwin Alban</p>
   <p>Subscribed and Sworn to Before Me, a Notary, this 19th day of May, A.D., 1922.</p>
   <p>[SEAL]</p>
   <p>Samuel Chapman,</p>
   <p>Notary Public</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
