<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-10">Apr. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Actresses on the American Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-10">Apr. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH ACTRESSES ON THE AMERICAN STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before has the American stage in Chicago seen such an array of famous Jewish actresses as now. The show at the Playhouse, now on its tenth week, is a success, despite the fact that the play has little literary value.</p>
   <p>The star of the play, Miss Elizabeth Brice, is alone responsible for this gigantic success.</p>
   <p>Miss Brice possesses all the qualities of a great artist; personality, refinement, character, looks, beauty, grace, and a very sweet, mellow voice.</p>
   <p>Throughout the play, she keeps her audience enchanted with her loveliness, poise and charm.</p>
   <p>Her lively and rhythmic gestures create an enchanted atmosphere which even the most pessimistic enjoy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0266.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A similar reputation is enjoyed by Miss Vivian Segal, who appears as leading lady in the musical comedy "O, Lady, Lady," at the La Salle Theater.</p>
   <p>Miss Segal has been only three years on the stage and already has made herself very popular.</p>
   <p>Miss Segal is proud of being the daughter of a Russian Jewish immigrant, not following the custom of many Jewish stage and opera stars who generally hide their Jewishness by changing their names.</p>
   <p>Being possessed of a strong and pleasant dramatic voice, Miss Segal expects to make grand opera her career.</p>
   <p>We meet other Jewish stars in the dramatic field: one is Miss Frances Lorimar, whose Jewish name is Adler, niece of the world famous Jewish actor, Jacob Adler. She climbed the ladder of success step by step, and has been on the stage for the last ten years. Miss Lorimar became famous through a mere coincidence: once she had to substitute for a famous actress and did it so well that ever since she has been assigned to star roles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0267.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another great Jewish actress on the American Stage is Miss Bertha Kalish, who will start next week at the Woods Theater.</p>
   <p>Miss Kalish is at present considered the greatest tragedienne on the American stage. She possesses a winning personality.</p>
   <p>Madame Kalish lives in a world of art and beauty. In her spare time, she takes her brush and paints and draws magnificent sceneries. Some claim that she has intimate abstractions in colors and hues.</p>
   <p>As in New York, her performances in Chicago will be no doubt a success, for Madame Kalish has here many admirers of art and beauty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
