<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-19">Apr. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Jewess Writes Important Work on Jewish Pioneers of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-19">Apr. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO JEWESS WRITES IMPORTANT WORK ON JEWISH PIONEERS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very important book in English has just been published, written by a young Chicago Jewess, Mrs. Anita Liebman Lebenson, and entitled, Jewish Pioneers in America.</p>
   <p>Anita Liebman Lebenson is one of the capable daughters of Morris and Liza Liebman, a family of businessmen and scholars who immigrated to Chicago twenty-five years ago from Vilna, Russia.</p>
   <p>A sister of the authoress is the wife of the well-known novelist and journalist, Ben Hecht. Mrs. Hecht, also an authoress, recently published a very interesting novel, and is employed at present as a newspaper reporter. A third sister is a doctor of medicine.</p>
   <p>Anita Liebman Lebenson devoted much time to her historical work. It took her nearly thirteen years to gather the material.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1082.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many critics who have already read the book claim that it is a very important contribution to the history of the first Jewish immigrants in America and the development of the first Jewish communities.</p>
   <p>The author is a well educated person. Born in Vilna, she came with her parents to America when still a little girl, receiving her education in Chicago, where she graduated from high school and college with high honors, later becoming a teacher at John Marshall High School.</p>
   <p>The book is rich in pictures and contains volumes of interesting information and bibliographical notes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
