<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-06">Feb. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[The Problem of Jewish Education]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-06">Feb. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[THE PROBLEM OF JEWISH EDUCATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two extreme positions are being taken on the problem of Jewish education, and that is why it is so difficult to solve. One extreme, the Reform, defends the Sunday school type of education--a purely religious education without a Hebrew or a national background. The other extreme, the Orthodox, defends the old-fashioned Talmud Torah--another form of a purely religious education, without a national background and without Hebrew. The educational problem cannot be solved on the basis of these two extremes. A middle ground must be found. This middle ground is neither the Sunday school nor the old-fashioned Talmud Torah, but the modern Hebrew school, conducted in the traditional spirit, in which the child receives a general Jewish education, with Hebrew as its foundation. A general Jewish education includes a religious education, but it is not an education exclusively religious.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1255.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Zionists of Chicago claim that this thesis will have to be accepted as a basis for a Jewish educational program, otherwise they will not participate in any educational work because they do not see any other way of realizing their program. There is no sense, the Zionists claim, in coming together with groups who are interested in education from an extreme point of view; there is no sense in quarreling with them, and then being unable to arrive at any conclusion. This is the Zionist reply to the various groups that have invited the Zionist organization to send representatives to their educational council. The Zionists are interested in everything Jewish, but they do not specialize in theology.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
