<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-01-10">January 10, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Zionists Announce Interesting Course on Zionism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1931-01-10">January 10, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ZIONISTS ANNOUNCE INTERESTING COURSE ON ZIONISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A course of lectures has been arranged by the Chicago Zionist Organization, Senior and Junior Hadassah, and, Avukah, under the auspices of the College of Jewish Studies.</p>
   <p>The course will be divided into three cycles. The first cycle dealing with the history of Zionism; the second with the theory of Zionism; and the third with Palestine. The program is as follows:</p>
   <p>CYCLE 1. History of Zionism, January 22, - The awakening of Jewish National Consciousness - Dr. Leo L. Honor. January 22, Zionist Activity Prior to the Balfour Declaration - Dr. Felix A. Levi. February 5, Zionism since the Balfour Declaration - Dr. A. L. Sachar.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>CYCLE 2. Theories of Zionism - February 12 - Political Cultural and Economic Zionism - Rabbi Max Kadushin. February 19 - Philosophic and Religious aspects of Zionism. Dr. Meyer Waxman. February 26, - The Philosophy and program of the Labor Factions - Dr. Eliezer Rieger.</p>
   <p>CYCLE 3. Palestine - March 5, The Land of its possibilities - Dr. Alexander M. Dushkin. March 12 - Jews and Arabs, Dr. Eliezer Rieger. March 19 - The Mandatory power and the League of Nations - Dr. William Halperin - March 26, Jewish achievements in Palestine, Rabbi Solomon Goldman.</p>
   <p>The first lecture will take place on Thursday, January 22, at 8:15 p.m. at the Covenant Club, 10 N. Dearborn Street. People may enroll for the entire course $2.00, or for any one cycle $1.00, or for a single lecture $.50. Tickets may be purchased at the office of the College of Jewish Studies, 30 N. Dearborn Street, Randolph 1824, or at the office of the Zionist organization and Hadassah Club Rooms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
