<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Herman Schur Reference Library</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0722</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0722.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HERMAN SCHUR REFERENCE LIBRARY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the reading room in our reference library is one of the brightest and largest rooms at the Institute, it is already proving too small for the students and readers who come to use it. In the center of a thriving Jewish community, with a variety of cultural activities in the same building - a high school, an elementary school, a series of lecture forums and the like - the library is admirably situated to attract large bodies of readers. The attendance has been mounting slowly, but steadily, on an average of about two-hundred persons, who come daily to utilize some of the 9,000 books on the various subjects available in the library, or to read the magazines and newspapers on file.</p>
   <p>The library is made up of four departments. First, the reading and study room; second, the Judaica section; third, the magazine room; fourth, the pamphlet section. About 3,000 of the books of our collection deal with social sciences, under which are classified such subjects as Philosophy, Psychology, Sociology, Criminology, Ethics, Economics, Foreign Relations, <pb facs="5423972_5_0723.jpg" n="2"/>Political Economy, Finance, Civics, Education, Domestic Economy, and Business.</p>
   <p>The Judaica section contains upward of 3,500 books, which in themselves make up a very exclusive library in this field. Some of the contents of this collection may be described by such generic terms as Biography, Drama, Psychology, Philanthropy, Education, Judaism, Philosophy, etc. Many books in this section are rare and cannot be duplicated except in some of the great collections of Judaica, elsewhere.</p>
   <p>The reference section contains about 712 reference books. All the important encyclopedias, source miscellanies, dictionaries, compendiums, of one kind or another are available. The seating capacity is about sixty-five persons in the main reading room alone. About 125 current magazines are on file in the library. These magazines are all of the kind that serious people and students wish to read. There are no trade magazines and none of the kind that do not merit real reading. All of the old numbers of important magazines are kept on file alphabetically, and are available <pb facs="5423972_5_0724.jpg" n="3"/>to readers. Within the last three months, another branch has been added to our library, and that is our pamphlet department, corresponding to the civics sections of the general library. At present we have pamphlets on about thirty-five different subjects, but from the rate of growth of this section, we may expect in the near future to find valuable information in a large pamphlet library.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
