<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-01">Sept. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[The Theater in Chicago]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-01">Sept. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[THE THEATER IN CHICAGO]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is lucky. The actors in all the Jewish theaters located in Jewish centers are on strike, and the theaters, therefore, cannot open. In Chicago peace reigns between the Jewish actors and the Jewish theater-owners, and, therefore, the Jewish theater will open its doors to the public, whereas the Jewish theaters in New York are temporarily closed. Mr. Elias Glickman, the owner of the largest Jewish theater in Chicago, is, of course, happy about the situation and laughs at the theater managers in New York. Had they adopted his policy, perhaps they too would be able to open the doors of their theaters today.</p>
   <p>The Jewish theater of Chicago is also lucky in having obtained the services of a truly great artist--Joseph Shengold. His technique is varied; at one <pb facs="5423972_5_0076.jpg" n="2"/>moment, he makes one shudder--at another, one's soul is frightened and one sees ghosts whispering.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to characterize the art of Joseph Shengold because it is many-sided. I have seen him in difficult tragic roles which made me cry. I have seen him in very funny roles and I nearly burst with laughter. I have seen him play dramatic and melodramatic roles with the skill of a master.</p>
   <p>Mr. Shengold can also sing. He sings Jewish melodies as powerfully and sweetly as--what shall I say--as my friend Manewich. It is a pleasure to hear him play and sing, I am sure that Chicago will enjoy him.</p>
   <p>I do not know whether he will enjoy Chicago. That depends upon you. If you believe that it is better to go to the Jewish theater to hear a Jewish word, see Jewish acting, listen to a Jewish song than to sit home and play <pb facs="5423972_5_0077.jpg" n="3"/>poker--then he will surely enjoy Chicago. Otherwise, he will curse the day he came to Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
