<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1914-02-12">Feb. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Fate of Jewish Actors</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1914-02-12">Feb. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE FATE OF JEWISH ACTORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Maguleskoe, the artist of the Jewish stage, is no longer among the living. And yet it seems as though he is still with us; as though his deeply felt humor is not yet removed from the Jewish stage; as though his character portrayals, his artistic mimical contortions, and his pure typically Jewish acting remain in the treasure of Jewish eternity.</p>
   <p>But when we remember his funeral, during which more than forty thousand Jews accompanied him to his everlasting peace and in which eulogies were spoken and songs were sung, we become positive that Maguleskoe is no longer here. Because if we commence to honor an artist, it is evidence that he has died. When alive Maguleskoe was a good actor, a great character <pb facs="5423972_5_0314.jpg" n="2"/>player, but the Jewish masses never thought of honoring him then. Did they show him any appreciation for his great services to the Jewish stage? Certainly not. We Jews honor our talented only when they are dead.</p>
   <p>The fate of artists among Gentiles is comparatively better. They know how to estimate the greatness of an artist when he is among the living, just when the people's recognition gives him courage and inspiration to develop his creative potentialities to a higher degree.</p>
   <p>We learn that the poor working girls of Paris have honored Charpenter, the composer of "Louise" and "Joumen," two operas in which he depicts the spiritual life of the French working girl. For these operas Charpenter <pb facs="5423972_5_0315.jpg" n="3"/>created a music the melodies of which represent the efforts and ideals of the working girl. They feted him with a magnificent banquet and presented him with a sword inlaid with precious gems.</p>
   <p>Thus have these poor girls exalted their poet, who lived in the Latin Quarter, the slum section of Paris, wherefrom he attained motifs for his works.</p>
   <p>Maguleskoe was the artist of all the Jewish people. His character roles were typically Jewish and, through his dramatic playing for a few decades, he beautified and glorified Jewish life. Yet it was not until death had called him, that the Jews showed their esteem for him. Such is the fate of a Jewish actor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
