<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-06">May 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Ben Hecht-Artist and Arbiter</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. B. Loeber (In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-06">May 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">BEN HECHT-ARTIST AND ARBITER</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. B. Loeber (In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ben Hecht, one of the most sensational of the modernist writers in America today, has made his public bow this week with the fifth number of his biweekly publication, the Chicago Literary Times. As in the previous numbers of this unique journal, Ben Hecht continues here his tirade against the absurdities of the literary cult. He is uncannily satirical and dispenses his advice quite freely to those authors with whom he can conveniently pick a quarrel. He arraigns the literature and the art of the day, the science, the politics, and the economic gospel of the times. These he considers as the essentials of life. He marshals life before him and issues his command. He cares never a whit for the doctrines of others. He follows his own counsel and pursues his way irrespective of the directions given him by others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0653.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ben Hecht dwells within a sphere entirely of his own making. Everything written by him represents the product of his mind. He is a well of many waters. He possesses a great fancy, an intense emotion, an original style, and is a fluent writer, a master of vocabulary. He is very prolific, too, and whether you fully grasp his meaning or not, you are fascinated by his language and are compelled to read him. He makes you curious and interested, and that, in effect, is really the greatest compliment an author can receive.</p>
   <p>Ben Hecht is a man with no long list of honorary degrees. He was born in New York thirty years ago of poor parents who were emigrants from Ekaterinoslav [now Dnepropetrovsk]. He went through the public and high schools and experienced many hardships before he could earn a livelihood of his pen. He was one of the star feature men on the staff of the Chicago Daily News, and its war correspondent. His war cables were read eagerly by the news readers, for they possessed the fascination that all such reports ordinarily lack. They were photographic in their realism, yet significant in a spiritual sense also, the <pb facs="5423972_5_0654.jpg" n="3"/>comment of a man who sees and does, not merely gaze. He is also the author of a play called Under False Pretenses, and several novels--Frik Dorn, Gargoyles, and Fantazious Mallare--the latest a psychological study, which the censor thought too radical an expression of opinion, as well as of a number of short stories published in magazines an anthologies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
