<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-20">May 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Report of Institution Committee of the Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-20">May 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[REPORT OF INSTITUTION COMMITTEE OF THE JEWISH FEDERATION OF ORTHODOX CHARITIES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of the institution committee of the Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities last night, the subcommittee, which consisted of Messers. Turner and Levinson, presented a report dealing with the conditions in the Chicago Talmud Torahs.</p>
   <p>According to the report, the Waller Street Talmud Torah is too small to hold all the children seeking to attend a Jewish educational institution, and hundreds must be rejected because of inadequate seating capacity. The committee criticized the present system of registering the students, since the parents of many children who are accepted [as non-paying students], can well afford to pay the tuition fee, and thereby, make room for the large number of poor children who are turned away. Therefore, a system should be inaugurated which will enable [the registrars] to determine the [economic] status of the parents.</p>
   <p>The committee also held that in order to improve the educational system, it is <pb facs="5423972_5_1773.jpg" n="2"/>very important to unite all the Talmud Toroth and the Yeshivah [theological college] under one board of directors.</p>
   <p>At the next meeting of the board of directors a plan will be discussed proposing to enlarge the Talmud Torah.</p>
   <p>The report on the Hebrew Sheltering Home was a very sad one. The sanitary conditions within the home are poor. The bed linen is ragged, torn and dirty. The food is bad, costing about twenty cents per meal. No records are kept, and the home is open to all as though it were a soup-kitchen instead of a sheltering home. A new building and a change of management was recommended by the [institution] committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
