<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-27">July 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Heard and Seen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1766</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1766.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-27">July 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">HEARD AND SEEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Jewry has unanimously approved the plan proposed by Harry A. Lipsky, a member of the board of education, that an attempt should be made to open Hebrew and Yiddish classes at the John Smith school.</p>
   <p>The national youth groups have begun to organize themselves to help carry this plan into effect. The number of students registering, exceeded the financial allotment for the classes.</p>
   <p>Through the efforts of Harry A. Lipsky, the board of education will allow its classrooms to be used free of charge. The principal of the John Smith school will voluntarily supervise the activities of the children, thereby adhering to the school ordinance [on supervision]. The classes will be conducted in the same manner as public-school classes are conducted. The only difference between the two types of classes will be the nature of the studies.</p>
   <p>A board of education of Jewish educators will be organized to prepare the <pb facs="5423972_5_1767.jpg" n="2"/>curriculum. We are informed that the subjects to be taught will be Jewish history, Jewish ethics, and the Yiddish and Hebrew languages. Subjects dealing with Jewish religious doctrines will not be taught.</p>
   <p>Those who are interested in preserving Judaism in America should take good care to see that this new type of Jewish education is supported as much as possible. We shall extend a helping hand in establishing these free schools. We shall also help financially, so that there will be no reason for rescinding [the proposal to hold classes in] the schools on account of a lack of money to pay the teachers or other expenses connected with the undertaking.</p>
   <p>It would be a pleasure to see our welfare workers raise the money necessary to assure the existence of these classes. Needless to say, our young nationalists, who have assumed the responsibility of establishing these classes, are not rich enough to aid them financially.</p>
   <p>A fund, out of which the teachers will be paid, must be raised as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
