<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-30">Apr. 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Hebraists Versus Yiddishists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-30">Apr. 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HEBRAISTS VERSUS YIDDISHISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is an accepted fact that no matter where or when a group of Hebrew and Yiddish journalists meet a clash will follow sooner or later about the language problem. A perpetual conflict has been going on between Hebrew and Yiddish writers. The conference recently called by the Peretz Farband was not an exception [to an usual Hebrew-Yiddish meeting]; and the reason why it did not last long was that the Hebrew journalists were not represented proportionately.</p>
   <p>Why should we deceive ourselves? We know that both Hebrew and Yiddish are "dying"--that both are in a "deplorable condition". Both languages are on the threshold of being destroyed in their struggle with the big and powerful living languages of modern civilization. The future of neither is secure: both hang from a burning thread; but instead of co-operating and helping each other, they are fighting against each other. I think it will be the greatest misfortune for the Hebrew language if Yiddish were to become dead--and vice <pb facs="5423972_5_0646.jpg" n="2"/>versa. The Yiddish language is still the biggest prop of the Hebrew language. In the countries where Jews to not speak Yiddish there are no Hebrew-speaking persons--with the exception of a few scholars who studied Hebrew much in the same manner as some study Sanskrit, Latin, Greek, or any other dead language.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Heder [Old World type of Hebrew school] has nourished the Hebrew and Yiddish languages throughout the ages. Should we close the Heder, it will mark the end of Hebrew and Yiddish--at least in the so-called Exile countries. If the Yiddish language disappears from the face of the earth so will the Hebrew language. Those Hebrew fanatics who bitterly attack the Yiddish language are not even aware of the fact that they are attacking themselves. These people are not only attempting to commit homicide but also suicide. The same misfortune would happen to the Yiddish language should the Hebrew language disappear.</p>
   <p>Without Hebrew--without the Hebraic elements and expressions which are found in Yiddish--the Yiddish language would gradually become a Germanic dialect. By losing its Hebraic peculiarities and content, the Yiddish language would <pb facs="5423972_5_0647.jpg" n="3"/>in time again become part of the German language. The Hebrew elements molded and shaped Yiddish and made it a rich and juicy language; they prevented it from degenerating--from good Yiddish into bad German. We all remember very well the peculiar Yiddish used thirty years ago in Europe and in America when it was more customary to write in German-Yiddish than in Hebrew-Yiddish. As matters stand now, Yiddish needs Hebrew no less than Hebrew needs Yiddish. This controversy is very harmful for both groups since they will only lose their energy and their strength--and gain nothing.</p>
   <p>Both language groups have very wholesome and very important arguments to advance. We must, therefore, say that each group is right according to its point of view. The Yiddishists are most certainly right when they argue that Yiddish is the living language of a living nation. This is the best and the strongest argument. We all like the Yiddish language. It is very natural for us to like it--without giving explanations--because it is like a mother's love for her children. Yiddish is our native tongue. We were reared in it; we learned how to think and express our emotions, ideas, and ideals in it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0648.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It appears to me at times rather preposterous that some of our theorists, educators, and philosophers should seek to convince us that Yiddish has "historical rights" because several prayer books were written in the vernacular, or because a Purim play was performed several hundred years ago in Yiddish. Yiddish does not need such historical rights to justify its existence. It is here, and it is alive; that is the best proof of its importance.</p>
   <p>However, the Hebraists also have claims which qualify Hebrew as the cradle language of the Jewish nation. The Jews have created cultural treasures in Hebrew which have been, and still are, of universal significance. Hebrew has accompanied the Jewish race for over three thousand years. During their long wanderings the Jews have used and discarded various languages of various countries, but Hebrew always stayed with them. It was their literary and religious language--not their "weekday" tongue.</p>
   <p>In Hebrew we find the literary treasures which the Jewish race has created during its long Exile. Even the literature of some of the foreign groups was <pb facs="5423972_5_0649.jpg" n="5"/>created by the Hebrews: for example, the Persian and Arabic literatures. Although very little remains of these literatures, their is still evidence of the priceless contributions of the Jews to the literary world. Had the Guide to the Perplexed, a work written in Arabic by the greatest of all Hebrew scholars [Moses Maimonides], not been translated into Hebrew, it probably would have been lost together with many other great works like The Fountain of Life, written by the world-famous poet and thinker, Solomon Ibn Gabirol.</p>
   <p>Yiddish does not need any historical rights because it is alive. Hebrew has enormous historical rights which cannot be ignored or slighted. In conclusion--both parties are justified in their claims.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
