<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Theater Notices</title><title level="a" type="sub">Northwest Side Jews Get Their Own Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THEATER NOTICES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Northwest Side Jews Get Their Own Theater</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Samuel B. Grossman and a company of select actors open tomorrow night at the Crown Theater, with Libbin's "One Law for Both".</p>
   <p>It is an old, old rule that your own [things] smell sweeter than the other fellow's; that your own is more honored and loved than the other fellow's; that your own is nearest to your heart. We recalled this rule now for this reason: the Northwest Side Jews have lived long enough to obtain finally a theater of their own--a thing that they have wanted for some time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Samuel B. Grossman, an old-time Chicago actor, is the one who has earned the thanks of the Northwest Side Jews for this gift. And let the Y'Yasher Ko-ach (literally, May He confirm your power, figuratively, Congratulations <pb facs="5423972_5_0280.jpg" n="2"/>and thanks) be expressed immediately.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grossman has truly estimated the great need that the Jews of that neighborhood have felt for a theater of their own. And he took the trouble to obtain the biggest and nicest theater that the Northwest Side has, namely, the Crown Theater, at Division Street and Ashland Avenue. This theater has sixteen hundred comfortable seats and a large stage. And tomorrow night it will open as a Jewish theater with Z. Libbin's successful drama of life, "One Law for Both". The play is one of the best that Libbin has written. And besides tomorrow (Friday) night, it will also be played Saturday Matinee and evening.</p>
   <p>For the Sunday Matinee and evening performances Mr. Grossman has arranged to present the four-act Musical comedy, "The Passionate Girl", by M. Goldberg. It will undoubtedly make a great hit with the public because of the fine songs and even finer humor that this work contains. In a word, this summer <pb facs="5423972_5_0281.jpg" n="3"/>will be a lively one on the Northwest Side, and we hope that, with God's help, we shall be able to enjoy it.</p>
   <p>The certain success of the Crown as a Jewish theater lies not only in the fact that Mr. Grossman stands at the head of this undertaking and will certainly direct all his efforts towards satisfying the public. The success is also guaranteed because together with Mr. Grossman there will always appear a company of select actors who are particularly well trained to amuse the public because they have had considerable stage experience. The actors are: Mr. Ziggelob and Miss Rubin, both of New York; Mr. Nusbaum, Mr. Yanover, and many others who are well qualified to perform on the Jewish stage.</p>
   <p>It is therefore expected that the Jews of the Northwest Side will know how to appreciate their own theater and will actually come tomorrow evening to celebrate the opening of the Crown Theater. For tomorrow will be a holiday on the Northwest Side; and all must be present at a holiday celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
