<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-03">Sept. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[The Workers' Culture League]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-03">Sept. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[THE WORKERS' CULTURE LEAGUE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Workers' Culture League created a great deal of interest among all local circles by its great accomplishments last season. It is making many new preparations for the coming season, which will begin shortly.</p>
   <p>The league is now planning a program of great cultural significance. The league is broadening its activities. It will plan a wonderful program for the masses this season, among whom it found many sympathizers. Primarily, the league is determined that its undertakings should not be available only to West Side residents. Therefore, it will sponsor undertakings on the Northwest Side. The affairs will be given on the Northwest Side Friday evenings and in the Douglas Park District Sunday evenings.</p>
   <p>The league engaged the well-known artist and musician, Paul Lampkoff, the musical director of the Palace Theater. Mr. Lampkoff is a graduate of the Petrograd Conservatory. He became famous in Europe for his great musical ability. At the league he will have full charge of the choir and orchestra.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1368.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The league also engaged the noted English actor and producer, William Owen, as the manager of the English department of the dramatics division, which will be under the direction of a famous Jewish artist, whose name can not yet be announced.</p>
   <p>L. Schaffner, chairman of the league, travelled to New York to complete the transactions with the above-mentioned artist. Schaffner will also arrange with the well-known painter, S. Astrowsky, to become the manager of the art and painting division of the league.</p>
   <p>The league will open its season with three grand undertakings: a banquet will be held September 22; an Art ball on October 7; and a theater performance in the Palace Theater on October 17 where the entire cast of the league will appear.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
