<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-10">Aug. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For the Benefit of the Children</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1596</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1596.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-10">Aug. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE CHILDREN</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago, they speak of a Beth Hamedreth Lamudim (an institution for Hebrew teachers).</p>
   <p>Chicago has not started such plans before - not because the necessity for such an institution was not felt - on the contrary there was a scarcity of Jewish teachers who thoroughly understood their profession - but it seems that no one before raised the question in Chicago. Many Jews here have an idea of a school of religious lore, because it is a complete thing of which they have an example before them. Very few Jews in Chicago know how to direct a course for teachers.</p>
   <p>To speak of such an institution, one must himself be an experienced teacher with a constructive mind, and of such, unfortunately we have few in Chicago, and if there are any they evidently have not brought themselves to the attention of the Jewish people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1597.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Credit is due Mr. Maximan, the superintendent of the North Side Talmud Torah, who has not only talked about, but has worked out a program for such a teachers' institution with all particulars.</p>
   <p>Everyone realizes that in order to obtain effect on young children a teacher need not necessarily be a learned man or exceptionally versed in learning, but he must know how to act with American children. He must be able to talk their language as well as they do and must be able to instill his knowledge into the children in a systematic manner.</p>
   <p>In Chicago's present generation among the youths that have recently graduated from high school, there is considerable material for teachers.</p>
   <p>There are high school boys and some girls who know the foundation of Hebrew and Jewish and a few years of learning in the Beth Hamedreth Lamudim would <pb facs="5423972_5_1598.jpg" n="3"/>make them good Hebrew teachers. But such young people have not the means to go forward with these studies. They must earn enough for a livelihood. In order that they be given the opportunity to study to become Hebrew teachers they must be supported until they graduate as Hebrew teachers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Maximan figured out that a capital of seven or eight thousand dollars is needed for the first year. We do not know whether Mr. Maximan is as good a finance budgeter as he is good in making a program for education and learning, but finances for such a purpose should not be in question.</p>
   <p>There are enough well-to-do Jews in Chicago, to whom future Jewish education should be dear, and who would be anxious to give cash to see such an institution developed. It would be a great encouragement for the small minority of Jews who take this matter seriously to heart, if the Jews who sympathize with this undertaking and are in a position to help, would respond.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
