<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-04-19">Apr. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Workmen's Circle School Will Be a Model for the World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-04-19">Apr. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE SCHOOL WILL BE A MODEL FOR THE WORLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Herein we present a statement of the problems and principles of the Jewish Socialist Workmen's Circle Schools, whose opening will be celebrated by all workers' movements in Chicago, with a fine concert at the Ashland Auditorium, April 27.</p>
   <p>Preamble: It is a regrettable fact that, in a capitalistic society, the public schools are controlled largely by capitalists, the enemies of the working class. They are interested in making the younger generation faithful and devoted slaves to their interests. The teachers, who exert the greatest influence upon the children and inculcate their views of life upon them, educate them to become unquestioning protectors of the present rotten system. The teachers are forced to implant within the young, innocent hearts, the greatest reactionary chauvinism. They sow hatred, the plague of humanity, against every progressive radical movement; poison every threat of revolution; and instil prejudice against every person in the present society, even though it be the child's own parent, who <pb facs="5423972_5_1533.jpg" n="2"/>envisages a better social system.</p>
   <p>Therefore, every clear-minded worker, who strives towards a more beautiful and better world for humanity, cannot permit himself to remain indifferent with regard to the education of his own children, who are capable, either of carrying on the fight for liberty, equality and justice, or of becoming obstacles in the struggle toward that goal. The foundation of this new order must be carefully prepared, and the proper education of the young children is essential for the realization of this purpose. Without the younger generation serving as the rebuilders of a ruined world, the worker's struggle to guide the future of the ship of life is lost.</p>
   <p>It is a recognized fact that, so long as nations with various languages and cultures exist, so long will the Jewish people exist. For, like all other nationalities, the Jewish people possesses its own culture and its Yiddish language, which is spoken by the majority of Jews.</p>
   <p>The American melting pot built a stone wall between parents and children. The <pb facs="5423972_5_1534.jpg" n="3"/>children speak a new language, thus making it impossible for parents and children to understand each other. This lack of understanding seriously disturbs the child's education.</p>
   <p>To eradicate this difference the Workmen's Circle decided to create a daily Jewish Socialist school. It should be the task of the teachers to raise the children in a broad-minded manner, in the spirit of national socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
