<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">February 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Friends</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">February 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR FRIENDS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past few days, we have been receiving inquiries from our friends concerning the difference in opinion between the Daily Jewish Courier and the standkeepers selling this newspaper. We find it, therefore, necessary to quiet them by the following explanation:</p>
   <p>A great number of newsdealers, selling Jewish newspapers, a few weeks ago united into an association. Neither as individuals, nor as members of the association have the newsdealers had any reason to complain against the Courier's treatment of them. A few weeks ago a committee of the association approached Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, manager of the <pb facs="5423972_5_1053.jpg" n="2"/>Courier, and informed him that they had a few complaints they would like to make. Mr. Lipsky's response was that he would consider them if they were written in full on paper.</p>
   <p>The committee called a few more times in regard to this matter, but never proposed their complaints in writing, and therefore there were no negotiations. At their last visit the committee requested Mr. Lipsky to exert his influence upon the city administration so that the police should overlook the order that out-of-town papers must not be sold on the stands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1054.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Lipsky fulfilled their request. He turned to the Chief of Police and found out that the order forbidding the sale of out-of-town papers was issued on account of the Saturday Evening Post since discrimination between this and other papers could not be made. However, he promised that the Jewish newspapers will be excluded from this category. Tuesday evening at a meeting held by the association, Mr. Lipsky brought the news that the Chief of Police had issued a new order to the effect that the newsdealers selling out-of-town papers should not be harassed. Mr. Lipsky was accompanied to this meeting by Park Commissioners S. J. Rosenblatt and Louis Hertzfield.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1055.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After the report, the association unanimously accepted a proposal extending its gratitude to Mr. Lipsky for his good work. A few hours later, after mid-night, a committee returned and declared that the members of the association had determined not to sell the Courier any longer. On Wednesday, about noon, Park Commission S. J. Rosenblatt called the Courier and related that Attorney Peter Sussman, who represents the association, had requested a conference with a representative of the Daily Jewish Courier. Out of respect for this distinguished lawyer, we answered that a representative of the Courier would be highly pleased to talk to him at any time after 7 o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1056.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A representative of the Courier met Mr. Sussman at the set time, and told him the Courier's standpoint in this matter. The newsdealers are considered customers of the Courier as long as they buy it: it is possible that disputes between the buyers and sellers shall breakout and these should be settled. But as the Courier understands it, the members of the association do not want to be the customers of the Courier any longer, and as a result, both parties no longer have business relations with each other, and, therefore, there are no disputes and nothing further can be said.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sussman saw how justified these contentions were, and after discussing the matter with the association, the members again decided to become the customers of the Courier.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1057.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>After this decision, Mr. Sussman declared that the customers of the Courier, who have organized themselves into an association, have various complaints. They think that if the management of the Courier would listen to them and grant them their demands, their business would be improved. The Courier's representative told Mr. Sussman that whenever he conveys the demands in writing, the management of the Courier will consider it in a regular business way. Mr. Sussman gave a list of complaints to the Courier's representative, and asked that the Courier consider them by Sunday, after which date there will be a conference between Mr. Sussman and the Courier.</p>
   <p>The Courier's representative then stated that the management of the Courier will undoubtedly also present its demands, and therefore all demands should be discussed together and if they cannot agree, an arbitration board should be used. Mr. Sussman approved this and as a <pb facs="5423972_5_1058.jpg" n="7"/>result the newsdealers, who boycotted the Courier Tuesday, resumed their buying yesterday. We can assure our friends, as well as the Chicago Jewish community that under any circumstances and at any time, whether or not the Courier finds the demands of the association justifiable, the management will use every means to settle the dispute in a respectable way as is becoming to the only Chicago Jewish newspaper and which is no more than the voice of Jewish public opinion.</p>
   <p>We also wish to announce to the general public, especially to organized labor, that the Courier is a union newspaper, and is composed and printed by union people. The office of the Courier became unionized before any other Jewish newspaper had had it in mind even to employ union men. The union label can always be found on the Courier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
