<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-07">October 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Theater World - I. S</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-07">October 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH THEATER WORLD - I. S</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our local Jewish community there is much rejoicing. Again we have a truly Jewish theater with Jewish artists who promise to remain here providing the large Jewish audiences desired them. They do. Theatergoers approved them as can be witnessed by the large attendance which fill the theater to capacity. Such were the greetings accorded the Jewish theater at its opening performances.</p>
   <p>Of course we are speaking of the Globe theater and the entire Liptson troupe which came to bring Chicagoans a truly Jewish theater.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even at present, New York, as it appears, does not have a truly Jewish theater to present the finer class of Jewish drama. Her five theaters feed the public only trash, each succeeding play being worse than the previous one. Regardless of press criticism these New York managers do not even make an effort to offer something better to their patrons than such plays as "Souls", "Hearts", and Dots". Apparently their audiences are satisfied.</p>
   <p>Thus when word was brought that the Liptson troupe headed by Madam Kenie Liptson, Herr Elias Rothstone, and Jacob Cohen was coming here to present the better plays of the Jewish repertoire, we were somewhat astonished, even though we have long known that in our region the Jewish audience has for sometime been seeking the finer and better qualities that make for a true, earnest, and interesting drama.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0322.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fact is not built on supposition. The Liptson players have always played Jacob Gordon's finer dramas......</p>
   <p>We feel it is unnecessary to review these plays since they are well known to all Jewish theater-goers. They include "Miraleh Ephris", "The Unknown", "The Slaughter", "Der Momzer", etc. It is also more or less known that in these plays Madam Liptson presents her strongest characterizations, those that have brought her fame. The same may be said of Herr Rothstone, Cohen, Madam Wellinsky, Katzman, and others......</p>
   <p>Mr. Rothstone informed us that the company had come for only twelve weeks in which time they have prepared the very best of drama to be shown here. But these twelve weeks can at anytime be extended indefinitely if the Chicago public will approve such high standards as will be presented to them on the Jewish stage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
