<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1931-01-26">January 26, 1931</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1931-01-26">Janurary 26, 1931</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Board, Mr. Becker spoke on the work of the Jewish Telegraphic Agency and its importance to world and American Jewry. He then introduced Mr. Jacob Landau, representative of the J. T. A. who presented the work of the Agency in covering throughout the world news of importance to the Jews.</p>
   <p>Not only has the Associated Press and the Reuter Agency unqualifiedly accepted and paid for the news items which the Agency furnished them, but the active distribution of such news has been a protective force to the Jewish communities of Eastern Europe.</p>
   <p>He stated that the Agency had a gross budget of some $250,000 against which it had an internal income of $125,000 leaving a deficit of about $125,000 which had to be made up by contributions. Messrs. Felix and Paul Warburg, Mortimer L. Schiff and Julius Rosenwald among others had for a number of years generously contributed to the Agency. The American Jewish Committee had investigated the conduct of its affairs very thoroughly and was so convinced of the <pb facs="5423972_5_0770.jpg" n="2"/>importance of the Agency to Jewry that it had departed from its previous practice and had endorsed and sponsored a fund raising campaign for the Agency at a time when the Committee itself was in great need of funds.</p>
   <p>Mr. Becker then emphasized the fact that the Chicago Community had not been doing its share in regard to the Agency and other national organizations and that it was the duty of the Board to see that Chicago participated and contributed its proper share to all such national and international activities.</p>
   <p>Messrs Kline and Wormser pointed out that the problem can only be solved by creating a fund for this purpose. The Executive Director remarked that such a fund was in contemplation as soon as conditions permitted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
