<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-21">June 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Two Important Books for Intellegent Men and Women</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Haim Malitz (Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-21">June 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TWO IMPORTANT BOOKS FOR INTELLEGENT MEN AND WOMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Haim Malitz (Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scriptures For God And Man--sermons and speeches for each weekly section of the Pentateuch. A source of knowledge, wisdom, and wit, for rabbis, presidents, welfare workers, and especially for intelligent people who must or wish to stand before an audience and speak, and call forth recognition and admiration.</p>
   <p>It is a book from which you can learn much for yourself and draw knowledge to teach others. It is a marvelous work, beautifully printed and bound. Price--$1.50</p>
   <p>The Home And The Woman--a book written specifically in the interests of family life, and dedicated to the women as the true martyrs that give their lives for <pb facs="5423972_5_1124.jpg" n="2"/>humanity, and do not receive enough recognition for their work. It is a wonderful piece of work that should be found in every home. It comes magnificently bound. Price--$1.50</p>
   <p>Perpetuate your name through great works. The greatest wish of an intellegent person is to perpetuate his or her name through great works, so that children and grandchildren may proudly point to it and say: "Here is printed my father's or my mother's name in honor and glory."</p>
   <p>You can now attain this perpetuity at the following place and in the following manner.</p>
   <p>These two works will be definitely completed in the press and the bindary about the first week in Elul [August-September]. And everyone that will subscribe and pay for these books during the next fifteen days in Av [July-August] will have his or her name perpetuated. For I shall print in the books the names of all those subscribers who will send in their remittance before the <pb facs="5423972_5_1125.jpg" n="3"/>fifteenth day of Av.</p>
   <p>Whatever book you will subscribe to, in that book will you have your name printed. If you subscribe to both books, your name will be printed in both books.</p>
   <p>Checks and money orders should be addressed to: C. Malitz, 285 Hewes Street, Brooklyn, New York.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
