<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-15">Sept. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Shelter Home Will Be Turned into Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-15">Sept. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SHELTER HOME WILL BE TURNED INTO TALMUD TORAH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night, several hundred of the most prominent Jews of Chicago, officers of local Orthodox congregations, gathered at a mass meeting at the Waller Street Talmud Torah, and ironed out the matter of the shelter home very satisfactorily.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Weil was chairman of the meeting, and Mr. Paul Rissman acted as secretary. As soon as the meeting opened, everyone present felt a strong desire to settle the matter peacefully. When a motion was made to the effect that Chicago should have only one shelter home, everyone applauded. This motion was made by Mr. H. Iglowitz, president of the new shelter home, and supported by Mr. Swartz, chairman of the building committee of the new shelter home.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the various congregations approved this motion, and then another was made and unanimously adopted. The second motion declared that the Jewish community of Chicago recognized the shelter home on Morgan Street as the only authorized one; that it belonged to all the Jews of Chicago and must be <pb facs="5423972_5_1626.jpg" n="2"/>supported by them.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Ephraim Epstein said that a conference had been held between both groups [Translator's note: One group was in favor of having another shelter home, and the other was in favor of a Hebrew school], before the mass meeting began. At this conference, it was decided that the building, which had been intended for a shelter home, should be converted into a Talmud Torah. This recommendation was presented at the meeting in the form of a motion, which was unanimously adopted, without debate.</p>
   <p>After these motions had been adopted, and peace had been established, the question arose as to who should be responsible for the completion of the Talmud Torah. This question was quickly answered when Mr. Sam Ginsberg suggested that this matter should be turned over to the Jewish community itself. Let the community elect a committee made up of one representative from each congregation in Chicago. This committee should take up the question of raising the required <pb facs="5423972_5_1627.jpg" n="3"/>sum of money for the completion of the building, in order to make it a beautiful and modern Talmud Torah. The delegates at the meeting accepted this proposal.</p>
   <p>Action on this question, however, must not be delayed because thousands of dollars have already been tied up in this building. It was finally resolved, therefore, that this committee, which shall be composed of representatives from all the synagogues in Chicago, should hold a general meeting this Sunday, at 3 P. M., in the Waller Street Talmud Torah, where they would take up the question of raising funds for the completion of the building as a Talmud Torah. All synagogues are requested to send delegates to this meeting.</p>
   <p>Many of the speakers remarked that last night's meeting was the finest meeting ever held by the Jewish community of Chicago. It will go down as a glorious chapter in the history of local Jewish life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
