<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-01">May 1, 1927</date><title level="a">Our Thirtieth Anniversary</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Abraham Cahan, Editor-in-Chief of Forward</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-01">May 1, 1927</date><title level="a">OUR THIRTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Abraham Cahan, Editor-in-Chief of Forward</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is thirty years today since a group of men and women, of whom the writer is one, founded the Forward. The Forward was called into being for a double purpose: (a) To organize the Jewish workers into trade unions and disseminate the principles of Socialism among them. (b) To act as an educational agency among the immigrant Jewish masses in the broadest sense of the word, and to spread among them high ideals of humanity.</p>
   <p>Thirty years is a long time in the life of an individual; yet it is a very short period in the life of a movement or people. The last thirty years have been uncommonly rich in stirring events. The past decade will go down in history as perhaps the most eventful period of all time. Politically speaking, and to a large extent economically as well, vast upheavals have taken place.</p>
   <p>The Jewish immigrant from Russia has undergone great vicissitudes during the last three decades. The Forward has been a living mirror of events in <pb facs="5423972_5_0821.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish life. It has remained true to the ideals which inspired its founders a generation ago, but it also kept abreast of the progress of events. As a consequence it has been growing stronger, and more influential from year to year.</p>
   <p>The founding of the Forward was made possible through the self sacrifice of the Jewish working men and women who gave up their bank accounts, engagement rings and trinkets and in this way scraped together the necessary amount to start the paper. Today the Forward has a circulation of more than 200,000 copies daily, devoting much of its profits to the labor movement and other worthy causes.</p>
   <p>The Forward today is what it always has been - a Socialist organ and promoter of culture among the masses. Its principle and program are identical with those of the Great British Labor Party. The numerous changes during the past decade have brought new needs and problems, and the Forward has been quick to meet them. Thirty years ago the Forward was a paper for immigrants only. Today it is read by very many American citizens, a large <pb facs="5423972_5_0822.jpg" n="3"/>proportion of whom are Americanized in the best sense of the word. Not only the parents, but their American born children as well, find in the English section of the Sunday Forward a much needed organ of discussion, entertainment and intellectual and literary interests.</p>
   <p>On the occasion of the 30th birthday of the Forward, I extend hearty greetings to all our readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
