<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-11">Mar. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Talmud Torahs Will Remain with the United Jewish Charities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-11">Mar. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE TALMUD TORAHS WILL REMAIN WITH THE UNITED JEWISH CHARITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Association of Rabbis met yesterday afternoon at two o'clock at the Hebrew Theological College to consider the situation that has arisen as a result of Rabbi [Judah Leb] Gordon's decision regarding the Talmud Torahs and the United [Jewish] Charities. Only two members of the Association of Rabbis were absent. Rabbi Judah Leb Gordon was chairman of the meeting. The entire discussion centered around his decision. Rabbis [Ephraim] Epstein, [Saul] Silber, [Samuel] Shach, [A.] Rubenstein, [Abraham] Cardon, [A. R.] Mushkin, and [J.] Goldman participated in the discussion, which was very heated and at times stormy. The following prominent citizens also took part in the discussion: Mr. B. Horwich, Mr. Gray, Dr. S. M. Melamed, and Mr. M. P. Ginsburg.</p>
   <p>The rabbis attempted to find a compromise between the decision of Rabbi <pb facs="5423972_5_1226.jpg" n="2"/>Gordon and the program of the Charities regarding the management of the Talmud Torahs. Mr. Horwich pointed out in his speech that there is no ground for the fear that the Charities will interfere in educational matters. Dr. Melamed and Mr. Gray laid stress upon the agreement of last Tuesday's conference, at which three rabbis accepted the agreement, since they did not protest it. Both speakers declared emphatically that we must not estrange ourselves from the Charities, as long as the Charities have done nothing wrong. We must take a chance upon an agreement made with an honest group of people. There will be time to protest if the Charities do not abide by the agreement and interfere in [Jewish] education. The rabbis, with the exception of Rabbi Silber, repeated their old complaints, but expressed the opinion that something must be done to get out of this unpleasant situation.</p>
   <p>The rabbis made various proposals for arriving at an understanding. Rabbi Gordon declared that if the conditions which the Charities imposed remain unchanged, he would be unable to change his decision. His chief objection <pb facs="5423972_5_1227.jpg" n="3"/>was that he felt that the Reform Jews will have a voice in the appointment of Talmud Torah teachers. Rabbi Gordon declared that he would modify his decision if the Charities would modify that condition.</p>
   <p>At last a proposal was adopted that the chairman of the Committee on Education of the Charities should issue an official assurance that the necessary approval of newly appointed teachers would not be given by one person alone, but by a Committee of fourteen, of which seven would be representatives of Chicago Orthodoxy.</p>
   <p>This proposal was adopted and we hear that Mr. James Davis declared that he was willing to issue such a declaration, but that he would await the return of Dr. [Alexander] Dushkin, who left Monday for New York, to issue such a declaration.</p>
   <p>The incident which arose last Friday, is thus closed. The committee of five can now go on with its work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
