<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-13">Feb. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Bezalel Exhibit</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-13">Feb. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BEZALEL EXHIBIT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Jewry is now ruled by a holiday spirit. From Jerusalem, the country for which the soul covets and longs, friendly and hearty greetings came in the form of the exhibit of the Bezalel's antiques, and every Jew, man or woman, attired in holiday raiment, goes to see it and admire the fine artistic work the Bezalel [Palestine's Art School] creates for the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>It is a beautiful holiday filling us with hope and comfort. The Bezalel, with its exhibits, reminds the Jews living in Diaspora that the Jewish spirit is awakening to new life, that there, in Jerusalem, dwell Jewish artists creating art that will kindle the light of Jewish national reminiscence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0053.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And if there are still people who believe that the Jews have no art whereby to express their characteristics and culture, let them visit the Bezalel Exhibit and see what the Jewish intellect can create and how far aesthetic art has advanced among the Jews.</p>
   <p>The holiday of the Bezalel Exhibit, becomes even more exalted to us when we consider the twofold practical value of it. Everybody now has the opportunity to bring home an embellishment which will beautify it, giving it a typically Jewish appearance that will always keep him in close contact with the Jewish art temple, and which shall portray to his children the aesthetics in which the Jews are engaged.</p>
   <p>The second value is even more important, in that this exhibit demonstrates that Bezalel is not a dream, that Professor Shatz's (the founder) idea of a Jewish art temple is now a reality, a fact which goads us forward to do everything within our means to help the Bezalel School stand on a higher plane and on firmer foundations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0054.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The holiday of the Bezalel Exhibit in Chicago has proved that all Jews regardless of personal convictions, give the exhibit such a character as will make Professor Shatz deeply feel that he is not alone, that the thousands of Jews in Chicago, like the Jews of other cities and countries, are taking a warm and active part in this sacred work; that here in Chicago we know how to estimate and respect that which is so significant to Jewish culture.</p>
   <p>That is why the Bezalel is so popular among the Jews in Chicago. Everyone considers it his duty to attend and to purchase antiques from it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
