<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1926-05-11">May 11, 1926</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1926-05-11">May 11, 1926</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An outline of the courses to be included in the department of cultural studies is herewith presented:</p>
   <p>Literature. Course in the history of English literature from the early beginning through the Elizabethan Age. This course will include particularly a study of Chaucer and Shakespeare; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>History of English literature, from the Puritan Age to the Modern Period. Special emphasis on the study of Byron, Keats, Shelley, and the contemporary dramatists; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>Contemporary literature. A special course of lectures, discussions and readings in contemporary literature. English and American works will be the basis, with some attention to the continental schools. The background of our contemporary writers and their works will be emphasized. Poetry, fiction, drama, and art will feature the calendar of the course in contemporary literature. Class sessions weekly on Sunday evenings; twenty sessions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>French I. Course in elementary French is being offered under the instruction of one who has studied and traveled in France; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>Science. The Essentials of Modern Physics I. A study of the elements of the science of physics. Discusses the why and wherefore of mechanics, force, motion, machines, heat, etc.; sixty sessions of double periods, including individual work in the laboratory.</p>
   <p>Principles of Chemistry I. Study of the elements in nature and of the human body; the action of the air; gases and their measurements, the composition of water, the atomic and molecular theories, the composition of various chemicals, etc. Sixty sessions of double periods - individual work in the laboratory.</p>
   <p>Botany I. Study of the origin of plant life, various forms of plant life. Study of specimens of plants and flowers. Weekly field trip to Forest Preserves, Botanical Gardens, etc.; eighty-four sessions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1199.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Physiology I. A study of the structure of the human body, its functions, and the principles of hygiene in the home and the community; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>The History of Greek Civilization. The ancient East and its civilizations; art, literature, philosophy and culture of ancient Greece; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>The History of Medieval Times I. A study of the decline of the Roman Empire. the rise of the Papacy, conflict between church and state, Feudalism, the Renaissance, the Protestant Reformation, the Rise of New Powers; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>The History of Modern Times II. Wars and revolutions, the rise of modern states, the break-up of feudal institutions, the Age of Science and Discovery, the French Revolution, the Napoleonic Era, the Industrial Revolution, the Revolution of 1848, the Rise of Modern Nationalism, economic expansion, world's conflicts, modern social movements, World's War; sixty sessions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1200.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>American History I. European backgrounds, the Era of Colonization, the Settlement of the Atlantic seaboard, the American Revolution, the organization of the Federal Government, national expansion, etc.; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>Civics I. An elementary course in the principles of the American government; community life and problems, introductory to more advanced courses in the organization and functions of federal, state and city governments, and the study of social life and institutions; sixty sessions.</p>
   <p>This is an age of science and invention. It is an age of learning and specialization. The papers write about the theory of relativity, the principles of synthetic chemistry, quantitative measurements in economics, business cycles. It is becoming increasingly difficult to follow even the newspapers intelligently without some grounding in the elements of science, history and literature. Here is an opportunity to get at these things from the bottom up. A mastery of elementary principles is essential to an understanding of the more advanced theories.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1201.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>One of these special study classes that has been very successful and has interested a rather large group of intelligent young men and young women is the course in Contemporary Literature, 1890-1925, given every Sunday evening during the winter semester. The subject is presented by means of lectures and discussions. Mimeographed outlines of the subject to be discussed are distributed. An informal social hour concludes the meeting. The following is an outline of the work:</p>
   <p>I. Introduction. Background. The Receding Giants: Meredith, Swinburne, Henry James, Mark Twain, Thomas Hardy and the philosophy of fatalism, Fess, Jude, The Return of the Native.</p>
   <p>II. Samuel Butler, satire, audacity, paradox, common sense, humor, epigram, influence on G. B. Shaw and Gilbert Cannon. The Way of All Flesh; The Notebooks; Erewhon.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1202.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>III. Oscar Wilde and the Nineties; Fin de Sieclisme; Decadence, The Nineties in America, Wilde's Picture of Dorian Gray; Beerbohms' Zuleika Dobson; Morrison's Tales of Mean Streets; The Savoy, the Yellow Book.</p>
   <p>IV. Movements. (a) Poetry: John Davidson; Francis Thompson; Lionel Johnson; the Catholic Movements; Yeats, Bridges, The Shropshire Lad. (b) Art: Aubrey Beardsley. (c) Drama: Wilde; Jones; Pinero; Sutro; Synge; early G. B. Shaw.</p>
   <p>V. The influence of the Nineties. Theory of naturalism. Symbolism. Socialism in Shaw; Dandyism in Max Beerbohm; Imperialism in Kipling; Optimism in R. L. Stevenson; Naturalism in Mangham and Dreiser; Romanticism in Stevenson and his followers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1203.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>VI. William Henry Hudson: The vitality of Romanticism, nature, style. Green Mansions, El Hombre.</p>
   <p>VII. Joseph Conrad: The Polish sailor who appreciated life in pictures of exquisite form and proportion. The careful artist who thought in French and wrote in English. The world as a spectacle. Influence of Flanbert, Dostoiensky, Youth, Lord Jim, Nostromo, etc.</p>
   <p>VIII. Bennett, Wells and Galsworthy. (a) Wells: Scientifically trained liberal. The journalist in literature. Through Science to Socialism, to aristocracy, to utopianism. Tono Bungay, Research Magnificent, New Machiavelli, Outline of History. (b) Bennett: The solidarity of the English Middle Classes, The Old Wives Tales. (c) Galsworthy, novelist, dramatist, essayist, poet, stylist, The Forsythe Saga, Justice.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1204.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>IX. Dreiser: Naturalism and its American predecessors, Crane, Pierce, Morris; influence, problems, pessimism, rank; The Genius. Criticism in America. European Naturalism. Hamson.</p>
   <p>X. Willa Cather. Epics of women and some men. Compare her treatment of the Middle West with that of Hamlin Garland, and her attitude and style with that of Edith Wharton. The note of poignant regret: Optima dies prima fucit. Compare with Sheila Raye Smith. O'Pioneers, The Song of the Lark, My Antonia, The Lost Lady, The Professor's House.</p>
   <p>XI. H. D. Lawrence and Sherwood Anderson. Psychology and sex. Psychoanalysis and literature. The maturity of the American novel. Psychological naturalism. Lawrence: Sons and Love, Women in Love; Anderson: Winesburg, Ohio; The Triumph of the Egg, Heroes and Men.</p>
   <p>XII. The New Romance, James Branch Cabell, Robert Nathan, Don Byrne, <pb facs="5423972_5_1205.jpg" n="9"/>Joseph Hergesheimer. Cabell: Romantic realist, the economic theory of literature, Cream of the Jest, Jurgen, Figures of Earth. Hergesheimer: A sophisticated romantic, half artist, half charlatan, Three Black Bennys, Linda Condon.</p>
   <p>XIII. The new poetry, 1912. Poetry, a magazine of verse. Ezra Pound, Des Imagistes: free verse. French influence, Spoon River Anthology.</p>
   <p>XIV. A survey of contemporary American poetry. Frost and Robinson. New England, Sandburg and Lindsay; Chicago, Edna Millay and Elinore Wylie, heart and mind. F. S. Eliot and E. S. Commings; new writers.</p>
   <p>XV. Recent tendencies in the American theatre. The little theatre. Foreign influences. Susan Glaspell, Eugene O'Neill, Realism and Naturalism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1206.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>XVI. The new biography. Essayists and belles lettres. Lytton Strachey, Queen Victoria, Eminent Victorian.</p>
   <p>XVII. The literature of insurgency. Floyd Dell. Main Street. Miss Lulu Bett, Ben Hecht: Bodenheim, 1920. Aldous Huxley's Antic Ilay. European corollaries, Rolland, Hauptman, Strindberg, Ibsen.</p>
   <p>XVIII. The Irish movement. Celticism. (a) Poetry: Yeats, A. E. and Stephens; (b) Drama: Synge, Yeats, Colum, Lady Gregory, Drinsany. (c) Fiction: Moore Stephens.</p>
   <p>XIX. Ireland in the world, Joyce, Ulysses.</p>
   <p>XX. General resume of course. A glimpse into the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
