<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-28">Apr. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Hatikvah on the Stage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-28">Apr. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">HATIKVAH ON THE STAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To see 1000 or 1200 persons on a Thursday afternoon in a packed theatre, and all Jews who had come to see a dramatic portrayal of Hatikvah (Jewish national anthem), is, of itself, surprising. But a much greater surprise is the production itself, particularly since it comes to us quite unexpectedly, and from a class from whom we would least expect such a production.</p>
   <p>Usually, it is assumed that the South Side Jews of the well-to-do class, particularly the German Jews, are as far removed from concern about Zion and the hope of a Messiah, as East is from West. From outward appearances, this would seem to be the case. That which is usually heard from the pulpits in the Temples will not satisfy the listener's desire for the ancient Jewish ideal, for a homeland in Palestine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this reason the performance of the one-act play, "Hatikvah," yesterday at the Chicago Art Institute, must have been a tremendous surprise to the large audience, chiefly composed of American-German Jews, both men and women. This was more of a religious service than a theatrical performance, although Greek art in the form of dancing was commingled with the deep Jewish content of the masterpiece. Even the Jewish songs, "Palaces of Stone" and "On The Forepart of an Oven Burns A Fire" which were sung in a somewhat Germanic style, evoked deep feeling and typically Jewish sentiment.</p>
   <p>The symbolism of the entire play--the young daughter, "Zion," who is blind, regains sight when "Hatikvah" appears, the sanctity of the Sabbath which is observed without bread and wine, and the vision of the young daughter, "Zion," of a land and a home in the future--must have spoken forcefully to the hearts of the assembled Jews, even when the hope in their hearts has been long obscured. Many eyes were wet, and when the climax was reached, an atmosphere of sanctity pervaded the audience which kept them from applauding. Later, applause broke out when the playwright, Mrs. Jacob Abbet was presented to the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0434.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no doubt but that this performance, and the many others that will surely follow, will increase the membership of the Palestine Welfare Committee who arranged this program. It [the play] also suits the Jewish consciousness, and the love for Zion, even in those quarters where these sentiments have long been weakened. In this manner it will deliver a pertinent sermon which is not heard from the pulpits in the temples.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
