<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-06">Feb. 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Pleasant Surprise</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-06">Feb. 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEASANT SURPRISE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cantors' concert, under the direction of the famous conductor, Mr. Loew of New York, which took place last Sunday, was a very pleasant surprise to all lovers of Jewish music in Chicago. The concert, which was organized by the Douglas Park Day and Night Nursery with the co-operation of all the cantors in Chicago, would have convinced even the most skeptical that there is such a thing as Jewish music, which is worth cultivating. The concert proved that Chicago has cantors of whom it can be proud, as far as voice and musical talent are concerned. Mr. Loew himself was inspired by the material that he found in Chicago, and he believes that if the cantors would continue to work with the same seriousness as they did in preparation for the concert, they could accomplish wonders, and they would be able to introduce modern Jewish music in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The fact that Jewish music has not only a great cultural value, but also a great <pb facs="5423972_5_0358.jpg" n="2"/>educational value and that it can aid in attracting the youth to Judaism, makes the continuation of activity by the cantors very desirable.</p>
   <p>We hope that this city will appreciate the value of the cantors' talents and will give their efforts in this field attention and interest. The cantors know that the famous Loew is always willing to help them and they should take advantage of this willingness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
