<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-08">April 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Great Exhibition at the Hebrew Institute</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. Harry Lipsky Wants to Acquaint the Jewish Public of Chicago with the Riches and Life of a Large Area of the United States All Are Expected</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-08">April 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT EXHIBITION AT THE HEBREW INSTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. Harry Lipsky Wants to Acquaint the Jewish Public of Chicago with the Riches and Life of a Large Area of the United States ALL ARE EXPECTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To acquaint the Jewish masses of this city with the development of commerce and industry of the West, and to show the steps one must take in order to work oneself up, is the last plan to be carried out at the Hebrew Institute. The creator of this plan is Mr. Harry Lipsky, the associated superintendent of the institution. Mr. Lipsky is arranging an exhibition for which he is gathering numerous pictures representing in graphic form the wealth of the various states in the West, and he will be there to explain to the visitors the meaning of these pictures.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0766.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In this undertaking Mr. Lipsky received the cooperation of the large publishing houses, most of the railroad companies, mine owners, manufacturers, and farmers, and from all those who have been closely connected with the rapid growth of the wealthy regions in the country.</p>
   <p>Most of the pictures, and valuable materials linked with them, necessary to make this exhibition a success, have already been collected by Mr. Lipsky, and in several days an announcement will be made when the opening will take place.</p>
   <p>The exhibition at the Hebrew Institute will be called: "Industrial and Educational Museum." Through the pictures, maps, and literary works which are being gathered for this occasion, each visitor will get some idea of the activities and life of the Americans in the West, as well as to get a glimpse into the lives of those who live in the new states of Texas, Oklahoma, Colorado, Wyoming, Idaho, and Montana. The visitor will be shown, among other things, the development of various industries, such as horticulture, sugar plantations, cattle raising and modern farming.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
