<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-13">June 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Call to Hebraically and Nationally-Minded Jews in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-13">June 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A CALL TO HEBRAICALLY AND NATIONALLY-MINDED JEWS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At this time, when the Jewish people [as a whole] are living through a period of terrible destruction on the one hand, and national awakening and great hope on the other--we find that Hebrew literature in America has entered upon an era of revival and new fruitful activity. Upon the ruins of the Hebrew literature of Europe and Palestine, which has been restricted during the last four years by the terrible war, there has gradually begun to take shape in America the structure of the Hebrew language [sic].</p>
   <p>During the past three or four years, we have seen before us a phenomenon which has no equal in the whole history of American Judaism. In the last three or four years we have seen ,developing before our eyes, Hebrew magazines and newspapers which have gained a great number of readers. The American Hebraists, scattered in all corners of the land, had felt, until the last couple of years, lonely and forsaken, without any spiritual centers for their mental life. Now <pb facs="5423972_5_0688.jpg" n="2"/>they are organized and enjoy a lively and prolific activity.</p>
   <p>During the past few years there have already appeared several Hebrew enterprises that have succeeded in publishing several books. Thus they have enriched the field of Hebrew literature which, because of the war, had become forsaken and desolate.</p>
   <p>This splendid and promising phenomenon that fills the heart of every true Jewish nationalist with hope and pride, has also, however, its detrimental aspect. And that is that the activity of most of our American Hebraists is one-sided and is directed towards one end, and that is towards beautiful literature, belles-lettres, poetry, etc. The realm of Jewish knowledge, of the "Wisdom of Israel" has to date been neglected. The portals that should have been opened to us, portals leading to the great treasures of creative Jewish genius, have hitherto remained closed. Many [works] of the Jewish spiritual nobility, which have lit the long road from the Diaspora with their aura, <pb facs="5423972_5_0689.jpg" n="3"/>and are the foundation upon which Judaism exists, lie to this day scattered in dark dusty corners of libraries.</p>
   <p>And because of this isolation [of Jewish spiritual lore] there arose a danger that Jewish thought would become impoverished, that its clear spring, which had not ceased to flow during the whole period of the Diaspora, would, God forbid, dry up. In order to avert this great danger, the organization "Ashkoloth" was founded.</p>
   <p>The Ashkoloth Society assumed the task of issuing a whole series of important books in the field of the Wisdom of Israel. The Ashkoloth Society has assumed the task of creating in America a great spiritual center of Jewish thought. This society believes that just as it is the duty of the three million American Jews to preserve the physical life of the hundreds of thousands of our suffering and starving brothers and sisters abroad, so also is it their sacred <pb facs="5423972_5_0690.jpg" n="4"/>duty to strengthen them spiritually. And this can best be done by founding a large publishing house that can feed the Jewish spirit with the best creations of our great men in [the realm of] Hebrew spirit and thought.</p>
   <p>The Ashkoloth Society has been incorporated under the laws of the State of New York. Among its founders are renowned Hebraists and Jewish intellectuals who have placed it on a sound basis and a strong foundation. It appeals to all Hebraists in America to assist in this great permanent national work that this society has undertaken.</p>
   <p>Hebraists of America! Help erect the structure of the Hebrew culture.</p>
   <p>Hebraists of America! Buy shares of the Ashkoloth Society, become subscribers to the books which the Ashkoloth will publish. And thus help establish and strengthen a new center in America for the Hebrew language.</p>
   <p>With respect and friendly greetings</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0691.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Ashkoloth Society,</p>
   <p>159 East Broadway,</p>
   <p>New York City.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
