<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-17">Apr. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Big Crowd at the Laying of the Cornerstone of the Hebrew Theological College; Fifteen Thousand Dollars Raised</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-17">Apr. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A BIG CROWD AT THE LAYING OF THE CORNERSTONE OF THE HEBREW THEOLOGICAL COLLEGE; FIFTEEN THOUSAND DOLLARS RAISED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish Chicago yesterday had a great holiday; the cornerstone of the Hebrew Theological College, to be one of the most important institutions in Chicago, was laid at Douglas Boulevard and St. Louis Avenue.</p>
   <p>A large crowd of men and women gathered for the celebration in which all the rabbis of Chicago, all the synagogue presidents and representatives of various Jewish organizations, participated. The public expressed its enthusiasm for the new, great, and important institution by raising the sum of over fifteen thousand dollars for it, including the twelve thousand dollars in cash that was raised during the dedication ceremony.</p>
   <p>The ceremony began with a grand march by the children of the various Talmud <pb facs="5423972_5_1390.jpg" n="2"/>Torahs, pupils of the Etz Haim Seminary, and students of the Beth Midrash La-Rabbonim (theological seminary). The band of the marks Nathan Orphan Home marched ahead playing music. The line of march was from the Grenshaw Street Talmud Torah, via Roosevelt Road, Independence Boulevard, Douglas Boulevard to St. Louis Avenue, where the Hebrew Theological College is being built.</p>
   <p>Mr. B. Leizerowich, the president of the College opened the ceremony. He introduced the chairman of the building committee, Mr. B. Eisenstein, who in a few words reviewed the history of the building. The chairman of the program, Mr. Samuel Ginsburg, was then introduced. Rabbi Ezriel Epstein greeted the assembly and pointed out the importance of such an institution as the Hebrew Theological College, which will become the center of Talmudic education in the Middle West.</p>
   <p>Speeches were made by Rabbi B. Margolin, Rabbi Olshwanger, Rabbi Saul Silber, <pb facs="5423972_5_1391.jpg" n="3"/>Max Shulman, Joseph Weil, Abe Kaplan, M. Goodman, and others. Committees from various synagogues greeted the institution in the name of their synagogues and turned over their checks as a contribution from the synagogues to the institution.</p>
   <p>The following synagogues turned over their checks:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Kneseth Israel</cell>
     <cell>$1,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Beth Medrosh Hagudol</cell>
     <cell>1,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Shaarei Thora Anshei Maarov</cell>
     <cell>600</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Sholom</cell>
     <cell>500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Liebawitch</cell>
     <cell>500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Kehilath Jacob</cell>
     <cell>500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Motele</cell>
     <cell>200</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Mishne V'Gmoro</cell>
     <cell>200</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1392.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Atereth Isarel North Shore</cell>
     <cell>$200</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation B'Nai Isaac</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation B'Nai Reuben</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Vilna</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation B'Nai Israel</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation B'Nai Zion North Side</cell>
     <cell>50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Congregation Anshe Shavel V'Yanowo</cell>
     <cell>25.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Many synagogues announced that they were going to hold a meeting to decide upon the amount of their contribution, which they will promptly remit.</p>
   <p>Next on the program was the selling of cornerstones and windows of the institution. Mr. I. Shechtman paid $1,350 for the first cornerstone; Mr. B. Hindzel bought the second cornerstone for $1,000, and paid $200 for a window; the third cornerstone was bought by Mr. and Mrs. Jaffe for $400; the fourth, <pb facs="5423972_5_1393.jpg" n="5"/>by S. Goldman for $250; the fifth, Emil Braude for $250; the sixth, by N. H. Bolotin for $250; the seventh, by Leizerowich for $200.</p>
   <p>The windows were purchased by M. Sklamberg, Mrs. S. H. Cohen, N. H. Bolotin, and Mrs. Jaffe at $100 a window; Isidor Grant paid $75 for his window and Rabbi Margolin, M. Rubin, W. Miller, Max Shulman and others paid $50 a piece for a window.</p>
   <p>Various sums were contributed by individual persons. Mr. B. Horwich gave $250; Mr. B. Stone, $200, Abraham Gershon Shulman, $100; Michael Rosenberg, $100, and others. A detailed list of the contributors will be published in the Courier within a few days.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
