<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-01">June 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Help the Torah!</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Appeal by the Rabbis of Chicago]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-01">June 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">HELP THE TORAH!</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Appeal by the Rabbis of Chicago]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, the rabbis of Chicago, appeal to the Jews of Chicago to support the Torah.</p>
   <p>Today, Chicago is one of the leading Jewish cities [in the world], and Chicago should become a place for the Torah, a center of the Torah. Now, when we are celebrating the giving of the Torah to us [Translator's note: This appeal was published on the eve of the Feast of the Pentecost, which commemorates the giving of the Torah to the Jews], it is proper that every Jew should remember to disseminate the teachings of the Torah among the young Jewish generation in America, because only a generation raised on the Torah can assure the further existence of Judaism in America.</p>
   <p>A group of Chicago Jews, who are devoted to the Torah, decided, with the approval of the representatives of Orthodox Judaism, to build a Hebrew Theological <pb facs="5423972_5_1379.jpg" n="2"/>College in Chicago, a center for the Torah, which would accomodate beginners, advanced students, and scholars, who desire to devote themselves entirely to the study of the Torah. The building, a beautiful and noble building, will soon be ready if the Orthodox Jews of Chicago will do their duty and will support this great and important institution, whose task it is to raise a generation of lovers of the Torah in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Torah, which is the foundation of our existence as a nation, we appeal to you Chicago Jews: support the Hebrew Theological College; help create an institution which will enforce and strengthen Judaism in Chicago and will make our city a great center of the Torah. Everyone of you is duty-bound to give something for the Hebrew Theological College, because the Hebrew Theological College should be the institution of the entire Orthodox community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Do your duty as Jews! Come to the aid of the Torah! And may you witness, as <pb facs="5423972_5_1380.jpg" n="3"/>a reward, the redemption of Zion and Jerusalem!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
