<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-27">Mar. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Lawndale Theater Is Making Preparation for Passover</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-27">Mar. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAWNDALE THEATER IS MAKING PREPARATION FOR PASSOVER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A splendid, festive program of entertainment will be presented in the Lawndale Theater, on the second night of the Passover. Theater lovers will enjoy a very interesting melodrama with delightful music. Jennie Goldstein, popular Jewish actress, will play the leading role. The name of the play is, "Her Golden Dream."</p>
   <p>Miss Goldstein made a big hit with this role in New York, and it is certain that she will be a big success in Chicago also.</p>
   <p>This noted actress has been absent from Chicago for the last three years. During those years Miss Goldstein played on the English stage with enviable success.</p>
   <p>The length of Miss Goldstein's stay in Chicago is not determined as yet. However, she may perform here for at least six weeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0409.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Goldstein is beginning her performance Thursday night.</p>
   <p>The coming program in the Lawndale Theatre will include Morris Schwarts, Molly Picon, and Michael Michalesco.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday night, the well-known Celia Adler bid farewell to her Chicago fans. The theater was filled with admirers who came to say good-by, to her, and also to see her in the title role of "Street Women."</p>
   <p>The plot of the show was gay and sad in turn. The performance was splendid. Miss Adler was unique in her role.</p>
   <p>The artistic performances of the two famous Hebrew actors, formerly with the Moscow Art Theater, and later with the Habima, have aroused great interest among the intelligent theater patrons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0410.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These noted artists were highly praised for their artistic performances by Gorki, Stanislavsky Shaliapin and noted Jewish critics.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vardi is an exceptional comedian, his characterizations bringing laughter and happiness to his audiences.</p>
   <p>Madam Yoliet will recite passages from the Bible and also Hebrew poems from classical and modern Palestine.</p>
   <p>Vardi will play roles from his own plays. He will perform scenes from the Russian Revolution and show pictures of American-Jewish life and scenes from Italy and Palestine.</p>
   <p>Among his popular presentations will be the "Jewish Mother;" "Trotzky near the Red Square;" "The Japanese and the Jen Tribes;" "Three and Four;" "Sabbath in a small Town," and numerous other worth while and entertaining numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
