<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Notice to All Hebraists in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A NOTICE TO ALL HEBRAISTS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comrades, Hebraists! The greatest Jewish spiritual center, which was an inexhaustible source of spiritual nourishment for the whole Jewish Diaspora, has been totally destroyed by the violence of our Jewish renegades. Our national Hebrew educational institutions have been forced, through a barbaric decree, to close their doors. Our Hebrew publications have been confiscated, and the works of our talented poets and writers are to be found in stables; the immortal work of our old, and yet eternally young, literature is being destroyed by the Jewish "Jesuits." The Jewish spiritual home in Russia has been totally destroyed.</p>
   <p>But in spite of the machinations of the Jewish apostates, the Hebrew literature and the Hebrew movement live on. Our national poet, H. N. Bialik has founded the publication Hadavar, which is to serve as a rallying point for the renaissance of our literature. Even here in America, in the land of our spiritual poverty, the first faint traces of a Hebrew movement have begun to appear. We, the <pb facs="5423972_5_0591.jpg" n="2"/>Hebraists of Chicago, are the only ones who sit with folded hands and do nothing. We are "platonic friends" who sometimes lament our poverty and let it go at that. It seems to be high time that a Hebrew Center was organized in our city, which could become a torch of light for our Hebrew movement and all its branches.</p>
   <p>A group of Hebraists in Chicago have undertaken the task. At the first meeting which took place January 7, the Hebrew Center was founded. It already has many members. The society, "Lovers of Hebrew," entered as a unit into the new organization, which, from now on, will be known as the Hebrew Center.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, appeal to all Hebraists in Chicago: Come to our great organizational meeting to be held Saturday evening, January 21, in the hall of the Kehilath Jacob Talmud Torah, at Hamlin Avenue and Douglas Boulevard. Dr. S. M. Melamed, Dr. A. Levinson, and Dr. A. Agranot will be the speakers. Come, help us create a Hebrew Center in Chicago!</p>
   <p>M. A. Brams, president,</p>
   <p>A. Katz, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
