<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-16">Apr. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Shortage of a Library</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-16">Apr. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE SHORTAGE OF A LIBRARY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Public Library of Chicago, in recent years has conducted its affairs on modern business principles. It publicizes its reading material and seeks to attract an even larger number of children to its various branches throughout the city. It takes pains to reach the masses who cannot come to the local centers. First comes the downtown library and then many branches in different localities of the city. When it is found that the patronage is too small for the establishment of a branch library, it opens up delivery stations and traveling libraries. We are at a loss for an explanation why the board of directors of this energetic institution is neglecting the opening of a branch library in such a large section of the city, as the Douglas Park neighborhood where there can be found many thousands of Jewish children who have always shown their eagerness for knowledge. Not only in this country, but in other countries also.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0744.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jewish district begins on the east side of Douglas Park and runs along the west side of 40th Ave. It is approximately twenty-five blocks in length and ten blocks in width. Its population will run into the tens of thousands who feel that they are being mistreated by the board of directors of the Chicago Public Library. The board certainly does not fail to do all it possibly can for many other neighborhoods in the city. This district which is settled by a much larger population is very much neglected. We find that the public library has many interesting books, such as German, Jewish-English, and much Jewish literature, too numerous to mention, which can be utilized in a new library branch in the Jewish district. So it is nothing but right and fair, that the Jews, who live in the Douglas Park district and who always did their part in carrying the burden of public duties should have the same library privileges as any other part of the city. The nearest branch for the Jewish inhabitants of the Douglas Park district is the Hebrew Institute. As even the most <pb facs="5423972_5_0745.jpg" n="3"/>eager readers are not very anxious to take the long walk to the Hebrew Institute; the result is that they get weaned away from reading and they spend their leisure time in other places which is not at all beneficial and very often detrimental to the upbuilding of the youth's character.</p>
   <p>The Jewish public in the district feel the lack of a library very keenly and claim that an injustice has been done to the Douglas Park district by the board of directors of the Public Library.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
