<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-10-07">Oct. 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">In the Chicago Hebrew Institute</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-10-07">Oct. 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE CHICAGO HEBREW INSTITUTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>English classes in the C.H.I. are being conducted with great success. Pupils have made remarkable progress in a short time. Classes are given four nights a week (Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and Thursday), from 7:30 to 9 P.M., both in the institute and in the evening high school, which opened recently. Among the various subjects taught there are German, advanced English, and mathematics.</p>
   <p>The public speaking class, headed by a competent instructor, is open every Sunday afternoon, from 2 to 4.</p>
   <p>The special attention given to the pupils in the shorthand and typing department, under teachers in this field, is the reason why students are progressing so rapidly. These classes are open Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and Thursday, from 7:30 to 9 P.M.</p>
   <p>Able instructors are also to be found in the millinery and dress-making classes, to which small girls and young women are attending regularly. The millinery class is open Tuesday and Thursday evening and the dress-
<pb facs="5423972_5_1611.jpg" n="2"/>making class on Monday and Wednesday evening.</p>
   <p>Parents desirous of giving their children an education in the Hebrew language, should remember that there are special classes for this purpose in the Hebrew Institute. These classes are open daily from 4 to 6 P.M.</p>
   <p>If you notice in your children an inclination to music, bring them to the Institute. There are violin and piano classes. The violin class is open every Tuesday afternoon, from 3:30 to 6, and the piano class every afternoon, from 3:30 to 6.</p>
   <p>There is quite a large number of children inclined to painting and in the Institute they would have the opportunity to develop their talent. Lessons in sketching and painting for beginners are being given in the art and clay rooms by a talented instructor. The clay classes are open on Mondays and Wednesdays, from 4 to 6, and the painting classes on the same days from 7:30 to 9 P.M.</p>
   <p>For further information apply at the office of the Hebrew Institute at any time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
