<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-09">Jan. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A Resolution Concerning Jewish Education in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-09">Jan. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A RESOLUTION CONCERNING JEWISH EDUCATION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Educational Council of the Rabbinical Association called a meeting for Monday, December 31, at nine o'clock in the evening, at the Hebrew Theological College. The meeting was attended by representatives of the Rabbinical Association, Hebrew teachers, synagogue presidents, and prominent citizens who are interested in the problem of Jewish education. The meeting, after hearing a report by Rabbi Ephraim Epstein on the plans of the Educational Council of the Rabbinical Association, and a report by Rabbi Saul Silber on the condition of Jewish education in Chicago, resolved, as follows:</p>
   <p>Whereas, Only ten per cent of all the Jewish children in Chicago receive a Jewish education; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The Jewish charities subsidize only one-half of all the Talmud Torahs of Chicago; and <pb facs="5423972_5_1284.jpg" n="2"/>Whereas, A community organization must exist to represent Jewish education before the broad Jewish masses, and to subsidize in part a number of Talmud Torahs, including the one in the Lawndale district; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That an Educational Council in the city shall immediately be organized, which shall include representatives of the Rabbinical Council, the Association of Hebrew Teachers, the Zionist organization, the Mizrachi [the Orthodox group of the Zionist movement], and the pedagogical institutions. The Council is to deal systematically with all problems relating to Jewish education in Chicago, its progress, development, organization, and so on.</p>
   <p>The meeting appointed a committee of seven to work out a program and to submit the material and plans before a large community meeting, which is scheduled to take place on Thursday, January 17, 1924.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
