<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-25">Feb. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">My Visit to the Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">By D. K</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-25">Feb. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MY VISIT TO THE ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By D. K</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After listening to the praises about the work for the education of our youth being carried on in the Alliance I determined to visit it in order to convince myself.</p>
   <p>I did so last Sunday morning, and what I saw and heard will linger in my memory for a long, long time. I went first to the National School, which conducts three classes. In the first class where Hebrew reading is taught, all children are beginners and for the short time that they have been there, they are progressing splendidly. In the second class Yiddish composition is taught, and in the third history.</p>
   <p>From there I went to the Sabbath School. In its hall there were a few <pb facs="5423972_5_1710.jpg" n="2"/>hundred children, who sang Anglo-Yiddish hymns and following that the teacher related an anecdote with reference to their subject. I eventually found my way into the Junior Club, a spirit of the Order Knights of Zion, consisting of children between 11 and 14 years of age, and which is under the supervision of Miss Sadie Dorf, L. Agranot, Mr. Eisner, and Mr. Becker. It would be seen that a Jewish generation was being reared here. This group have decided to perform a Purim Play with the intent of having the proceeds go for Palestine. Upon witnessing all the activities of the four hundred children, I sighed. I thought, if all our Northwest Side Jews would only send their children to the Jewish Alliance, we should need not fear that Judaism will die out. One division in the Alliance is worthy of mention, and that is the library, which is under the supervision of the Young Men's Hebrew Association. The library is at present very poor, having only 500 books. Efforts are being made, however, to raise a larger fund to purchase many more, and an appeal has been made to those <pb facs="5423972_5_1711.jpg" n="3"/>willing to donate books in Hebrew, Yiddish, English, and German. Such books may be forwarded to the Jewish Educational Alliance, 1243-49 N. Wood Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
