<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-16">July 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish and Other Education</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-16">July 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH AND OTHER EDUCATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Jewish school for boys and girls was opened a few months ago, in the Anshe Knessis Israel Synagogue. The writer of this article, (together with several other men and women), has noticed how the Jewish education of our youth is being neglected in that district. Our Maxwell Street Yankees around Douglas Boulevard are much more interested in a whist or poker game than in a Jewish school for their children. They think that their children do not need any Jewish training. We opened a school in the beautiful synagogue of that neighborhood, where children are taught history, religion and Hebrew. Real Jewish parents would approve <pb facs="5423972_5_1691.jpg" n="2"/>of this, and take great interest in such a school. But we find that only a few mothers and fathers are actually interested in it. Why isn't the attendance larger and why have so many children dropped classes? The school has qualified teachers who are devoted, heart and soul, to children's courses. In a short time the children have acquired a knowledge of many things concerning Judaism. As soon as it was mentioned that money was required for the support of the school the attendance began declining. And who dropped out? The wealthy children!</p>
   <p>Money can be had for everything; for music, and dancing, but when it comes to Jewish education only excuses are offered. How cheap Judaism has become to many of our parents. Don't you remember how your parents <pb facs="5423972_5_1692.jpg" n="3"/>would rather suffer than deprive you of a Jewish education? What will happen to our Judaism in the future, if we do not teach our children? You have such wonderful opportunities. You ought to praise highly your children's Jewish education. Don't lose so much in whist or poker games and pay a little more to the Hebrew Schools. Last week your children witnessed in their school, The Anshe Knessis Israel, how the elderly Jews celebrated, when they completed the study of the Talmud. But just think, who will study the Talmud a few years from now? Elderly Jews should not drive children from the synagogues. On the contrary, they should extend a welcoming hand to them. The rabbis and parents should cooperate with the teachers in their work.</p>
   <p>Be considerate with your Jewish teachers. Take an interest in the Sabbath and Hebrew schools and in the education of your children.</p>
   <p>Anna Goldberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
