<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1908-10-09">October 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Our Theatrical Benefit and Further Activities</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1908-10-09">October 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">OUR THEATRICAL BENEFIT AND FURTHER ACTIVITIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday night our entire family of the Jewish Labor World assembled at the Metropolitan Theatre for the benefit of our paper, the Jewish Labor World. When the audience came, we noticed that we have a big family. The theatre was filled to its capacity, hundreds of people were turned away.</p>
   <p>The performers did all in their power to make this benefit a success, each actor played his part to the best of his ability. The public left perfectly satisfied. Comrades Ziskind and Litman held short talks. A collection was made to cover the deficit that the paper had, and everybody marched out of the theatre with the orchestra playing the Marseillaise, feeling satisfied that the Labor World will continue to exist.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1004.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It now remains to our comrades and friends to take a little more interest in the Labor World. Each one who realizes the necessity of having such a weekly paper, should get to work and get subscribers. This is the main thing and easy to do.</p>
   <p>Each one of you have friends and acquaintances who read papers, talk it over with them, show them the importance of having a labor paper in Chicago, then you will get their subscriptions, especially now when the public is commencing to stay more and more at home and read more. That should make it very easy for our readers to obtain two thousand new readers in a month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1005.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If every one will do all he can, each one shall act as a free, willing, agent for for our paper - for your paper. This must be done without fail, if we want our paper to exist and to fulfill its mission.</p>
   <p>We have no capital, and we all know that our income is limited. We do not have the income which any one of the capitalist papers have, and for that reason, we appeal to you again.</p>
   <p>Comrades, you must take more interest in the paper than you have in the past. To you Socialist organizations, appeals the Jewish Labor World.</p>
   <p>The publishers of the Jewish Labor World ask that you read our appeal to yourself, and act as your heart and mind dictates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
