<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Festive Show Given Approval by Fifty Thousand Spectators</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Epic of a Nation" Staged Impressively</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH FESTIVE SHOW GIVEN APPROVAL BY FIFTY THOUSAND SPECTATORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Epic of a Nation" Staged Impressively</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About fifty thousand attended the great Jewish festive show "Epic of a Nation" at Soldiers' Field yesterday, with which the Jewish Day reached its highest point at the World's Fair. Four thousand years of the history of the Jewish people were symbolized in the show in a realistic manner. It found an enthusiastic reception on the part of the spectators.</p>
   <p>The individual episodes were carefully selected and arranged in accordance with historic facts. It resulted in portrayals which must have made an overpowering impression upon non-Jews.</p>
   <p>It is known that the Jewish people have behind them a history of tribulations and assaults inflicted upon them. Indeed, as indicated more than once, they are not fully spared from such trials even today. These various persecutions were vividly portrayed in scenes which took us back to the times of the <pb facs="5423972_5_0453.jpg" n="2"/>Spanish Inquisition in which Torquemada gave the Jews the alternative of either becoming converted to Christianity or being subjected to unspeakable tortures in the torture chambers.</p>
   <p>In this connection the choir intoned "Ei Maley Rakhamin," the hymn so well knownto every Jew, and which was made all the more impressive by the choir's being placed in deepest darkness while the altar, around which the singers were grouped, gleamed in a bright glow of fire.</p>
   <p>A later picture, based upon the predictions of the prophets who promised the Jewish people salvation and eternal peace, made an effective impression in a triumphant procession of torches, symbolizing the eventual triumph of the persecuted people. Still later, the festive show used Palestine as its background where the Jewish people had built homes and where they might be undisturbed in their peaceful modes of living.</p>
   <p>The finale was staged to pay homage to the land of the Stars and Stripes in which the Jewish people can enjoy full freedom, with equal rights guaranteed <pb facs="5423972_5_0454.jpg" n="3"/>them.</p>
   <p>The singing of the national anthem, "The Star-Spangled Banner," brought the imposing festival to an end.</p>
   <p>The show was preceded by speeches by Congressman Samuel Dickstein, and by the well-known Zionist, Alexander Kahn, both of whom were from New York. Dickstein pointed out that the next Congress will take issue with the Nazi propaganda and other un-American activities which have recently become noticeable in this country. Kahn directed his attack particularly against Hitler and the persecution of Jews in Nazi Germany, condemning both with the sharpest of phrases. Hitler's name was mentioned repeatedly by other speakers, too; but the audience took these remarks without any demonstrations, which would have created an unpleasant situation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
