<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-15">Nov. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A National Jewish Weekly in English in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-15">Nov. 15, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A NATIONAL JEWISH WEEKLY IN ENGLISH IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The East and West Publishing Company, with offices at 138 North La Salle Street, has issued the following statement: The East and West Publishing Company aims to publish a national Jewish weekly in English for the educated section of the Jewish population in America, and particularly for the Jews who do not read Hebrew or Jewish and who have to be enlightened about our problems.</p>
   <p>The new Jewish weekly, East and West, will, like a mirror, reflect the entire life of our people in the East and the West. Its platform will be:</p>
   <p>1. To preserve historical Judaism.</p>
   <p>2. To fight for Jewish Solidarity.</p>
   <p>3. To enlighten our readers concerning all national Jewish problems in all the lands of the Diaspora and in Palestine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>4. To acquaint the educated Jewish groups in America with all the tendencies and currents in the life of our people and with the spirit of the new Hebrew culture.</p>
   <p>5. To fight against all the destructive tendencies in the spiritual life of our people.</p>
   <p>Dr. S.M. Melamed has been entrusted with the editorship of the East and West. P.S. Rudens is associate editor. The following will be the steady contributors to the East and West:</p>
   <p>Israel Zangwill, Max Nordav, Hakam, Dr. Moses Gaster, Nahum Sokolow, Dr. Abraham Lipski, Louis Lipski, Dr. Frank Rosenblatt, Professor M. Slonimski, Dr. Isaak Milner, Dr. M. Berenfeld, Dr. Nahum Goldman, Dr. Jacob Klatzkin, Dr. Joseph Klausner, Dr. David Star-Jordan, Dr. Abraham Levinson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1036.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The first issue of East and West will appear in December. With the appearance of East and West, Chicago will become the greatest center of American-Jewish journalism.</p>
   <p>Edward Katzinger, president,</p>
   <p>Max Shulman, vice-president,</p>
   <p>Alex Eisenstein, treasurer,</p>
   <p>David Pollack, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
