<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is no surprise to find a Jewish newspaper in America containing, in addition to its usual reading matter, an English section also. The surprising thing is that the venture is successful. Thus the English page of the Courier is a success--a very great success. This is so because the editorials offer a wealth of material and the articles throughout its other columns are selected, and because the public has shown great interest in them.</p>
   <p>With every mail, the letter carrier, brings stacks of congratulations from readers of this English page. Neither does he fail to bring contributions from talented English readers both locally and from other <pb facs="5423972_5_0911.jpg" n="2"/>states where the Courier is read.</p>
   <p>Since the advent of the English page our circulation department has been busier than ever before, taking large orders from newsdealers and filling those orders that call for delivery either by carrier or by post. We can truthfully say that, whereas formerly there was one reader for every copy of the Courier, there are now many more per copy. These are [new readers] the children of the older readers to whom the Jewish language is unfamiliar.</p>
   <p>Yes, it is for these sons and daughters of Jewish parents that the publisher of this newspaper introduced the English page, in order that he might keep them in contact with Jews and their interests. Neither had he <pb facs="5423972_5_0912.jpg" n="3"/>far to seek for an editor. His own editor of the Jewish Courier, Dr. S. L. Melamed, also fills this capacity for the English page adding therein his unusual adroitness and ability. Dr. Melamed is a great editor in English as well as in German, Yiddish, and Hebrew. He writes in all these languages for various newspapers and journals in addition to the daily articles written for the Courier. That Dr. Melamed can write, especially that he has something to write about, is attested by those buying this newspaper and by those who peruse the famous American Jewish Chronicle (in English) of which he was editor.</p>
   <p>It is the object of Dr. Melamed, by means of the English page, to keep young American Jews of Chicago and of the Middle West in contact with Jewish life, Jewish traditions, and Jewish aims, and thus induce them to take an active interest in all matters pertaining to Judaism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0913.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And, by the way, Jewish readers of the Courier enjoying our Jewish news and literary items can now share these joys with their children and friends who read only the English page. Many articles from the pens of Mr. Leon Zolotkof, Dr. Margolin, S. Greenblue, Dr. M. L. Kord, M. Indritz, Dr. Morris Reinhardt, and others will appear in English on the English page as well. The two Galician Jews who have won so much popularity for their wit and tricks in the weekly Courier will not fail to appear on the new sheet.</p>
   <p>Our young generation, the American born and reared Jewish sons and daughters, and all who now read the Courier's English page will acquire thereby the spirit and knowledge of the various Jewish problems both in America and across the sea.</p>
   <p>All of us may congratulate ourselves upon this new undertaking. It is a</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
