<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 10th, 1914, the Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club of the Chicago Hebrew Institute will celebrate its fifth anniversary. The Club was organized five years ago by a few immigrant Jewish young men and women of this city. It is a self-supporting organization, which has received no support or assistance whatever from any outside sources.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club is the result of that general awakening of art feeling, and love of art pleasure that has penetrated the souls of our modern Russian-Jewish youth. It is the result of that wave of protest against the modern Yiddish Theatre, which is at the present time controlled by a few lucre-hungry individuals who produce such plays as appeal to the baseness and vulgarity of the mob and satisfy the appetite of the populace. This conviction tends inevitably to lower the standard of Yiddish dramatic literature in this country.</p>
   <p>The members of the Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club realize and are fighting for the recognition of the distinction between popular amusement and drama. In this connection it is important to quote the opinion of the greatest art critic the world has ever produced: John Ruskin. "All art which has for its purpose to amuse,and purposes amusement to its end, must be of an inferier <pb facs="5423972_5_0611.jpg" n="2"/>character, and is usually more harmful than good."</p>
   <p>The young men and women of the Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club advocate the freedom of modern Yiddish dramatist of portray all aspects of life, the freedom of phrase and style, and of all dramaturgic technique that makes for artistic drama, and in accordance with these views and aims they have produced plays that constitute the acme of modern Yiddish drama. Within the last few years they have produced such plays as God, Man and Devil, by Jacob Gardin; With The Current, by Sholem Asch; a dramatist whose plays have been translated from the Yiddish and played in the Royal Theater at Berlin; Hear, O Israel, by Osip Divov; The Sisters, by J. L. Peretz, The Brothers, by Abraham Reizin, and The Doctor, by Sholem Aleichem, the Mark Twain of modern Judea; German literature occasionally, and, at different intervals, the Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club has arranged literary evenings, when readings of the greatest Yiddish poets have been given by the most talented of its members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0612.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1911 and 1912, the Progressive Literary and Dramatic Club arranged a series of discussions of the modern drama and questions of dramaturgic technique and construction were intelligently discussed. The educational value of these discussions cannot be overestimated. This season the following plays will be produced: Hear, O Israel, by Osip Dimov; People, by Sholem Aleichem; The Eternal Song, by Mark Orenstein. With even more enthusiasm, the future work is being planned. Next season the Club will present Ibsen, Hauptman, Suderman, and Schnitzer, in Yiddish Translations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
