<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">What the Five Years of the Forward in Chicago Have Accomplished for the Labor Movement</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE FIVE YEARS OF THE FORWARD IN CHICAGO HAVE ACCOMPLISHED FOR THE LABOR MOVEMENT</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In celebrating the fifth anniversary of the Forward, it will not be amiss of the difficulties encountered in attempting to induce the Comrades of the New York Forward Association, to establish a daily periodical in Chicago with its own printing plant, and with expenses amounting to $200,000.</p>
   <p>The Jewish socialists and trade unionists of Chicago, always strived to possess a daily working paper in Chicago, and it was always their hope that the New York Forward would publish a paper in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The writer has at hand, a copy of a letter which Comrade Sam Golden, secretary of the board of directors of the Jewish Labor World, had sent to the Forward <pb facs="5423972_5_0844.jpg" n="2"/>Association in New York, demanding,on behalf of all Jewish Trade Unions, Workmen's Circle, branches, and the Socialist branches, the establishment of the Forward in Chicago as a daily newspaper.</p>
   <p>That was on October 20, 1914, more than nine years ago. At that time, a conference was already organized to collect money for publishing a daily newspaper in lieu of the weekly Jewish Labor World.</p>
   <p>The Comrades of New York were, however, at that time, unable to undertake such a difficult task, and they did not accept our proposal.</p>
   <p>In 1916, we began anew our transactions with the Forward Association of New York, and Comrade Held, manager at that time of the Forward, came to Chicago, and at a conference of delegates from all parts of our movement, promised that we would have our own daily newspaper, if onlythe technical side of the issue will be met to the satisfaction of the Forward Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0845.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our hopes, however, were in vain, due to certain impediments that barred the publication of the Forward in Chicago. The Socialist movement of Chicago was unwilling to wait, and we, ourselves, undertook to publish a daily paper, The World, which existed for one year and nine months.</p>
   <p>The first number of the Forward appeared January 1, 1919, in Chicago, and our movement was liberated from the burden of supporting a daily periodical.</p>
   <p>Who brought the Forward to Chicago and why? The answer is:- The Jewish organized labor movement, the trade unions, the Workmen's Circle and the Socialist branches influenced the Forward to establish itself in Chicago, to serve the movement.</p>
   <p>Together with the general labor movement, which had undergone a crisis in the first few years after the war, the Jewish organized movement had also suffered very much.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0846.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The economic crisis compelled several large unions to accept a reduction in wages and a few small unions were weakened, due to the chaos that prevailed during the first few years after the war. However, most of the unions survived and determined to continue their services, to obtain higher wages and other improvements in labor condition.</p>
   <p>For the past five years, we have seen how the men's clothing workers of Chicago have enlarged their union from seven thousand to thirty five thousand members, and built an organization which surpasses that of all other cities of America, and despite the fact that the greatest percentage of members are not Jewish workers, the Jewish members are the most aggressive and active in the organization.</p>
   <p>The struggle to organize the clothing workers on as great a scale as they are now, was not a very easy task.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0847.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Clothing Manufacturers fought bitterly against the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union and against the leaders. They applied severe agitational methods to divide the workers in the shop.</p>
   <p>During the first few months of the Forward's appearance in Chicago, the greatest clothing manufacturers (with the exception of Harte, Schaffner and Max), carried on propaganda in the shops against the Jewish union leaders, among the gentile workers. They attempted to organize company unions, promising the workers prosperity, and representation by committees to deal with the management. Kuppenheimer, Alfred, Decker and Cohen, Charles Kaufman and Brothers, and several others mutually agreed and contrived several panaceas to bar the Amalgamated from organizing the workers. This, however, did not help them.</p>
   <p>A great number of workers were already members in the Amalgamated, and they declared a strike in their shops.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0848.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Throughout that strike, the manufacturers applied methods which indicated to what extremes the bosses will go to bring the workers under their yoke and control. One of the large concerns sent a letter to its employees which reads, in parts, as follows:-</p>
   <p>"Do you know that the organization to which you belong is being controlled by Russian Jews? (The firm is Jewish.) That's why Hart, Schaffner and Max signed an agreement with the Amalgamated. Ten percent of the workers were Jews, the other ninety percent were of different religions. But now, ninety percent of the workers at Hart, Schaffner and Max, are Russian Jews. If you do not believe this, see the names on the committees.</p>
   <p>"The Amalgamated Clothing Workers, is a scab organization, the letter reads on, and is not recognized by the American Federation of Labor. Do you know that there is no money in their treasury? That their treasury is in such condition that Hillman avoided any strikes until after May 1?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0849.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"Now answer the following questions:- Do you want to work in a shop that is being controlled by Russian Jews?</p>
   <p>"Why am I on strike?</p>
   <p>"How much have I lost by the strike?</p>
   <p>"What will I gain by it?</p>
   <p>"What protection can the Amalgamated offer me?"</p>
   <p>This is only a part of the letter that the large Jewish firms distributed to thousands of its now Jewish employees.</p>
   <p>The Forward, in that struggle between the employers and employees, as well as in all other struggles involving other workers, supported the workers with everything possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0850.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The influence that the Forward exerted at that time evidenced by a letter B. Kuppenheimer and Company sent to the Forward March 26, 1919, stating that they have not settled with the union and that they will always, as before, conduct open shops and will deal with the workers individually and not as an organized body.</p>
   <p>The result of the struggle which the Clothing Manufacturers carried on in 1919......their anti-semetic propaganda(they, themselves, being Jews who played the role of philantropists), their injunctions, their golden promises for profits and dividends in the business, was unsuccessful. The Amalgamated Clothing Workers triumphed and the Forward contributed its share in the struggle, as it does with every working class struggle.</p>
   <p>The same is seen when we relate the history of the Cloak Makers Union in Chicago, which had undergone in the past few years strikes and struggles to improve their conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0851.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>In 1919, the cloak makers were successful in introducing week work in the industry. Two years later, in 1921, the Cloak Manufacturers wanted to nullify their victory, by installing, anew, piece work, but the cloak makers defended the gained position, and did not permit the resumption of piece work.</p>
   <p>In this, as in all other events of the cloak makers, the Forward served as the organ and defender of the workers of the women's garment industry.</p>
   <p>The Jewish unions of the building trades, the carpenters and painters, have undergone a great struggle, which has required many sacrifices, and expenditure of much energy and money. The well known open-shop citizens committee, which was organized with the support of the enemies of organized labor, applied all methods that money could buy to force open shop conditions on the carpenters and painters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0852.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>To the credit of these two trades, the citizens committee did not develop its reactionary plan. It is, here, important to mention the Jewish bakers, the fur workers, the butchers and Shochtim, (Orthodox Butchers) Unions, the Retail Clerks Union, Cap Makers Union, Amalgamated, Cigar Makers Union, Cleaners and Dyers Union, Shoe Repair Union, and the youngest Jewish union, the Waiters Union.</p>
   <p>All these unions have, at various times during the last five years, struggled to improve their conditions, did not permit reductions in their wages, upheld union conditions, and withstood attacks by their bosses. The Forward was their place of shelter, and defence in all these struggles. The Chicago Forward has a portion in all their victories as one who struggled with and protected organized Jewish Labor in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The United Hebrew Trades, to whom the above unions belong, participated in all their activities and struggles which occured in the last five years and is convinced that the great assistance of the Forward to the unions, can not be measured.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0853.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>In concluding this survey, we wish to state that the Forward will continue to serve the interests of the organized labor, as it has served until now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
