<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-07-30">July 30, 1920</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1047</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1047.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-07-30">July 30, 1920</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"As I stand before God, I swear that I gave the editor of the "Courier" $50.00 to write an editorial for the Beth Hamedresh Larbonim." This oath was sworn by Rabbi Ephraim Epstein of the Beth Hamedresh Larbonim, at a meeting of the Rabbinate. "I gave this $50.00 to the editor in the office of the "Courier, in the presence of one of his assistants. While talking, the publisher of the paper entered. Immediately, the assistant covered the money with a newspaper." The Rabbi, then told the entire story how the "Courier" had attacked and reviled him and the other Rabbis.</p>
   <p>This meeting was called to take a stand against the hateful and continuing attacks by the "Courier" upon the Rabbinate and the others who oppose their deliverance into the hands of the political bossdom. The Rabbinate were unable to understand how such matters as Kehillahs and Yeshivahs, interest the editor of the "Courier, so that he desires to become the dictator. The answer is simple - to use the Kehillah for his political benefit.</p>
   <p>The meeting opened under the chairmanship of Mr. Samuel Phillipson, one of the <pb facs="5423972_5_1048.jpg" n="2"/>most prominent Chicago merchants. Rabbis Ephraim Epstein, A. I. Cordon, and Saul Silber, stated their complaints against the attacks by the Courier. Rabbi Epstein produced the articles from the "Courier" in which the Rabbinate were referred to in the most reviling terms.</p>
   <p>The chairman left the meeting at this point. His place was taken by Max Shulman, who, however, did not retain his chairmanship very long. His place was taken by M. Pearlstein. When Rabbi Silber began to talk and attacked the "Courier" rather sharply, the editor of the "Courier" stood up and threatened him with his stick and before the end of the meeting there was danger that brawling would break out, but this was prevented.</p>
   <p>After the discussion, a resolution was passed demanding that the "Courier" print in its first page an apology. Mr. Max Shulman, who is being boomed for the office of Judge by the "Courier" began to present legal quibblings that the resolution was not lawful. After a heated debate, the entire matter was referred to a committee consisting of Samuel Ginsberg, Max Shulman, Harry Bernstein, A. S. Platt, R. Isaac. B. Lazorovilth and A. M. Goldberg. Harry Bernstein, a personal friend of the "Courier's editor, was elected chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
