<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-12">October 12, 1908</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-12">October 12, 1908</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great Succoth Celebration in the Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <p>A great congregation of Jewish people consisting of 2,225 men and women who for a long time have not experienced the delight of a Succoth affair, assembled in the colossal Succoh, at the Chicago Hebrew Institute. They enjoyed themselves and ate very appetizing dishes, which were served under the management of Mrs. Kale. Mr. Kalish and a corps of assistants saw to it that none present left with an empty stomach but made sure, that they left with empty pockets. Mrs. J. Levin and Mrs. F. Shapiro deserve honorable mention for their wonderful work. These women certainly knew their customers!</p>
   <p>But eating alone is not sufficient,for Succoth is a period of joy and gladness. Thus, all who were present participated in the joyful celebration. As for money, no one was asked for more than they had in their pockets.</p>
   <p>One of the outstanding values, which may be obtained at present at the Hebrew Institute, is a $25 vase for only 10¢, which is sold by Miss Phillipson - the <pb facs="5423972_5_0546.jpg" n="2"/>only daughter of Joseph Phillipson. In view of a misunderstanding, she had sold this vase to several hundred persons, and in order to give every one an equal chance, the vase will be raffled off and it will go to some lucky winner.</p>
   <p>Mrs. J. L. Marks, who is in charge of the ice cream, did very little business. The vaudeville show, under the direction of Mr. Markus, was very attractive and inexpensive and therefore enjoyed a full house continuously. Mrs. Rubin chairman of the flower booth, had something new and entirely different. For the price of a dime or two nickels - a quarter and sometime 50¢, one could possess a flower, which never withers, has a perpetual color and odor. When questioned by a reporter, whether or not these flowers were made of paper, she replied with dignity - shrugging her shoulders. Mrs. Nathan displayed remarkable skill in selling these flowers.</p>
   <p>The Roamward Club possesses privileges of Monte Carlo and the wheel of chance. These young men have voices, which can awaken the dead, and even though you <pb facs="5423972_5_0547.jpg" n="3"/>are financially embarrassed, they will take away the car fare, which you have carefully tucked in your coat lining.</p>
   <p>Mrs. B. Baumgarten is queen of the needle craft booth, and everyone gladly takes a chance for these wonderful articles. The public is very anxious to obtain these articles. Beautiful girls under the guidance of Mr. Nathan Kaplan, are distributing applications for membership and are recruiting members by the dozen.</p>
   <p>The Succoth celebration will continue for the entire week. It will be open to the public twice a day, at 2 P. M. and 7 P. M. Each performance will have special attractions, in order to draw a crowd.</p>
   <p>On the day when the Torah is being honored, the celebration will end with a grand ball.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
