<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-30">Mar. 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Modern Hebrew School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-30">Mar. 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE MODERN HEBREW SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most important questions confronting American Jewry is the question of Jewish education for the children; how they should be taught, and to which schools they should be sent. Because this is a free country, anybody can become a Hebrew teacher and can teach as he pleases, according to his ability. That is why we have, much to our regret, so many illiterate adults.</p>
   <p>It is not important that your child should receive a Jewish education in a modern Hebrew school, from a responsible and experienced teacher. Mr. A. Rubinstein's Modern Hebrew School, at 1261 North Lincoln Street, is, unquestionably, a reputable institution. This school is practically the only one of its kind, not only in Chicago, but perhaps in the whole country.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rubinstein is a very competent and qualified teacher and principal. He has native teaching ability and has adapted himself to the customs of this <pb facs="5423972_5_1316.jpg" n="2"/>country and understands the psychology and characteristics of the American-born Jewish children.</p>
   <p>The Modern Hebrew School is sanitary, clean, and in many respects, it even surpasses the public schools. In the Modern Hebrew School, the pupils have the utmost respect for their studies and their teachers. Everything is conducted in a friendly and respectful manner. Never has a harsh word been used to maintain order.</p>
   <p>Hebrew is taught according to a modern technique, and a true Jewish and nationalist spirit prevails in the School. Mr. Rubenstein, who has his own methods of teaching, has been in the profession for more than nineteen years.</p>
   <p>The subjects taught in this school are Hebrew, the Bible, Jewish history, the significance of the holidays, and the reading, writing, and speaking of Yiddish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1317.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those who wish to give their children a genuine Jewish education, so that their children can grow up with a knowledge of Jewish history and can become conscientious Jews, should send them to the Modern Hebrew School.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
