<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1931-02-05">February 5, 1931</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1931-02-05">February 5, 1931</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Executive Committee of the United Drive, James H. Becker presented a few facts with respect to the Jewish Telegraphic Agency.</p>
   <p>The Agency was organized 10 years ago and consists of two distinct organizations, 1) The Jewish Daily Bulletin, published in this country and probably the best news medium for Jewish news from all parts of the world. 2) The Agency itself, which functions somewhat like the Associated Press in this country, the Reuter Agency in England and the Havas Agency in France. It has representatives gathering news in all important Jewish centers and sells it to newspaper services in this and other countries. In this manner it obtains about half of its expenses.</p>
   <p>The Agency started the year 1931 with a deficit of $30,000. Together with its 1931 needs is will be obliged to raise over $100,000. The Agency obtains money from individuals and from several community chests. Mr. Rosenwald gives $10,000 a year and the Schiff and Warburg families $25,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0807.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Agency is a powerful instrument for the Jews. This has been exemplified by the situation in Rumania during the past few years. During the Palestinian riots in 1929 it was of great service to Jewry in spreading quickly the actual facts.</p>
   <p>There is a particular need for the news service of the Agency at the present time with anti-Semitism becoming so strong in Germany. The American Jewish Committee made a careful investigation of the conduct of the Agency, gave it its unqualified endorsement and stated that it was being efficiently conducted.</p>
   <p>These facts on the J. T. A. were followed by considerable discussion by members present.</p>
   <p>Mr. Davis remarked that the Reuter and Havas Agencies were subsidized by their governments. Although the Jews have no government, they must have their news service. The fine standard set up by the Agency is seen from the fact that <pb facs="5423972_5_0808.jpg" n="3"/>the Associated Press accepts, without qualifications, its news items.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kline stated that the work of the Agency was more important now than ever before with the anti-Semitic agitation in Germany as well as in several of the eastern European countries. If Germany becomes definitely anti-Semitic it will affect unfavorably, Jewry throughout the entire world. In his opinion the Agency is more necessary, more important than any other request before the United Drive Committee.</p>
   <p>On a motion by S. I. Frank, seconded by James Davis, it was unanimously voted that the sum of $7,500 be appropriated to the J. T. A. for the year 1931.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
