<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">What's New in Town</title><title level="a" type="sub">Workers Institute</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT'S NEW IN TOWN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Workers Institute</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The activities in the Workers Institute are proceeding energetically this season. The elementary classes, as well as the high school department, are already in full swing. The sound method of instruction, which is applied in both departments, has attracted a great many students and the result is that there are hardly enough seats for everybody.</p>
   <p>The Sunday School has become an important factor in the life of the Institute. The finest teachers have expressed their respect for the system which has been introduced in this school, and they claim that it is one of the best in the country.</p>
   <p>A musical department offering piano and violin lessons, has also been opened and is under the personal supervision of Professor von Libiech and Frank Lyon, well-known authorities in the musical world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1613.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The university courses will be conducted regularly, beginning October 15, and a public forum is now being arranged for every Sunday evening, beginning October 1.</p>
   <p>A class in civics and citizenship will open October 1, and will be under the supervision of the Young American Branch 227, Workmen's Circle. This class will also be connected with the Naturalization Bureau, which is open twice a week in the Institute.</p>
   <p>A lecture on "Mark Twain, The Greatest American Humorist" will be given Sunday evening, September 24, at the Workers Institute. The lecture, which has been arranged by the Institute's Educational League, will be delivered by Herman Jacobson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1614.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Union of South Side Jews</p>
   <p>The mass meeting, which took place Sunday evening at Congregation Keser Israel, 4719 South Marshfield Avenue, under the auspices of the Union of South Side Jews of Chicago was a great success. A large crowd filled the small but beautiful synagogue. Charles Tiktin, chairman of the Union's committee on education, opened the meeting. He spoke of the purpose of the meeting, and then introduced Rabbi Saul Silber.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Silber demonstrated his powers of oratory by enumerating the maladies of the Jews and their cures. "I am not a doctor who can cure those who are physically ill," he said "but for those who are spiritually ill, a rabbi is a good doctor." He concluded by stating that he wished to see some results from his speech. Thereupon $315 was pledged as a fund for a Talmud Torah. A board of officers was elected for the Talmud Torah and a ladies auxiliary <pb facs="5423972_5_1615.jpg" n="4"/>was formed to assist the project.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Preparatory School</p>
   <p>William [E.] Rodriguez, the Socialist alderman, will be the principal speaker at the commencement exercises of the [Progressive] High School, which will take place in the auditorium of the Lawndale Hall, 3437 Ogden Avenue, Saturday, September 23, at 8 P. M. Mr. Isadore Berger, director of the Berger Studios, and Leon A. Blum, director of the Chicago Musical College, Independence Boulevard Branch, Mr. B. Shanen, and Miss J. Paul will participate in the musical program.</p>
   <p>An innovation which was introduced in the Progressive School this season is a class in psychology under the supervision of William Nathanson. This course will serve a double purpose: first, it will give the student an understanding of psychology, and second, it will give them the necessary credits for college.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1616.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For information about this or other courses offered in the Progressive Preparatory School, please inquire at one of the three branches: 2058 West Division Street, 1637 West Twelfth Street, or 2317 West Twelfth Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
