<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-31">July 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Modern Jewish Folk Schools</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1684</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1684.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-31">July 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE MODERN JEWISH FOLK SCHOOLS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only two years ago, among the two Socialist-Nationalistic bodies in America, the Poale Zion and the Jewish National Workers' Alliance, the concept of establishing radical schools here, in this country emerged.</p>
   <p>The success of the enterprise is certainly known to every race-conscious man who has faith in the Jewish future and strives to rear Jewish youth in a national radical manner. Today schools of this type exist in all large Jewish centers of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1685.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The national sentiment has been revived and spread itself widely among the Jewish masses in America. The fetid, cosmopolitan idea of becoming more Gentile than the Gentile himself is a thing of the past. Many advocates of such social assimilation have finally been convinced that they have erred, and with a self-conscious national pride they have retreated to their home - to the large Jewish masses who live and work as national-socialists.</p>
   <p>There are three national radical schools in Chicago, which stand on poor financial basis.</p>
   <p>The fault, I believe, can be attached to the local organized and nationally inclined, working masses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1686.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The individuals who helped organize the national radical schools sacrificed a great deal and even offered their lives for the unrealized dominion. But, they could not offer their useful work and hard-earned savings, and the Poale Zion and the members of the National Workers' Alliance, who are the parents whose task it is - (and if it is not it should be) - to support the expanding schools, have practically done nothing.</p>
   <p>The central bodies of the Poale Zion and the Alliance have realized this. Their active work in this field is just beginning to grow and become noticed. A conference was held and a steady program, which was approved by the masses, was adopted. But, we, the Poale Zion and Alliance members of Chicago - how did we respond? And what are we doing for the radical national schools?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1687.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>An example will serve to show how the Jewish people react toward this phenomenon.</p>
   <p>One Sunday morning I was sitting in the office of the Jewish People's School on the North West Side, during classes. A man entered with his 13-year old son whom he wanted to enroll in the school.</p>
   <p>"Mr." I said, recognizing him to be a religious man, "classes are conducted quite differently than in a Talmud Torah (Hebrew School). We teach the children Jewish history, legends, writing and reading Jewish and Hebrew, and we discuss important events of Jewish history of the past and present. In short, we intend to acquaint the children with their ancestry and make them national radical Jews."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1688.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"That isn't bad," the man replied, "let me inform you that my son attended a Talmud Torah for two years and he can't read a single word in Jewish. He can only read a few words in Hebrew, but cannot interpret the meaning. I now want him to attend your school."</p>
   <p>I have come to the logical conclusion that the people want to send their children to such schools. There is naturally room for improvement and further development of the beautiful sprouting, outspreading branch of our national culture. But in addition to this, financial and moral work by all who love the idea, is required.</p>
   <p>The Talmud Torahs are not capable of creating a proud national generation. The assimilated schools were born with the ardor of a cemetery where they are, shortly after their birth brought to eternal rest, and now we can see how the national schools have been established under very unfavorable conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1689.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Trusting that the national-radically inclined idealists will not remain indifferent to this factor, which life itself has brought forth. The schools are expecting us to do our duty. - Jacob Siegel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
