<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time the Board of Education in conjunction with the McCormick Fund and the Anti-Tuberculosis Sanitarium have been conducting an open air class in the Foster School. For one reason or another, this school was not conducted during the Summer months, in spite of the fact that the Summer months would probably have proven of greatest value to the children, who were members of the class. This year, however, those interested in the class applied to the Institute for accomodations on the grounds. After very careful investigation, it was decided to cooperate with these organizations and to operate this open air class on the northwest corner of the grounds.</p>
   <p>These children are anemic, heart diseased, and some of them predisposed to tuberculosis. There are about thirty in the class. Twenty-six of them are Jewish children. This class will be conducted during the Summer weeks on the grounds, provided the organizations interested in the work are willing to abide by the following agreements:</p>
   <p>1. That during the time the class meets on the grounds of the Institute, the supervision and general responsibility for the activity be turned over to the <pb facs="5423972_5_1717.jpg" n="2"/>Institute, from a supervisory standpoint. (The reason for this request is that the Institute at no time feels that it cares to turn over any part of its grounds or buildings to any association doing work not directly supervised by it).</p>
   <p>2. That the food be prepared and served as kosher custom demands.</p>
   <p>3. That each of the thirty children register individually at the office and pay fifteen cents for the entire Summer season, for the privilege of making use of the grounds. (This item is nominal and is a requisite on the part of each child who makes use of the grounds during the Summer. In this way, the children who receive the benefits of this open air class would be none other than regularly registered ground-children who are entitled, by virtue of their registration and payment of their fee, to all of the activities conducted by the Institute.)</p>
   <p>4. That each child be examined by a reputable physician and a certificate filed in the office of the Institute to the effect that there is absolutely <pb facs="5423972_5_1718.jpg" n="3"/>no danger of contagion in the case of the children who are members of the class. The hours of instruction are from 9:00 in the morning until 3:00 in the afternoon, five days a week. The children are to receive a shower bath every morning. There will be a charge made of twenty-five cents for each ten towels used. This charge is made to other persons connected with the Institute, who use our shower baths, and is made to defray the expense of laundry, wear and tear. The children are also to receive a warm lunch at noon, and will be under instruction and supervision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
