<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-09">Jan. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An Interesting Discussion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-09">Jan. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTERESTING DISCUSSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The leading Hebrew teachers in the City of Chicago are discussing the merits of one of the best known Hebrew schools on the West Side because of a statement issued by the representative of the school that it is educating a generation of Hebrew scholars. This statement was objected to by one of our best Hebrew educators in the City because according to his opinion a school in which Hebrew is taught in Yiddish and the children do not receive any instruction in Jewish literature and in Hebrew proper cannot be productive of results. The representatives of the school on their part maintain that all the Hebrew book knowledge imparted by other Hebrew schools to the children notwithstanding, their school is very productive of its results for the reason that it brings up good Jews and God-fearing Jews. Now it is true that one of the objects of the Hebrew school is to bring up God-fearing Jews but we must take into consideration that the Hebrew school is not a purely religious school.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1446.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is not a purely religious school because Judaism is not only a religion but also a way of life. The object of the Hebrew school is to bring up Jews--that is to say, to impart to the children a thorough knowledge of all branches of Judaism, religion, Hebrew, Hebrew literature, history, Jewish institutions, etc. Unless the pupils receive a manifold Jewish education covering at least the rudiments of these subjects, one cannot possibly maintain that it is doing its duty to its pupils. There are a great many Hebrew schools in the City of Chicago in which only religion is taught to the children and nothing else. We completely agree with the modern Hebrew educators that such schools have outgrown their usefulness. Even in the old world the old-fashioned Cheder has undergone radical changes. The Cheder in its old form is no longer in existence. It has been replaced by the up-to-date Hebrew school. If the old-fashioned Cheder has become obsolete there, it is surely an obsolete institution here because there Jewish life is still intense and the Jewish atmosphere so strong that even the Jew without much knowledge of Judaism must remain a Jew. Here, however, it is different. Unless a Jew receives a thorough Jewish education and knows why he and his people are <pb facs="5423972_5_1447.jpg" n="3"/>suffering he will not remain in the fold and will surely desert Judaism as soon as the opportunity offers itself and such opportunities there are many. Therefore, the Hebrew school in America, to be really productive of results and to fulfill its mission, must not only attempt to bring up religious Jews, but it must impart to the young children a thorough knowledge of Judaism. Unfortunately there are not many modern Hebrew schools in Chicago. Most of the Hebrew schools are entirely old-fashioned and being old-fashioned they have outgrown their usefulness.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to be misunderstood. We do not wish to convey the impression that we are for the secularization of the Hebrew school. The Hebrew school, even the most up-to-date one must to a certain extent be a religious school, but we do wish to say as clearly as we can that since it is not only the mission of the Hebrew school to teach religion but to teach other subjects as well, it is necessary that the Hebrew schools give the children an opportunity to make themselves acquainted with all branches of Judaism, theoretical as well as practical--religious as well as secular,--ethical as well as literary, <pb facs="5423972_5_1448.jpg" n="4"/>and only in that way it is possible to bring up a generation of Jews even in this new world, who will be loyal to their people and to their people's religion. All the efforts of the old-fashioned orthodox to bring up their children in America just the same as they have been brought up in the Eastern European ghetto, will be of no avail and will result in nothing tangible. A few of the pupils of an old-fashioned Hebrew school in America may cling to old-fashioned orthodoxy but most of them desert it upon reaching manhood. It is in the interest of orthodoxy to modernize its educational establishments and thus to strengthen the very foundation of Judaism in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
