<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-27">June 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">How to Help Talmud Torah Children During the Vacation Period</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-27">June 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HOW TO HELP TALMUD TORAH CHILDREN DURING THE VACATION PERIOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Soon the schools will close. And, as usual, the richer children will go to the country with their parents, and the poorer ones will go--to work. But the children who are attending Talmud Torahs [Community Hebrew Schools] find themselves in a sorry predicament during the vacation period. They have to earn some money to help the family budget, and, therefore, they must give up their studies in the Talmud Torah. The result, upon the school children, is naturally bad. They miss three months of Jewish education, and when they go back, they know very little about their work.</p>
   <p>The president of the Talmud Torah, Mr. Ben-Zion Lazarovitch wants to avoid this. He, therefore, has decided to appeal to the Chicago Jews to whom Jewish culture is dear, to help these students remain at their studies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1551.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bigger and brighter pupils of these schools can be free [from their studies] at one o'clock in the afternoon at the latest, and some, even earlier, at eleven o'clock in the morning. If they want to, they can work from that time on until the evening.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lazarovitch's plan is that the Jews who need boys to work for them during the vacation, should hire pupils of the Talmud Torah, and give them work after school.</p>
   <p>Jews who wish to aid these school children, can obtain information daily at the new Talmud Torah, at Winchester Avenue near Twelfth Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
