<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-09">Feb. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Moving Pictures for Jewish Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-09">Feb. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MOVING PICTURES FOR JEWISH CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the annual report of a Jewish women's council in New York, we learn that they present interesting Jewish biblical moving pictures to the children every Sunday afternoon. Last year these pictures were presented regularly in the Fulton Theatre.</p>
   <p>This project, sponsored by Jewish women in New York for the past few years, deserves our felicitations. It is through these activities that these women give the Jewish children an opportunity to acquire a deeper knowledge of Jewish <pb facs="5423972_5_1163.jpg" n="2"/>history, to which they now devote merely a few hours per week. By attending these movies, small children are drawn closer to biblical times and are carried away by their fantasy into Jewish spheres.</p>
   <p>Particularly is this important here in America, where the Jewish child attends the public schools, imbibing more or less glorious conceptions of Christian legends. Thus the biblical moving picture idea is a remedial measure to bring sentiments of the child in relation with Jewish legends.</p>
   <p>The most significant feature of these moving pictures is that they prevent the child from attending the regular moving picture houses, which are poisonous <pb facs="5423972_5_1164.jpg" n="3"/>to his body and soul. As we know, these places are constantly overcrowded, and unsanitary. Sitting in such places, where there is a heterogeneous crowd the child is apt to fall a victim to a disease. These moving picture places are far more injurious to the child's mind than to his body. By going to the movies, a three-year old child, who can hardly talk, becomes familiar with words such as "bomb," and "shoot," words which fill him with noxious illusions. And it is a long established fact that children's crimes have a great deal to do with what they see in the movies. It is a scientific fact that children are strongly impressed by the things they come in contact with. They ape everything they see, and if they witness a picture in which murder is "committed before their eyes," it arouses their passion to do likewise.</p>
   <p>If, however, good Jewish biblical pictures are shown to the children, like the <pb facs="5423972_5_1165.jpg" n="4"/>one in which Moses emancipates the Israelites from Egyptian bondage and leads them to the Promised Land, they will mimic them.</p>
   <p>There is still another injurious feature about the moving pictures. In Chicago, in some Jewish districts, pictures are shown which expose the Jew in a libelous manner. This impresses the youth to look upon their parents as objects for derision.</p>
   <p>It is therefore of the utmost importance that we establish special, well-ventilated, and roomy places in Chicago, where biblical films may be shown to Jewish children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
