<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-29">Oct. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Peretz and Dienenzon</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-29">Oct. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PERETZ AND DIENENZON</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish National Workmen's Verband of America, together with the Puela Zionist, have established many Jewish Folk Schools, (among them the free school at the John Smyth School of our city), whose Jewish children are taught Jewish in a new light or method. The National Workmen's Verband has recently decided to use and distribute to the children a series of Jewish stories. The first series consisted of group of Peretz' famous folk stories of King Solomon's Days, "Arbitration with the Wind."</p>
   <p>The office of the National Workers Verband sent Peretz compensation for permission to print his stories, and explained to him the essence of the new Jewish Folk Schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1741.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Peretz' and Jacob Dienenzon's answers to this letter read as follows:</p>
   <p>"My dear, dear gentlemen of the Jewish National Workmen's Verband:</p>
   <p>"You have given me the most beautiful day of my life. Truly the most beautiful and one of the happiest. I have never yet received any finer or more inspiring news than that sent me in your loving letter. It is the most gratifying letter anyone could possibly receive from the Jewish World. I do not want any remuneration. Please buy books instead and distribute them to the poor children.</p>
   <p>"May you and your children receive the same comforting compliments that you have thus accorded me. Will you write to me from time to time to let me know how your worthy work is progressing? I shall be extremely thankful.</p>
   <p>"Regards to all the children, and if possible read my letter to them?</p>
   <p>Your faithfully,</p>
   <p>E. L. Peretz"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1742.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"My dear beloved Brothers and Children:</p>
   <p>"To no lesser degree, has your letter to my friend Peretz, also given me untold happiness. I thank you from my heart, dear brothers, for a true comfort and hope that your efforts and important work extend to our unfortunate folk, not for ourselves. After rereading the contents it seeped deeply into my heart while an inner voice broke forth: 'Israel is no widower'. The proud yet truly truthful words of the Tonach. A true widow and widower are those who have no faithful children to sympathize or feel their sorrowful state. But, having with us such conscientious children, so wholeheartedly loyal to their people as you are, dear brothers and children, it is certain that our race is no widower or orphan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1743.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Proceed, dear brothers, in the fine exalted way in which you have so nobly begun. The way is long, hard and thorny, but as for a more certain road to the future, there is none.</p>
   <p>"And you children, dear beautiful Jewish children, you are our future. Be Jews and be proud of it. You will see that you have a right to be proud. My regards and kisses from afar, from one who loves you.</p>
   <p>Jacob Dienenzon"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
