<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-03">Mar. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Jewish Historical Society a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-03">Mar. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE JEWISH HISTORICAL SOCIETY A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Jewish Historical Society of Illinois took place last night in the Rose Room of the Morrison Hotel. Approximately one hundred and fifty of the most prominent Jews of Chicago were present. A fish dinner was served. Alexander Akimoff, of the Petrograd Opera House, sang some operatic arias and some Jewish folk songs. He has a powerful but sweet voice and he made a hit. He was accompanied by Miss Miriam Firstenberg, the celebrated pianist. Stereopticon pictures were then shown of the development of Chicago and the part the jews had played in it; the explanations were given by Professor A. A. Friedlander.</p>
   <p>The speakers were: Judge Harry M. Fisher, Jacob M. Loeb, James Davis, M. E. Greenebaum, B. Horwich, and Nathan D. Kaplan. S. J. Rosenblatt was chairman.</p>
   <p>In speaking of the purpose of the gathering, Mr. Rosenblatt pointed out the <pb facs="5423972_5_0776.jpg" n="2"/>difficult work that had been done during the past five years by Mr. H. L. Meites to gather material for the history of the Jews in this state. Mr. Rosenblatt declared that every Jew would be privileged to own the book that is soon to be published. Those present showed their great interest in this enterprise by subscribing for the forthcoming book.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
