<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-04">Mar. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Our Jewish Citizens</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-04">Mar. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">OUR JEWISH CITIZENS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is generally conceded that our Jewish citizens have a well-developed sense of benevolence, and an exceptional opportunity is provided this week to practice humanitarianism. Der Friedhofs-Verein Der Faeien Soehne Israels (The Cemetery Association of the Free Sons of Israel) has arranged a bazaar at Uhlich's Hall, to provide funds for the cemetery. The splendid arrangement of the exhibited items in itself makes a visit well worth while for anyone enjoying an artistically grouped display of valuable articles. A large number of nice, ambitious young ladies comprise the sales force. At the very entrance the visitor addicted to smoking is given a chance to spend a quarter for fragrant Havanas, displayed by Mrs. Julie Neumann and Miss Rosalie Stein, two very attractive salesladies. Then one approaches the dining room, supervised by Mesdames Hart, Schwarz, and Brueckner, and managed so efficiently that even the most fastidious will be able to satisfy his appetite in a most pleasant manner.</p>
   <p>Returning to the hall, one finds an assortment of porcelain, enamel, and <pb facs="5423972_5_0578.jpg" n="2"/>glassware in charge of the Misses Carrie Unger and Dula Michaelis; next, a very attractive display of notions, embroidery, dolls, etc.; this stand is under the supervision of Mrs. Philipps and Mrs. Hart, assisted by four young ladies, the Misses Golberg, Heymann, Frick, and Schwarz. Then comes the post office, where five young ladies serve as letter carriers: the two Michaelis girls, Bertha Heller, Sarah Heine, and Sophie Oestreicher. We now approach the candy stand where most tempting tidbits are served by Mrs. S. H. Myers, Mrs. D. Greenberg, and Miss E. Isaacs; then, a display of hand-made, luxurious articles which are being sold by Mrs. Affenheim, the two Misses Affenheim and Miss Philipps; a large stand where embroideries, perfume, etc., are shown. Among the items is a beautifully woven silk cover, a present of Mr. N. Schwarz of New Orleans. Mrs. A. Diamond, Mrs. Jacob Kuhn, Mrs. S. A. Diamond, and Miss Anna Nathan preside at this booth. Next, there is a stand with paintings, perfumes, candies, etc., in charge of Mrs. Abeles, Mrs. A. Costa, and Miss Foster; then the lottery, where an immense bowl of fruit attracts instant attention. Here sewing machines, clocks, easy chairs, wine, etc., are raffled off; this part is located at the west end of the hall- - the realm where Mrs. D. Meyer, J. Simonds, A. Richter, and Mrs. S. Livingston hold sway. Next is another lottery <pb facs="5423972_5_0579.jpg" n="3"/>stand, where young people with an inclination to seek the "Promised Land" of marriage may find everything required--from a double bed to a pin cushion--and where Mrs. Rosa Meyers, Miss Carrie Elsas, and Miss Bertha are fully prepared to accept orders--if you win.</p>
   <p>Of course, no one will pass Rebecca's well, in the center of the hall, where Miss Eva Diamond and Miss Mathilde Marks dispense the nectar.</p>
   <p>The bazaar is to be held for the entire week, and undoubtedly a large crowd can be expected.</p>
   <p>Good concert music provides diversion and entertainment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
