<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-10">May 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">War in the Jewish Quarter</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Director of the Jewish Theater Causes a Riot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-10">May 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">WAR IN THE JEWISH QUARTER</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Director of the Jewish Theater Causes a Riot</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A violent riot occurred at the Jewish Theater, Jefferson and O'Brien Streets, yesterday. More than one thousand Jews of the neighborhood participated in the riot, and the director of the theater, Mr. Ellis Glickman, was arrested.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Philipson, a department store owner, who has a store in the theater building, had been trying for some time to gain control of the part of the building occupied by the theater for an extension to his store, and his attempts in this direction were the cause of the riot. The lease of Mr. Glickman--who had been in possession of the theater for two years, where he had been giving plays in Yiddish--had expired on May 1, and Mr. Philipson claimed that he had signed a lease for the theater with the owner of the building, Mr. M. Nathan. Mr. Glickman declared that he had a verbal contract with Mr. Nathan for two more years and refused to vacate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0346.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Philipson put a large sign outside the theater offering for sale all the fixtures of the place. This enraged Mr. Glickman, who immediately made plans for revenge. In the windows of a saloon located in the same building, Mr. Glickman exhibited a mass of old shoes and ragged clothes, with the announcement that the department store was holding a great sale. In order to bring a crowd together, he hired a band to play the liveliest tunes.</p>
   <p>Soon a crowd of more than a thousand dwellers of the Jewish quarter had gathered, everybody having his or her own opinion as to whether Mr. Philipson or Mr. Glickman was right. Suddenly a group of those who were siding with Mr. Glickman began to storm the entrances to the store while the adherents of Philipson broke into the theater, and for a while it looked as if the riot might assume serious proportions. The Maxwell Street Police Station was called, and a patrol wagon came up with a dozen officers under the command of Sergeant Harding. The officers attempted to break their way through toward the door of the theater, but the crowd resisted. The policemen pulled cut their clubs, <pb facs="5423972_5_0347.jpg" n="3"/>and Sergeant Harding asked the Canalport Avenue Police Station to send more men.</p>
   <p>When this second group of officers arrived the riot was at its height. The Jews had started fighting each other, women taking part as fully as did the men. When the noise had reached its highest peak, Mr. Glickman and his group of actors appeared, all of them dressed in theatrical costumes. This was the signal for increased rioting, and the actors were at last compelled to withdraw. After a while the policemen made the band stop playing, and little by little the crowd was dispersed, but Mr. Glickman was arrested, charged with disorderly conduct.</p>
   <p>Mr. Glickman was released by Judge Dooley. He has entered suit against Mr. Philipson who caused his arrest, and is demanding $25,000 for false arrest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
