<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-14">July, 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jotting</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L. M</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-14">July, 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JOTTING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L. M</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What happened to the original scenario which was written by Rabbi Goldman? Who had the "Chutzpah" to trim it and cripple it so unmercifully? Moses and the Ten Commandments, which lends itself most admirably to striking presentation and which was on all ads and bill posters, was spurlus verzenkt. But above all, what happened to that glowing period of American Jewish life where millions of our people have had greater opportunities for life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness than anywhere on earth?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0458.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Why was that not shown? What a beautiful and inspiring spectacle the Statue of Liberty would have made at the close of the performance instead of a group of Sunday School kids running into the stage, helter skelter, which was confusing and meaningless. Disappointment on that score seems to be growing from day to day. Those who worked so zealously and so devotedly for the success of "Jewish Day" and the people who have so cheerfully forked over their ducats are entitled to an explanation because they were sadly disappointed. Will the story of what transpired behind the scenes ever be told? We doubt it. As inspiring as the audience was, so disappointing was the performance. True, since it was the first attempt on such a gigantic scale, many of its shortcomings may be overlooked.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0459.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the "machers" would not have taken things upon themselves, but would have called into consultation others who have had some experience in such affairs, the result would have been much more gratifying.</p>
   <p>The various organizations which participated in "Jewish Day reaped a harvest. It is reported that over $100,000 was the amount profited by them, which will enable most of these institutions to liquidate their indebtedness and continue their respective activities undisturbed and unhampered by unpaid bills. To most of them "Jewish Day" proved a "red letter day." Those who had sufficient vision to take advantage of this splendid opportunity worked hard and are now rejoicing in the fruit of their efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
