<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-04">Apr. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Growth of the Chicago Hebrew Theological Seminary</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1311</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1311.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-04">Apr. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE GROWTH OF THE CHICAGO HEBREW THEOLOGICAL SEMINARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a remarkable interview with a representative of the Courier, which is published elsewhere in the Yiddish section in this issue, Rabbi J. L. Gordon, recognized dean and leader of the American Orthodox rabbinate, said that the Beth Medrosh L'Torah, or as it is known in English, the Hebrew Theological Seminary, is already a great center of Talmudic and rabbinic studies. Rabbi Gordon summed up the scholarly accomplishments of the students of that institution by saying:</p>
   <p>"I have examined a great many of them and I can tell you that those whom I have examined are thorough Talmudic scholars and know much more Talmud and the Codes than even the most optimistic of us imagine. I have examined some of the students in the Codes and have found them to be regular lomdim <pb facs="5423972_5_1312.jpg" n="2"/>[Scholars]. Their knowledge of the Talmud is remarkable. Some of them are so mature and have accumulated such a vast knowledge of the Talmud and rabbinic literature that they are already fit to be rabbis and teachers in Israel, and in some not very distant time, they will probably be ordained rabbis."</p>
   <p>Rabbi J. L. Gordon, whose own scholarship and erudition is never short of marvelous, is a severe critic and a more severe examiner, and if he says that after he examined the students of the Beth Medrosh L'Torah that they are making rapid strides in their learning, and that the institution is doing wonderful work as a center of Talmudic and rabbinic learning, one feels sure that the Hebrew Theological College is serving well the community and is serving well the purpose for which it was established. This testimonial of the great Rabbi should fill the heart of every Orthodox Jew in Chicago with pride and encourage him to do for the institution whatever he can.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1313.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Unfortunately Chicago Orthodox Jewry is not yet quite alive to the situation before it. Only a minority of the Orthodox Jews has contributed toward the maintenance of the institution, and the maintenance alone requires five thousand dollars per month, or sixty thousand dollars per annum. We still contend that Chicago Orthodox Jewry alone can maintain this institution without resorting to appeals to outside Jewish communities. The sum necessary for the maintenance of the institution can be procured by voluntary contributions or by a membership campaign. There is no reason why the roster of the institution should not have at least four thousand names. If four thousand Jews in Chicago will consent to contribute toward the maintenance of the institution from ten to twenty-five dollars a year, the bulk of the money will be procured, and should there be a deficit, the leaders of the institution will find ways and means how to cover it.</p>
   <p>As soon as the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] drive is over, the first task before the Orthodox Jewish community of Chicago is to <pb facs="5423972_5_1314.jpg" n="4"/>provide for this wonderful institution. We should not wait until the institution will face a financial crisis. The Beth Medrosh L'Torah is naturally very dear to the heart of the Orthodox rabbis in Chicago, and if the entire rabbinate in Chicago will make an effort to secure funds for the institution, it will surely be successful, especially since it will get the co-operation of hundreds who are equally interested in the welfare of the institution and who are anxious to help it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
