<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-04">Sept. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">To Create New Literary Forces</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-04">Sept. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TO CREATE NEW LITERARY FORCES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Courier will soon begin a literary contest for the best treatises, articles, essays, short stories and poems about Jewish matters, Jewish problems, and Jewish types and motives.</p>
   <p>The literary contest of the Courier has only one big purpose: to rouse the Jewish literary forces in Chicago, to give them an opportunity of self-development, to waken in them literary and artistic ambitions, and to give them the opportunity to begin their literary career.</p>
   <p>In Jewish Chicago there are certainly many latent literary and artistic forces. They do not reveal themselves and are lost, because they haven't had the opportunity to appear in public. The Courier wishes to give them this opportunity, to gain a literary technique and a literary experience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0668.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Courier strives to become the literary and artistic center in awakening the literary forces, and to encourage them further to work and develop their talent.</p>
   <p>The Courier, in its striving to awaken the dormant literary forces in Jewish Chicago, pursues the great traditions of the Jewish press, which has always been the school of all our great writers and poets. Israel Zangwill began his brilliant career as a co-worker of the Jewish Chronicle of London. The great Nahum Sokolow began his writing career as a co-worker of the Hatzfiroh etc.</p>
   <p>The Jewish press has constantly aroused, reared, and constructed great literary forces, and the Courier wishes to emulate these splendid traditions of the Jewish press throughout the world, and help to awaken the Jewish literary forces in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0669.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The enterprise is inextricably bound with a lot of money and much work, yet the Courier will spare no money nor work in its undertaking of this new feature, in summoning the young Jewish literary and artistic forces of Jewish Chicago.</p>
   <p>In a few days we will publish three lists in connection with this literary contest. One list of themes for essays and articles. A second list for literary connoisseurs, who are to render their decisions over the literary contributions and a third list for prizes.</p>
   <p>The Courier will soon make known all the details of the contest; to whom the contributions should be sent; how they should be signed in order that the literary judge should be absolutely impartial; how large the sums of money will be for the first, second, and third prizes. Other contributions will receive mention in accordance with the judges' decision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
