<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-28">August 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Hebrew Theological College to Ordain Rabbis</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-28">August 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">HEBREW THEOLOGICAL COLLEGE TO ORDAIN RABBIS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On August 27, 1927, the second graduation exercises of the Rabbinical Department of the Hebrew Theological College of Chicago will take place. The occasion is auspicious for the entire Middlewest as it indicates that the Hebrew Theological College is rapidly becoming a vital source of traditional Judaism, and it is already firmly established as the Torah Center of the West. It is an indication that the Hebrew Theological College is continuing to bear fruit and supplies the communities of the Central and Western parts of the United States with capable spiritual leaders, men who can carry the message of the Torah to the American Jew.</p>
   <p>With this graduation traditional Judaism will be enriched with an infusion of new strength and fresh spirit, and added impetus will be given to the movement of bringing the Jewish youth back to the traditional hold. The graduation will take place at the Anshe Sholom Congregation, Independence Blvd. and Polk St.</p>
   <p>There are nine candidates for the Rabbinical Degree, including P. J. Bender, Gerstein, Meisel, H. Miller, Notis, M. Rissman, H. Shambam, H. Shapiro, and <pb facs="5423972_5_1194.jpg" n="2"/>D. Winchester.</p>
   <p>All of them are American young men and have attended American colleges. They have all received an adequate training to enable them to fulfill efficiently their duties in the respective communities to whose leadership they shall be called. The graduation is especially significant in that it betokens the rise of an American-trained Rabbinate. It shows that American traditional Jewry has become self-supporting, that it can create its own leaders and is no longer dependent on foreign centers of Torah. Moreover, it indicates that traditional Judaism is again coming into its own and that it shall surely triumph in the near future. All traditionally-minded Jews will certainly perceive in the forth-coming graduation a symbol of the religious revival that is taking place in American traditional Jewry, and a symbol of the healthy growth and spread of traditional Judaism that is one of the miracles of our time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
