<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-10-03">October 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish People's Institute Rental Library Opens This Week</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-10-03">October 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH PEOPLE'S INSTITUTE RENTAL LIBRARY OPENS THIS WEEK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish People's Institute Rental Library opened this week on Sunday, September 28, at 3. P. M. We wish here to bring to your attention some of the latest books, many of which will not be publicly advertised for a few weeks. These are called September books by publishers and are not for sale till the end of the month. These books will not be in the public library for months. You have the opportunity to read them here, now, for 1/10 to 1/20 their value, while the critics are evaluating and discussing them. Also, we shall conduct a bulletin board, bringing to your notice books recommended by literary periodicals and famous critics, together with good reviews.</p>
   <p>We wish to emphasize that this is your library and any time we can do anything for you, if possible, we shall, if you let our librarian know of it. For instance, if you wish to buy books, we will do that for you, getting you books at less than retail value. If you wish to read special books, let us know. We will put them in the rental library. Our book shop will be behind the information desk, the right hand corner. Our rates are 15¢ minimum to be paid <pb facs="5423972_5_0721.jpg" n="2"/>upon the drawing of book. The book can be kept for 4 days. 5¢ will be charged for each day thereafter. A membership fee of 25¢ a year will be charged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
