<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1916-12">December, 1916</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1916-12">December, 1916</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Socialist Singing Society. by I. B. Bailin.</p>
   <p>There were several attempts for the last ten years to build up in Chicago a singing society in Yiddish, although the existence of small groups of singers may be traced back to the beginning of this century. The National Singing Society was the last futile attempt of a score of youths to keep up the existence of a permanent Jewish singing group. Others tried before and failed.</p>
   <p>As it is not my object now to go into any details of the underlying causes for this failure, I just want to suggest that apparently the main cause may be looked for in the fact that no organizations of any weight and importance were behind them. The groups had to depend largely upon their own resources for subsistence, and upon their own immediate friends to serve as audiences. With no strong and shining ideal to inspire, without organizations to depend <pb facs="5423972_5_0368.jpg" n="2"/>upon on a rainy day, without adequate and capable leaders, their fate could not be otherwise than sealed. It took the ambitious and virile Jewish Socialists to do away with all the obstacles and difficulties, and to organize a permanent and strong institution of an educational and beneficial character in the Ghetto.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Socialist Singing Society was organized by the City Central Committee of the Jewish Socialist Party branches, in November, 1914, with a membership of about fifty, mostly untrained singers, but possessing fair voices. Its first meetings and rehearsals were held in Maxwell Settlement, and later on in various halls of the West and North West Sides. They were crowded with guests and never was the room large enough. The preparations for the first public concert were elaborate, and noted for their strict attendance of practically all members. Altruistic exertion and sacrifices of the leaders permitted to engage a capable instructor, thus contributing <pb facs="5423972_5_0369.jpg" n="3"/>largely to the successes of the task. Mr. Jacob Schafer, the conductor, himself of proletarian society, Socialist and musician, has given away many an hour freely and served the Society with fervent devotion. Within several months he succeeded in creating as harmonious a team as can only be formed out of workingmen dilettantes.</p>
   <p>The day of the first concert, the 11th of April, 1915, in the West Side Auditorium, was a real holiday for the members of the Society. They all were in uniform and beamed like children performing for the first time an important duty. It proved to be a moral as well as a financial success. Over one-thousand people cheered and rejoiced over this accomplishment. Especially remarkable was the execution of the Martirer Blut (Martyr's Blood), a poem by O. Liesin, in a difficult musical interpretation, a successful creation of Mr. Schafer himself. Then a few more concerts followed suit, among them one composed of folk songs, exclusively, unique of its kind, but most of the concerts were of popular and classical pieces.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0370.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is already the tradition of the Society to publish an elaborate and expensive program, containing the text of all the poems and songs, as well as some selected articles pertaining to the activities of the Society, and to distribute them among the audience. One of the most important aims prominently figuring in the Constitution of the Society is to distribute Jewish Socialist poetry and workingmen's melodies among the Jewish laboring masses. A program like this is a heavy expense, and the advertisements gathered from sympathizers do not usually cover it in full.</p>
   <p>The last concert was exclusively devoted to the Russian Revolution, and was given in the gymnasium of the Hebrew Institute on the 12th of May. It was attended by an interested and intelligent audience. Again the Martirer Blut proved to be the big hit. Mr. Absfield, the tenor, was this time at his best, and the other soloists gave also a good account of themselves. Miss Roral and Mr. Manievitch betrayed a deep understanding of their respective parts, and brought the audience to its feet. Plans are underway to publish the music of the above, as well as of several other productions of Mr. Schafers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
