<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-22">Aug. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Birthday Party of the Workers Institute</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-22">Aug. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE BIRTHDAY PARTY OF THE WORKERS INSTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jonah Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every living thing eventually finds its way to the sun and to life. The seed that is thrown into the depths of the soil remains in darkness for quite some time, as though it had gone to waste. The seed, however, is penetrated by heat and moisture, and there in the darkness, where it is hidden from the sun, in compressed air, it cracks open, sprouting tendrils which first become rooted in a small clod of earth and then break through the surface of the soil in the form of the ear of grain, the fruit, or the flower.</p>
   <p>These thoughts come to us when we read the Workers Institute Review, which was recently sent to us. The first number of this journal, in which is celebrated the "birthday party" of the Workers Institute which is a year old, intimates that in the Workers Institute there is life; that the seed of <pb facs="5423972_5_1631.jpg" n="2"/>independence has planted roots within the hearts of a portion of the radical working class. And it is also expected that they [the workers] will support this institution so that it may have a successful and happy future.</p>
   <p>The Workers Institute was brought into being by a sad and involved incident which occurred in the local Hebrew Institute; a man who was appointed "straw boss" for a few weeks, through rash conduct, led the Institute into conflict with the radical element of the working class, which made up a large proportion of the membership. This radical group felt that it was in a position, by itself, to maintain an institution where it could act and move freely, according to its own convictions, and where it could throw light upon its revolutionary theories which are contrary to the theories and ideological trends of general educational institutions.</p>
   <p>In speaking on an educational plan, the German poet-philosopher Goethe says <pb facs="5423972_5_1632.jpg" n="3"/>in his book Wilhelm Meister that man's adoration for things is neither innate nor natural, but must be learned by heart. It depends upon how the person's mind is developed and by what thoughts and ideas he is influenced. At times a person is taught to admire only a stone or a log, and at other times he is taught to revere the "superman" and mystical philosophies of infinity.</p>
   <p>Each respective system of education claims that only it is right; that only it can influence its students in the correct way; that only it can instill in their hearts the veneration of everything that is noble, beautiful, and idealistic. The parochial system [of education] instills in the hearts of its students reverence for its saints. The capitalist system seeks to influence youth to respect capital and energetic human activity. And the new revolutionary system [of education], which consists of theories concerning the productive working class, arises as an opponent of the aforementioned two systems, claiming that all elementary subjects should be illuminated from the <pb facs="5423972_5_1633.jpg" n="4"/>materialistic and economic standpoints, and that love and respect for the productive working class should be implanted within the hearts of the students.</p>
   <p>The speculative sciences, for example, history, are the peculiar expressions of the people who teach them. The more speculative sciences reflect the mental biases of certain personalities, and, therefore, upon them lies the stamp of a particular personality. A historian, influenced by a monarchistic spirit, will explain the past in a different manner than the historian who is influenced by a republican spirit. This is also true of the sociologist and other educators.</p>
   <p>The interests of the radical workers are different and completely divorced from the interests of other classes. It is, therefore, very natural that they should seek information and enlightenment on certain scientific subjects, particularly the speculative, according to their own biases, and should also seek to instill in the hearts of young students, upon whom first impressions <pb facs="5423972_5_1634.jpg" n="5"/>have a great effect, a strong love and admiration for the productive workers.</p>
   <p>In his report, the superintendent of the Workers Institute, Mr. A. Tobinson endeavors to show that the motive and reason for their [radicals'] existence is the desire to have freedom of thought, and to resist the imposition of blind obedience and the superficial culture of narrow individualism which exists among people of selfish ambitions. The radical immigrants also seek to Americanize themselves in a truly American spirit--in the spirit of Nathaniel Bacon, Thomas Paine, Jefferson, Emerson, John Brown, Debs, Giovannitti, and Joe Hill.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tobinson classifies the educational activities of the Institute in three divisions: elementary school courses, high school courses,and university courses. Between one and two hundred boys and girls, men and women, attend the elementary classes in the Workers Institute. The teaching method is the same as in public schools. Mr. Tobinson complains about the textbooks which are not in</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1635.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>conformity with the spirit and problems of the Institute. But he hopes that in due time, when the necessary funds are available, proper textbooks will be available.</p>
   <p>In reference to the high school, Mr. Tobinson said that a condensed high school course is now being completed, which will be published in the next edition of the Institute's journal. At present, the Institute has a fine high school class in which new students enroll daily. In regards to the university extension courses of the Institute, Mr. Tobinson said that they would consist of something more than mere lectures. Unlike most lectures which are delivered in radical circles, these will be scientific and educational, and will help to broaden one's scope of knowledge.</p>
   <p>Whether Mr. Tobinson's opinions on education are founded on sound logic or merely on sentiment, is not the question to discuss here. But the fact is that the Workers Institute on Ashland Boulevard arose from a desire to <pb facs="5423972_5_1636.jpg" n="7"/>maintain itself, and the fact that it has life-force in it is the reason why it has been, since its inception, generously supported by the Jewish Courier, where its activities have been published each week, by the local Workmen's Circle, by the Socialist press and by the Jewish working class in general.</p>
   <p>It is said that when the Greek legislator Lycurgus began to reform and change the laws of Sparta, someone advised him to introduce complete equality and freedom. In answer to this advice, Lycurgus said, "My dear sir, begin practicing this first in your own home."</p>
   <p>The radical group of Jews have, therefore, accepted Lycurgus' advice, and have introduced their system of revolutionary education in their own institute where they themselves are the bosses. And by establishing their own home, they are now saved the trouble of giving advice to other people who seldom accept such advice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
