<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-01-18">Jan. 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish-Socialist Schools for Children: the Different Opinions on the School Question in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Bakal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-01-18">Jan. 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH-SOCIALIST SCHOOLS FOR CHILDREN: THE DIFFERENT OPINIONS ON THE SCHOOL QUESTION IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Bakal</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The school question has been renewed in Chicago. Again there is a dispute going on as to what sort of schools the organized, class-conscious, Jewish worker should open: English or Yiddish [schools]. This question springs up every time a school is to open--not only in Chicago, but throughout the entire land. Yiddish has been taught in the majority of schools lately. But the fact that there is a misunderstanding calls for a clarification of the question because no school is capable of succeeding unless all work in unison and harmony.</p>
   <p>Why should Yiddish be taught in a socialist school? Those who are against the <pb facs="5423972_5_1575.jpg" n="2"/>teaching of Yiddish argue that there are no academic nor nationalistic motives involved, nor for that matter, any motives at all. This does not mean that it is unimportant for our children to know Jewish literature, or to be acquainted with our cultural treasures. This is surely a necessity; for the deeper our spiritual and cultural knowledge is embodied in our children, the more certain we are that they will grow up to be deep thinkers and better citizens. No one can deny that Jewish literature--that such writers as Perez, Sholom Aleichem, Abramovitz, Ash, Raisen, and others--will be better understood by Jewish children, even in this country, than American literature. Jewish literature can have very deep effects on our children because it reflects the life of their fathers and grandfathers. This is not, however, the main thing.</p>
   <p>We open schools in order to bring our children closer to the ideology of freedom--so that they may continue the chain of socialist principles for which we struggle. It is understood that we cannot preach socialism to children in the same way as we do to adults. We should not prematurely rob our children <pb facs="5423972_5_1576.jpg" n="3"/>of their youth. On the contrary, we should awaken in them the finest sentiments and an aesthetic eagerness. The greater the awakening [of the desire] to strive for truth and justice, for freedom and democracy, the greater will the fire of protest burn within them.</p>
   <p>One thing is important: the children should come closer to their parents. They [the children] should be able to speak to the parents,and respect and understand their ideals. It is also important, from purely a pedagogical standpoint, that children should have a good home atmosphere. The fact that a number of children do poorly in school can be traced to the improper attitude of the parents toward their children. It is a fact that the children of radical-Jewish parents, who do not understand Yiddish well, are estranged from their own homes. They are not affected by the principles of their parents. It is, therefore, necessary to construct a bridge between the children and the parents.</p>
   <p>Our schools have the task of fighting against the unwholesome impressions which the public schools make upon our children. We want to weed out the false illusions that the capitalistically inclined teachers implant within them. If we <pb facs="5423972_5_1577.jpg" n="4"/>create a condition that will permit our children to go to the religious, Hebrew schools, to rabbis, and to the Zionist schools, we then will fail in fulfilling our mission.</p>
   <p>We are not of the opinion that children should not be taught English. On the contrary, we are certain that the children do speak and understand English well. The study of Yiddish, however, will not harm them; on the contrary, it will enrich their knowledge and will broaden their spiritual horizon. Yiddish should be taught to our children if we believe in the expansion of our movement and its effect on Judaism and Jewish life. This point must be made clear: Will our movement terminate? Will our children have no part in spreading socialism among the Jewish masses? We all believe that the Jewish labor movement will continue. If not, why build such great institutions? Why devote so much energy and activity to it?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
