<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-06">Jan. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[The "Ford-Ward" Offers an Alibi]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-06">Jan. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[THE "FORD-WARD" OFFERS AN ALIBI]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The yellow "Ford-Ward" has at last broken its silence. It spoke up yesterday and it spoke in a manner that was to be expected from it. It claimed that about two years ago, the Courier printed an ad of Ford's and it wondered why the Courier was raising such a fuss now. The "Ford-Ward" to prove its contention, printed a two-line ad which a Chicago Jew, who had a few Fords to sell, had placed in the Courier last year and for which he paid a few dollars. The "Ford-Ward" calls this a Ford advertisement. The yellow journalists know that this contention is ridiculous but they could not remain silent any longer. The readers had begun to ask questions and since they could not answer those questions, they did what the rich thief in a certain story did. When the judge asked him why he had stolen the watch, the thief replied: "Why shouldn't I have a right to wear a watch? Don't you wear a <pb facs="5423972_5_0835.jpg" n="2"/>watch?"</p>
   <p>A Ford ad is an ad that Henry Ford places in a newspaper and for which he pays with a Ford check. When a Jew advertises that he has an old Ford for sale, it is a Jewish ad, and a Jewish newspaper may print a Jewish ad. The "Ford-Ward" is the only Jewish newspaper in America which gets Ford checks--all in the name of socialism, in the name of the Jewish workers, in the name of trade union principles. Ford will not permit any unions in his factories, and, logically, a Socialist newspaper should not accept any advertisements from him, but the Judaism of the "Ford-Ward" is worth as much as its love of truth, and its love of truth is worth as much as the education of its editors and managers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
