<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-27">May 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Is the Jewish Press Old-Fashioned?</title><title level="a" type="Sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-27">May 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">IS THE JEWISH PRESS OLD-FASHIONED?</title><title level="a" type="Sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The accusation is often made against the Jewish press, and especially against the great Jewish dailies in this country, that they are old-fashioned and do not compare favorably with the American dailies printed in the English language, because the Yiddish dailies devote less attention to the human side of things than the other papers in the country. Many people who read both Yiddish and American non-Yiddish dailies maintain that the former is somewhat dull and altogether old-fashioned, for they carry no social column, do not publish stories relating to crime and divorce scandals, and carry no bedroom stories and so forth. Instead the Yiddish dailies publish articles of a purely theoretical and intellectual nature and thus partake more of the nature of magazines than of newspapers.</p>
   <p>The facts as stated above are true, but the interpretations placed upon them <pb facs="5423972_5_0860.jpg" n="2"/>are false. Every newspaper must reflect the mind, the sentiments, and the emotions of their readers, and the Yiddish dailies reflect the sentiments and the views of the Yiddish readers and these readers are not interested in bedroom stories, in crime, or in stories of scandal. They are interested in news and they want their newspaper to be a political, literary, social, economic, and religious world history of yesterday. That is all they seek in the newspaper, and therefore the Yiddish dailies would only impose upon their readers if they were to publish scandal stories and the like.</p>
   <p>It must further be borne in mind that there are only two Yiddish monthlies in the country, both of which are not all too popular, either in tone or in content, for they publish more articles of a purely theoretical nature than so-called live-wire stories. The Yiddish daily, therefore, must serve a double purpose, that of a newspaper and that of a magazine, and this explains why the Yiddish dailies are not devoted to news only and why they publish more articles of a purely theoretical nature than the average American daily. In <pb facs="5423972_5_0861.jpg" n="3"/>addition, many features that make up part of the contents of an average American daily, such as the sporting section, the commercial page, the fashion page, the society page, the religious page, would have no place whatsoever in a Yiddish daily, for the man or woman who is already interested in sports or in fashions, or in the social side of religion, is as a rule a reader of an American daily, and it would only be a duplication of effort to publish such features in the Yiddish press. The Yiddish dailies are so made up as to serve the specific purposes, tastes, and needs of the Yiddish reader. He wants to find in his daily a great deal of international news, because he is more interested in international news than the average American reader, for the simple reason that he has seen more of the world than the American reader; he also wants to find in his daily all the local, national, and international Jewish news available, and, in addition to that, a few articles of a more theoretical character. The women folk are interested in a good serial story and therefore all of the Yiddish dailies carry one or two serial stories, mostly of a melodramatic or popular character. These and a few other features, such as an editorial, theatrical and literary <pb facs="5423972_5_0862.jpg" n="4"/>criticism, and letters to the editor, make up the average Yiddish daily.</p>
   <p>Taking the average American daily as a standard, the Yiddish daily seems to be old-fashioned, whereas in fact it is not, because it gives its readers all they want to find in it. The standard of a daily is the demand of the reader, and to give him something other than his demand or what he has no use for, is merely a waste of energy and an imposition on him. If the Yiddish daily is old-fashioned, then one might say that the French, English, or Italian dailies are also old-fashioned because they are so fundamentally different from the average American daily, yet no one claims that they are old-fashioned, because they serve the purpose of their readers and fit their taste.</p>
   <p>The Yiddish dailies, with perhaps one exception, are a power for good from every point of view, because they do not carry demoralizing stories and instead publish articles that must enrich the knowledge and widen the vision of the <pb facs="5423972_5_0863.jpg" n="5"/>reader. In addition to their being daily newspapers, they are also educational agencies, and if this is to be called old-fashioned, then we wish that they remain old-fashioned for a long time to come, since by being so, they continue to remain a power for good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
