<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Hebrew Institute Must Become a National Institution</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">HEBREW INSTITUTE MUST BECOME A NATIONAL INSTITUTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a conference of all central organizations, called by the United Jewish Workers Alliance, the affairs of the Hebrew Institute were discussed in detail, as well as the movement, which is now going on in the Jewish community against this institution. This movement was due to the Hebrew Institute's action, when several weeks ago it closed its doors to Alexander Berkman, who was supposed to speak under the auspices of the Labor Defense League. The conference unanimously resolved to submit the following demands to the Hebrew Institute:</p>
   <p>Requests to be considered later:</p>
   <p>1. A board of delegates of the different clubs and organizations of the Hebrew Institute should be formed, which shall conduct the educational work of the Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1653.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. Three delegates of the board of delegates to become members of the Board of Directors of the Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <p>3. Recognition of those, who spend ten dollars a year for the support of the Institute, as regular ten dollar members with voting privileges.</p>
   <p>Requests to be considered at once:</p>
   <p>1. The Hebrew Institute shall recognize a temporary elected committee of this conference, until the board of delegates can be organized.</p>
   <p>2. The Hebrew Institute shall reinstate all employees, discharged on account of the meeting of the Labor Defense League.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1654.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>3. The Hebrew Institute shall apologize in the Jewish and English newspapers for its stand regarding the meeting of the Labor Defense League.</p>
   <p>4. The Hebrew Institute shall permit A. Berkman to speak when the latter is invited by a club or organization.</p>
   <p>A committee elected by the conference saw Mr. Phillip L. Seaman, superintendent of the Hebrew Institute yesterday and handed him all the requests. It seems that Mr. Seaman agrees in principle with all the points except the one regarding the reinstatement of the discharged employees. Mr. Seaman maintains, that this is a personal matter. The discharged employees, Mr. Seaman claims, were rude and tactless, and their reinstatement therefore is impossible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1655.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Seaman promised to bring this matter before the Board of Directors at its next meeting, September 22nd. He believes, that the directors will come to an understanding with the representatives of Chicago's Jewish Alliance, and that the life of the Hebrew Institute will become once more normal.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the local workers alliance are determined to continue their campaign, until the Hebrew Institute shall become a real national institution with a true free platform. The meeting of the September 22nd will have the deciding vote on this matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
