<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-01-21">Jan. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">History of the Chicago Jews</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_5_1094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_5_1094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-01-21">Jan. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">HISTORY OF THE CHICAGO JEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The history of the Jews in Chicago for the last seventy-five years has at last come to light. The material for this history was compiled by the Jewish Historical Society, which will give it to the public in connection with the celebration of the day, seventy-five years ago, when the first Jew came to Chicago.</p>
   <p>The history of the Jews, which has been published at the cost of many efforts and expenses, owes its appearance to the untiring work of Mr. Hyman L. Meitas, who spent five years at this difficult task in the Jewish Historical Society, an organization founded in 1918 for the purpose of writing it. The Society's first president was Julius Rosenwald. This position is now occupied by S. J. Rosenblatt.</p>
   <p>Only three thousand copies of the book will be published. The history <pb facs="5423972_5_1095.jpg" n="2"/>contains all the activities of the Jews from the time of the first Jew settled in Chicago until this day. Copies will be distributed to all members of the Jewish Historical Society next Monday night at a meeting of the society, as well as to all newspaper publishers, libraries, and colleges. Very few copies will be sold.</p>
   <p>President Rosenblatt declared yesterday that the task of writing this book was a very difficult one, but that the results are worth the trouble.</p>
   <p>"I feel," said Rosenblatt, "that this book will be kept sacred by all Chicago Jews because it is a memorial to their marvelous participation in the growth of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
