<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 34,
<date when="1903-08-21">Aug. 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Who Are Obstructing and Baiting Us?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 34,
<date when="1903-08-21">Aug. 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">WHO ARE OBSTRUCTING AND BAITING US?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the civilized nations the clergy found out that the baiting of people among themselves often brings bad consequences to the priests. In Germany and France the clergy have stopped the baiting of people, but among the Lithuanians the clergy still do it, making fights between brothers. The clergy, through the pulpit and confession, denounce those who are spreading literature, who are making the people cultured and intellectual. The clergy never have uplifted the people; the clergy wants to see the people in ignorance, darkness and poverty. Those who want to uplift the ignorant Lithuanians are denounced by the clergy with malice and malignity as infidels. Even among us there are people who blindly believe the priests. The greatest aim of the clergy is Divide et impera (divide and rule), as the clergy have done in ancient times. They are teaching nothing except obstruction and baiting.</p>
   <p>At present the living conditions of the clergy are so good that in order <pb facs="5423970_3_1641.jpg" n="2"/>to have such a life always, this clergy are keeping the people in ignorance and darkness. The clergy will become better when the people themselves will force the clergy to do useful work. Today the clergy are calling the people their sheep and cutting the wool, but when the people get enlightenment they will not permit wool to be cut. Every priest's aim is to keep his parishioners like beasts of burden. We must enlighten ourselves, then we will see the harm the clergy are doing to us; then we will force the clergy to preach the real Christian science, the real morality, not hypocrisy and exploitation of the people.</p>
   <p>J. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
