<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-07-26">July 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Candidates for Hanging</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-07-26">July 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CANDIDATES FOR HANGING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently four criminals, condemned by the courts, were executed at Sing Sing and eight more wait their turn. That is a real harvest for the executioner. But, truly, what benefit is there to accrue to humanity by executing criminals? Execution is a cruel bequest of the Jews, unfit for those who profess the religion of love. Execution is truthfully not a real punishment. The person suffers only fear. If criminals are executed because they have sinned against humanity by their deeds, in what way do they repay humanity for the harm that they had done? It must be admitted that in no way do they repay humanity. It would be more beneficial if the courts, in place of sending them to be hanged or to the electric chair; would send them instead to do dangerous work; for instance, to the arsenic or quicksilver mines, where the poisonous dust and gases kill a person. Humanity cannot get along without those materials. Then a murderer would even the score with humanity for his crimes. Why then do our courts, instead of sending criminals to such places, send them to <pb facs="5423970_3_0447.jpg" n="2"/>be hanged, to the electric chair, or to be beheaded? That is, in fact, neither punishment nor a repayment to society. Why do not the courts give a transgressor the opportunity to square himself with humanity for his misdeeds?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
