<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian National Council Holds First Meeting in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1258</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1258.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN NATIONAL COUNCIL HOLDS FIRST MEETING IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Officers of the larger Lithuanian-American organizations are now receiving copies of a pamphlet entitled "The First Meeting of the Lithuanian National Council". This meeting took place in the Great Northern Hotel, Chicago, and was attended by Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, Attorney A. Slakis, Reverend F. Kemesis, Mr. J. Vasiliauskas, and Mr. J. Sukevicius. The Reverends Jakaitis and Misius were also invited to attend, but Reverend Jakaitis reported that he was unable to do so; and although a telegram was sent to Reverend Misius inviting him to come to the conference, he did not come. Those who attended the meeting represented the largest Lithuanian-American right-wing organizations.</p>
   <p>The name of the new organization will be "The National Council in America". It is to be "the highest, and the central Lithuanian-American organization; its purpose is to unify, regulate, and direct all the national activities of Lithuanians in <pb facs="5423970_3_1259.jpg" n="2"/>America." The aims and activities of the National Council in America are described as follows: (1) To support the movement to regain political liberty for Lithuania; (2) to establish and maintain contact with a similar public or secret organization in Lithuania; (3) to concern itself with all public matters pertaining to Lithuanian-Americans, such as politics, education, promotion of Lithuanianism, organizations, etc.; (4) to support and assist all movements for the promotion of national culture in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Any Lithuanian-American organization that is authorized to establish lodges in the United States may send a delegate to the Council. Organizations which have less than one thousand members may send only one delegate; organizations with not less than five thousand members may send two delegates. A delegates may be elected only at the convention of an organization. Every organization is to contribute twenty-five dollars for every delegate it elects to the council.</p>
   <p>The following decision was made at the meeting in regard to the various war relief and autonomy funds that now exist among Lithuanians in America: "All public funds of those Lithuanian groups that are represented in the Council are expected to <pb facs="5423970_3_1260.jpg" n="3"/>conform to the decisions and advice of the Council." The constitution of the Council can be changed only by the votes of at least two-thirds of all the members of the Council. Conventions of the Council shall be called annually during the month of February. The officers of the Council are: Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, president; J. S. Vasiliauskas, vice-president; and Reverend F. Kemesis, secretary.</p>
   <p>Much has been said and written about the proposal to form a National Council. The nationalist press agreed with this proposal in principle. There was no agreement, however, on the manner in which the proposal was to be put into effect, The organizational plan of the proposal contained a number of defects, which threatened the success of this beautiful proposal. Although these defects had been pointed out, nevertheless those who took into their own hands the business of putting the proposal into effect did not pay any attention to them. They excused themselves by saying that "it is too late."</p>
   <p>The Chicago convention which gave effect to the proposal was in reality a factional convention. For that reason, the decisions that were made at the convention can affect only that faction which was represented at the convention. Other factions are being told that "the die has been cast," and that it is too late to make any <pb facs="5423970_3_1261.jpg" n="4"/>fundamental changes. In other words, as the Russians would say, "Byt Po Semu" (it must be this way, and cannot be any other way).</p>
   <p>We fear that this "Byt Po Semu" attitude will probably produce some very unpleasant results. The Chicago convention, which authorized the Temporary National Council to act, could not have spoken in the name of all Lithuanian-Americans, because it did not represent all factions. Likewise, the Temporary National Council could not have spoken in the name of all Lithuanians in America, because it was established and authorized by the above-mentioned convention. Instead of engaging only in preparatory works, and acting only in an advisory capacity, the convention and the Temporary National Council made permanent decisions and presented to the Lithuanian-American public a definite and unchangeable project. It is customary for persons who propose something to submit a plan of their proposal for the consideration and approval or disapproval of all those who are affected by the matter.....</p>
   <p>The plan of the National Council in America did not meet with the approval of all <pb facs="5423970_3_1262.jpg" n="5"/>Lithuanian-American factions. The nationalists stated that the plan would fail unless certain changes were made. The Socialists reacted negatively to the proposal. The Chicago convention and the Temporary National Council received ample warning to proceed with the creation of the National Council by a middle-of-the-road policy, to avoid all factionalism. Nevertheless, the warning was not heeded. Now, as before, the nationalists enthusiastically agree with the idea of forming a National Council, but they are completely opposed to the present one because it was formed by the right-wing faction; the Council is composed of members of the right-wing faction, and it is organized in such a manner as to render powerless the other two Lithuanian-American factions.</p>
   <p>The present setup of the Council permits the rightists to control everything and act as they please. In the present Council there is not even one representative from the center faction; the same is true in regard to the Socialist faction. We doubt if any of these two factions would be willing to support the Council in its present form. Therefore, the so-called National Council in America will remain <pb facs="5423970_3_1263.jpg" n="6"/>as an organization of the right-wing faction. Only rightists are represented in the Council. For that reason, as we see it, that Council has no right to speak in the name of all Lithuanians in America. That Council especially has no right to speak in the name of the whole Lithuanian nation.</p>
   <p>The nationalists are willing to support a national council that would really represent all Lithuanian factions. The present Council should be reorganized to meet this requirement. Representation in the Council should be, not according to organizations, but according to factions. The Council should be composed of about two representatives from each of the three Lithuanian factions; one other member should be selected to represent the nonpartisan group. If those persons who now control the affairs of the Council really desire to avoid quarrels and to see peace and unity among our people, then they should either reorganize the Council to satisfy all factions, or cease speaking in the name of all Lithuanians and call the Council a center of only one faction. That should be done for the sake of honesty and peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
