<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-29">Mar. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Fourteen Societies Co-Operate to Aid Starving Lithuanians</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Ambrozevicia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-29">Mar. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">FOURTEEN SOCIETIES CO-OPERATE TO AID STARVING LITHUANIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Ambrozevicia</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago, an alliance of fourteen societies was organized on the West Side for the purpose of collecting donations for our starving brothers in Lithuania and Russia. Each of the societies has appointed delegates who meet from time to time and who act for the societies.</p>
   <p>Although this alliance was formed only a comparatively short time ago, it has already distinguished itself. A successful mass meeting was called not long ago. In addition, the alliance was responsible for the printing of special blanks which are being distributed to Lithuanian homes. Those who receive these blanks will indicate thereon the amounts they will donate from their weekly pay checks for the war sufferers. From what has been learned, it can be expected that the plan will be successful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0283.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The alliance has not yet decided through which of the existing funds the collected money will be sent. [Translator's note: Three relief funds were maintained by the Lithuanians.] Because no one fund is being favored, the alliance is composed of people of various views whose only purpose is to collect as much as possible.</p>
   <p>Generally speaking, the affairs of the alliance are conducted in an exemplary manner. The delegates of the societies give serious consideration to the problems discussed at the meetings, and harmony is maintained.</p>
   <p>The collection of money and its safekeeping is also well organized. Every cent is entered in the books and is then entrusted to a treasurer who is under a thousand-dollar bond. Knowing all this, one can feel assured of the safety of the donated money. Not one cent will be used for outside purposes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
