<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 3,
<date when="1904-01-15">Jan. 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Account of the Aurora Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0970</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0970.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 3,
<date when="1904-01-15">Jan. 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACCOUNT OF THE AURORA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few years ago the question of national affairs was brought up by the Lithuanian newspapers. The most important of these was helping poor Lithuanian students. At that time the problem of helping students was entirely neglected. In Europe societies were organized to help students, but such societies were persecuted by the governments. Therefore, they could not become strong. They are still weak. The European people were the first to make plans to help students. American Lithuanians, though they were not persecuted by government, have begun only lately to understand and to take action in helping poor students. For this purpose, in the month of December, 1901, a meeting was called at the office of Dr. A. L. Graiciunas in Chicago. These men succeeded in organizing such a society under the name of Aurora. The new society secured more members and named a committee to make by-laws. At the second meeting the by-laws finally were adopted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0971.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Later on the membership and the capital of the society both increased. They were able to give to one girl student a stipend. When the news of the Aurora Society's purpose spread throughout the Lithuanian colonies of America, the Lithuanians sensed the need of the students and began to contribute to the Aurora Society's student fund. So the assets of the society increased. They were able to give stipends to another student. Today the Aurora Society is financially strong and gives help has been increased to some of the students.</p>
   <p>Last year the Aurora Society called on all the national Lithuanian societies of Chicago to join in helping students. Some of the societies sent their delegates to our meeting, while others gave no answer. At the meeting the majority were in favor of helping students while a few were against it. The delegates said that they would present our purpose at the meetings of their societies, but so far we have received no reply.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0972.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There are some people who are against this great cause. We are going forward in our membership and the budget also is increasing. The Aurora Society, during the past two years, has accomplished a gigantic task.</p>
   <p>Since the organization of the Aurora Society we have contributed to students this amount: $808.82</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Paid in stipends and help to students</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$421.24</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For the by-laws</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>13.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>7.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Total expense</cell>
     <cell>441.24</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>367.58</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The Aurora Society at present is giving stipends to four students and to two students other help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
