<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 40,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">American Lithuanians Must Help Lithuania</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 40,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN LITHUANIANS MUST HELP LITHUANIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>War is already in Lithuania! Russians and Germans have concentrated close to a million soldiers near the Prussian border. This announcement was made by several newspapers in the United States.</p>
   <p>We have been notified that the Germans have captured the Lithuanian town of Kibartai, near the Prussian border. We have also information that Russians and Germans have been fighting for three days near the Lithuanian town of Eitkunai, which is also located very close to the Prussian border.</p>
   <p>This is only the beginning. Russia did not have enough time to mobilize its army and send it to the Prussian border to meet the Germans before they cross the border. The armies are approaching one another, and the battle between Russians and Germans is expected almost any hour. This battle, as we all know, will be fought in Lithuania, on our land, where our brothers and sisters are living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our unfortunate Lithuania will have to suffer the horrors of this terrible war, which is brought upon them by two great powers, Russia and Germany. On account of their hate for one another, an innocent nation, such as Lithuania, must and see its homes destroyed by both armies. There is no other nation in the world that has suffered more than the Lithuanian nation. Lithuania's geographical position is known to historians as the threshold between two great powers, Russia and Germany. Lithuania suffered many terrible wars for more than five hundred years. Most of the past wars and battles were fought on Lithuanian soil. Perhaps this twenty century Gruenwald-Battle on Lithuanian soil will decide the fate of our nation in the future. What will happen to Lithuania? What will happen to our fatherland? One thing we know, that Lithuania will be destroyed by fire and her soil will be soaked with the blood and tears of our people, and all the land will be covered with dead corpses. That <pb facs="5423970_3_0374.jpg" n="3"/>is what will happen to our fatherland. No matter how we look at this situation, there is no salvation for Lithuania. We don't know whether our country will survive or disappear entirely from the map of Europe. Fire and starvation may annihilate all Lithuania completely during this horrible war. We hope this will not happen. We have no idea who will be the winner in the present European tragedy, Russia or Germany. The fate of our nation depends upon the winner in the war. The progressive group of Lithuanian people are in favor of Germany to win the war, and the Catholic group are in favor of Germany to win the war only for religious reasons. The progressive group prefer to be under Germany from the cultural viewpoint only.</p>
   <p>After this European tragedy it takes many years for Lithuania to heal the wounds of war, which she is getting now. In this case it is the same as in any other case, the stronger always takes advantage of the weaker. Might is right and we have no right to <pb facs="5423970_3_0375.jpg" n="4"/>question it. Nobody pays any attention to the weaker and the weaker will always be ignored and his pleadings will always be overlooked. The stronger one never asks any questions from the weaker one, whether right or wrong, the weaker one must always agree. This is the very same situation which our country is facing today. Our nation is small and weak and the war made her still weaker. Our voice of protest and pleading for justice to our nation never reach the proper authorities, and if it does reach them is ignored by the power of Europe. We cannot avoid now what is going on in Lithuania, our fatherland, and we cannot protect our country from this horrible war, we have to face the facts as they are today.</p>
   <p>Brothers, who will wipe away the tears of our fatherland? Who will remove the cause of poverty and who will lighten the burden of starvation of our fatherland? Who will show the mercy and extend a helping hand to our weary and ruined fatherland?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0376.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Will Germany do it? Will Russia do it? No, none of these countries will help our country; only we can help our fatherland.</p>
   <p>From the very beginning of our immigration to the United States we haven't faced such an important moment as we are facing now. Our nation never needed as much help before as she needs now. Our fatherland has not made any appeal to us for help as yet, but we cannot wait for her appeal, we must act immediately and make all necessary preparations to help her as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Lithuania is facing a very dangerous situation, and she does not know what will happen tomorrow and what the future will be. She has no time to communicate with us, for she is spiritually demoralized by this horrible war.</p>
   <p>In the first place, it would be improper for us to wait until our <pb facs="5423970_3_0377.jpg" n="6"/>fatherland makes the appeal to us for help. If we did not help our fatherland without an appeal, it would prove that we have no love for our country. We must make every effort to organize immediately all our forces for helping Lithuania, our fatherland, where our fathers, mothers, brothers, and sisters are suffering the hardships, poverty and horrors of war. We must immediately establish the fund by contributions for helping our nation.</p>
   <p>Let this fund unite all American Lithuanians without any discrimination and regardless of their political or religious views. This is an unusual situation which our country is facing today. We must forget our politics and religion for the time being; we must put everything aside and forget our differences for a little while. And if we don't do that we will not be united and we will not be able to accomplish anything worthwhile without unity. This <pb facs="5423970_3_0378.jpg" n="7"/>time we need the support of every Lithuanian in America. Our fatherland needs all the help we can give right now; we cannot afford to delay it one day. This is an emergency; our nation is in great danger and it is our duty to help our country as much as possible. If anybody has any heart and feeling and will make some contribution to that fund, it will help our fatherland.</p>
   <p>We, the undersigned of the Lithuanian Alliance of America and the elected "Martyrs Aid Commission," and the members of the executive board, appeal to all American Lithuanians, asking them to help Lithuania, our fatherland. We are not asking but demanding to help Lithuania, this is an emergency and our country needs the help. This is not charity work. This is a duty of sons of the fatherland to help their country in time of national emergency. A man cannot call himself a Lithuanian if he does not extend his hand of help to a sinking Lithuanian and does not want to save him from drowning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0379.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Morevoer, we don't believe that there is a man who would not be willing to help his brother whose life is in great danger. We don't doubt that every Lithuanian society will understand the importance of this moment and will make every effort to do its share in helping Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Send your contributions to the Martyrs' Commission of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The Martyrs' Commission has been appointed by the Lithuanian Alliance of America to help Lithuania in times of great national emergency. The Martyrs' Commission has been in existence for a good many years and has been supervised by the executive board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The Martyrs' Commission, under supervision of the executive board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, will make arrangements with the committee in Lithuania to help those people first who have suffered the most from this war. Every cent will be accounted for and published in the newspapers, in order to show to the public how the funds are handled by the <pb facs="5423970_3_0380.jpg" n="9"/>Martyrs' Commission.</p>
   <p>We, the undersigned, ask all the societies and their leaders in every Lithuanian colony, to call immediately a special meeting for determining the exact date for collecting contributions for our fatherland. The day is to be known as Lithuanian Relief Day. For this kind of work must be selected those who can be trusted upon their word of honor. Those people will be authorized by the Relief Committee to go from house to house and collect the contributions for our people who are suffering in Lithuania. Every Lithuanian should help our fatherland by contributing at least a small amount to the relief fund. Every single contribution will be a great help to our people who are suffering in this horrible war.</p>
   <p>All the societies in every Lithuanian colony should make certain resolutions at their meetings and publish these resolutions in all <pb facs="5423970_3_0381.jpg" n="10"/>the Lithuanian newspapers. All the contributions collected in every Lithuanian colony must be accounted for up to a cent and the amounts collected must be published in all the Lithuanian newspapers in the United States of America.</p>
   <p>The American Lithuanians, the societies, the benefactors, the workers and the contributors now have the opportunity to show themselves to Lithuania, not with their name, but with their work in time of national crisis. The Lithuanian people who live in the United States of America have a real opportunity now to show their patriotism to their fatherland.</p>
   <p>The undersigned members of the Martyrs' Aid Commission of the Lithuanian Alliance of America are as follows: Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, V. J. Sliabis and V. K. Rackauskas. The Lithuanian Alliance of America Executive Committee members are as follows: F. Zivatkauskas, <pb facs="5423970_3_0382.jpg" n="11"/>A. B. Strimaitis, P. Mikolainis, T. Paukstis, K. Varasius, T. Astramskas, Dr. J. S. Liupas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
