<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-05-22">May 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Execution of a Lithuanian</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-05-22">May 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE EXECUTION OF A LITHUANIAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Matthew Riktoraitis, of Waterbury, Connecticut, was hanged May 8 for butchering his wife.... Until the last minute Riktoraitis believed that the death penalty would be voided. However, the Board of Pardons found that to be impossible and the unfortunate man had to perish by hanging in the State Prison. Riktoraitis was led into the death chamber immediately after midnight. The noose was put around his neck, the trap under his feet was sprung, and in a little while only the corpse of the late Riktoraitis was hanging. Riktoraitis was calm to the very last moment. He admitted that he was guilty and that he had committed the murder during a quarrel with his wife.</p>
   <p>One shudders when one thinks of that moment when this unfortunate man, a razor in hand, attacked his unarmed wife and unmercifully butchered her. It seems that sympathy for such a person would be impossible. And yet, one must feel <pb facs="5423970_3_0462.jpg" n="2"/>sorry for him. He, like every murderer, was the victim of earlier inborn and developed habits and inclinations which created his cruel and wild character. He is an example of how bestial inclinations can be victorious over good, virtuous, human inclinations in a man.</p>
   <p>There was a time, in the history of humanity, when all people were of such wild character, leaping at each other's throats at the slightest provocation. That was the time when people differed but little from wild animals--when civilization was yet unknown to them. However, the human race did improve by degrees and its character became more gentle. Thousands of years elapsed before we reached our present stage. However, the bestial deeds occurring even now, from time to time.... testify that we are not yet free from the indications of that barbarism. The time will come, however, when they will finally disappear and the present-day hangings, executioners, and prisons will become merely memories--the same kind of memories as we now have of the medieval, brutal tortures: burning live people, driving them on sharp stakes, removing fingernails, etc. This will be effected by civilization, culture, <pb facs="5423970_3_0463.jpg" n="3"/>and the improved education of the progeny of the human race.</p>
   <p>The foundation of the future character of a man is education in youth. [Translator's note.-- "Education," here, is a translation of the Lithuanian word, "Auklejimas," for which there is no exact English equivalent. "Auklejimas" does not pertain to training in the arts or sciences, but to training of the character: in morals, will, and propriety.] It must be begun at the very beginning: form the days of youth, from the days of infancy. This should be remembered, first of all, by the parents.</p>
   <p>It is true that there is not one bad mother in the world: each one would gladly give her life for the happiness of her child; each one sees in her child a prince, a genius. But there is more than one mother and more than one father who forget that a bad sprout, having taken root in the heart of a sensitive youth, soon grows into a leafy, thorny weed which the gardener, arriving later, must remove with gloved hands lest it [the weed] injure the other plants.</p>
   <p>Speaking in this manner, we do not wish to cast the slightest shadow upon the <pb facs="5423970_3_0464.jpg" n="4"/>parents and family of the above-mentioned murderer. They might be good people, worthy of the sincerest respect, who should be sympathized with in this painful moment. But we all know that we recognize the coming storm only when the thunder rolls. Therefore, we are taking the opportunity at this moment to turn attention toward the last awful moment of that unfortunate man--when the hangman put the noose around his neck. Let every youth who is passing his days at the bottle; let every parent who is raising his children "as God wills it"--let them all visualize that scene and no other advice will be necessary. It will be obvious to all that having once started on the wrong path one can rise high--even to a hanging.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
