<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">South Chicago Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">SOUTH CHICAGO LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Up to the present time we have given money to the glory of God. The majority of the parishioners have refused to give money to the priest, because the wealth of the priest was increasing while the parishioners were becoming poorer and poorer. The debt of the church was increasing and the interest on the mortgage was not being paid. Later the parish committee received a letter from the bishop. He warned them that if the interest was not paid in fifteen days, the bishop would take away the church from them and give it to the Poles. When the parishioners heard about this danger, those who had received material benefit from the church elected collectors and sent them to the Lithuanian homes for donations. The collectors obtained more money than was necessary to pay the bishop's interest. Now the committee's and the church's businesses are flourishing better than before. As a matter of course, the church is the businessman's affair, but the parishioners made a demand that the treasurer must be under bond. A parishioners' meeting was called. They elected a laborer for treasurer. Having deposited his bond, he <pb facs="5423970_3_1604.jpg" n="2"/>demanded from the committee that they turn over to him the parish money.</p>
   <p>The committee voted to turn the money over to the treasurer, but some of them refused to give him all the money.</p>
   <p>Not long ago Rev. Petraitis came to Chicago. His way of managing the parish affairs was the same as that of any other Catholic priest in America. He called a parish meeting and demanded from the treasurer all the parish money. The parishioners willingly complied with the priest's demand. It looked as if the parish meetings would be unnecessary after that. But after Christmas the priest called a meeting for the glory of God and decided to have two banquets: one in Kensington, and the other in South Chicago. The Kensingtonians refused to have the banquet, while the South Chicagoans agreed to the priest's proposal. The banquet was held on February 25. The priest had this banquet in a hurry, before the national societies had theirs, because he wants to empty the pockets of the people before they go to the national societies' banquets. The priest wants above all to harm the 74th branch of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, but the obstructive methods of the priest cannot damage our branch because it well organized and is growing fast.</p>
   <p>Reviewer</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
