<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-12-17">Dec. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">More about the Lithuanian National Council of America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-12-17">Dec. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT THE LITHUANIAN NATIONAL COUNCIL OF AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Much had been written in our press in the early part of the year concerning the Lithuanian National Council of America, which was formed by the rightist [Catholic] faction mainly for the purpose of aiding Lithuania to regain political freedom. It will be recalled that the other two Lithuanian-American factions, the middle [Nationalist] and leftist [Socialist] factions, refused to support the Council because it was formed and controlled entirely by the rightists.</p>
   <p>Now the Lithuanian-American press has begun to devote much space to the suggestion to form a national council of all factions, one that would be primarily devoted to the common interests of Lithuanian-Americans but would also promote the interests of Lithuania as much as possible. It is a good thing that this matter is receiving so much attention. It shows that our newspapers have realized the futility of dividing our people into partisan <pb facs="5423970_3_0726.jpg" n="2"/>factions during these historic times. Another thing, it is better to talk of unity and harmony than to fight and quarrel as we have been doing in the past. An old proverb states that "a straw union [weak union] is better than golden quarrels [big quarrels]".</p>
   <p>The following quotation is the opening paragraph of an article by Mr. Purenas, published in the Draugas (The Friend), suggesting how the Lithuanian National Council of America should be reorganized:</p>
   <p>"It appears that everybody wants the Lithuanian National Council of America to be composed of delegates from all factions, so that the Council would be able to speak in the name of all Lithuanian-Americans and receive the support of Lithuanian-Americans of all factions. In other words, it is desired that the Council should have the confidence of all Lithuanians. That is how it should be, and not any other way. Then, every statement made by the Council would have greater significance and power and would really be an expression of the opinion of all Lithuanian-Americans. On the other hand, if the Council <pb facs="5423970_3_0727.jpg" n="3"/>is not supported by all Lithuanians, by all factions, then its power and influence will be considerably diminished."</p>
   <p>In the above paragraph Mr. Purenas told the real truth. However, he failed to maintain this intelligent attitude to the end of his article. He wishes to unite the various Lithuanian-American factions but states that the Lithuanian National Council of America should be composed only of delegates from organizations and not from factions. He further states that anyone who disagrees with this plan does not deserve to be called a Lithuanian. Mr. Purenas is also against the inclusion of delegates from the Lithuanian-American newspapers.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, the quickest and most pratical way to form a united front of the Lithuanian factions is to form a national council that would be composed only of delegates from the various Lithuanian-American newspapers.</p>
   <p>Who precipitated and who is really responsible for all the quarrels and disputes, from which we all strongly desire to free ourselves but thus far <pb facs="5423970_3_0728.jpg" n="4"/>have been unable to do? Our organizations? Our factionalism? No, of course not! It is our newspapers that lead and guide our organizations and various factions. They knew how to create antagonism and disunity among our people, now let them try and create harmony among them.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that is one of the most practical methods, because nothing can be accomplished among our people without the full support of the newspapers. However, if anyone can think of a better plan, then we would be glad to give it consideration.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, while this question is being discussed, it would be a good idea to adopt a more tactful tone of expression. Let us negotiate, talk, and deliberate, but let us not abuse one another unnecessarily; otherwise, instead of achieving harmony, we will be drawn into still greater quarrels and disputes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
