<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of Lithuanian Farmers' Society</title>, <date when="1937">1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Farmers' Society, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of Lithuanian Farmers' Society</title>, <date when="1937">1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Farmers' Society, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lithuanian Farmers' Society meetings are held in the West Side Hall, 2242-44 W. 23rd Place. The first meeting was held on August 17, 1906 in the J. Zilis Hall, 1 W. 24th St.</p>
   <p>Record of the First meeting:</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by citizen Michael Duda, who told the people that the purpose of the meeting was to organize a Lithuanian Society in that neighborhood.</p>
   <p>Further, they wondered what name to give the society. Michael Duda made a motion that the name should be "Farmer of Lithuania; so it would always remind them of Lithuania, her farmers and our brothers. Also, the name was fitting to them, as they themselves, had been mostly Lithuanian farmers. So they unanimously voted the name: "Society of the Farmers of Lithuania."</p>
   <p>Citizen J. Jilis, took upon himself the task of getting a charter, thus doing a service to the newly organized society. The task of making a constitution was given to Michael Duda.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0651.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Society's Aim:</p>
   <p>1. Assistance to members in case of sickness, a fitting funeral for deceased members and best possible relief to orphans.</p>
   <p>2. Giving the members facilities to acquire more knowledge and strengthening the mutual understanding among Lithuanians in America.</p>
   <p>3. The society will try to the best of its ability to uphold and strengthen the love of Lithuania and the Lithuanian language among her members as well as among those who do not belong to the society. Also, if their means permit, to start a library, a reading place and to organize a school with a farmer's course.</p>
   <p>4. The society aims to be neutral in all religious and political affairs both in Lithuania and America. The society will participate only in such Lithuanian affairs as bring honor and help to Lithuania. Also, it will undertake to work for all Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>What the Society did for Enlightening and Cultural Work:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0652.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>1907 - The Society's first and hardest work was to organize a reading and writing school. Further, as the society grew stronger it was voted that women should be admitted.</p>
   <p>1911 - A family dance was given, of which the proceeds were set aside for a National home in Vilna and after that all the members put together in gifts $60. Also, they gave another dance to help the "Sun Society," which is in Kaunas. This same year $46 was sent to the "Sun Society."</p>
   <p>A society member, S. Biezis, translated from a Russian book, "Story of the Seven Hanged," and gave it to the society free of charge. The society printed it and sold 2,000 copies.</p>
   <p>1912 - The society gave a picnic and dance, sending the profits to a Lithuanian library in Lithuania. Also, another dance was given. The money was to help John Sileikis, who wanted to be an artist, and was a student at the "Art Institute."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0653.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This same year, the society loaned its books (121 copies - worth $123.00) to the West Side Lithuanian Public Library. They also paid 5% out of the society's income for the upkeep of the books. The library was organized by the society in 1911, and was opened in 1912. There were all sorts of books, Lithuanian newspapers and magazines, which could be used free of charge.</p>
   <p>1913 - Representatives of the Lithuanian Knowledge Society arrived from Lithuania to get gifts for the building of the national home in Vilna. This society gave $21.</p>
   <p>1914 - When the war began in Europe, the society was worried about its countrymen. They participated in the Lithuanian Conference and it was voted to hold an all Lithuanian Convention. It was fixed that the Convention would be held in New York. The society gave some money and sent its delegates to the Convention. The society gave $100.00 from her treasury and got more gifts from the meetings. The Lithuanian veterans of the war got $115.00 from the society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0654.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>1915- This year the society sent $126.00 to Lithuania for the veterans. Also $300.00 was loaned to S. Biezis, so he could go through his medical course.</p>
   <p>1916 - $150.00 made from dances was sent to the Knowledge Society, Vilna. Also, on Lithuanian Flag Day, November 1, gifts were collected. In the streets $212.00 was collected.</p>
   <p>1917- $95.00 made from dances was sent to the Lithuanian Antonomy Fund. The society gave $80.00 to a sick member who had been ill for a long time. A dance was held for his benefit.</p>
   <p>Barbara Zilvitaite, a Valparaiso University student was freed from payments.</p>
   <p>1918 - The society gave money for the expenses of a national parade, which was held town town on October 12. The Lithuanians participated in the parade with the aim of acquainting the Lithuanian nation with other nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0655.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>At the end of the war a cry arose to gather money for the purpose of freeing Lithuania. The society decided to give $300.00. The members held meetings and got $63. The entire gift for the year was $500.</p>
   <p>1919 - The society's gifts were as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Lithuanian Bublic Library</cell>
     <cell>$15.00;</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sick member</cell>
     <cell>65.00;</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lithuanian Bill fund</cell>
     <cell>100.00;</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lithuanian Red Cross Society</cell>
     <cell>25.00.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>1920 - The society took part in the impressive Chicago Lithuanian demonstration protesting against Poland. One hundred eighteen dollars were collected from the society members and sent to the Lithuanian Protection Committee.</p>
   <p>1921 - The society took part in the greeting of the newly arrived Lithuanian representative, V. Carnecki. Being mindful of the national needs, the society gave for such over $185.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0656.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>1922- Decided to give 1% to the Gold-Silver Fund and $50.00 to the Vilna Orphans.</p>
   <p>1923 - It was discovered that the West Side Library was discontinued and all the books were returned to societies from which they had been borrowed.</p>
   <p>1925 - It was decided to collect money for the purpose of erecting a statue in Lithuania in honor of the Lithuanian historian, Simon Daukantas.</p>
   <p>1934 - Darius' and Girenas' gifts for statue $10. J. Janusauskas' gifts for flying fund $10.</p>
   <p>There are about 500 members. The society's property at present is worth $13,279.</p>
   <p>J. Zurkauskas, president, 1957 W. 23rd St.</p>
   <p>A. Linkus, secretary, 2144 W. 23rd Pl.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
