<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Providence of God Parish in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD PARISH IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, March 2, at the police station court was held for the parishioners for breaking the windows and for a riot in the church. The policemen were the witnesses against the arrested, and the following were found guilty and fined:</p>
   <p>Paul Povilonis, fined $50; Monica Peciukaitiene, $150; Anton Peciukaitis, $50; John Ustaitis, $75; Dominio Pivarunas, $50; Frank Masinskas, $100; Catherine Masinskine, $200; Mary Bruoziene, $250; Casimir Simkus, $11.50; Michael Jurgaitis, $10; Michael Blazys, $50; Anton Kelvetis, $5; Frank Strikauskis, $5.</p>
   <p>The last five indicted whose fines were small have paid their fines, but the eight persons who fines are higher did not pay. They appealed to the higher court and were sent to the grand jury. They will be tried on February 20. If the police is able to prove their guilt, they will be held responsible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The names of those incriminated are: Catherine Masinskiene, Paul Bugvilionis, Anton Paciukaitis, Monica Peciukaitiene, John Ustaitis, Peter Bugvilaitis, Frank Strikauskis, Peter Venckus, Peter Ganaitis, Michael Blazys, Joseph Markunas, Casimir Sereika, Alexander Dargis, and Mary Bruosiene.</p>
   <p>For both Paciukatis's above named the bonds are set at $1,000 each, all others' bonds are $500 each.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday the parishioners of the Lithuanian Providence of God parish held their meeting at the Freiheit Turner Hall, 3417 S. Halsted St. The hall was packed with people. Never before was there such a multitude of people at any church gathering in Chicago as at this meeting. There were twenty-five speakers at this large meeting. The speakers bared the black deeds of the priests and the bishops, the injury of the church to humanity, etc. Some of the speakers even brought tears to the public. The speeches started from 1:30 and lasted up to 8 P. M. Almost every speaker stated that the clergy have been for centuries the oppressors of humanity, <pb facs="5423970_3_1599.jpg" n="3"/>and that the Catholic church is the worst enemy of human rights. The speakers wished that the people would leave the Catholic church, not build any churches, and quit supporting the clergy.</p>
   <p>But the people do not agree with the speakers: the people say that the churches are good, only the priest Steponavicia and the bishop are no good. If the bishop will not give this parish a better priest, the parishioners will build another church and will assign this new church not to the bishop, but to the pope.</p>
   <p>This is a good project. That means we shall not give it to the Gypsy, but to his wife. Would this scare the Gypsy? Whether they give the church to the bishop or to the pope, the church will not be the parishioners', but the clergy's. First of all the people should know that the pope will not accept them as good Catholics if they do not obey the bishop. As the priest is the agent of the bishop, so is the bishop the agent of the pope. As the bishop does not listen to the parishioners but to the pariest, so the pope will not listen to the parishioners but he will listen to the bishop.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1600.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Even the church of the Providence of God has been built by the parishioners who were not satisfied with the Rev. Krawczunas's conduct at the St. George Church on Bridgeport. By building this church the people believed that they built it on a better foundation; they believed that the priest would have no rights to control this church; they believed that the parishioners would control it. How long have the parishioners controlled the church? When you build another church it will be the same as with the first. If you do not give the church to the bishop, he will not give you a priest and you will be denounced as infidels. And when the denunciation of the bishop becomes loathsome, then you will assign him the new church, as you did with the former one. By building churches you will benefit the bishop, but not yourselves. You will empty your own pockets for the benefit of the bishop. You will do no harm to the bishop even though you would build hundred churches. He will be the richer, the more new churches you build for him. Instead of building a new church, you would do much better to build a new Lithuanian hall, to hold meetings, concerts, theatrical performances and other cultural activities. The Lithuanian hall is very <pb facs="5423970_3_1601.jpg" n="5"/>essential and the demands for such a hall are increasing daily. We are renting the halls from strangers. For any larger meeting, or for better theatrical performances we must rent a large hall and pay dearly for it. The money spent for the most common church could build the best hall, and this would be an honor to Lithuanians. They would have something to show. Would it not be nice if the next convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, which will be in Chicago, could be held in the Lithuanian hall? Now we must pay strangers for renting a hall for the convention. In Chicago the Lithuanians have built five churches; the sixth church is being organized by the priest Ambrozaitis, and now the parishioners of the Providence of God parish are preparing to build the seventh church! It is time to take care of ourselves, of the wealth of the bishop of Chicago we should not care. The Catholic bishop of Chicago is rich; he has several hundred churches; he is a millionaire. The Catholic bishop does not care about Lithuanians; he cares about the Lithuanians as little as we care about the Chinese. Why pour water into <pb facs="5423970_3_1602.jpg" n="6"/>the marsh when it is wet enough? Why build more churches for the bishop when he has too many of them and does not care about the people when they are fighting and killing each other for the wealth of the bishop?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
