<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 14,
<date when="1900-04-06">April 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">From the New Parish in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1691</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1691.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 14,
<date when="1900-04-06">April 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE NEW PARISH IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The West Side Chicago Lithuanians held a meeting on March 30 in the affairs of the new parish. It was decided to establish a new parish under the name, the Providence of God, Chicago. There was elected an administration of sixteen members: for President, John Petroszius, 46 W. 18th St.; vice-president, Vincent Liuberskis; Secretary, Silvester Dargewyczia; Treasurer, George Balczaitis.</p>
   <p>John Aglinskis, John Szemaitis, Frank Volinskis, Andrew Jurgaitis, Paul Jowaisza, Theofil Radawiczia, Joseph Zubawiczia, Joe Czepkauskis, Vincent Urbonas, Tadeusz Globis.</p>
   <p>All the said men gave $100 each as a bond, and the money is deposited in the Northern Trust Company bank. This bond is a protection for the money to be collected for the new church to be built. The deposited money cannot be taken from the bank by separate committee members, nor by all the committee, without the approval by the parish meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1692.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Collection started the fourth of this month. Each collector has a letter from the bank as proof that he is under bond. Therefore, we warn all the Lithuanians that they should donate money only to those collectors who can show the letters from the bank.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we decided to have two large meetings in the affairs of the parish: one on April 7th (Saturday), at 7 P. M., 531 Noble St.; another on Sunday, April 8th, at 2 P. M., W. Wallius Hall, 8801 Houston Avenue, South Chicago. To both meetings we are inviting all the Lithuanians to come so as to get acquainted with the new parish plans and the building of the new church.</p>
   <p>John Petroszius, President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
