<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 45,
<date when="1899-11-10">Nov. 10, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">From the Simonas Daukantas Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1195</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1195.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 45,
<date when="1899-11-10">Nov. 10, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE SIMONAS DAUKANTAS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, November 5, the Simonas Daukantas Society held its 106th yearly festival in memory of the honorable Lithuanian historian, Simonas Daukantas. The celebration was so successful that it could not be better. The day was sunny and warm, and the Lithuanians came from all parts of Chicago. The celebration started at 2:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>Seven Lithuanian societies participated in this celebration: The Simonas Daukantas Society, the Grand Duke Gedeminas of Lithuania, the Sons of Lithuania, the Liberty, the Truth Seekers, the Providence of God, and the King David. They marched with national emblems, Lithuanian and American flags, and a band was at the head of the marchers. Ladies rode in two coaches and were holding pictures of Simonas Daukantas, the Grand Duke Vytantas, and the Grand Duke Gedeminas. All pictures were decorated with flowers. When the marchers <pb facs="5423970_3_1196.jpg" n="2"/>came into the hall, the pictures and flags were placed on the stage. The curtain in the hall bore an inscription in large letters, "Long Live Lithuania." The hall was packed with people to capacity.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the program the choir sang the first song, "The Vilija, our Mother of the Rivulets." (Translator's note: The Vilija is a river in Lithuania, being tributary to the river Nemunas at Kaunas). The inaugural speech was delivered by Mr. A. Olszewski, publisher of Lietuva. He spoke about the purpose of this celebration and about the life of Simonas Daukantas, and later he invited the other speakers. Then the choir sang, "Lithuanians, enough for us to sleep!" The second speaker was Mr. M. Varanka. He told about the hard work in the literary field that Simonas Daukantas performed, and asked the Lithuanians to follow his steps. The speaker told that we must have in Chicago a Lithuanian national school to teach our young generation the Lithuanian spirit. Then John Bagdziunas said a poem, "Hop, hop, who is there?" The third speaker was S. Kodis, <pb facs="5423970_3_1197.jpg" n="3"/>who read an essay about the fatherland. Then Mrs. Olszewski declaimed, "Lithuania, the dear land of our old ancestors." The fourth speaker was Rev. Servetka, from Spring Valley, Ill. (Even though Rev. Krawczunas stated that this national celebration is for the propagation of infidelity, Rev. Servetka knew better what infidelity meant and took part in this national festival). The priest urged the Lithuanians to unite, work together for the cause of Lithuanianism. Then Miss Jadvyga Kanapeckaite declaimed, "Oh, I hear how the enemy of Lithuanianism is roaring." The fifth speaker, Mr. F. Masionis, spoke about the benefit of Simonas Daukantas' writings to Lithuanians. Then the choir sang, "Where the Nemunas is Billowing." The sixth speaker was Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, who urged to strive for education and enlightenment, because enlightenment will resurrect Lithuanianism and will subdue all the obstructors. Then Miss Mary Serekaite said a declamation, "Nevertheless, nevertheless, you lived up to." The seventh speaker was Mr. P. J. Jonaitis, who showed the 'doggishness' of some of the spiritual leaders in Chicago, how the Lithuanians donated their hard-earned money for the church and the priest gave the church to <pb facs="5423970_3_1198.jpg" n="4"/>the bishop, while those who donated their last pennies got a fist. They even started to publish a newspaper, Katalikas, in order to make the Lithuanians fight among themselves. Further, Miss J. Kanapickaite sang a song, "This is the Samogitians (Zemaiciai) Country." The eighth speaker was the treasurer and Judge Alexander Vienviskis, from Spring Valley, Ill. (Translator's note: Alexander Vienviskis, when he came from Lithuania to Spring Valley, Illinois, was unable to read or sign his name. He opened a butcher shop and grocery business. His customers' names he used to mark on a stick. Later he learned to read and to sign his name. He was very industrious and shrewd. He joined politics and was elected treasurer and judge of that mining town. At present his son is a well known judge in Illinois. His name is Vinbiscus).</p>
   <p>The judge said the Lithuanians must educate themselves and have unity in order to prepare themselves to great national deeds. Then the choir sang, "The Longest Years."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1199.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The ninth speaker, Alex Bijanskis, said that the number of Lithuanians who are seeking enlightenment is increasing yearly; we can judge at this present meeting by comparing it with the past celebrations in Chicago. The tenth speaker, Mr. Anton Steponavicze, said that the Lithuanian nation in Europe is the oldest and was the most cultured nation in the past. He said that the great men of Lithuania raised up the weak Polish nation. That all the greatest Polish writers are Lithuanians, that the Polish nation gave nothing good to Lithuania. When the Polish nobility and clergy baptized Lithuania, Lithuania lost her culture and independence. That the Daukantas has done more good to us than all the Polish priests together, that Simonas Daukantas gave lessons to Bishop Valanczauskas in Lithuanian and German languages. Then, when Simonas Daukantas was lying on the death bed in the room of Bishop Valanczauskas, the bishop chased the sick Daukantas out of his residence. Simonas Daukantas has done more for Lithuania than all the bishops together, that Simonas Daukantas stands closer to Lithuanians than even the pope in Rome. Then, at <pb facs="5423970_3_1200.jpg" n="6"/>the end of the program, the choir, accompanied by the band, sang the Lithuanian march, "Let the Forests Rustle." The banquet lasted until 2 A. M.</p>
   <p>We are thanking all that have taken part in this great national festival.</p>
   <p>After paying all the expenses, the Simonas Daukantas Society will have a net profit of several hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>F. Papauskis.</p>
   <p>The Celebration's Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
