<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-06-06">June 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Installation of the Bell at the Lithuanian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-06-06">June 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">INSTALLATION OF THE BELL AT THE LITHUANIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, 5,000 (or more) Lithuanians from Chicago celebrated the installation of the bell and the opening of the cemetery at Leafy Grove, 82nd Street and Keane Avenue. The bell was named Peter. Reverend Plage performed the ceremony. Reverend Mickevicia from Scranton, Pa., did not come. Reverend Plage took Mickevicia's place. Reverend Plage, after the ceremony, delivered a speech. Then a picnic was held for the benefit of the new cemetery.</p>
   <p>(Translator's note: At that time transportation was not as convenient as it is today. At that time, on Archer Avenue from Cicero Avenue to Joliet, one streetcar was running. Thus when thousands of Lithuanians came to the Archer and Cicero streetcar station, they found that the cars were not running that day. Hundreds of Lithuanians walked from Archer and Cicero Avenues to the Lithuanian National Cemetery at 82nd Street and Keane Avenue. Rumors were circulating that the Lithuanian Roman Catholic priests had asked the <pb facs="5423970_3_1541.jpg" n="2"/>streetcar company not to run the cars on that day; their ostensible purpose being to prevent the Lithuanians from attending the celebration in honor of the opening of a cemetery where the Lithuanians could be buried regardless of their faith or creed.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
