<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1899-06-09">June 9, 1899</date><title level="a">From the King David Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1738</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1738.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1899-06-09">June 9, 1899</date><title level="a">FROM THE KING DAVID SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When Rev. Krawczunas announced that he would chase out of the church all those societies that are protesting against him, the Society of King David, on May 21, sent its delegates to the Rev. Krawczunas to find out if he would permit them to hold their meeting in the church hall on May 28.</p>
   <p>The priest replied: "If you will revoke through the newspapers, under notary public, the statements in which you called me a thief and otherwise blackened me, then I will permit it."</p>
   <p>The committee answered: "We never called you a thief, but our society, as a church society, demanded from you to give us an honest account of the parish budget."</p>
   <p>The priest said: "Does your constitution say that you have the right to interfere into the parish affairs?"</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1739.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee answered: "Our constitution does not say anything about the interference with the parish affairs, but we, as parishioners, have the right to look into the parish affairs."</p>
   <p>Then the priest said. "Go away! You cannot belong any more to the parish."</p>
   <p>Therefore, our society called a meeting on May 28, at Azukas Hall. But when the priest saw that the society was not afraid of him and would hold its meeting, he announced in the church that the King David Society would hold its meeting in the church hall on Sunday. So the meeting was held in the church hall. The priest asked one of his followers, P. S., to persuade the society to approve the priest's aim, that is, that this society should not go against the priest. But the society refused to be persuaded and still demands of the priest to give us an honest account of the parish budget.</p>
   <p>A Member of the King David Society</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
