<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-11-05">Nov. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Our Lady of Vilna Parishioners at Odds with Their Pastor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-11-05">Nov. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LADY OF VILNA PARISHIONERS AT ODDS WITH THEIR PASTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The parishioners of the Our Lady of Vilna Lithuanian Roman Catholic parish, located at 23rd Place and Oakley Avenue, are at odds with their pastor, Reverend A. M. Brozaitis. About three hundred families belong to this parish. Harmony had prevailed in the parish for a comparatively long time, but lately, due to an increase of the church debt and to some other matters, quarrels have arisen between the parishioners and their pastor. The pastor had planned a tour of his parish for the purpose of collecting money to meet payments on the debt, but fearing it might antagonize the parishioners, he temporarily abandoned the plan.</p>
   <p>The pastor called a general parish meeting on October 24. At the meeting, he announced that he needed $3,000 to meet current payments on the church debt. The parishioners then requested a detailed expense account, covering all the years since the inception of the parish. Such financial statements were never <pb facs="5423970_3_1566.jpg" n="2"/>made by the pastor. He agreed to do this, but said it could not be done immediately. He announced that while the statement is being prepared he plans to tour the parish and collect the required sum of money. The parishioners disagreed and began to raise a rumpus. They censured the priest for his "mistakes" and behavior. He was berated for "abolishing" the parochial school (he had replaced the nuns, who taught in the school, with lay teachers and this action so antagonized the parishioners that they withdrew their children from the school). He was scolded for discharging the organist, who was "liked by everybody," and for his failure to issue financial statements of the parish.</p>
   <p>The priest answered that such matters were his business and not that of the parishioners. This statement of the pastor so angered the parishioners that they left the meeting saying, "if you can do everything alone, then why did you call the parishioners together?" The parishioners are very angry at Reverend Ambrozaitis, and are appealing to the archbishop to remove him from the parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
