<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-05">Dec. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Riotous Meeting Closed by Police</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Bridgeporter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-05">Dec. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">RIOTOUS MEETING CLOSED BY POLICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Bridgeporter</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday evening, not only the Freiheit Turner Hall, Bridgeport, but also several blocks of Halsted Street were crowded with people. They wanted to know who called the meeting and who was the person who signed the leaflet as the "Parishioner."</p>
   <p>The meeting, as far as we can judge from the leaflets, was called against the priest, Deacon Krauciunas of St. George's parish. But if a person were to have entered the hall, he would have thought that this meeting was called, not by the enemies of the priest, but by himself, because the deacon was sitting on the stage with a group of people around him. Among them were many policemen and detectives. With such a scheme, the deacon played a clever trick on the public. In the hall there was such a turmoil that it was impossible to bring order, and finally, with the help of police, the meeting was closed. In the <pb facs="5423970_3_1523.jpg" n="2"/>hall were not only the enemies of the deacon, but his supporters too, and both sides created such disorder, that it was impossible to have an orderly meeting.</p>
   <p>It is plain enough that the meeting was called against the deacon, but the public had no chance to hear why it was called. The opponents of the deacon are angry because he closed the meeting with the help of police, while his supporters are glad that their deacon thought up this scheme to disrupt this meeting, and that in the hall he acted as if he were in his own rectory. Well, no matter how it was, the public had a "free show," and we believe that in the future we will see more of such comedies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
