<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-21">Jan. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Statistical Survey of Roseland, Chicago Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-21">Jan. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">STATISTICAL SURVEY OF ROSELAND, CHICAGO LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Roseland Chicago Lithuanian colony is located in the vicinity of 108th and State Streets. It is estimated that about fifty Lithuanian families, two hundred single people, and six young ladies live in that colony.</p>
   <p>There are only three Lithuanian business establishments in Roseland: One saloon, and two meat markets.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians of Roseland have two organizations: The St. Peter and St. Paul Society, and the St. Vincent Society. However, these two societies are barely existing, because they do not promote the intellectual development of our people. The intellectual level of the Lithuanians in Roseland is rather low. Very few Lithuanian newspapers are received in this colony. The Lietuva (Lithuania), Tevyne (Fatherland), and the Keleivis (Traveller) are some of the Lithuanian newspapers that are read here. However, very few people read them. The greater majority of our people seem to prefer the saloon, and it is here that they spend most of their leisure moments. The saloon is the only place <pb facs="5423970_3_0549.jpg" n="2"/>where the Lithuanians of Roseland seek an "education".</p>
   <p>Most of the Lithuanians of Roseland are employed in the local railroad car factory. However, employment is rather slow here at present. Newcomers find it impossible to find jobs, as many long time residents of this colony have been unemployed for long periods.</p>
   <p>The All Saints Lithuanian Roman Catholic church, which is attended by most of the Lithuanians of Roseland, is located at 108th Street and Wabash Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
