<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Refuse Church Hall for Library Benefit Affair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">REFUSE CHURCH HALL FOR LIBRARY BENEFIT AFFAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the annual meeting of delegates from the organizations that support and maintain the Lithuanian Public Library at 1815 South Union Avenue, it was decided to hold a benefit social with speeches for the Library. An arrangements committee was elected for that purpose.</p>
   <p>The committee decided that the best place to hold the affair would be in the Providence of God (Lithuanian) parish hall, which is located at 18th Street and Union Avenue, directly across the street from the Library. Accordingly, the committee went to see the pastor, Reverend Krusas, to engage the hall. Instead of giving a definite answer, the priest displayed to the committee a letter, which he had received in November, 1913. It is written in the letter that directly across the street from the Providence of God Church there is a Lithuanian library in which all newspapers of Socialists and freethinkers are read.</p>
   <p>The priest then asked the members of the committee if the statement in the letter is true. The committee gave an affirmative answer. Then the priest <pb facs="5423970_3_1467.jpg" n="2"/>asked: "Where are those opportunities for intellectual advancement in that Library as you claim? All the filthy newspapers are found there, and there cannot be any educational opportunities in that filth." A member of the committee explained that besides those "filthy" newspapers there are Catholic newspapers and even Catholic literature in the library. He also explained that the Library is being operated on a strictly non-partisan and non-sectarian basis; no discrimination is made against any group or faction.</p>
   <p>The priest did not like the above explanation. He then asked the committee: "How would it look if God, the devil, and a Socialist were placed together on the altar of a church? Would that be non-partisan?" A member of the committee answered the priest by saying that "it would not be bad idea, because then a person who enters the church would have an opportunity to make a choice."</p>
   <p>The audience with the priest ended with heated arguments between the priest and the committee. The use of the parish hall was denied to the committee. When members of the committee were on their way to the priest, they did not even imagine that the priest would refuse the use of the hall to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
