<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-30">Oct. 30, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Commemorate Birthday of Simonas Daukantas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-30">Oct. 30, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATE BIRTHDAY OF SIMONAS DAUKANTAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, Oct. 25, the local Simonas Daukantas Society held its fifteenth annual commemoration of the birthday of Simonas Daukantas (1793-1864), famous Lithuanian historian, at the Freiheit Turner Hall, 3417 So. Halstod St.</p>
   <p>In the past, all commemorations started with a street parade. This year there was no parade. Chicago Lithuanians assembled in the Freiheit Turner Hall at 4:00 P.M., when a long and interesting program of orations, songs, recitations, and music began. The celebration was started by A. Bijanskas, president of the Simonas Daukantas Society. He explained the purpose and significance of the gathering and introduced the next speaker.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the occasion was attorney F. P. Bradchulis. His main <pb facs="5423970_3_1181.jpg" n="2"/>topic was love of our fatherland. He advocated the use and preservation of the Lithuanian language among our people in America. He described his impressions of Lithuania, where he spent his vacation last summer. He stated that a spectacular change has taken place in Lithuania since the Lithuanians regained the freedom of their press in 1904. The people in Lithuania are now very active in an effort to regain their full cultural and political rights. The Poles, who have been persecuting Lithuanians for centuries, are now being denounced in Lithuania as the greatest enemies of the Lithuanian race. Attorney Bradchulis urged the Lithuanians in America to remain true to their nationality, perpetuate their national unity, and never forget the holy land of Lithuania, which is covered with the blood of our forefathers.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was A. Olis (Olsevskis), publisher of the Lietuva. He spoke about Lithuanian Socialists; how they are fighting against people <pb facs="5423970_3_1182.jpg" n="3"/>who are just as poor as they are, and how they fail to reach and harm the real capitalists. He explained how the present misery of the masses is due not to capitalists, but to drunkedness and laziness; people who make an effort to improve their living and to possess wealth always succeed. He said that modern Socialists promise the people a heaven on earth only with words and not with deeds; Lithuanian Socialists, especially, have drifted away from the real principles and tactics of Socialism in the same manner as our priests, who drifted away from the principles of the Catholic religion. He also asserted that our priests, instead of teaching morality and brotherly love, antagonize brother against brother and fill the hearts of the people with hatred.</p>
   <p>A choral group of the Birute Singing and Dramatic Society sang the following Lithuanian songs: 1. "Ant Kalno Karklai Siubavo" (The Willows on the Hill Were Swinging); 2. "Kur Namas Mus" (There Where Our Home is Located);</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1183.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>3. "Noriu Miego" (I Am Sleepy); 4. "Ko Liudi Putineli" (Why Are You Sad, Little Tree); 5. "Eina Garsas Nuo Rubeziaus" (An Echo From the Border); 6. "Oi Tu Jieva" (Oh, You Eve!). The choral group was directed by K. Strumskis, successor to Mikas Petrauskas who left for Lithuania a few months ago.</p>
   <p>Miss Aldona Karalius recited a Lithuanian poem about the Nemunas (Niemen). River in Lithuania, and sang a song entitled "Sudiev Lietuva" (Good-bye Lithuania). Mrs. P. Karalius recited a Lithuanian poem entitled "Delko Ten Zmoniu Didis Buris Stovi?" (Why is a Large Crowd of People Standing There?).</p>
   <p>A Lithuanian orchestra, under the leadership of J. Keturakis, played an overture entitled "Philadelphia," and an extract from the opera "Martha."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1184.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>At the conclusion of the program Mr. Bijanskas delivered a short talk. He advised the Lithuanians to improve their conduct at social functions. He said Lithuanians should observe strict silence during the progress of a program, the same as they do when in church. He mentioned the fiftieth anniversary of the birthday of Dr. Vincas Kudirka (1858-1899), famous Lithuanian writer and author of the Lithuanian national anthem "Lietuva Tevyne Musu" (Lithuania, Our Fatherland). He asked the audience for contributions to a fund to publish the literary works of Kudirka. Two young Lithuanian girls, Miss Laukis and Miss Jonaitis, passed among the audience and collected a total of $7.40. This money was later turned over to the Lovers of the Fatherland Society, which is in charge of the fund for the publication of the literary works of Kudirka.</p>
   <p>In spite of rainy weather a capacity crowd attended the commemoration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
