<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 9,
<date when="1906-05-11">May 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Grand Celebration of the Lithuanian Alliance Xxi Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 9,
<date when="1906-05-11">May 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">GRAND CELEBRATION OF THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE XXI CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, May 27, 1906, there will be a grand celebration. The parade will start to march from 33rd and Morgan streets to the convention hall on 31st and State streets. The societies and clubs which will participate in this parade should come before the parade at 1 P. M. to the following places: L. Azukas, 3301 Auburn Avenue; L. Szlakis, 3321 Auburn Avenue; J. Rugis, 3301 S. Morgan Street; K. Liandanskas, 3117 S. Morgan Street; and T. Radaviezia, 942 W. 33rd St. Our sergeants-at-arms will inform all the societies where to come and start the parade. From 33rd and Morgan streets all the marching societies with music will start to march to the South Side Turner Hall, where the program will be held.</p>
   <p>In this large hall there is room for several thousand people. Therefore, besides the societies participating in this celebration, we are inviting the public in general to come, because there will be room enough for all. Let the governor of Illinois and the mayor of Chicago see a great multitude of Lithuanians. There will be good speakers, songs and music. On Wednesday, May 30, there will be a banquet at the Turner Hall. The <pb facs="5423970_3_1365.jpg" n="2"/>best orchestra of Chicago will play. The delegates and the guests will have a good time.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
