<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Plea for Unity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEA FOR UNITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Stasys Simkus, famous Lithuanian composer and musician, who arrived in America a few days ago as a representative of the Lithuanian War Relief Society (in Lithuania) to solicit contributions among Lithuanian-Americans, is now in Chicago. From this Lithuanian-American center he will begin his activities in America.</p>
   <p>With mixed feelings we recall the previous delegates of Lithuania to America. The first delegates, Reverend Alsauskas and Reverend Tumas, came here in the interest of education--to solicit funds for the establishment of Catholic schools in Lithuania. The next delegates, Dr. J. Basanavicius and Mr. Ycas, the latter a Lithuanian member of the Russian Duma, came here for purely national reasons--to solicit contributions for the <pb facs="5423970_3_0319.jpg" n="2"/>erection of buildings to house Lithuanian national institutions. An overwhelming majority of Lithuanian-Americans heartily welcomed all of these delegates, and supported the causes which they represented. Factional differences were put aside because it was agreed that schools and buildings for national institutions were important and desirable. All factions, except the Socialists, worked together in harmony.</p>
   <p>However, times have changed, and it now appears that our people also have changed. We cannot say that the change has been in the right direction: it has really been in the wrong direction. Something went wrong with the Lithuanian-American machine. It appears that some devil threw a monkey wrench into the machinery and put it out of commission.</p>
   <p>The situation among our people is really strange--very strange.....War victims, our starving brothers in Lithuania, are in great need of immediate assistance. That is recognized by every Lithuanian-American without exception. <pb facs="5423970_3_0320.jpg" n="3"/>Everyone also agrees that we should assist our suffering brothers in Lithuania. That every Lithuanian-American desires to help them also appears to be an unquestionable truth.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we have before us an urgent matter of common interest to all our people. We all have the same desire regarding this matter, and we all agree--as we must necessarily agree--that we can produce greater results by working in unison. Nevertheless, our forces are divided, and we are unable to form any kind of united front.</p>
   <p>If we would explain our situation to a foreigner [a non-Lithuanian], and ask him for his opinion, what would he say? It seems to us that he would make the following answer: "Call a doctor! Have him examine your heads, because there is probably something wrong with them." Perhaps he might give another answer, the kind Napoleon gave to the barons of Lithuania more than a hundred years ago. It is said that when Napoleon arrived in <pb facs="5423970_3_0321.jpg" n="4"/>Vilna, ancient capital of Lithuania, he called the barons of Lithuania together and asked them the following question: "What do you men of Lithuania desire?" The barons were said to have answered that they did not yet know what they desired. Napoleon then turned to his officers and said, "Appoint a shepherd for this bunch of sheep; they are in need of much whipping."</p>
   <p>It seems to us, too, that Lithuanian-Americans are in need of either a whip or a doctor. Such a remark is unpleasant to make, but it nevertheless seems to be true.</p>
   <p>The presidents of the three Lithuanian-American war-relief funds, which have been set up by the three Lithuanian-American factions [Nationalists, Socialists, and Catholics], were called together in Chicago last Saturday by Mr. Simkus. The purpose of the meeting was to discuss the question, "Can we all work in unison?" Mr. Simkus is about to make a tour of all <pb facs="5423970_3_0322.jpg" n="5"/>Lithuanian-American colonies, and it would be much more economical, and also more convenient and productive, if only one mass meeting in each colony would be arranged for him by the combined efforts of the three Lithuanian war-relief funds. He made a strong plea at the meeting for all possible co-operation. He asked whether, if it was impossible for the three funds to co-operate with him as one united body in all Lithuanian-American colonies, such co-operation were possible in at least some of the colonies.</p>
   <p>The presidents of the three funds agreed that it was necessary to collect money, that the people of Lithuania were in dire need, and that they, the three presidents, strongly desired to aid their brothers and sisters in Lithuania. However, they stated that it was impossible for the three funds to work in unison, impossible even to arrange conferences or hold mass meetings together.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. Sliupas, president of the Lithuanian War-Relief and Autonomy Fund <pb facs="5423970_3_0323.jpg" n="6"/>[set up by the Nationalists], was the only one of the three presidents at the meeting to express a desire to work in unison with the other two funds. He was of the opinion that the Nationalists have great confidence in the representative from Lithuania and that they will heartily support him. The presidents of the Lithuanian Assistance Fund [Socialist] and the National Fund [Catholic] refused to consider any united action.</p>
   <p>The position of the National Fund appears to be particularly strange. Its president, Dr. Anthony K. Rutkauskas, stated that his faction will support Mr. Simkus and the organization he represents as strongly as the Nationalists will, but will not work in unison with the funds of other factions.</p>
   <p>Really, this is a new phenomenon, strange to Lithuanian life. It is not only something strange and unprecedented; it is also a very sad state of <pb facs="5423970_3_0324.jpg" n="7"/>affairs. That is the reason why we believe that there is something radically wrong with us, and that we need a doctor to examine our heads.</p>
   <p>Who can act as our doctor? Mr. Simkus made a valiant effort to cure us, but failed. We believe that only one doctor remains who can cure our disease--our right-thinking public. It should raise its voice and say to our leaders: "Enough of this childishness! You have been shouting to us for years to unite. You have told us that 'where there is unity there is strength'. But now, when a moment has arrived that makes apparent the utmost need for unity, you refuse to lead us toward unity. Instead, you openly try to draw us still further apart."</p>
   <p>This matter ought to be deeply pondered by our leaders and by our public. We are in complete accord with the statements expressed by Dr. J. Sliupas, and believe with him that not even one true Lithuanian nationalist will <pb facs="5423970_3_0325.jpg" n="8"/>refuse to participate in any united front activities for the benefit of our fatherland. We advise Lithuanians of all factions to arrange joint mass meetings wherever possible, and to support Mr. Simkus in his efforts to collect funds for the relief of Lithuanian war victims.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
