<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance</title>, 419 Lorimer St., Brooklyn, N.Y.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance</title>, 419 Lorimer St., Brooklyn, N.Y.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance was started in 1930. It originated at the 36th convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, June 19,1930, Chicago,Ill. After two days of discussion and turmoil, (The main course of this turmoil at the convention was that the nationalists did not want to admit to the mandate committee a delegate of the Communists.) The Communists and their sympathizers, 208 delegate left the convention hall and went to the Meldazis Hall, where they formed the nucleus for this new Alliance.</p>
   <p>On October 14, 1930, the new alliance was incorporated in the state of New York as the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance is a protective and benefit fraternal organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The members pay their designated dues. In cases of sickness or death the beneficiary received a specified sum. The death benefit is from $150 to $1,000.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance has an endowment fund into which the members (young and old) pay monthly dues, and after twenty years they get their money back.</p>
   <p>Besides being a protector and benefactor, the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance is a cultural and enlightenment organization; it supports the various activities of the progressive labor movement for freedom and better livelihood.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance publishes twice per month the newspaper Tiesa (The Truth). Every member gets the newspaper free. The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance takes part in the spreading of enlightenment. On March 1, 1937 the <pb facs="5423970_3_1064.jpg" n="3"/>Lithuanian Workers' Alliance had over six thousand members and about five hundred young members.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance has one hundred and seventy branches in America. In Chicago it has fifteen.</p>
   <p>During the more than six years existence of the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance it has paid to its members over $60,000 in death benefits and $120,000 in sick benefits.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance (March, 1937) has a fortune of over $160,000.</p>
   <p>Due to the initiative of the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance, there was called in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1935, a General Convention of the Lithuanian Workers of America, with the aim of conducting a campaign in favor of the restoration of a democratic regime in Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1065.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance center and its branches supported the American Lithuanian Convention which took place in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1936 and it participated in this convention. The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance sent delegates to the "Lithuanian World's Convention" at Kaunas, Lithuania in 1935.</p>
   <p>It upholds the movements: (a) To free the anti-fascists political prisoners; (b) To restore the democratic form of government to Lithuania and to uphold democracy in the United States; (c) It supports the Spanish people's struggle against fascism; and (d) It protects against the persecution of the foreign-born workers in the United States.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance was the first organization to start action to organize and enlighten the American-born Lithuanian youth. At present, the <pb facs="5423970_3_1066.jpg" n="5"/>Lithuanian Workers' Alliance has close to fifteen hundred organized youth. Many young people are supporting their own branches; they are taking care of their affairs in the English language (if the youth desires so). In the organ Tiesa (The Truth), the youth have their own section in the newspaper for their own affairs. The youth is taking part in cultural, art and sports activities.</p>
   <p>During the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance convention held in 1936 in Rochester, N.Y., the Lithuanian youth had their own sport Olympiad. The Lithuanian youth from all over the United States took part in this sport festival.</p>
   <p>At the fourth convention, which will be held in 1938 in Pittsburgh, Pa., the Lithuanian youth will strive to have a larger and more successful Olympiad.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1067.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian Workers' Alliance is organizing the Lithuanian youth from two to sixteen years of age, establishing schools at the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance branches, where the young people are taught the Lithuanian language sports, and other things that are beneficial to the youth.</p>
   <p>The members are allowed to enroll for a weekly sick benefit of: $6, $9 and $12.</p>
   <p>Besides dues paid for the needs of this youth's organization each member contributes:</p>
   <p>For the expenses of the protective fund, 15 cents; for the branch-local affairs, 10 cents; for the benefit expense fund, 5 cents; for the extraordinary benefit fund, 20 cents a year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1068.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The initiation fees of the members are as follows:</p>
   <p>I Grade - $2; II - $3, III $4; IV $5.</p>
   <p>For the benefit section the fees are; Grade I- $1.50; II - $2.25; III -$3.</p>
   <p>The payments are: 30 cents, 60 cents, and 90 cents per month.</p>
   <p>Branch No. 2. Holds its meetings at the Zalatorius Hall, 700 W. 119th St.</p>
   <p>K. Statkus, secretary, 11915 Eggleston ve.</p>
   <p>No. 53. The Lithuanian Auditorium, 3133 So. Halsted St.</p>
   <p>A. Povilonis, secretary, 3116 So. Halsted St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1069.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>No. 72. The J. Macinkuicins Hall, 1036 E. 93rd St.</p>
   <p>M. A. Macukevicius, secretary, 103 E. 93rd St.</p>
   <p>No. 76 Hollywood Hall, 2417 W. 43rd St.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Baranauskas, secretary, 2959 W. 38th St.</p>
   <p>No. 102. Ezerskis Hall, 4600 So. Paulina St.</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. Yuricne, secretary, 950 W. 59th St.</p>
   <p>No. 104, 3917 W. 14th St.</p>
   <p>S. Dybcius, secretary, 4057 Jackson Blvd.</p>
   <p>No. 109. The Lithuanian Liberty Hall, 14th St. and 49th Ct., Cicero.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1070.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>No. 112. Hungarian Hall, 1630 Milwaukee Ave.,</p>
   <p>Mrs. M. Chesniene, secretary, 1524 N. Hoyne Ave.</p>
   <p>No. 127 Schultz Hall, 2449 W. 69th St.,</p>
   <p>A. Chapas, secretary, 7200 So. Campbell Ave.,</p>
   <p>No. 129, 1750 So. Union Ave.</p>
   <p>J. Stasiunas, secretary, 3116 So. Halsted St.</p>
   <p>No. 139. The Workers' Hall, 10413 So. Michigan Ave.</p>
   <p>J. Pinikas, secretary, 10748 So. Michigan Ave.</p>
   <p>No. 202. Woodman Hall, 33rd St. and Lime St.</p>
   <p>Miss A. Bedaukiute, secretary, 3309 Emerald Ave.</p>
   <p>No. 204, 10731 So. Prairie Ave.</p>
   <p>J. Baramauskas, secretary, 10542 Indiana Ave.</p>
   <p>No. 211. Hollywood Hall, 2417 W. 43rd St.</p>
   <p>B. Baranauskas, secretary, 2950 W. 38th St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1071.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>No. 216. - 3437 W. 62nd St.,</p>
   <p>H. Meldzius, secretary, 7322 So. Daman Ave.</p>
   <p>The president of the Lithuanian Workers' Alliance is Mr. R. Mizara.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
