<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 36,
<date when="1906-09-07">Sept. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">To the Members of the Newly Organized Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0929</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0929.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 36,
<date when="1906-09-07">Sept. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE MEMBERS OF THE NEWLY ORGANIZED SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very often we see in the newspapers that there was organized a new society under the name of some Lithuanian hero. We are sorry that such societies do not belong to the Lithuanian Alliance of America. It would be very practical if these societies would belong to this Lithuanian organization.</p>
   <p>Brothers and sisters who are organizing or thinking of organizing a mutual benefit society, or a theatrical or dramatic society, it would be a good thing to read first the constitution of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. It will cost nothing to inquire. By applying to the secretary you will get by-laws and all information on how to organize societies. Such societies are getting their charter from the Lithuanian Alliance. The death benefit is $150, while the yearly dues are only $2.25. By joining the Lithuanian Alliance, you become a member of one of the largest Lithuanian organizations in America. All other nations have their alliances in America. The Englishmen have lived for generations in this country. They have various <pb facs="5423970_3_0930.jpg" n="2"/>political and industrial organizations and they are reaping the benefits from such organizations. Why are we Lithuanians neglecting ourselves and why do we not care about our future? We cannot depend on some one else, we must look out for ourselves as long as we are alive in the world. There are many places in America that have too few Lithuanians to organize a local society. Such people very easily can join the Lithuanian Alliance organization. This organization has nothing to do with political or religious views. Public meetings, banquets, theatrical performances, etc., are not restricted in this organizations. The meetings of our local branches are like school. You can bring any question for discussion. Everybody has the right to express his opinion. The Lithuanian Alliance of America took the middle road. Its aim is to help its members in distress and help them culturally.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanians can join this organization's branch No. 36.</p>
   <p>M. J. Damijonaitis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
