<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 29,
<date when="1905-07-21">July 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Providence of God Parish "Revolution"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 29,
<date when="1905-07-21">July 21, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD PARISH "REVOLUTION"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As was previously stated in Lietuva, the parishioners' chosen committee went to the archbishop to find out if the priest has the right to prevent the parishioners holding a parish meeting. During the sermons of the last two Sundays, the priest denounced the committee that went to the archbishop. The priest said that it is a great sin for the committee to interfere in the parish affairs.</p>
   <p>In order to fool the parishioners still more, the priest brought another priest, Ambrozaitis, to help denounce the parishioners. Our priest told us that we have no right to inquire into the parish budget, nor the affairs of the parish, and that it is against the church rules and regulations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gedvila, one of the committee members who went to the archbishop, raised his voice in protest. He asked the priest to bet <pb facs="5423970_3_1628.jpg" n="2"/>$500 to prove his statement in the presence of the archbishop. The priest continued to denounce Mr. Gedvila and the committee for going to the archbishop.</p>
   <p>As the priest and his committee do not permit the holding of the meeting at the parish hall, we, the committee who went to the archbishop, called the meeting of the Providence of God Parish. At this meeting we will explain what the archbishop said concerning the duties of the priest and of the parishioners. At this meeting every parishioner will have the right to express his views, because this meeting will not be at the parish hall. Neither the priest nor his committee will control the meeting. Therefore, the committee has printed leaflets and distributed them, calling all the parishioners to come to the meeting on July 23, at 6:30 P. M., 635 S. Canal St.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
