<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-08">Oct. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Community Center Opened in Bridgeport</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-08">Oct. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN COMMUNITY CENTER OPENED IN BRIDGEPORT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Community Center at 3149 South Halsted Street was formally opened to the Lithuanian public on Saturday evening, October 2. The Center is being sponsored by the Lithuanian Club (also known as the Lithuanian Circle), which is an organization of the Lithuanian intelligentsia of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the evening was Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, who is the president of the Club. A. Olsevskis, publisher of the Lietuva (Lithuania), and J. J. Hertmanavicius also spoke.</p>
   <p>From the talk of Mr. Olsevskis, it was learned that the Club has twelve members, and that the Lithuanian Center was established not for business, personal,or charitable reasons, but for the general welfare of all Lithuanians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0097.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Club is endeavoring to unite all the Lithuanian intelligentsia so that they will work together for the uplift of American Lithuanians, especially those of Chicago. In order to further these aims, the Club decided to establish a community center with a hall, which our organizations can use for meetings and other purposes. The hall will be rented to Lithuanian organizations at the lowest possible rates, that is, just enough to meet the cost of lighting, heating, and cleaning the place. The approximate rental prices for meetings and lectures will be $1 for 50 people, $1.50 for 100 people, $1.75 for 250 people, and $2 for more than 250 people; for rehearsals, lectures, concerts, the rates will be from fifty cents to one dollar.</p>
   <p>It is true that our societies can obtain saloon halls without any rental charges, but it is also true that the members of a society spend more money for liquor during a meeting in a saloon hall than the cost of renting a hall here for several meetings. Furthermore, many of our people form the drinking habit while attending meetings in saloon halls. Here, at the Center, instead of drinking at a bar, our people will be able to spend their spare moments during <pb facs="5423970_3_0098.jpg" n="3"/>a meeting by reading good books and newspapers. Saloon halls are suitable only for political meetings of the lowest type but not for meetings of respectable societies.</p>
   <p>In the very near future, the Club will establish a library in the Center, where our people will be able to develop their intellectual and moral powers. A Lithuanian proverb reads: "Kas Skaito, Raso, Tas Duonos Nepraso"--"He who reads and writes does not beg for bread." That is very true. It is possible to learn as much from books as by attending school. There are people who have learned more by reading good books than some people who have attended higher institutions of learning. If all people would read books, then there would not be even half as much misery, misfortune, and sickness in the world as there is today. For example, take an uneducated person who has ruined his digestive system, because he did not know how to take proper care of his health. He does not understand the nature of his illness, nor when or how he got sick. He believes that he has "strained" himself, but our old women call it the "Gumbas" (bewitched) and attempt to cure him with dust scraped from stove pokers, brooms, and doorsteps.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0099.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And what is worse, when he sees a doctor he pretends to be very intelligent; being ignorant of the laws of hygiene, he does not know how to follow the health instructions of his doctor. Finally, he goes to a medical institute, advertised in newspapers, where he is led to believe that he is suffering from blood poisoning, and spends all his hard-earned money for some kind of carrot juice, instead of real medicine. All this would not have happened to him if he had the habit of reading good books.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hertmanavicius described the merits and the great importance of the Lithuanian Community Center. He also spoke about the value of an education.</p>
   <p>The hall has a seating capacity of one hundred and fifty. There are four tables in the library, each with four chairs. At present, the following Lithuanian newspapers have been received at the library: Lietuva (Lithuania), Vienybe Lietuvninku (Unity of Lithuanians), Keleivis (The Traveler), Saule (The Sun), Draugas (The Friend),Lietuviu Zinios (Lithuanian News), Zvaigzde (The Star), Dagis (Thistle), and a number of books published and donated by the Keleivis (The Traveler).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
