<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-27">Aug. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Statistical Survey of West Side Chicago Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-27">Aug. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">STATISTICAL SURVEY OF WEST SIDE CHICAGO LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the West Side Chicago Lithuanian colony, which is also known as the McCormick colony, there are altogether nineteen Lithuanian organizations; thirteen are non-Catholic, and six are Catholic. Eleven of these organizations are mutual aid societies; six are non-Catholic, and five are Catholic. The balance of the organizations are classified as follows: One Lithuanian Roman Catholic parish and church, Our Lady of Vilna; two musical societies; two building and loan associations; one political club; and four lodges of nationwide Lithuanian organizations.</p>
   <p>There are altogether thirty-four Lithuanian business establishments in the colony. They are classified as follows: fifteen saloons; six food shops; three tailors; three barber shops; two printing shops; one men's furnishings store; one bakery; one steam bathhouse; one dairy; one photographer; and one midwife.</p>
   <p>The boundaries of this colony are as follows: From Blue Island Ave. north to <pb facs="5423970_3_0575.jpg" n="2"/>23rd St.; from Western Ave. east to Hoyne Ave. Most of the Lithuanians live in the neighborhood of 23rd P1. and Leavitt St. The rest of the Lithuanians are scattered in the neighboring German, Polish, and Czech colonies. Two Lithuanian saloons are located at Wood St. and Blue Island Ave.; which are supported mostly by Polish trade.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians in this locality appear to be prosperous. Several Lithuanian stores have a very attractive appearance. Nevertheless, it is apparent that not a small number of Lithuanians patronize Jewish stores, many of which are located around Oakley Ave. and Leavitt St. Compared to the size of the Lithuanian population of this colony, the Lithuanians should have five times as many business establishments as they now have.</p>
   <p>About forty Lithuanians own their own homes, which are mostly of brick, from <pb facs="5423970_3_0576.jpg" n="3"/>two to three stories high. The wealthiest Lithuanian here is J. Bagdziunas, who has a three-story brick building on two lots; besides that he owns seven lots. Most of the Lithuanian owned property is located in the area around 23rd Pl., where about thirteen buildings are owned by Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>This Lithuanian colony is surrounded on the west and south sides by factories. For that reason more jobs can be obtained here than in any other Chicago Lithuanian colony. The most important factory is the McCormick Harvesting Machine Co., which is located at Blue Island Ave. Other factories are: Ajax Forge Co., at Blue Island Ave.; Concord Piano Works, at Western Ave,; W. Dalen Mfg. Co., a brass foundry; Chicago Cast &amp; Die Co.; A. Turner Mfg. Co., a cabinet works; a marble factory, and others.</p>
   <p>The streets in this colony are neither paved nor improved. However, preparations are now being made to improve the streets. Sanitary conditions are not as bad as in some other parts of Chicago, but the alleys are very filthy. The sidewalks are <pb facs="5423970_3_0577.jpg" n="4"/>mostly wooden. Generally speaking, this locality cannot be classified with the poorest sections of Chicago; the Lithuanians here do not appear to be as ragged as they are in the less fortunate sections of the city.</p>
   <p>The non-Catholic Lithuanian organizations of this community are as follows: Biruta Music and Dramatic Society; Simanas Daukantas Building and Loan Association; Grand Duke Gediminas of Lithuania Building and Loan Association; 28th chapter of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society; 22nd branch of the Lithuanian Socialist League; and the Simanas Daukantas Lithuanian Republican Club. The non-Catholic mutual aid societies are: Young Singers Society; 109th lodge of the Lithuanian Alliance of America; Young Men's Lithuanian Fellowship Club; Grand Duke Keistutis of Lithuania Society; Brothers Educational Society; Farmers of Lithuania Society; and the Varpas (bell) Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0578.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Catholic mutual aid societies are: St. Rocco Society; St. Stephen Society; Our Lady of Vilna Society, for men; Grand Duke Algirdas of Lithuania Society; Our Lady of Vilna Society, for women; and the 100th lodge of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian business establishments in this colony are as follows: Food stores, by K. Girijotas, Krotkus &amp; Kodis, Romanowski, Tuputis, Dobrovolskis, B. Vaidzunas; tailor and cleaning shops, by A. L. Zacharewicz, F. Donaitis, Fr. Kuzmarskis; dairy, by Filipavicius; bakery, by Wisztort; printing shops, together with steamship and money order agencies, by J. Bagdziunas, and G. Pupauskis; barber shops, by Vaicekauskas, Adomavicius, Grigula; steam bathhouse, by Adomavicius; men's furnishings store, by A. L. Zacharewicz; photographer, A. F. Burniewicz; midwife, A. Stankiewicz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
