<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1906-02-23">Feb. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Disputes in the Parishes and the Causes of Them</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1906-02-23">Feb. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE DISPUTES IN THE PARISHES AND THE CAUSES OF THEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All the altercations in the Catholic parishes, as in Chicago, in the Providence of God parish; in Philadelphia, in the Rev. Kaminskas' parish, and others, were caused by the misunderstanding and the ignorance of the people. The people buy lots, build churches and donate money to the bishop to use for his own benefit. Then, when the bishop sends his agent, the priest, to the parish, and when the priest reaps the profit, the parishioners become irate and say, "This is our church! We have built it and we are supporting it. You have no right to use the collected money for your own benefit!" When the priest gives no heed to such a cry from the parishioners, but does as the bishop tells him to do, the altercation starts. The parishioners beat the priest in order to convince him that the church is owned by the parish. How can we characterize this understanding of the matter by the people? Is it reasonable?</p>
   <p>Let us take for example the Providence of God parish in Chicago. When <pb facs="5423970_3_1610.jpg" n="2"/>the people organized the parish and bought the lots, they started looking for a priest. They wrote letters to all the Lithuanian priests in America and to several priests in Lithuania, offering them a rector's position in their parish, but, because of the church property not being assigned to the bishop, every priest politely refused to accept the rectorship. Then the parishioners, willingly or unwillingly, were forced to give the church property to the bishop in order to get a priest. When the bishop obtained the property he sent the priest to do business for him. And the priest did what the bishop told him to do. Six months had not passed before the parishioners forgot that they had donated their church property to the bishop. Now they cry: "This is our church! We maintain it! The priest is running it as though it were his own home. The priest is doing what he pleases with our money, without our permission! Let us chase him out!"</p>
   <p>Last Sunday they tried to chase him out. Is this a wise action? They have forgotten that they donated the church to the bishop and the church <pb facs="5423970_3_1611.jpg" n="3"/>does not belong to them, but to the bishop. They forgot that not they, but the bishop gave the rector's office to the priest. The priest must obey his superior, the bishop. Even though they broke the windows of the rectory, the priest did not get scared. He replaced the windows and is doing business again. The suspected offenders were arrested. If there is proof that they took part in the riot, they will be punished for obstructing the bishop's business. Only then they may understand that the money collected in the church belongs to the bishop, not to the parishioners.</p>
   <p>The bishopric is a corporation like any railroad. The bishop has a charter in the state of Illinois to do business. His charter has the name of the Catholic Bishop of Chicago, a sole corporation. That means that such corporation, much like the Illinois Central or Grand Trunk, expects to do business.</p>
   <p>To hear confessions, to baptize, to perform marriages, and officiate <pb facs="5423970_3_1612.jpg" n="4"/>at funeral services, needs no charter. A charter is necessary in order to do business. When the bishop has a charter in the state of Illinois to do business, then no other person or party can have or get a charter allowing to do the same business. The charter is the bishop's monopoly. No other Catholic church in his diocese can be organized without his permission. He has a monopoly on his diocese churches, like Rockefeller on the oil resources. He has the right to forbid any church to use the name of "Roman-Catholic," if the church property is not assigned to him. He has the right to denounce and to excommunicate every Catholic who is opposed to his rights. For this reason the charter is necessary to him.</p>
   <p>Even though the people have built the church at their own expense, by donating the church property to the bishop they have no right to keep and to hold the money collected in the church.</p>
   <p>Suppose the people build a station and donate it to the railroad company, could they sell tickets and keep the money for themselves? The company would eject them at once. The same situation exists in connection <pb facs="5423970_3_1613.jpg" n="5"/>with the bishop's business. The difference between the railroad company's business and the bishop's is this: When the railroad company sells a ticket to a passenger he reaches his destination, but when the bishop's agent sells a ticket to heaven the people do not demand a proof of the fact that they will reach their destination, and no bishop's agent (priest) has proved that the people ever reached heaven.</p>
   <p>Now then, if the people could understand that when they donate a church to the bishop the church does not belong to them any longer, they would not start fights in the church. No one wants to fight for somebody else's business - the bishop's business. The people ought to know that when they donate anything to some one, the thing donated does not belong to them any longer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
