<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Statistical Survey of 18th Street Chicago Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">STATISTICAL SURVEY OF 18TH STREET CHICAGO LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The approximate boundaries of the 18th Street Chicago Lithuanian Colony are as follows: from Halsted Street east to String and Jefferson Streets, and from Canalport Avenue to 14th Street. Many Lithuanians also live in the area from Halsted Street to Canal and Clinton Streets,between 14th and Taylor Streets.</p>
   <p>The area around 18th Street, between Halsted and Stewart, is inhabited by Lithuanians and Czechs. The area around Canal Street is populated by Jews and Lithuanians. The area north to Taylor Street is inhabited by Italians, Jews, Czechs, and a few Poles and Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>The living conditions and economic standing of the Czechs and Jews are not any higher than those of the Lithuanians. However, the intellectual level of the <pb facs="5423970_3_0580.jpg" n="2"/>Czechs and Jews is higher than that of the Lithuanians; the Czechs and Jews have not one, but several, periodicals in their own languages.</p>
   <p>This locality has a very unsanitary appearance, especially in the Jewish-populated districts. And who is not acquainted with the filthy appearance of Jewish neighborhoods? Their neighborhoods emit a very offensive odor, are full of rubbish piles, and all their stores are secondhand stores of old rags and hardware; their streets are very obnoxious and are filled with children, all dirty like pigs.....However, Lithuanians are accustomed to Jews, and apparently cannot get along without them. Local Lithuanians purchase everything, except certain foods and intoxicating drinks, from Jews. Although the Lithuanian population in this locality is large, Lithuanians do not have even one clothing, shoe, or drugstore. In order to attract Lithuanian trade, some Jewish-owned drugstores have the words "Lietuviska Aptieka" (Lithuanian Pharmacy), usually horribly misspelled, painted on their windows.</p>
   <p>Around Canal Street, where many Lithuanians live, is one of the most unsanitary <pb facs="5423970_3_0581.jpg" n="3"/>spots in the district. Everywhere the air is foul, the houses are cheap and in bad condition, and it appears that the yards and streets are never cleaned. It is very pitiful to watch the children, who abound everywhere, as they walk in filth and search rubbish piles. Almost all the homes are filthy and give off a bad odor. Most of the Lithuanian saloons are concentrated in this neighborhood. Lithuanian saloons and food stores, except two or three, have a very bad appearance.....Many fights occur here among the Lithuanians. Not so long ago the Lithuanians were divided into gangs, according to the provinces in Lithuania from which they came. The "Kauniniai" (those who came from the province of Kaunas, Lithuania) and the "Vilnieciai" (those who came from the province of Vilna, Lithuania) met in battle very often until the police finally broke up their gangs. Here, as elsewhere, there are many Polonized and Americanized Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>A very bad habit of distorting names predominates among the Lithuanians. They use their real names among their own people, but when they write or tell their names to foreigners, they "Polonize" their names by adding Polish tails, such <pb facs="5423970_3_0582.jpg" n="4"/>as "Ski" or "Wicz", to their original names; for example, Purvis to Purviski, and Sinkus to Sinkewicz. The following is a list of the Lithuanian businessmen of this colony who have distorted their beautiful, original Lithuanian names: Waitkewicz, Milasewicz, Liutkewich, Tananewicz, Janulewicz, Montwill, Radovitz, Urbik, Stulpin, Anglinsky, Raszinski, Klinch, Elsberg, Shemiot, etc. They apparently believe that the Lithuanian endings, "as", "tis", "is", and "us", are comparatively cheaper than the Polish tails, "ski" and "wicz".</p>
   <p>The 18th Street Lithuanian colony has the following number of Lithuanian organizations and business establishments: 21 organizations of which 15 are mutual aid societies--9 non-Catholic, 6 Catholic; one Roman Catholic parish and church, Providence of God; and 62 business establishments. The latter are divided as follows: 32 saloons, 13 food stores, 5 barber shops, 3 tailors and cleaners, 1 photographer, 1 printing shop, and 7 other kinds of business.</p>
   <p>Most of the Lithuanians of this colony are employed at the Crane Company, a metal products factory which is located at 13th and Canal Streets. That factory <pb facs="5423970_3_0583.jpg" n="5"/>is now being trebled in size. It will occupy the entire area from 15th to 12th Streets, and from Canal to Stewart Streets. Therefore, there will be a large increase in the number of jobs there.</p>
   <p>About four weeks ago, a new organization named Workers' Alliance was organized here. It has already received a charter, and has about twenty members. Meetings are held every Saturday evening at the home of Mr. Pauga, 675 South Union Avenue. It is a mutual aid society. However, the main purpose of this society is to find work for its unemployed members. In this way, this society can be more useful than the others, provided that it adheres to its purpose. Many of our societies have very praiseworthy aims written in their bylaws, but of what use are they if no effort is made to carry them out? It is difficult to find employment for one another, especially when jobs are very scarce. However, it is much easier for a member to find a job when all other members of the society make an earnest effort to help him.</p>
   <p>The following is a list of the Lithuanian organizations in the 18th Street Lithuanian colony: (1) Providence of God Roman Catholic Parish, church and parochial <pb facs="5423970_3_0584.jpg" n="6"/>school (taught by nuns), with Rev. E. Steponavicius as the pastor; (2) Lietuva Building and Loan Association; (3) Lithuanian Butchers' Union; (4) Lithuanian Political Club; (5) Independent Lithuanian Political Club; (6) Branch 129 of the Lithuanian Alliance of America; (7) Branch 37 of the Lithuanian Socialist League. The non-Catholic mutual aid societies are as follows: (1) King Mindaugis (of Lithuania) Society; (2) Lithuanian Educational Society; (3) Society of Blessed Lithuania; (4) Society of the Sons of Lithuanian; (5) Unity Society; (6) Liberty Society; (7) Workers' Alliance; (8) Plowmen's Society; (9) Truth Lovers' Society. The Catholic mutual aid societies are as follows: (1) St. John the Evangelist Society; (2) Providence of God Society, No. 1; (3) St. Francis Serafin Society; (4) SS. Peter and Paul Society; (5) St. Anthony of Padua Society; (6) Blessed Virgin Mary Rosary Society of Girls and Women.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian business establishments of the colony are as follows: 32 saloons; 13 food stores operated by J.Pauga, Capas, Steponaitis, Milaszewicz, Zivatkauskas, G.Sereikis, J.Sereikis, Peldzis, M.Kasulis, C. Rakauskis, F. Dapkus, Klinch; A. Bockos; 5 barber shops, operated by Kodis, Joseph Montvila, Elsberg, Navickas, Skirmontas; three tailors and cleaner's shops operated by J. Cernis, J.V. Mockus, J. Juknis, <pb facs="5423970_3_0585.jpg" n="7"/>P. Popleikis; one photographer, A. Woitkewicz; one printing shop, operated by M. J. Tananewicz; two bookstores, operated by M. J. Tananewicz, J. Derkentis; one music store, operated by J. Derkentis; one undertaker, K. Katutis; one men's furnishing store, operated by Shemiot (Semaitis); one shoe repair shop, operated by Elsberg; one coal salesman; one general store; one clothing store. There are only two Lithuanian professional people in the colony: Mrs. A. Dzugas, and Mrs. A. Montwill, who are midwives.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
