<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-02-24">Feb. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Closer Relationship with Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-02-24">Feb. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A CLOSER RELATIONSHIP WITH AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last year Lithuanians participated in the celebration of the national holiday, the 4th of July. This year, they took part in the celebration of Washington's birthday. This was the first time that Lithuanians joined in American civic activity.</p>
   <p>This is a new activity for us. It may not be so bad. Some type of fraternal association with Americans is necessary. We cannot live with the memories of our fatherland alone. We must take care of ourselves in this country, and a friendlier relationship with Americans may benefit us. The Americans do not shun us, they are glad to see us participating in civic activity. Of course, Americans want to see the complete Americanization of foreigners, or to see them establish in some way a close relationship with this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0544.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To achieve this end, they spend large sums of money. They have a special organization for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Of course, we do not want to be completely Americanized, but this does not mean that we must stand aloof from Americans. Another point--Americans do not want us to forget our own language. For example, at our request, Americans are buying our books and newspapers, and are placing them in their libraries. By establishing closer relations with influential Americans we could get a great deal of support from them. Here is an example: through the efforts of some Americans with whom we had established contact, we were able to send one of our artists, J. Sileikis, to Europe to study art.</p>
   <p>Not only for enlightenment, but also for possible material aid to our fatherland, is it important to cultivate Americans. Take for example the Chicago-Lithuanian women's handiwork exhibit. Every American who came to this exhibition had a chance to see original Lithuanian handiwork. There was one unfortunate thing about the exhibition; the Lithuanian products had been <pb facs="5423970_3_0545.jpg" n="3"/>placed in corners where the visitors rarely went, and they therefore had little opportunity to see the Lithuanian handiwork. Of course, some Americans have purchased Lithuanian handiwork. If the products had been placed in a better position, where the public could see them without any obstruction, all the Lithuanian pieces might have been sold. If the exhibit had been properly conducted, there is no doubt but that some of the Americans would have placed orders for Lithuanian products to be imported from Lithuania.</p>
   <p>If we want to have a successful Lithuanian handiwork exhibition, we must develop friendships with prominent Americans, and especially with the Hull House directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
