<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 47,
<date when="1906-11-23">Nov. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Troubles of the Providence of God Parish Have Not Ended</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 47,
<date when="1906-11-23">Nov. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE TROUBLES OF THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD PARISH HAVE NOT ENDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Perhaps only one Roman-Catholic parish in all America, the Providence of God in Chicago, has its own constitution and charter. When last winter the riots occurred in the Providence of God parish, Rev. Steponavicia, ignoring its charter and constitution, dismissed the parish-elected committee and appointed a committee of his own which does not require either a charter or a constitution. With the dismissed parish committee went a certain number of the parishioners. How large a number of them left the priest is not known. It looks as if many of the parishioners remained with the priest, as otherwise he would not have been able to make a living at the parish.</p>
   <p>The parishioners, who have left Rev. Steponavicia, have the charter and the constitution of the parish. Now these parishioners are holding picnics, banquets, dances, and the profits from these festivals are deposited in the bank. They do not give the money to the priest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1584.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the priest can get no profit from these banquets, he requested the bishop to do something about the matter, so the Catholic bishop, in order to protect his agent's and his own business, went to court and demanded an injunction against the parishioners who are not giving the profits from the fairs, dances, etc., to the priest. The bishop's attorney was Cavette. The parishioners' attorney was Elliot, who won the case for Olszewski against the Rev. Krawczunas. Of course, the judge issued an injunction against the parishioners in favor of the bishop.</p>
   <p>When the parishioners were organizing the parish, they should have taken the charter in the name of the Lithuanian Catholic Church, instead of the Roman-Catholic. The bishop could not have interfered with their affairs in such a case. At present the bishop has the corporation charter in the name of the Roman-Catholics. Consequently, <pb facs="5423970_3_1585.jpg" n="3"/>no other corporation is permitted to get a charter in that name, or to business for anyone's benefit, except the bishop's. For that reason, we suppose, the judge issued an injunction against the parishioners, because they were interfering with the bishop's business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
