<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Record Ourselves as Lithuanians in the United States Census</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0860</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0860.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LET US RECORD OURSELVES AS LITHUANIANS IN THE UNITED STATES CENSUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States government takes a census of the population of the United States every ten years. The last census was taken in 1900. Therefore, the next census is scheduled to be made in 1910. It is the duty of all Lithuanian newspapers and organizations to launch a campaign in advance to urge all Lithuanians to record themselves in the 1910 census as Lithuanians, and not as Poles or Russians.</p>
   <p>This question is not new. It was raised and discussed several times prior to the 1900 census. However, merely because the government census blanks of 1900 did not have a form for Lithuanians the census enumerators classified <pb facs="5423970_3_0861.jpg" n="2"/>most Lithuanians as Poles or Russians, even in cases where our people insisted that they were Lithuanians and not Poles or Russians.</p>
   <p>We are pleased to announce that, through the efforts of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, the United States census board has agreed to have a form for Lithuanians on the 1910 government census blanks.</p>
   <p>Therefore, brother Lithuanians, let us not forget to register ourselves as Lithuanians during the next census; otherwise we will defraud and make fools out of ourselves. The census is made for educational reasons. A grave injustice will be done to our nationality if one-half of the 500,000 Lithuanian-Americans are recorded as Lithuanians and the other half as Poles and Russians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0862.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Apparently this campaign through the newspapers will reach only a small fraction of our people in this country, because less than one-tenth of our people read newspapers. Therefore, it is the sacred duty of every reader to acquaint all non-readers with this important matter. It should be mentioned by our public speakers in all their addresses, and it should be discussed in the meetings of all Lithuanian organizations. Lithuanians, be Lithuanians!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
