<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-09-15">Sept. 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">By-Laws of the Association of Lithuanian Societies of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Summary.--(By-laws are omitted)]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0815</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0815.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-09-15">Sept. 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BY-LAWS OF THE ASSOCIATION OF LITHUANIAN SOCIETIES OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Summary.--(By-laws are omitted)]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Name</p>
   <p>1. "This organization will be known by the name of the Association of Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>2. "This organization will consist of the Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, Ill., and it will not interfere with their administration or finances.</p>
   <p>Purpose</p>
   <p>3. "The Association of the Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, Ill., in general, will take care of all the Lithuanian affairs.</p>
   <p>4. "[The promotion] among our people of friendship, unity, and brotherly love.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0816.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. "The promotion among our nationals of a higher degree of enlightenment and morality; to prevent denationalization and moral degeneration.</p>
   <p>6. "To bring succor to widows and orphans; in general, to every Lithuanian, who is in distress.</p>
   <p>7. "To find employment for the unemployed; and to help the immigrants of our nationality.</p>
   <p>8. "For a better achievement of all these [purposes]we must devote all our energy in uniting all of the Lithuanian societies of Chicago. Every Lithuanian in Chicago must belong to this organization or any other Lithuanian society, so that he could in some way help our orphans, the poor, and the invalid persons.</p>
   <p>9. "The Association of the Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, will establish an employment office which will help in finding jobs for the unemployed; <pb facs="5423970_3_0817.jpg" n="3"/>the legal bureau, is offering assistance in legal affairs and naturalization in the United States; it will establish asylums for the widows, the poor, and other benevolent institutions.</p>
   <p>10. "Lithuanian societies from other cities, will have full rights to join the Association of Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, for the purpose of helping their own members, who are in distress or for the Lithuanian immigrants.</p>
   <p>11. "The Association of Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, III., will arrange for celebrations to honor the national holidays of their [adopted] country or for the celebration of our own nation's historical events."</p>
   <p>The Committee:</p>
   <p>Pranas Butkus</p>
   <p>J. J. Hertmanavicius</p>
   <p>M. Kadzewskis</p>
   <p>J. Biezis</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Zymontas</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
