<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-06">Oct. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Bud Died before it Began to Bloom</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-06">Oct. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE BUD DIED BEFORE IT BEGAN TO BLOOM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The united front of all Chicago Lithuanian factions that was formed recently for the coming Lithuanian Day (Tag Day) on November 1, 1916, terminated after existing for a few days--the bud died before it began to bloom. The united front was dissolved last Sunday at the meeting of the Central Chicago Lithuanian Committee, which was recently formed for the purpose of making plans for and to conduct the Lithuanian Tag Day on November 1. The Socialists dropped out, but the Nationalists and Catholics are still united and will carry on the work for the Lithuanian Day.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to act as judges and will not, therefore, make any indictments. We will relate here only the incidents that brought about the disunity.</p>
   <p>After unity was established at a private meeting on Monday of last week, two <pb facs="5423970_3_0193.jpg" n="2"/>Socialist delegates, Kleofas Jurgelionis and Casimir Gugis, were invited to attend the meeting of the Central Committee last Sunday. They accepted the invitation and attended the meeting, in which about sixty delegates participated. At that meeting the delegates were happy over the apparent fact that all Chicago Lithuanian factions had finally united for the Lithuanian Day. It was believed that the unity would last.</p>
   <p>However, during the course of the meeting, one of the delegates raised the question: "Can we be assured that the newspaper Naujienos (News) will not continue to play partisan politics in connection with the Lithuanian Day?"</p>
   <p>The question was answered by Mr. Jurgelionis (who felt insulted at the question). In his own name and in the name of the Naujienos he stated that he and Mr. P. Grigaitis (editor of the Naujienos) always did adhere to the policy that there should be no politics or factionalism in regard to war relief matters, and that it is out of place to discuss the question of politics and factionalism at the meeting. He also stated that the Socialists will adhere <pb facs="5423970_3_0194.jpg" n="3"/>to the united front as previously agreed upon and will work in harmony with the other two factions. However, the Socialists did not do so, because on the very first day after the united front was established the Naujienos began to propagate partisan politics and continues to do so; instead of fostering the principles of unity the pages of the Naujienos are filled with controversial articles about Socialists, Nationalists, and Clericals [Catholics].</p>
   <p>Some delegates at the meeting openly condemned the Naujienos for employing such splitting tactics. Mr. Jurgelionis answered the charge by saying that neither he nor his colleague, Mr. Gugis, is able to control the Naujienos and therefore is not responsible for what is published in it. He further stated that although he is president of the Socialist delegation he is not a member of the Socialist party.</p>
   <p>The explanation of Mr. Jurgelionis created a strange situation. After the united front was established the Socialists continued their attacks against <pb facs="5423970_3_0195.jpg" n="4"/>the other two factions in the Naujienos, and now the Socialist delegates claim that they have no control over what is being published in their organ, the Naujienos.</p>
   <p>By continuing to attack the other two factions in the editorial pages of the Naujienos, after the establishment of a united front, the Socialists have demonstrated bad faith. As a result, the Central Chicago Lithuanian Committee came to the conclusion that Socialist participation in the united front is more harmful than beneficial; even at this, the first meeting of all factions of the united front, much valuable time and energy have been wasted on various explanations and partisan disputes. And since there is no assurance that such waste of time on explanations and partisan disputes will not be repeated at all other meetings, the Central Chicago Lithuanian Committee notified the Socialist delegation at the conclusion of last Sunday's meeting that further united activities with the Socialists is impossible.</p>
   <p>In that manner the "unity" of the Nationalists and Catholics with the Socialists came to an end. This happened because the Socialists refused to cease <pb facs="5423970_3_0196.jpg" n="5"/>playing partisan politics even for one day.</p>
   <p>This incident is very significant. First of all, it shows that even if all the conditions of the Socialists for entering into a united front with other factions are met they, nevertheless, will not stop playing partisan politics. It therefore becomes very evident that any real united front with the Socialists in regards to the Lithuanian Day is impossible, because to them their party is more important and more dear than the plight of our brothers and sisters in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>This is very unpleasant, but it is impossible to come to any other conclusion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
