<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Rt. Rev. A. Kaupas Dies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">RT. REV. A. KAUPAS DIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rt. Rev. A. Kaupas, editor of the Catholic weekly newspaper Draugas (The Friend), died in Chicago on October 27, from an incurable disease--cancer of the throat and stomach.</p>
   <p>The Rt. Rev. Antanas Kaupas was born February 1, 1870, in Ramygala Township, County of Panevezis, Province of Kaunas, Lithuania. He was graduated from Siauliu Gymnasium and the Ecclesiastical Seminary in Kaunas. In 1892, he came to America and completed his education at the Ecclesiastical Seminary in Detroit, Michigan.</p>
   <p>The first charge he had was in Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania; later he had others in Scranton and Pittston, Pennsylvania. While in Pittston, he became editor of the newspaper Draugas, which was published in Wilkes Barre.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last year,the newspaper Draugas and Reverend Kaupas, both moved to Chicago. He remained editor of Draugas, until several weeks ago, when, on account of illness, he was forced to resign as editor.</p>
   <p>The deceased, as an editor, a journalist, and an able writer, played an important part in our public life.</p>
   <p>As a journalist he was known not only as an editor, but also as a contributor, for many of his articles were published in newspapers and journals in Lithuania, and some even in English, newspapers. He also helped edit the great Catholic Encyclopedia.</p>
   <p>As he was a priest, he upheld the clerical viewpoint, but, we must say, that he was more liberal and progressive than other Lithuanian priests. He was one of the progressive priests, who maintained that in general national affairs, which should be of interest to all Lithuanians, there should be no reason for us to be separated into various parties and groups. For national culture, which concerns all the people of Lithuania, priests, progressives, freethinkers, socialists, etc., can all work together.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As editor of the clerical newspaper Draugas, published by the clerical alliance, he fought hard against extreme socialist views. He also fought with other progressive newspapers, and even our newspaper had several hot disputes because of our different views. Despite our struggle, his influence has made the Lithuanian clergy of America more liberal toward Lithuanian national affairs. While clerical editor, the deceased did everything possible to separate religious from national affairs. As he was a strong nationalist, he tried to appease the clergy's religious fanaticism that forbade our clergy to work in common with other people in cultural affairs among Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>One of the most outstanding examples of his efforts is the support of the National Museum in Vilnius [Vilna]. If today our Lithuanian clergy of America support affairs of Vilnius [Vilna], if church societies show interest in national cultural affairs by contributing such large donations--we should be thankful to the work of the deceased. Reverend Kaupas himself donated one hundred dollars for the National Museum in Vilnius [Vilna]. Not only that, he urged others to contribute according to their means to support this <pb facs="5423970_3_1527.jpg" n="4"/>institution.</p>
   <p>Although we cannot agree with some of the ideas of the deceased, and we have argued and have had many disagreeable disputes with him, because we have found many weak points in his arguments (but who of us have not?)--but in general, we can say,as his tomb is still warm, that Lithuanian public life, especially Lithuanian newspapers, have lost one of its greatest actors.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: At the time of Reverend Kaupas' death, Lithuanian newspapers wrote that he had died because of a severe beating by other clergymen, who claimed he had had love affairs with the sweethearts of other priests. Other newspapers said that he was beaten because of his liberal views. Rumors still persist that the beating was the cause of his death.</p>
   <p>[Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, who was the physician of Reverend Kaupas during his illness states that the Reverend A. Kaupas was severely beaten by the clergy three times. The first time was in Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania; the second <pb facs="5423970_3_1528.jpg" n="5"/>time in Philadelphia; the third time in Pittsburgh. In Philadelphia, Reverend Kaupas' abdomen was severely injured and two ribs were broken. It was from that abdominal injury that cancer developed. At these cities the Lithuanian clergy held conventions to discuss how to fight liberalism. The Rev. A. Kaupas was against such an idea. His idea was that, on cultural problems, everybody--clergy, freethinkers, socialists, liberals--could work together for the good of Lithuanian national culture. All of the clergy were against such an idea. When the clergy were unable to present better arguments to break down those of the Reverend Kaupas, they beat him so that he would accept their point of view--backwardness.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
