<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-08">Aug. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Arrival of the Guests from Lithuania</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-08">Aug. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ARRIVAL OF THE GUESTS FROM LITHUANIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The honorable guests Dr. J. Basanavicius and Attorney M. Ycas arrived in Chicago July 31. The chairman of the [reception] committee, Right Reverend F. B. Serafinas, met the guests at the railroad station and took them to his residence in Roseland. The lecture tour arranged for them in Chicago is as follows:</p>
   <p>The lectures will begin at 7:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>The meetings of August 3rd and 5th have been held already. Many people came to these meetings. In Roseland, on August 3, more than 500 people came to the meeting. Right Reverend F. B. Serafinas introduced the guests to the public. The first speaker was Dr. J. Basanavicius. He spoke on the importance of the Lithuanian Science Society, and the benefit to Lithuanians of the National Museum. The second speaker was Attorney M. Ycas. He spoke on present national affairs in Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0398.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then, Right Reverend Serafinas delivered a short talk and closed the meeting.</p>
   <p>At this meeting, $279.30 was collected. Right Reverend F. B. Serafinas donated $100. Then they went among the businessmen, and collected more than $130. Many people bought land certificates of the Lithuanian Science Society in Vilnus. The price of the certificate is $10.50. Everyone who buys one or more of these certificates, receives a very beautiful charter. Those who donate $100 or more, receive an honorary membership charter from the Lithuanian Science Society. The names and pictures of such donors will be published. Later on, an album of the honorary donors will be made, and the names and pictures of these donors will be published in the album. Also, the names of the honorary donors will be inscribed on a slate, and will be placed on the wall of the building when such a building is erected in Vilnus, Lithuania. The names of these people will remain forever in the memory of Lithuanians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0399.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us do our best to place our names on this honorary scroll. If we cannot place our individual names there, let us place the names of the societies of which we are members, and inscribe their names in the pages of the history of honor. Let us prove that we love our nation not less than the Lithuanians of Lithuania, or anywhere else!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
