<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-09-24">Sept. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Students' Convention in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-09-24">Sept. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN STUDENTS' CONVENTION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday and Saturday, September 17 and 18, the fourth convention of the Lithuanian Students' Alliance of America was held in Chicago at the Ausra Hall, 3149 South Halsted Street. About thirteen delegates and a group of guests attended the convention, which had a total of five sessions. Those who officiated at the convention were Mr. D. Bagocius, chairman; Mr. J. Vitkus, vice-chairman; Mr. Frank Zurvalis, secretary.</p>
   <p>One of the main decisions made at the convention was the resolution to stop the publication of the Jaunimo Sapnai (Dreams of Youth), which was published monthly as an organ of the Students' Alliance. It was decided to merge the Jaunimo Sapnai with the Jaunoji Lietuva (Young Lithuania), which is being <pb facs="5423970_3_1241.jpg" n="2"/>published at 4611 South Paulina Street, Chicago, Illinois. Hereafter a students' section will be conducted by the Alliance in the Jaunoji Lietuva. This students' section will be named "Jaunimo Keliai" (Roads of Youth), and will be conducted by an editor appointed by the Alliance. Later, the convention appointed Mr. K. Augustinas as editor, and Mr. Frank Zurvalis as assistant editor of the students' section.</p>
   <p>It was also decided at the convention to establish closer ties with the Lithuanian-American intelligentsia and with Lithuanian students in the eastern states.</p>
   <p>The following officers of the Alliance were elected for the coming year: D. Bagocius, president; Frank Zurvalis, vice-president; Mr. Benosius,Astramskas, secretary; Mr. Mankus, financial secretary; Mr. Benosius, treasurer; Mr. Kliauga and Mr. Sukys, board of trustees.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1242.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the evenings of Friday, Saturday, and Sunday entertainments were sponsored by the convention in various sections of the city. They were held in the Meldazis Hall, Ausra Hall, and in a hall on the North Side. A mass meeting with lectures and orations at the Ausra Hall was also sponsored by the convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
