<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 3,
<date when="1899-02-20">Feb. 20, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is Propagating Infidelity?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 3,
<date when="1899-02-20">Feb. 20, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS PROPAGATING INFIDELITY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the honorable editor of Lietuva:</p>
   <p>I do not know what has happened that for some time I find nothing in Lietuva about the detestable behavior of the Rev. Krawczunas. He may have made some kind of agreement with you that you would keep quiet about the priest's shameful conduct. This is not for me alone, but for all the public.</p>
   <p>Not one of our brothers is wailing that infidelity is spreading, the good Catholics are quitting going to church and stopping donating to the church. Many have joined the Independent Church, but they do not want to know why this happened, and why the infidelity is spreading.</p>
   <p>Dear brothers, if you want to know who propagates infidelity, just take a good look at our Rev. Krawczunas' activity. You will understand who is bringing forth this infidelity. Until the Rev. Krawczynas was in Chicago, there were no infidels; nobody ever heard such a name. But when the Rev. Krawczunas came to Chicago, he grabbed the <pb facs="5423970_3_1769.jpg" n="2"/>parish charter and the Lithuanian church property he assigned to the bishop; the money donated for the church the priest took for his own use and benefit, and he have made more debts on the church than the property is worth. Now, when any one asks the priest what became of the parish money the priest at once execrates him and gives him the name of infidel. Here, last Sunday, the priest execrated the St. Casimir Society. This was the first society that was organized in Chicago; it was organized when our Rev. Krawczunas was tending the pigs at his father's farm in Lithuania. (Tr. n.: The saying, "To tend the pigs," is a very disgraceful offense among Lithuanians). This society was the builder of the parish; its members donated not single dollars, but tens of dollars for that church.</p>
   <p>Now the priest execrated the society because it asked the priest to give an honest account of the parish budget. The priest said that St. Casimir Society is pagan and that he will not allow this society to hold its meetings in the parish hall. This society has 100 members, and according to the execration the priest has made, 100 new infidels in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1770.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He also excommunicated the Simonas Daukantas Society because the society demanded an honest account of the parish budget. Now, then the priest made another 93 infidels.</p>
   <p>The priest has told all other societies to bring their by-laws to him and he will rewrite the by-laws to suit himself, and that no member of any society will have any right to ask about the parish budget. Anyone who asks questions about the parish affairs, which is a deadly sin, will be excommunicated from the society. As much as we can see, not a single society will agree to such anarchistic demand of the Rev. Krawczunas and none will allow him to deform their constitution. Then in such a case, of course, the priest will have to execrate all the societies and again we will have a few hundred more new infidels.</p>
   <p>Now, everyone knows that the Rev. Krawczunas with such activity of his, is propagating infidelity in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Parishioner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
