<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1899-01-19">Jan. 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Local News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1899-01-19">Jan. 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Found Guilty. John Baublis, a young man, who came from Lithuania to America last summer was arrested and sentenced three years to prison and sent to the state penitentiary to serve his sentence for killing a hoodlum.</p>
   <p>John Baublis was attacked by a group of hoodlams at 4500 S. Paulina St., and accidentally killed with a revolver one of the hoodlums by the name of Riebandt, who died instantly. According to our opinion, young Baublis is innocent, because he killed this hoodlum in self-defense; nevertheless he was sent to prison for three years. In this case, John Baublis should have been acquitted. However, if this young man had been the son of a rich man, no doubt he would have been acquitted with no trouble. It is very pathetic case to see this innocent young man sent to prison, just because he did not have a few thousand dollars to give to politician and judge. We are all in the very same situation; if we are poor, we have to suffer injustice in this cruel world of ours.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian people consented with Reverend Father to call a special meeting to elect a committee for the purpose of helping this innocent young man who has been sent to prison for three years. The purpose of this committee is to raise funds from contributions by people and have an attorney for John Baublis.</p>
   <p>Most of the credit is due to Stanley Marcinkevicia and Joseph Kushleika for their efforts and energy for raising this fund. We are very grateful for their work, devotion, spending their own money and time to help their brother. We are also grateful to those who contributed to that fund. Although we don't know you, Mr. Baublis, we are sending you our words of sympathy and consolation.</p>
   <p>Let this prison be a boat of salvation to you, and with the help of God you will be more cautious when you come back from prison. There is an old proverb saying that "One who is loved by God is punished." You must except this penalty as a God's personal love and a token of mercy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
