<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 50,
<date when="1899-12-15">Dec. 15, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to Katalikas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 50,
<date when="1899-12-15">Dec. 15, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO KATALIKAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Truth Seekers Society held its monthly meeting on Dec. 10, 1899. The society decided to reply to Katalikas' lying assertions which slandered the Chicago Lithuanian national celebration, and insulted the Truth Seekers Society as being a society of infidels. The Truth Seekers Society, in answering the Katalikas' writer, says that he knows about God as much as a hog knows about peppers. His God is the dollar, for which he serves his boss, Rev. Krawczunas, who sees the dollar as his god. Our God is the ruler of the universe, who controls and takes care of everything. While the Katalikas' god does not know of anything else but to take dollars, while those who refuse to give him dollars are called infidels. We do not believe in a god whom you can bribe.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, Katalikas slanders the national celebration, saying that <pb facs="5423970_3_1715.jpg" n="2"/>this festival was arranged by A. Olszewski. This is a dirty lie. The Truth Seekers Society received invitation, not from Mr. Olszewski, but from the Simonas Daukantas Society. Katalikas says that there were only a few people in the hall, and that when the speakers began to speak many people left. This is a great lie! The Katalikas' editor himself sat in the gallery during the entire program. He saw that the hall was crowded, that nobody left the hall during the program, that all the people were listening with great attention to the speakers. Why does Katalikas lie? Because its god is the dollar, and for this god the poor editor has sold his conscience.</p>
   <p>The Truth Seekers Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
