<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-07-10">Jul. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to All Lithuanian Catholic Societies in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-07-10">Jul. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO ALL LITHUANIAN CATHOLIC SOCIETIES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[In spite the fact that] a movement to organize all Lithuanian non-Catholic mutual benefit societies in America into one strong organization was started several years ago, no effort has been made so far to do the same for the Lithuanian Catholic mutual benefit societies. Such a merger, however, is just as important and beneficial to Catholics as it is to non-Catholics.</p>
   <p>It is true that we Catholics have the Lithuanian Roman-Catholic Alliance of America, a mutual benefit organization established thirteen years ago and <pb facs="5423970_3_1576.jpg" n="2"/>with branches in the principal Lithuanian colonies in the United States. However, it is also true that there are hundreds of small Lithuanian Catholic mutual benefit societies, named after saints, in all the Lithuanian colonies in America. Steps should be taken to merge all these little societies into one strong organization, as the non-Catholic Lithuanians are now doing.</p>
   <p>Unquestionably, such a merger would be of great benefit, both culturally and financially, to all members. Instead of working separately with divided forces, we should work together with united forces. In this manner we would be in a far better position to do more good for our nationality and for our <pb facs="5423970_3_1577.jpg" n="3"/>individual welfare. It would be easier also to detect fraudulent claims.</p>
   <p>As we all know, many society members are forced to move from city to city to seek employment. When living in distant towns or cities, some members make fraudulent claims by pretending that they are sick. They do so by securing false medical certificates through the bribing of doctors.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, members who have moved to other cities find it very inconvenient to keep up their membership so that when they get sick, they are not able to enjoy all the benefits provided for them by their societies. They invariably find it more convenient to drop their membership and join a local society, even at a financial loss. Such hardships would be avoided if all societies would merge into one strong unit, with branches in all the Lithuanian colonies. No other nationality group has such small mutual <pb facs="5423970_3_1578.jpg" n="4"/>benefit societies as we have. Their societies, such as the Foresters, are organized on a strong, nationwide basis. The Czechs have a strong, nationwide mutual benefit organization. We should follow their example.</p>
   <p>Therefore, fellow-countrymen, let us give this appeal serious consideration. Let us get together and merge all our societies into one strong, nation-wide organization, from which we are certain to derive greater benefits. This is a step necessary for the promotion of our general and individual welfare in this country. Those interested in this important movement are invited to write to George Juozapaitis, 37 Roosevelt Avenue, Torrington, Conn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
