<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-08-21">Aug. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Farm Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-08-21">Aug. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN FARM COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After three years of careful and extensive investigation of the farm lands in all sections of the United States and Canada, the Lithuanian colonization society "Zinycia," (Fountain of Knowledge) has selected the state of Michigan as the most ideal site for the establishment of a Lithuanian agricultural colony in America. The society is now engaged in a campaign to form a Lithuanian farm colony in Clark county, near Thorp, Michigan. It is planned to name the colony Zinycia, Michigan, after the name of the colonization society.</p>
   <p>The farm land in that section of Michigan is very fertile, and lies between two railroads. A beautiful river, the Black River, runs through the territory. The climate is healthy and suitable for people of the Lithuanian race. There is an abundant supply of pure and healthy water. Many Lithuanians, including the officers and members of the society, already have purchased farms in that vicinity. Many have already settled down, and are working their farms with very good results.</p>
   <p>The land is now being sold by the society at fifteen dollars an acre and up.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0886.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to afford an opportunity for a larger number of Lithuanians to free themselves from slavery as city workers, the society has decided to sell the land on a partial payment basis: twenty percent down, and balance within five years. The society will also erect farm buildings, and sink wells on a partial payment plan. This work can be done at a much lower cost by the society than by individual farmers.</p>
   <p>It is advisable for those who are interested to visit and inspect the colony as soon as possible before harvest time. It is easier to ascertain the nature and value of the land by inspecting the crops. The railroad fare from Chicago to Thorp is only six dollars and twenty-five cents one way, and twelve dollars and fifty cents for a round trip. This fare is eventually refunded by the society to those who purchase land. Trips to the colony are being made in groups from Chicago; each group is accompanied by a guide from the society. Those who are interested, should write or call at the Chicago office of the society, which is located at 3252 South Halsted Street. When writing, address Zinycia, A. Olszewski, Manager.</p>
   <p>The following are the names and addresses of the society:J. J. Gertmanavicius, <pb facs="5423970_3_0887.jpg" n="3"/>president, 3252 South Halsted Street; Justinas Jakavicius, vice-president, 1512 West 19th Street; M. M. Juska, 581 West 22nd Street; Aleksandra Olszewski (Olis), secretary; 1418 West 21st Place; Niceforas Zilius, treasurer; A. Olszewskis (Olis), general manager, 3252 South Halsted Street. All are of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Many choice farm lands in the colony are still available at the original low rates. It is advisable for those who are interested to act quickly before the prices go up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
