<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 15,
<date when="1904-04-08">April 8, 1904</date><title level="a">Is it Worth While to Help the Lithuanian Students Who Are Attending the Foreign Universities?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0966</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0966.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 15,
<date when="1904-04-08">April 8, 1904</date><title level="a">IS IT WORTH WHILE TO HELP THE LITHUANIAN STUDENTS WHO ARE ATTENDING THE FOREIGN UNIVERSITIES?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Aurora Society's branch in the month of March we read the article which was published in No. 8 of Lietuva, about "Help for Young Lithuanian Students," who are attending the universities of other countries. The problem discussed was, "Is it beneficial for the Lithuanians to help such students?"</p>
   <p>Of such Lithuanian students as are attending the universities in other countries, very few after graduation, are coming back to Lithuania. Some of them cannot return, while others who have returned, were forced to flee the country never to return.</p>
   <p>We, at the meetings, have discussed very broadly, whether it is best for students to come to America to study in the universities. On some scientific subjects the American universities stand on the same level as European universities. In the Lithuanian colonies of America we are lacking certain professional classes, especially those of doctors and lawyers. As the <pb facs="5423970_3_0967.jpg" n="2"/>Lithuanians can speak readily the Russian, Slavonic, Ruthenian and Polish languages, it would be very easy for them to practice their profession among those nationalities. This is not all. We should have more speakers and writers of articles in newspapers and books.</p>
   <p>Then if freedom were obtained in Lithuania, many such professional persons could return to Lithuania if they cared to do so. The Lithuanians in America stand very high, even though we have no intelligentsia. Graduates in American universities would find a large field for their activities among Lithuanians because the Lithuanians are increasing by birth and by immigration.</p>
   <p>Another thing we have considered, is that many Lithuanian students, after graduation, are marrying girls of other nationalities. Those students who are seeking our help, or even those who are receiving help, should agree not to marry girls of other nationalities after their graduation. When such graduates marry foreign girls they then work for the cause of the girl's nationality, and neglect the Lithuanian.</p>
   <p>P. Mikolaines.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
