<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-09">Mar. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">To Clean-Up Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0497</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0497.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-09">Mar. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TO CLEAN-UP CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The capitalist press, the local police, and Federal government agents are now conducting a campaign to "rid" Chicago of criminals. Hundreds of foreign born Americans, especially Mexicans and Italians, already have had an opportunity to learn the true meaning of this so-called "cleanup" drive. Many of them were arrested, thrown into jail, and put through all the old familiar degrees of police "courtesy".</p>
   <p>That is only the beginning. In the near future we can expect to see many more similar arrests, and a still greater howl in the capitalist press against aliens and foreign born Americans. A bitter war is now being waged in Chicago's "gangland" by opposing camps of corrupt politicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0498.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rival politicians and their henchmen, who place their bosses in office by stealing and buying votes, have stepped on one another's toes and now are trying to assassinate each other. We cannot deny the fact that among these politicians and henchmen there are some aliens. The politicians are employing that flimsy fact as a shield with which to cover up a very ugly capitalist ulcer--the complete decay of a capitalist political party.</p>
   <p>A very sharp factional war is now going on in the Republican party in Chicago. Both factions are looking forward to the coming elections, and for that reason the leaders of both factions are fighting for supremacy. This war is forcing each faction to employ professional killers. And in order to fool an unsuspecting world, these politicians and their kept press have raised a hypocritical howl against aliens.</p>
   <p>The net result of all this political warfare and attack against aliens can be described as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0499.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When hundreds of aliens are arrested and thrown into jail for "investigation", then the real culprits, after washing their bloody hands, find asylum under the roofs of the very individuals who are directly responsible for the crimes--the so-called 100% political patriots.</p>
   <p>The deceitful character of these shameless tactics are so obvious that no sane person can be fooled by them. It is very easy to see that an attempt is being made to place the blame upon all aliens for the acts of a band of criminals; it is also another attempt to poison the public opinion of America.</p>
   <p>It is very significant that this attack against aliens is being launched at a time when the U. S. Congress is about to consider several anti-alien bills.</p>
   <p>We must employ every possible means at our disposal to repulse these attacks against aliens in America. The first and most important step to take in this struggle is to form organizations for the defense of the rights of aliens. We must fight in an organized manner, and we must not lose any time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
