<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 2,
<date when="1900-01-12">Jan. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">From the Committee of the New Parish in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 2,
<date when="1900-01-12">Jan. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE COMMITTEE OF THE NEW PARISH IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As it was announced in the last issue of Lietuva, the parish meeting was held for the purpose of organizing the new Lithuanian parish. The question was brought up, Do we need a new parish in Chicago?</p>
   <p>All the people at the meeting unanimously decided that we need another parish. It was discussed why we need the second Lithuanian parish: Because for the West Side people it is too far to go to Bridgeport, St. George's Church. Often the people are late for the mass. When the people come to the church they find the priest preaching the sermon. The people hear nothing good in the sermon, but slander and denunciation. There is a school at the St. George's Church, but the Lithuanian children are taught by the Polish nuns.</p>
   <p>The young Lithuanian generation is Polanized by the priest. The Lithuanians of today began to understand that it is time to throw away the Polish skin with which the clericals dressed us. The most important cause why we need the new parish is because the St. George's parish is unsuitably conducted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1701.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The money of the parishioners is wasted. The proponents of this new Lithuanian parish desire to have such a parish, where more humane order would exist in accordance with God's order.</p>
   <p>At the meeting a committee was elected of seven people, whose duty it is to make plans on how to start to organize the new Lithuanian parish, where to build the church, or to buy a ready built church and for how much, etc.</p>
   <p>The committee has made the plans, now they are calling another meeting at Pulaski Hall, 800 S. Ashland Avenue, 7:30 P. M., Saturday evening, January 13. We are inviting all the Roman-Catholic Lithuanians to come to this meeting. We believe that with the help of God our started work will be fulfilled.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
