<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1,
<date when="1892-12-10">Dec. 10, 1892</date><title level="a">Brothers and Countrymen!!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1,
<date when="1892-12-10">Dec. 10, 1892</date><title level="a">BROTHERS AND COUNTRYMEN!!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is well known to all of us that in Chicago there are not a few groups of Lithuanians, there are a few societies, we have started to build a Lithuanian church where one can assemble to worship our Creator in our own language.</p>
   <p>We know that it is hard to understand and to have unity among ourselves is such a large city like Chicago. It takes at least two hours' time to get together among ourselves.</p>
   <p>By seeing the causes why we cannot work closer among ourselves to make acquaintances and to express our thoughts we find it very convenient to publish a Lithuanian newspaper which will come to assist us in spiritual and material needs.</p>
   <p>Brothers, you will understand without our explanation what benefit our newspaper will be to us. Sponsoring the building of a church, the Home of God, we are anxious to increase the membership of our parish. We can <pb facs="5423970_3_0637.jpg" n="2"/>announce and express our views in a broader way. It makes better understanding among us, when one understands in his own heart and thoughts. When a society wants to give its program through the newspaper we can give moral support to help our brothers in their activities.</p>
   <p>We publish this newspaper not for personal gain but to recover the Lithuanian spirit, language and to unite Lithuanians into one organization. This newspaper will not be against the church. We have many deeds unfinished, and new ones to begin, therefore we will work for what is more necessary to us.</p>
   <p>You see how our brothers are suffering under that cruel dragon of Russia who wants to rob our native language, prohibit us to read and to write in order to keep us in darkness, and when we are ignorant they do with us what they please. We all know the purpose of Russia: to teach us the Russian language, to prohibit our newspapers and then without any difficulty convert us to orthodoxy. Let us look to other nationalities, <pb facs="5423970_3_0638.jpg" n="3"/>Czechs and Poles. They have their newspapers, many Lithuanians read Polish papers. Those who are reading literature and newspapers are more educated. They earn more. It is easier for them to make a better living and to gain wealth.</p>
   <p>Therefore, brothers, let us not slumber. Wake up from the sleep of lethargy. We must begin to read newspapers and books. Let us teach each other. Let us live in brotherhood and unity. We must tie ourselves in one brotherly knot. Do not pay attention to the differences of our thoughts and ideas. We must go with one purpose. Let us have one thought among us, unity, education and mother country, then there will be no misunderstandings among us. With our united strength we will obtain a better livelihood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
