<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1899-05-19">May 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Protest against Rev. Krawczunas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1899-05-19">May 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN PROTEST AGAINST REV. KRAWCZUNAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas the Rev. Krawczunas, the rector of our St. George's parish, Chicago, unjustly behaved with the parish budget and when the parishioners demanded an explanation about the money, the priest cursed them as infidels, pagans, excommunicated them from the parish, and refused to confess them, and</p>
   <p>Whereas he called his meeting on April 30, and where with the help of police he threw them out as undesirables because they protested and demanded from the priest an honest accounting, and then, when the priest remained in the hall with a few of his ignorant followers, they approved and adopted the following lying resolution:</p>
   <p>"Resolution approved at the public meeting by the parishioners of St. George's Lithuanian Parish, April 30, 1899:</p>
   <p>"Whereas the publisher of Lietuva, for some time in his fury, shamelessly <pb facs="5423970_3_1754.jpg" n="2"/>attacked in his newspaper the character of the honorable Rev. Krawczunas, wrote with maliciousness humiliating and untruthful articles (in order to blacken our honorable rector) saying that he fraudulently took the parish money, (inculpating him) that he stole the money and divided same with the honorable Archbishop of Chicago, and with such devilish conduct he wants to destroy the people's confidence in our priest, provoke parish riots, destroy the great and good work of our priest and the fidelity of the parishioners. In order to obtain successfully his devilish aim, the publisher of Lietuva is doing this in provocation. When our rector, with the state's attorney, brought Olszewski into court, he got a band of dissolute wretchs like himself, who with satanic glee found unexisting things; and untruthfully swore against the priest. Therefore, we, the parishioners, members of St. George's Parish, at the parish meeting, are protesting against such villainous conduct by the publisher of Lietuva and his friends, and we are marking them as open destroyers, who are destroying the peacefulness amidst the Lithuanians. They are hurting us by debasing our name among other nations, by holding us as unworthy <pb facs="5423970_3_1755.jpg" n="3"/>sons of the Lithuanian Catholic church, even unworthy to call ourselves citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>That when the Rev. Krawczunas came, he found the lots vacant. During the last five years our honorable priest built the church, organized the parish on a strong basis, brought many Lithuanians to the church, uplifting our name and our nation among the other nations. Therefore, we have full confidence in our Rev. Krawczunas, and we are promising to stand by him, that he may do in the future as he has done in the past for the sons of the Holy Mother Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>After discussing the causes of the conduct of the persons who are raising the quarrel among the members of the Catholic Church, it was plainly shown that the national meetings under the name of Dr. John Szliupas were for the purpose of taking away the Catholic faith from Lithuanians. Therefore, we decided, on and approved taking away the rights of such people, that they should have no rights, voice or power to interfere with church affairs. And we decided that one copy of this resolution be sent to the honorable <pb facs="5423970_3_1756.jpg" n="4"/>rector of ours, and one copy to His Grace the Archbishop of Chicago, and 5,000 copies be distributed among the St. George's parishioners.</p>
   <p>The meeting presidium: S. Marcinskewicze,</p>
   <p>K. Pocius.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
