<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-05-17">May 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-05-17">May 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanian societies, bound in one alliance for the purpose of coping with more important matters, having for such purposes chosen several special committees, reacted quickly to the report on the Dillingham Bill by the chairman of the Immigration Committee. The following resolution against the limitation of immigration was drawn up in the name of the directors of the Alliance!</p>
   <p>A Resolution</p>
   <p>Decreed by The Chicago Lithuanian</p>
   <p>Societies' Alliance</p>
   <p>Whereas in the past the inhabitants of the United States often expressed their sympathies for all movements having as their aim the introduction of democratic principles into other lands, and supported such movements financially and morally; and</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0641.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas, Senate Bill 3,175, known as the Dillingham Bill, advises the banishment of every immigrant who, while living here, would plot against the government of foreign kingdoms, and would thus force our government to send back to almost certain death, not only the leaders but even the lowliest followers of such a movement; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, since this same Bill and its amendment, No. 22,527, called the Burnett Bill, in requiring a reading and writing examination of the immigrants, does not provide this country with any greater defense from defective, criminal, or diseased classes, but, on the other hand, contrary to the tendencies and policies of this country, blocks the path to the majority of the immigrants, who are probably the objects of political persecution; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Dillingham Bill requires the identification of the individual immigrant, which is nothing else but the beginning of the un-American <pb facs="5423970_3_0642.jpg" n="3"/>passport system; therefore</p>
   <p>Be it resolved that we, the Chicago Lithuanian Societies' Alliance, representing more than 50,000 Chicago Lithuanians, urge Congress not to allow this Bill to become law, and further,</p>
   <p>Be it resolved, that copies of this resolution be sent to the President of the United States, to the Secretaries of Commerce and Labor, and to the representatives of the City of Chicago in Congress.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Chicago Lithuanian Societies' Alliance,</p>
   <p>The Council of Directors, per: J.J. Elias, president; J.J. Hertmanowicz, secretary; Dr. A.L. Graiciunas, chairman of the Immigration Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
