<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 49,
<date when="1906-12-07">Dec. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Land for the Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 49,
<date when="1906-12-07">Dec. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">LAND FOR THE LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I am one of the members appointed by the XXI convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America to find a suitable place for the Lithuanian colony for the establishment of the asylum home for old and sick Lithuanians. I am announcing to the honorable members of the Lithuanian Alliance of America that I located a place which seems to me very good for that purpose. This suitable place I have found is in Du Page county, Lisle, Illinois, twenty-four miles north-west of Chicago. There are buildings on this farm (there is one building, but it is good for nothing). 267 acres, 85 acres under cultivation, 38 acres of good timber, and 90 acres pasture. The Du Page River runs through the farm; 50 acres of meadow and gravel pit. There is a small hill suitable for a cemetery, and the beautiful grove can be made into picnic grounds. This would be very profitable.</p>
   <p>At present all the land, 267 acres, is rented for $1,500 a year. The <pb facs="5423970_3_0085.jpg" n="2"/>tenant has 100 heads of cattle, and a great variety of domestic fowl. The tenant gets $500 per month for milk, because the farm is close to Chicago, 19 miles from Waukegan, 17 miles to Joliet, and 15 miles to Aurora. By the farm goes the Burlington &amp; Quincy Railroad, the round trip is 35 cents from Chicago. Half a mile from the farm the electric train goes from Chicago to Aurora. On the south and on the west sides of the farm are the common roads. The farm land is rolling, there is spring water, and a brook 10 feet wide runs through the farm.</p>
   <p>The price is $125 per acre. One half is to be paid and the balance will be taken back on a mortgage at 5% interest.</p>
   <p>Now, brother Lithuanians, from this description of the farm it seems to me that it is a very good place. It is much better to pay $125 per acre for a good farm which is located in a good place than to <pb facs="5423970_3_0086.jpg" n="3"/>buy one cheap, where the location is bad. This farm is a very good place. Anybody who visits it says that it looks like real Lithuanian country. If the tenant pays $1,500 per year rent, you must know that he makes good business out of this farm.</p>
   <p>Of course, the public must say and decide what place would be the best to establish the Lithuanian colony and the asylum home. Illinois is the center of the United States, and our brother Lithuanians constantly are coming from the East and West. Therefore, it would be the most essential place for such a Lithuanian colony. Let us donate as much as we can, the $30,000 can be easily raised.</p>
   <p>I have mailed the plans of this farm to other members of this commission. If they approve, we will make a cut and publish it in the newspapers. Next time we will give more information about the value of this farm place.</p>
   <p>F. A. Galubickas, 3305 Auburn Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
