<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-06">Oct. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting for War Relief</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-06">Oct. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING FOR WAR RELIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A total of $363.11 was collected at a mass meeting held last Monday evening at St. George's parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn [now Lituanica] Avenue. The principal speakers at the meeting were Mr. Martynas Ycas, Lithuanian representative in the Russian Duma, and Reverend Jonas Zilinskas. Both recently arrived in America from Europe for the purpose of raising funds for Lithuanian war relief.</p>
   <p>Reverend Zilinskas, the first speaker, delivered a long but very interesting address on what he saw in Lithuania after it was occupied by the German army.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ycas, the second speaker, explained the plight of Lithuanian refugees in Russia. [Translator's note: A copy of these two addresses appear in this issue of the Lietuva.]</p>
   <p>The hall was filled to capacity. Everyone listened very attentively to the <pb facs="5423970_3_0190.jpg" n="2"/>"voice of the Fatherland", the two guests from Lithuania. Both orations were illustrated with slides, which were made from photographs of Lithuanian refugees in Russia and war scenes in Lithuania. These photographs were brought to America by Mr. Ycas and Reverend Zilinskas.</p>
   <p>The principal donors at the meeting were: Vincent Petrauskas, M. Zaldokas, Reverend Matthew Krauciunas, Dr. K. Drangelis, Dr. A. J. Zimontas, Reverend Jerome Vaiciunas, and Attorney B. K. Balutis, all of whom donated five dollars each; Reverend Vincas Dargis donated three dollars; Casimir Andrijunas, John Dimsa, K. K. Genaitis, Mr. Simaitis, J. Stankunas, Anthony Misevicius, and D. Slenis each donated two dollars; I. Armuzis donated one dollar and fifty cents; others donated smaller amounts. [Translator's note: A long list of the smaller donors who contributed one dollar each is given.]</p>
   <p>A total of $224.50 was collected from those who donated one dollar or more; a total of $52.11 was collected from those who donated less than one dollar each; a total of $86.50 was realized from the admission of fifteen cents each. There fore, a total of $363.11 was raised at the affair for Lithuanian war relief.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0191.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: A photo of Reverend Jonas Zilinskas appears in this issue of the Lietuva; a photo of Mr. Martynas Ycas appeared in the September 22 issue of the Lietuva.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
