<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-07-14">July 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Collect $691.42 in Chicago for War Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-07-14">July 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">COLLECT $691.42 IN CHICAGO FOR WAR RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. A. M. Martus is touring Lithuanian-American colonies in the United States to collect funds for the relief of the war-stricken people in Lithuania and to help Lithuania regain her political freedom. He has collected a total of $691.42 at mass meetings held in four Chicago Lithuanian colonies.</p>
   <p>Mr. Martus collected a total of $346 at a mass meeting in the Town of Lake colony; $234.11 in the Bridgeport colony; $85.96 in the West Side colony; and $25.35 in the Englewood district at a mass meeting held in a hall on Bankans Street (sic).</p>
   <p>The following is a list of the principal donors in the Town of Lake colony: Antanas J. Bierzynskis, $50; Pranas Kibortas, $50; St. Marcinkevicius, $25; J. D. Malisevskis, $35; $10 each was donated by the New City Savings Bank, <pb facs="5423970_3_0269.jpg" n="2"/>Julius Slikis, H. J. Mallon, Antanas Ezerskis, Victoria Marcinkevicius, the Zemaitis Printing House, A. Barcius, Walter Pierzynskis, John J. Zolp, John J. Natkowski; $5 each was donated by Jonas Szukevicia, Michalina Marcinkevicius, Stanley Beinoris, Dr. C. Z. Vezelis, J. F. Eudeikis, Boles Zaleski, A. B. Zemaitis; $2 each was donated by W. P. Smith, Samuel Rizza, W. L. Jansen, A. F. Czesna, Mikas Vaicekauskas, Mary Brenza, Xavier Rimkiewicz, J. J. Jankauskas, K. K. Strzyneckis, F. K. Strzyneckis; others donated smaller amounts.</p>
   <p>The following is a list of the principal donors in the Bridgeport colony; Casimer Kasputis, $50; Julius Chmelauskas, $25; Dr. Anthony J. Zimontas, $20; $10 each was donated by S. P. Tananevicius, F. P. Bradchulis, A. Olsevskis; $5 each was donated by Dr. A. Tanevicius, Dr. J. Jonikaitis, J. Sinkus, John W. Zacharevicz, Dr. K. Drangelis, Dr. J. Kulis, Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, J. Sernas, F. A. Jozapaitis, B. K. Balutis; $3 was donated by Dr. P. Wiegner; $2 each was donated by Joseph Leszynski, P. Zilinskas, J. Kulis, J. Rakauskas, P. Kenutis, J. J. Hertmanowicz, A. J. Zukauskas, <pb facs="5423970_3_0270.jpg" n="3"/>J. A. M., and the P. Conrad Studio; others donated smaller amounts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
