<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-15">Aug. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">How the Guests Are Succeeding</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-15">Aug. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">HOW THE GUESTS ARE SUCCEEDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago because of lack of time, we are doing the best we can to arrange lectures for the delegates of the Lithuanian Science Society of Vilnus. But we can say this much; the Chicago Lithuanians will not allow the guests to leave Chicago with empty hands. Up to the present time, the guests have visited not even one-half of the Chicago-Lithuanian communities, but already they have collected over two thousand dollars for the erection of the Lithuanian science building in Vilnus. Every Lithuanian community of this city is trying its best to receive the guests and to raise as much money as they can for the benefit of the national building. The contributions are coming in, not only half dollars, dollars and five dollars, but ten and one hundred dollar bills.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, of all the Chicago Lithuanian groups, the West Side Lithuanian community, with its Reverend K. Ambrozaitis, has shown itself to be the best.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0393.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last Saturday evening, lectures were arranged at Meldazis Hall; and the Lovers of Motherland Society, branch 28, gave a banquet for the honorable guests at Gavrilavicius Hall, on the same evening after the lecture. At the hall, during the lecture, every seat was occupied, and many were standing in the aisles. Reverend K. Ambrozaitis introduced the speakers. Then Dr. J. Basanavicius and M. Ycas spoke and explained the purpose of their visit. Also M. Ycas, who is a representative of Lithuania in the Duma, explained the general conditions in Lithuania, and his activity in the Duma in regard to the affairs of Lithuania as a nation.</p>
   <p>The speakers made a great effect upon the audience. The Lithuanians were particularly eager to see Dr. J. Basanavicius, the patriarch of Lithuania, who has devoted his life for the revival of Lithuanianism, to uplift, to enlighten, to give culture to oppressed Lithuania....The Sacred Heart parish choir sang several songs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0394.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Reverend K. Ambrozaitis, in introducing the speakers, declared that he would give one dollar for every dollar collected in the hall. When the collection was over, the Reverend donated $208 (400 rubles).</p>
   <p>Then Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas donated one hundred dollars; both Mr. Juozas Molis, meat-market owner and Mr. Krotkus, another meat-market owner, donated one hundred dollars each. There were many who bought the "charter" of the Lithuanian science building at $10.50 per "charter.".... The collection on the West Side is not yet completed. So far as we know over seven hundred dollars has already been collected.....</p>
   <p>After the lecture, the Lithuanian Lovers of the Motherland Society, branch 28, gave a banquet for the honorable guests. In the main, the Lithuanian youth entertained at the banquet..... Our singers Miss Horodockaite, Mrs. Janusauskiene, Mr. Pocius and Mr. Janusauskas sang several songs. Dr. Rutkauskas delivered a short talk.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0395.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Then the young Lithuanians placed Dr. Basanavicius on a chair and lifted him up in the air many times....Dr. Basanavicius was so moved that he was unable to utter a word.....</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian women do not want to lag behind the men. Miss Miseviciute and several other girls and women on the West Side decided that they would raise one hundred dollars for the Lithuanian science building in Vilnus. So far as we know, they have already collected close to one hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>It is not enough to write the name of the Chicago Lithuanian women in the Lithuanian science building of Vilnus; the Lithuanian women of other cities should follow Chicago Lithuanian women, and inscribe their names on the slate of the Lithuanian house of Vilnus.</p>
   <p>Names of the large donors who have donated to the Lithuanian Science Society <pb facs="5423970_3_0396.jpg" n="5"/>of Vilnus, each having given one hundred dollars or more are:</p>
   <p>Reverend K. Ambrozaitis, $208; Mr. L. Radziukynas, chemist and superintendent, Sandovall Zinc Company, Sandovall, Ill., $100; Reverend A. Serafinas, $100; Mr. Jonas Grigula, barber, $100; Reverend A. Kaupas, editor of Draugas, $100; Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, $100; Mr. Juozas Molis, meat market, $100; Mr. Jonas Krotkus, meat market, $100; Reverend A. Skrypka, $100; Mr. J. Hertmanavicius, real-estate broker, $100.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians from other states, California, Arizona, Iowa, Nebraska, Oklahoma, Vermont, and other states, have sent money for the Lithuanian science building of Vilnus.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
