<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-01-26">Jan. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanians Net $2,540.26 for War Relief at Allied Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-01-26">Jan. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIANS NET $2,540.26 FOR WAR RELIEF AT ALLIED BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Allied Bazaar held in the Coliseum during the ten-day period from January 10 to January 20 came to a close last Saturday evening. The Bazaar was sponsored by several national groups, among them the Lithuanians of Chicago, to raise funds for the relief of the war-stricken people of the Allied nations of Europe.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian section at the Bazaar realized a net sum of $2,540.26. This money will be sent to Lithuania for the relief of the war-stricken people of that country. In addition to this sum, the Lithuanians will receive a share of the money that was realized from paid admissions to the Bazaar; the exact amount which they will receive is not yet known. It is believed that altogether about a half million dollars was raised at the Bazaar for war relief.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0160.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The last day of the Bazaar was one of the most profitable days for the Lithuanian section; receipts for that day were about five hundred dollars. Lithuanian Day at the Bazaar, Thursday, January 18, also netted about the same profit. The program on Lithuanian Day was provided by the Knights of Lithuania Chorus, under the personal direction of Anthony Pocius.</p>
   <p>The total value of the articles that were on sale at the Lithuanian booth amounted to $450, but some of the articles were not sold. It is therefore clear that the Lithuanian section realized an unusually large margin of profit [on the articles actually sold]. Most of the money raised by the Lithuanians came from the sale of white and green tags, which were pinned on visitors by beautiful Lithuanian girls. [At that time, white and green were the Lithuanian national colors.] Anywhere from ten cents to a dollar fifty--depending on the generosity of the visitors--was received for each tag. A fairly large sum was realized from the "Marriage Court" and the "Divorce Court" maintained in the Lithuanian section. These "Courts" <pb facs="5423970_3_0161.jpg" n="3"/>created much fun at the Bazaar as visiting couples were "married" and later "divorced" in mock ceremonies. Miss Ciurlonis officiated as the judge and showed unusually great ability in that role.</p>
   <p>Among the workers in the Lithuanian section were Mrs. Masulis, Mrs. Olsauskas, Mrs. Vasilauskas, Mrs. Slikas, Mrs. Kulis, Mrs. Kodis, Mr. Mockus of Cicero, Mr. Zaldokas, and Mr. Sileika.</p>
   <p>Most of the articles sold at the Lithuanian booth were low-priced items, such as dolls dressed in Lithuanian national costumes, and typical Lithuanian waistbands. These were very popular items and were completely sold out. Lithuanian handicraft goods sold well also.</p>
   <p>Among the higher-priced articles that were not sold was a beautiful portrait of Dr. Jonas Basanavicius [the father of modern Lithuania]. This portrait was priced at twenty-five dollars; later, it will be raffled off for the benefit of Lithuanian war relief.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0162.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A complete report of the results of the Lithuanian participation in the Allied Bazaar will appear in a later issue of the Lietuva.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
