<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-05-12">May 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Wouldn't it Be Better to Unite</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0951</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0951.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-05-12">May 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">WOULDN'T IT BE BETTER TO UNITE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2-3.... Looking at our accomplishments as well as our societies and organizations, other people who do not know the situation may think, that we are more industrious than other nationalities. However, the opposite is true. We are not as industrious as we appear. We are wasting our energies by attempting to do too many things at a time and so end up by not accomplishing anything worth while; and thus all our efforts are wasted. Werever we look, we see many new societies being organized with various names by various groups but none of them exist very long. The old and the new societies alike are disappearing rapidly. Some small societies are still in existence, but their days are numbered; they may disappear any day.</p>
   <p>We have one large society known as the Lithuanian Alliance of America, and although its aim is narrow; we all must support by joining it. This society is the oldest Lithuanian organization in the United States of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0952.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In addition, the society is the most important national organization in America today. Its membership may not be very large, but in comparison to other societies, it is the largest one in America. The society is a benefit organization and its aim is to help all widows, orphans and unfortunate ones who are in dire need. It appears,however, that it is concerned only with the material needs of the Lithuanian people.</p>
   <p>Would it not be much better if Lithuanians belonged to one large beneficiary organization such as the Lithuanian Alliance of America, instead of many small ones that do not exist very long. We can benefit much more by supporting a large organization. Small benefit organizations are not permanent, while a large set-up is much more so. Moreover, larger beneficiary organizations, such as Lithuanian Alliance of America pay a larger death benefit to its members.</p>
   <p>If you pay one dollar a month to the Lithuanian Alliance of America, you will receive help while you are sick and unable to work and also a death benefit. Therefore, it would be much cheaper to belong to a large beneficiary organization than to many small ones, where you pay 50 cents duesper month and in addition <pb facs="5423970_3_0953.jpg" n="3"/>each member has to give one dollar more for a death benefit every time a member dies within the organization. People do not realize that it is less expensive to belong to a large organization. If the people paid the same amount to the Lithuanian Alliance of America as to many small organizations; they could receive bigger benefits, and at the same time have more money for national needs.</p>
   <p>If we all would belong to the Lithuanian Alliance of American our forces would be united, and our organization would be much stronger. Then we would be able to accomplish more for the future generation. We would also be able to publish a newspaper for our organization, or else support other national newspapers that uphold our point of view as a group. This plan, however, cannot be effected without unity.</p>
   <p>First we must unite before we proceed with plans. Then we will be more successful in enlightening our people. Therefore, let us all unite by joining only one organization, the Lithuanian Alliance of America, not only individually <pb facs="5423970_3_0954.jpg" n="4"/>but as organizations. Let us all work in unity. We will all receive more by joining the large national organization, such as the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The organization helps its members by paying $75.00 to the members who are very badly injured; and $150 death benefit. In addition it aids unfortunate members such as widows and the orphans.</p>
   <p>People cannot exist very long upon small benefits. We can increase these benefits only by following the same example as the capitalists who discharges and forgets about those workers no longer profitable to the firm; by expelling those who are about to receive benefits. But the Lithuanian Alliance of America can easily avoid such difficulties, if all people who now belong to the many small benefit societies will join this Alliance. Then the Lithuanian Alliance of America would be in much better position to buy a large tract of land and build homes to shelter those members who are old or injured, widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>This plan is very important to Lithuanians in America, hence members of the Lithuanias Alliance of America and the members of other small beneficiary societies should <pb facs="5423970_3_0955.jpg" n="5"/>weight very carefully this plan. We should know that united we stand and divided we fall.</p>
   <p>At the next Convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, we must make every effort to discuss the question of unity, which is an important problem to Lithuanians living in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
