<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 7,
<date when="1906-02-16">Feb. 16, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Parishioners Kicked Their Priest Out of the Church; Shooting and Fighting in the Lithuanian Church of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 7,
<date when="1906-02-16">Feb. 16, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE PARISHIONERS KICKED THEIR PRIEST OUT OF THE CHURCH; SHOOTING AND FIGHTING IN THE LITHUANIAN CHURCH OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, February 11, 1906, the parishioners of the Lithuanian Providence of God parish, 18th Street and Union Avenue, Chicago, chased their priest, Edward, out of the church, and then broke all the windows of the rectory and wanted to chase out the priest from their parish. The chasing of the priest from the parish was similar to the Russian revolution. All the parishioners have revolted against the priest. Only the police have protected him. The parishioners wanted to break into the rectory in order to chase out their priest. The women stood in front in the fighting ranks at the rectory door. The police were protecting the rectory. One woman wrested a club from a policeman and struck his head so hard that the policeman fell down from the porch, and was taken to the hospital, where his wound was stitched. Then the big fight started. Women and men picked up stones, broke the fence, <pb facs="5423970_3_1616.jpg" n="2"/>smashed the windows of the rectory and beat the police. From inside of the rectory the attackers were fired upon. The following people were shot and wounded: John Tamulaitis, 53 W. 18th St., was shot in the abdomen and in the left arm. He was taken to the County Hospital, and may die; Vincent Pusaras, from 15th and Union Avenue, was shot in the neck; Alexandra Dargis, 168 W. 18th St., shot in the right leg and knocked on the head, was taken to the County Hospital; John Marazas, 32 Ruble St., shot in the head, was taken to the County Hospital; John Bendzaitis, the new sacristan, had his head cracked with a stone; Michael Kilgalen, policeman, had his head badly beaten, and legs broken, he was taken to the hospital; G. M. Buckstahler, detective, had his face hit with a board; John Leahy, policeman, was wounded in the head; Thomas Maynard, Policeman, was thrown down from the porch by a woman and half dead was taken to the police station; John Roche, detective, had his back injured with a stone; Frank Alex, detective, was injured in the back, and had his brain pierced with a hat pin.</p>
   <p>Fifteen n were arrested.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1617.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The causes of this struggle are as follows:</p>
   <p>The Providence of God people organized their parish and obtained a charter (no Catholic church in Chicago has such a charter). Using the rights granted by this charter, the people made their own by-laws, appointed fifteen members to act as the administrators of the parish, and to control the income and expenses of the parish. Even though, in compliance with the demand of the bishop, the parishioners were forced to assign the church property to the latter, and to entrust the funds to the priest, the parish administration has controlled the income and expenses.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Steponavicia, like all the Lithuanian priests, did not favor such a control, especially when the parish administration, at the parish meeting, openly announced that the priest had a shortage of several thousand dollars in the parish budget. The priest appointed his own parish administration, consisting of two persons, in accordance to the bishop's new regulations. The old administration tried to examine the <pb facs="5423970_3_1618.jpg" n="4"/>parish books, but the priest, with the help of the police, wrested the books from the old administration. To the old administration were left only the keys of the church and the safe, and one book showing the parish account. The old administration called a meeting on January 21, 1906. At this meeting the parishioners decided that, as the Rev. Steponavicia does not agree with the parishioners' wishes, he must leave the parish within five days. If during these five days the priest refuses to leave the parish, the parishioners will not give even one cent to the priest. The priest disregarded the demands of the parishioners, who then requested the bishop to remove Rev. Steponavicia from the parish. The bishop also ignored this parishioners' demand. The members of the parish administration collected money on Sundays at the church and did not give that money to the priest, but kept it in their own hands. The priest went from house to house to collect the money, but the parishioners did not let the priest in, and no one gave him any money.</p>
   <p>On Friday, February 9th, the priest with the police came to the church <pb facs="5423970_3_1619.jpg" n="5"/>basement, where the parish secretary was working on the parish books. The priest wrested the church keys from the secretary, forced him to open the safe, and took from there the parish money and books. The secretary also was the sacristan of the parish, so the priest dismissed him.</p>
   <p>Such conduct made the parishioners angry, and they decided to expel the priest.</p>
   <p>On last Sunday the priest Steponavicia invited a certain Irish priest to officiate the Mass. Rev. Steponavicia started to collect money in the church during the Mass. Several voices in the church were heard saying: "Do not give a cent to this shoemaker!" The priest went on with his collection, but only a few nickels were dropped into the collection plate. When the priest was going through the women's section, one woman arose from her seat, wrested the plate from the priest, and hit him with it on the head. Commotion arose in the church. The priest ran into the rectory and the Irish priest from the altar asked the people to permit him to finish the celebration of High Mass.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1620.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>When the Irish priest had done this, the Rev. Steponavicia came to preach the sermon, but the women stopped him and started to beat him. One women struck the priest on the head with a beer bottle. The priest started to run to the rectory and the people ran after him, but the police stopped them. The rest of the people ran out through the main door of the church. They surrounded the rectory and the fight and shooting started.</p>
   <p>On Monday the police arrested the suspected people. They arrested the parish president, Paul Bagvilionis, 707 S. Union Avenue, and Michael Balceris, 1707 Mechanic St. It is rumored that they will arrest Joseph Skinder, who owns the saloon at 12th and Canal Sts. It is said he incited the parishioners against the priest.</p>
   <p>On last Tuesday the Rev. Steponavicia swore out warrants for the arrest of forty parishioners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1621.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>After the fight the priest's faction went to the bishop with complaints and begged him to punish the priest's enemies. They showed their by-laws to the bishop, and he read them. The bishop said that such by-laws are the most horrible offense against the Catholic world; that it disagrees with the laws of the church like fire with water. If the parishioners will not agree to destroy this constitution, the bishop will remove the Rev. Steponavicia and will close the church. Let the parishioners cry then!</p>
   <p>The parish constitution is against the bishop's laws, because the parish money is under the control of the administration, not under that of the priest. This is the greatest violation of the church laws.</p>
   <p>The bishop is preparing a proclamation which will be read by every rector in the churches of the bishop's diocese. The proclamation forbids any parish to have their committees, or any other authority over the church, and God forbids the constitution. The church committee must be appointed <pb facs="5423970_3_1622.jpg" n="8"/>by the bishop only; two persons and the third is the priest. Only the priest can take care of the parish money.</p>
   <p>The bishop says that such an event is the first and the worst one in the history of his diocese, and he will see that such a thing does not happen again. If anyone dares cause any trouble in the parish, the bishop will inflict on him the highest punishment demanded by the laws of the church.</p>
   <p>Will the Rev. Steponavicia go to church next Sunday? No one knows. The attitude of the parishioners toward the priest is a very hostile one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
