<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-05">June 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Educational Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0896</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0896.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-05">June 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past year many articles have appeared in our newspapers about the Lithuanian Women's Educational Society of Chicago. The main purpose of that publicity campaign was to urge our women and girls to join the society and work together with united forces for the benefit of our nationality and individual welfare. However, we are sorry to say that all these efforts have apparently produced very little results, if any at all. In spite of the fact that there is a very large population of Lithuanian women and girls in Chicago, the membership of the society is growing very slowly. When will we, Lithuanian women and girls, get interested in our affairs and welfare?</p>
   <p>We are unable to boast of any outstanding feminine leaders among our national group in Chicago. No one can deny the unpleasant fact that we are backward intellectually and depressed by a low morale. However, the <pb facs="5423970_3_0897.jpg" n="2"/>situation is by no means hopeless! We can very easily overcome this sad predicament of our womanhood, if we will only make up our minds to take a greater interest in the collective efforts of our national group for our advancement. It is easy to understand that if we will continue to stay in our homes with folded arms, then we cannot even hope for a better and brighter future, either for ourselves as individuals or for our national group as a whole. In other words, if we do not try we cannot hope to succeed.</p>
   <p>It is a self-evident fact that our nationality and modern society demand a higher state of intellectual development among women. It is, therefore, our sacred duty to make an effort to achieve that end. We would then be in a far better position to endow our children with greater minds and rear <pb facs="5423970_3_0898.jpg" n="3"/>them to be more useful members of mankind. Everything is in our hands; the welfare of mankind is largely dependent upon us.</p>
   <p>If we will continue to sit in our homes with folded arms, as we have been doing in the past, then of what value will be the achievements of our men in the national and intellectual fields? Can mankind derive any lasting benefits from orations, labor strikes, and the attempts to eliminate all kinds of exploiters of the masses, if we women will raise idiots?</p>
   <p>Therefore, Lithuanian women and girls, it is very easy to understand that it is necessary for us, also,to seek an education by reading good literature and by attending educational meetings. Let us all strive to be more active, <pb facs="5423970_3_0899.jpg" n="4"/>because we too have obligations to fulfill. It is the sacred duty of each and every woman and girl to lead our lives in such a manner as to be of real assistance to our men in their efforts to fill this world with peace, honesty, and contentment; and not like most women are now living.</p>
   <p>There are very many women who, by their indifference or bad behavior, are casting shame upon all of us and degrading our name. It is true that each and every individual must answer for his or her own acts. However, it is the practice of the men to judge all women by the faults of a few. A situation of this kind is painful and difficult to endure by a moral and thinking woman.</p>
   <p>Therefore, dear women comrades, let us make a strong effort to get rid of our <pb facs="5423970_3_0900.jpg" n="5"/>bad habit of indifference; let us strive to become educated! Let us read good books, newspapers, attend educational meetings, and urge our friends and acquaintances to do likewise. Let us learn to read and write both the Lithuanian and English languages. By following these steps,we will be engaged in useful and pleasant hobbies and, before long, we ourselves will be surprised at the progress we will have made.</p>
   <p>All Lithuanian women and girls of Chicago are urged to take full advantage of the various educational opportunities which are offered by the Lithuanian Women's Educational Society. This society is engaged in a varied number of activities to promote the cultural advancement of women and girls. One of the main features of the society is the sponsoring of lectures, one of which is delivered at every meeting on an important subject by an advanced member <pb facs="5423970_3_0901.jpg" n="6"/>of the society. We can learn a great deal from these lectures.</p>
   <p>During the last meeting of the society, which was held on May 3rd, a very interesting lecture, "The Cultural Achievements of Women," was delivered by Miss M. Odiekis. At the next meeting, which will be held on June 7th, at 869 West 33rd Place, Mrs. M. Seskis is scheduled to give a lecture, "The Future of Womanhood." All Lithuanian women and girls are invited to attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
