<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Celebrate Fifteenth Anniversary of Vytautas Guardsmen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATE FIFTEENTH ANNIVERSARY OF VYTAUTAS GUARDSMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first cavalry division of the Guardsmen of Grand Duke Vytautas of Lithuania commemorated the fifteenth anniversary of their organization with a parade, concert, and some orations. The celebration took place on Sunday afternoon, September 12, in the Bridgeport Chicago Lithuanian colony, home of the organization.</p>
   <p>The parade started from St. George's parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn Avenue. It proceeded north to 31st Street, then west to Morgan Street, south to 34th Place, and then east to Halsted Street into the Freiheit Turner hall, 3417-21 South Halsted Street, where the concert and orations took place.</p>
   <p>Six Lithuanian organizations participated in the parade and celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0849.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About five hundred fifty people marched in the parade, including sixteen uniformed and mounted Vytautas cavalry guardsmen, five policemen, and three bands.</p>
   <p>The main speakers at the hall were: S. Pocevicia, P. Mazeika, Reverend Krusas, Dr. Graiciunas, G. Haight, S. Marcinkevicius, and Mr. Stulga.</p>
   <p>The musical program was furnished by the following: Two choirs of St. George's parish, under the direction of B. Janusauskas--one choir consisted of eighteen men and thirteen ladies, the other had sixteen ladies and two men. The Lithuanian orchestra of Casimir Globis played a few American dance numbers. Recitations by three Lithuanian girls completed the program.</p>
   <p>The most noteworthy orators were Reverend Krusas, assistant to the pastor of St. George's Lithuanian Roman Catholic church, and Dr. Graiciunas. The former <pb facs="5423970_3_0850.jpg" n="3"/>urged Lithuanian organizations to fight against drunkenness, which "disgraces the Lithuanian people more than anything else". He said "it would be a good idea if all Lithuanian organizations would add the word 'temperance' to their names." Dr. Graiciunas spoke only about the poisonous effects of intoxicating liquors.</p>
   <p>The addresses of most of the speakers were rather lengthy, which caused some discontent among the listeners. It was sad to note that while the talks against intemperance were being delivered, a number of Lithuanians, who were at the bar in the rear of the hall and some among the audience, were consuming intoxicating liquors. They did not heed the warnings of the speakers.</p>
   <p>The first church choir sang a religious hymn, and the following popular numbers: "Kur Bega Sesupe" (Where the River Sesupe Flows); "Tai Grazios Dienos Pavasarelio" (The Days of Spring are Beautiful); and "Lietuva Tevyne Musu" <pb facs="5423970_3_0851.jpg" n="4"/>(Lithuania Our Fatherland), the Lithuanian national anthem.</p>
   <p>The second church choir, which is composed almost entirely of ladies, sang "Kur Banguoja Nemunelis" (Where the River Nemunas Flows), which carries a Czech melody instead of Lithuanian, and "Sveiki Broliai Dainininkai" (Hail Brother Singers).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
