<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 35,
<date when="1907-08-30">8-30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of the Lithuanian Church Corner Stone</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 35,
<date when="1907-08-30">8-30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF THE LITHUANIAN CHURCH CORNER STONE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On August 18th, there was a great celebration in Kensington, the consecration of the corner stone of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic church, at 108th and Wabash Avenue, where the church is under construction.</p>
   <p>There was a large number of Roman sheep. The Rev. Skripka from Chicago said that you Lithuanians of Kensington ought to be proud of building the church, and of having such a good spiritual leader as the Rev. Serafinas. Yes, the Rev. Serafinas is very good, he took $500.00 from the parish budget and the money in the priest's hands melted like ice in boiling water. Then, one of the parish committee, A. Maslauskis, was brave enough to ask the priest what he did with the parish money. The priest unwillingly admitted that he bought new furniture with that money, because his maid wanted to have new furniture.</p>
   <p>When the bishop came to the Pullman station a parade of several Lithuanian societies marched to 108th and Wabash Avenue. The bishop in his speech said that he is proud of the Lithuanian people in Chicago, they have already six or seven churches... Of course, the bishop is glad of the stupidity of the Lithuanians, when the bishop has millions the Lithuanians are adding more to increase <pb facs="5423970_3_1581.jpg" n="2"/>his wealth. The follower of Christ, the bishop was unable even to walk the short distance from the station to the new church. While Christ walked half naked, bare-footed, and hungry, our bishop, because he has a fat belly was unable to walk, so rode in a carriage.</p>
   <p>Petras Sermunelis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
