<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Number of Lithuanian Home Owners Increasing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NUMBER OF LITHUANIAN HOME OWNERS INCREASING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lithuanians can be proud of the happy fact that the number of Lithuanian real-estate owners in Chicago is rapidly increasing. Not so very long ago, only a small number of Lithuanians in Chicago owned homes and lots. Today, several blocks of homes in the immediate vicinity of St. George's Lithuanian Roman Catholic Church, 33rd Street and Auburn (now Lituanica) Avenue, are owned by Lithuanians; only a very small number of foreigners (non-Lithuanians) still reside in this area. In about two years, it is predicted that the entire section of the city known as Bridgeport will become wholly Lithuanian. If this progress continues unabated, we will probably see the day when the entire Ward will be in the hands of Lithuanian people. Should this come to pass, then the voters of the Lithuanian section will be able to nominate and elect a Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_3_0474.jpg" n="2"/>representative to the City Council, and thus gain a voice in the city government.</p>
   <p>As Lithuanians gain control of homes and lots in the Bridgeport community, they should see to it that proper sanitary and aesthetic improvements are made; by doing so we will be able to show that culturally the Lithuanian people are not lower than citizens of other nationalities. It will be an easy matter to regulate the sanitary and aesthetic conditions of the community when all real-estate property falls into the hands of Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>The ownership of real estate insures future security. When a Lithuanian insures his future security by purchasing good income-producing property, he not only profits personally, but also brings honor upon his nationality; it is a patriotic as well as a profitable practice. In purchasing homes and lots from foreigners (non-Lithuanians), most Lithuanians were assisted by the competent advice and service of the real-estate firm of A. Olsevskis, <pb facs="5423970_3_0475.jpg" n="3"/>which is located at 3252 South Halsted Street. This firm plans to carry on until the entire community is in the hands of Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
