<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 4,
<date when="1903-01-23">Jan. 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The Most Important National Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 4,
<date when="1903-01-23">Jan. 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE MOST IMPORTANT NATIONAL AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How many times came to your mind, brothers, (the idea) of what is the strongest pillar of the nation? Everyone of us has a different idea of it. I think that the strongest pillar is science, because with the help of science nations stand higher in civilization and increase their wealth. Science brings fortune and power both to the individual and the nation. A nation which is able to understand the value of science can use it as a fundamental stone. A nation that holds science as the foundation of its existence will never be exterminated. We see that the high peak of civilization was won by men who took science as their foundation. The Jews understand the value of science, they go to school, they build scientific institutions, they organize charitable societies, they give assistance to poor students seeking higher education.</p>
   <p>What do we Lithuanians have? We have many churches and for every 100 people one priest for the extermination of sin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0989.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among our people we have many with great abilities who are anxious to obtain higher education and work for the nation and the good of society. We need more educated people, as only through them we can go forward and become equal to other highly civilized nations. Our misunderstanding and inertness is the cause that much of the flower of the Lithuanian youth withers away.</p>
   <p>With the intention of helping the poor Lithuanian students, the Aurora Society took the matter into its hands. It was organized by a few intelligent Lithuanians. The purpose of the Aurora Society is to help the poor Lithuanian students who are studying civil science. Can you, dear brothers, join with your donation or help get more members into the society? You should organize branches of the Aurora Society and ask your friends to join them. This worthy society was organized by secularists. Are you not glad when you read a book written by a secularist on natural science? After reading such a book you find who you are, and where you are. Brothers, join our ranks!</p>
   <p>R. Plunksna.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
