<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 6,
<date when="1899-02-10">Feb. 10, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The Duties of the Lithuanian Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 6,
<date when="1899-02-10">Feb. 10, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE DUTIES OF THE LITHUANIAN SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanian newspaper Katalikas (The Catholic) wrote an article about the duties of the Lithuanian societies toward the church. It seems to us that this article was written not by the editor, but it came from the pen of the spiritual leader. We do not want to have a controversy about such an article, but we will take into consideration the main points of the article, because the writer contradicts his own idea. In one part of the article he says that the societies not only should have as their duty the interference with the order of the church, but they must cooperate with the rector and work together for the benefit of the church, for the good of the parish and the brother Catholics.</p>
   <p>This is a very good statement, but let us look further how he contradicts himself. "Our teacher," in his statement, says that every society must take care of its own duties, and not to interfere with the other societies, especially they must not interfere with the parish affairs because the parish has its own and entirely different laws. One or few societies do <pb facs="5423970_3_1772.jpg" n="2"/>not represent a parish. Is it not a joke when a few men in the name of their societies want to examine the parish books, and they also want to be cashiers and to rule the whole parish? The Catholic Katalikas' writer, in the beginning of his article, invites the societies to join the activities of the parish, and in the end of the article prohibits the societies to participate in any parish affairs.</p>
   <p>Now then, the priest can do with the parish affairs the way he wants, to waste the parish money for his personal benefit and yet the parishioners and the societies have no rights nor power to stop such extravagancy of the priest. Nor have they the right to remove the priest in order to get in his place a better one. When the priest refuses to allow to examine the parish books and the condition of the budget, the parishioners must keep quiet, obey, and give more money, while the debts on the church are increasing.</p>
   <p>If such is the case, that those who donate their money to the church have no voice, right nor power to look into the affairs of the parish, then <pb facs="5423970_3_1773.jpg" n="3"/>it would be much better if the church were like any other business institution. Let the priest keep the church and set the price for his services. Then let those who want the priest's service pay for it; and the parishioners and the societies need not donate their money to uphold the parish, nor to worry about the condition or standing of the church and its debts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
