<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 20,
<date when="1902-05-16">May 16, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Youth of America Pleasure Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 20,
<date when="1902-05-16">May 16, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN YOUTH OF AMERICA PLEASURE CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, May 4, the Lithuanian Youth of America Pleasure Club held its monthly meeting. One determination of the club is worth mentioning. Mr. J. I. Badziunas made a few remarks about the Lithuanian martyrs who are exiled in Siberia and the other parts of Russia. They are suffering there just because they worked for the cause of Lithuanianism. He further mentioned the Lithuanian students who are attending schools in foreign countries; these Lithuanian young students were expelled from the Russian schools because they were working for the cause of Lithuanianism. Now they are trying to complete their education in other countries, and they are appealing to us for help. He made the motion that the dub should donate $10 for that cause: $5 for the martyrs and $5 for the Lithuanian students. The motion was seconded by the club's president, Mr. Zacharevicze, and the club unanimously voted the above mentioned sum of money, and the money was delivered to the office of Lietuva.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The above mentioned club was organized in the year 1900. At the beginning there were only six members, now the club has thirty-five members. The purpose of the club is to cultivate its members physically and mentally, to spread the enlightenment among them, to stand all for one and to help each other in every way. In case of sickness there is no stated amount of benefit; it is given according to the needs of the sick person.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there are over 40 Lithuanian societies. If every society would donate $10 each, it would be $400. At present the Lithuanian newspapers do not collect in an entire year that amount of money for this great cause. Some of the so-called national societies have their national celebration banquets, but from the profits of their banquets the societies never donate even one penny for national affairs.</p>
   <p>The club holds its meetings in Vaszkeviczius hall, 3301 Auburn Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0426.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The initiation fees are $2; the monthly dues are 50 cents. The officials of the club are Adolfas Zacharevicze, president; Jonas Urba, vice-president; M. Jananeivicze, secretary, J. Bagdziunas, financial secretary; Adomas Zacharevicze, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
