<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-09">Apr. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Organization Formed to Establish Day Nursery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-09">Apr. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION FORMED TO ESTABLISH DAY NURSERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An organization for the purpose of establishing a day nursery was formed last week in the Bridgeport district of Chicago. The nursery will take care of the children of employed mothers while the latter are at work.</p>
   <p>The newly formed organization is composed of Lithuanian and non-Lithuanian women. The following officers were elected: Mrs. Zimontas, president; Mrs. Davis, vice-president; Mrs. Damijonaitis, recording secretary; Mrs. Jerome, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Damijonaitis stated during an interview that the first step of the organization will be to raise sufficient funds for the establishment of the projected day nursery for children. A fairly large sum of money must be collected before the nursery can be opened. However, it is believed that the people of the neighborhood will recognize the importance of the day nursery and will not refuse to assist the organization. It is predicted that it will be possible to open the nursery sometime during midsummer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Employed mothers will be able to leave their children at the nursery in the morning and take them home in the evening. A trained and experienced nurse will be employed to take care of the children. An effort will be made to find a Lithuanian for that position.</p>
   <p>It is planned to charge ten cents per day for the care of each child at the nursery. For this money the child will receive supervision and food. Only children who are at least one year old will be accepted.</p>
   <p>The projected day nursery will be located in the first house east of Fellowship House at 831 West 33rd Place.</p>
   <p>The organization also plans to establish a clinic in Fellowship House where people of the neighborhood will be able to receive medical attention and medicine free of charge. The doctor of this clinic will also look after the health of the children in the day nursery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
