<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-19">June 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">13Th Convention of Catholic Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-19">June 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">13TH CONVENTION OF CATHOLIC ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, June 14, the Lithuanian Catholics of Chicago celebrated the opening of the 23rd Convention of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America. More than 1,500 Lithuanians, including delegates from all over the United States, marched in a parade to the Columbus Theatre, where the celebration exercises took place. The hall, which has seating accommodations for 1,500 people, was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>Previously there were rumors to the effect that nearly all the Lithuanian church societies of Chicago had decided to boycott the convention because of legal battles with Rev. Krauciunas, pastor of St. George's parish. However, the multitudinous participation in Sunday's affair indicates that the plan to declare a boycott had been withdrawn. The parade proved to be the largest Lithuanian parade that ever took place in Chicago. Even the members of the arrangements committee appeared to be surprised at the large turn-out.</p>
   <p>The hall was decorated in a typical holiday fashion. The front parts of <pb facs="5423970_3_1348.jpg" n="2"/>the balcony and gallery were draped with Lithuanian flags. The box seats were draped with American flags. The spacious stage was occupied completely by those who participated in the program. There were various organized groups of vocal artists, and a number of boys and girls, dressed in Lithuanian national costumes, who delivered recitations. In the front part of the stage, a row of priests, prominent guests, and speakers were seated.</p>
   <p>In writing about this celebration it would be very unfair if I failed to mention the fact that a number of non-Catholic vocal artists also took part in the program. Among the Catholic choral groups, which were led by V. Dauksa, there were quite a number of vocal artists from the non-Catholic Birute Singing and Dramatic Society, whose director is Mikas Petrauskas. Therefore, it appears that we are marching forward towards unity and brotherly love. But wait, reader, do not rejoice too soon; as you read on, you will find that our long standing flaws are still with us.</p>
   <p>The musical part of the program, rendered by an orchestra and choral groups, was very successful. The choral songs, especially, pleased the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1349.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many encores were requested. The best number was a duet by Miss Odeikis and Miss Jakstas. The best recitation number was delivered by a little eight-year-old Lithuanian girl, Ona Binkis, who recited a Lithuanian poem very passionately.</p>
   <p>However, the Lithuanian orators, except the secretary of the Catholic Alliance, spoke in the very same manner as our Socialists speak at their meetings.</p>
   <p>Besides the Lithuanian speakers, there were some foreigners who spoke in English. One was a representative of the Mayor of Chicago, and another spoke in the name of the Governor of Illinois. The propriety of the practice of inviting foreigners to speak at our gatherings is very questionable. The Mayor and Governor are neither Catholics nor Lithuanians, and the sincerity of their friendly gestures is doubtful. It is true that their representatives praised us as much as possible. The Mayor's representative, Dr. Evans, who is a member of the Chicago Board of Health, even went so far as to declare that the Lithuanians are the most charming people in Chicago. This highly flattering remark received some applause from the audience. However, whether or not he really meant what he said is very doubtful. Immediately after completing their talks, they rushed out through the door and <pb facs="5423970_3_1350.jpg" n="4"/>abandoned the "most charming people of Chicago." When in our presence, our public servants display great talent in the art of flattery; but when our backs are turned, they exhibit a corresponding ability to ridicule us and poke fun at our activities. A celebration, such as the parade and exercises about which I am now writing, furnishes them with a pretext for laughing at us. Most news items which appear in the American press about our activities, appear to be written in a ridiculous fashion, with the intention of demoralizing our spirit.</p>
   <p>The first speakers, to address the audience in the theatre were Rev. A. Skripka, pastor of the Holy Cross parish; Dr. Stupnickas, a Chicago physician; and Bishop P. Muldoon. Dr. Stupnickas did not delve into any problems pertaining to our nationality; he merely advised the delegates to raise the death benefit of the alliance to $1,000. Rev. Skripka spoke mainly on the subject of education. He has a very powerful voice and can shout loudly, but that is all. It seems that for such an important occasion he should have prepared a much better address. Apparently, our priests still regard themselves in the old-fashioned manner, as holy personages who, even without merit or good deeds, must be respected by everyone. He pointed out in his talk that people without an education are exploited by all sorts of swindlers, and that an education promotes the general <pb facs="5423970_3_1351.jpg" n="5"/>welfare of an individual. However, he strongly emphasized the point that an education without religion is disastrous. "In France," he said, many people are fairly well educated, but their education is separated from religion; for that reason French priests are being persecuted, their property is being taken away from them, they are being thrown out from their churches, and the people are being denied opportunities to save their souls. Therefore, "he stated, "we should beware of an education without religion."</p>
   <p>Reverend Skripka remarked that many dishonest apostles have sprung up in all parts of the world, and that the world is now flooded with bad literature. He said some good literature is still available in America, but not much. He lauded the Lithuanian-American weekly Zvaigzde (The Star), and the following Catholic publications in Lithuania: Saltinis (The Fountain), Vienybe (Amity), Viltis (Hope), Draugna (Society), and various books and pamphlets published and sold at popular prices by the St. Casimir Society, which has branches in both Lithuania and America.</p>
   <p>I am not a Catholic nor and adherent of any other organized religion. However, I would agree with Reverend Skripka if, in addition to religion, he would permit <pb facs="5423970_3_1352.jpg" n="6"/>the people to be concerned with their worldly welfare. What he calls religion, I call morality, which I recognize as essential to the welfare and happiness of mankind. However, I cannot agree with him that an individual can find happiness and contentment merely by being moral. He must also know how to provide himself with bread, clothing, and other vital necessities; he must understand nature, know himself, and study the various branches of science. All these branches of secular learning are separated from the conception of God, and considered to be of no importance in a moral education. This would be a very strange world if we all depended for our earthly welfare entirely upon the providence of God. Everything is all right in its own place, but our priests refuse to recognize that fact. We must learn to know life from all angles. The people already understand this fact, but our priests are still unable to see it.</p>
   <p>Reverend Skripka concluded his talk with the statement that it is absolutely necessary for Lithuanian Catholics to establish a Catholic school in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The secretary of the Catholic Alliance supported Reverend Skripka's suggestion to establish a Lithuanian Catholic school.</p>
   <p>The Bishop delivered a well prepared and appropriate address, which pleased <pb facs="5423970_3_1353.jpg" n="7"/>the Lithuanians. He expressed great satisfaction in the manner in which the Lithuanian Catholics honor the Pope, and later praised the Lithuanians for adhering to their native language and traditions. He stated that people of the same nationality are in a better position to understand and appreciate each other. It is apparent from the Bishop's talk, that he is a good Irish patriot, and that for that reason he urged others to be loyal to their nationalities. It is always pleasant to listen to those foreigners who wish for others the same thing which they wish for themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
