<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-08-31">Aug. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Hold Beach Party for Benefit of Day Nursery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-08-31">Aug. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">HOLD BEACH PARTY FOR BENEFIT OF DAY NURSERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the sponsors of the Lithuanian Children's Day Nursery held a beach party on the shores of Lake Michigan at 79th Street to raise funds for the upkeep of the Nursery. About seventy people attended; they went bathing in the lake, enjoyed refreshments, played various games and engaged in conversations. The group was composed mainly of members of the Chicago Lithuanian intelligentsia. A net profit of about eighteen dollars was realized.</p>
   <p>The Nursery, which is located in the Bridgeport section of Chicago, was founded several years ago by a group of Prominent Chicago Lithuanian women. It is the first institution of its kind in the United States. About 450 orphans and children of working mothers are sheltered in the Nursery every month. Working mothers who have no one to take care of their children while they are at work bring their children to the Nursery early in the morning and then pick them up after work in the evening. About twenty or twenty-five children are <pb facs="5423970_3_0059.jpg" n="2"/>cared for by the Nursery every day. Chicagoans should aid this worthy institution as much as possible.</p>
   <p>The beach party was organized by a committee composed of the following: Mrs. J. Zimontas, Mrs. M. Damijonaitis, Mrs. P. Giraitis and Mrs. O. Kiras.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
