<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 46,
<date when="1893-11-25">Nov. 25, 1893</date><title level="a">A Few Words to the Chicago Lithuanians</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 46,
<date when="1893-11-25">Nov. 25, 1893</date><title level="a">A FEW WORDS TO THE CHICAGO LITHUANIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are over six thousand Lithuanians in Chicago, but no people of other nationalities are so poor and so ignorant as the Lithuanians are.</p>
   <p>Everybody laughs at the Poles and the Jews. But look at the Poles, they have many judges; many Poles have city and county jobs; many Poles have big business concerns. Take the Jews, they have banks and all kinds of business establishments. Those people are strong in politics because they have their political clubs and they are citizens of this country. They are strong in politics, have big businesses because they are educated and they read books and newspapers.</p>
   <p>We Lithuanians have nothing. Hundreds of Lithuanians can get no jobs during the present industrial crisis just because they are not citizens. We have no political clubs worth mentioning, no political organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0629.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lithuanians' do not read papers or books. They spend their money and time in saloons.</p>
   <p>If we Lithuanians would educate ourselves, we would have our judges and other officials in city and county offices.</p>
   <p>We Lithuanians do not take into consideration what opportunities we have in this free country of America. Read good books and newspapers, educate yourselves, join political parties, then will Americans take us for a cultured people, but not as the lowest creatures of society.</p>
   <p>Every Lithuanian should become a citizen because when you are a citizen you will get a job even in the present industrial crisis. You will not starve as so many Lithuanians are starving now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
