<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-10-11">Oct. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Celebration of Liberty Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joseph J. Elias and John I. Bagdziunas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-10-11">Oct. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE CELEBRATION OF LIBERTY DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joseph J. Elias And John I. Bagdziunas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting concerned with the participation of Lithuanians in the observation of Liberty Day was held October 8 at St. George's Parish Hall. Many societies and districts were represented. There were representatives from the districts of Bridgeport, Town of Lake, West Side, 18th Street and Union Avenue, Brighton Park and Cicero. It was decided that Lithuanians would participate in as great numbers as possible. Other districts reported that they also would take part.</p>
   <p>Two big bands have been hired. One big float will be decorated. All members and friends of Lithuanian societies are requested to participate. The following information should be remembered:</p>
   <p>1. Promptly at noon the line of march will begin to form at the points designated for each division. At 12:45 the leader of each division will <pb facs="5423970_3_1114.jpg" n="2"/>report to the General that his division is ready to march. The parade will begin promptly at 1:00 P.M.</p>
   <p>2. The parade will start from Van Buren Street and Michigan Avenue. It will go north to Randolph Street, west to State Street, south to Jackson Boulevard, west to La Salle Street, north to Randolph Street, and west to Franklin Street, where the parade will end.</p>
   <p>3. The Lithuanians will be in the Fourteenth Division, which will meet in Grant Park at Van Buren Street near the Lake, on the far side of the railroad tracks.</p>
   <p>4. The Lithuanian Division will have one Lithuanian Flag and as many American Flags as it desires. Therefore, every society which has an American Flag is urged to use it for this parade. Do not wear society badges. The government will supply badges to those participating in the parade. Those who plan to march in the parade are advised to go to Van Buren Street near the Lake and join the Fourteenth Division. If any districts wish to march in groups to the designated place, they may do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1115.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5. A giant Lithuanian chorus, directed by Anthony Pocius, will head the Lithuanian Division, singing as it marches. There will also be a group of Lithuanian girls dressed in Lithuanian costumes and in the uniforms of Red Cross nurses.</p>
   <p>6. Delegates from all districts will meet at St. George's Parish Hall Friday night, October 11, at 8 P.M., to discuss final arrangements. Delegates of all districts and societies, as well as all Lithuanians who wish to learn more about the parade, are invited to attend this meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
