<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 23,
<date when="1906-06-08">June 8, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Twenty Second Convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1356</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1356.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 23,
<date when="1906-06-08">June 8, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE TWENTY SECOND CONVENTION OF THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE OF AMERICA</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America decided to establish a Lithuanian colony for old people. To find a suitable place, the following committee was elected; F. Golubickas, P. V. Birstonas, P. Lazauskas, J. Tareila, and A. Melninkaitis. They should find a suitable place, and describe it. The members of the Lithuanian Alliance of America will then vote for approval or rejection.</p>
   <p>A protest resolution was brought against the Chicago Lithuanian clergy for their warning and threatening the excommunication of their parishioners for taking part in the parade and for attending the convention's sessions.</p>
   <p>The convention set aside fifty dollars for the best written Lithuanian poem and composition. It donated fifty dollars for a monument to the deceased J. Paukstis, who was the first initiator to organize the Lithuanian Alliance of America. It <pb facs="5423970_3_1357.jpg" n="2"/>pays five dollars per month to the writer, Vistalis.</p>
   <p>The national cents (the national cents are paid, one cent a year by every member to the national affairs fund) were distributed as follows: $210 for the writer, Vistalis; $100 to the students fund; $100 to the Lithuanian old people's home and colony, which are to be bought; and the balance of $344.42 to the revolutionary movement in Lithuania. The Alliance will lend five thousand dollars without interest to the Lithuanian colony, if such a place is bought.</p>
   <p>The twenty second convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America will be held in Cleveland, Chio.</p>
   <p>The twenty first Lithuanian convention was closed at 7:30 P.M., May 31, 1906., Chicago, Illinois. J. Jlgaudas, reporter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
