<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 13,
<date when="1902-03-28">March 28, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">By-Laws of the Aurora Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 13,
<date when="1902-03-28">March 28, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">BY-LAWS OF THE AURORA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Purpose. The Aurora Society's purpose is to help Lithuanian students seeking higher education, so as to have Lithuanian intellectuals in every branch of science.</p>
   <p>Assistance. (1) Support will be given in the first place to those who after graduation cannot make a profitable living, as is the case with painters, musicians, students of natural science, philologists, etc. In the absence of such students, other students seeking higher education in other fields shall have the preference. Women will have the preference over men. Those exiled from the Fatherland for the cause of Lithuanianism, and who attend schools in foreign countries, shall be preferred to those attending schools in the Fatherland. (2) Only those students who are studying secular science will obtain support; ecclesiastical seminary students are excluded from this society. (3) Those with ability for certain <pb facs="5423970_3_1001.jpg" n="2"/>trades and who are striving to learn them, as well as boys and girls studying in foreign countries, shall get help from the Aurora Society. (4) Of the candidates, the society will give preference to those who are known for their activities in behalf of Lithuanianism. (5) The stipend and other help given by the society to students shall not be considered as a donation, but as a loan. After graduation students shall return the money loaned to them, or refund may be made through writings in behalf of our nation.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that the graduates (who receive) aid from the Aurora Society make their abode in Lithuania, where they would be in a better position to work for the benefit of the country. Should conditions prevent the student from living in Lithuania, the Aurora Society shall not press this requirement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1002.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Candidates desiring to get a stipend must apply to the society before the time of entrance to school, so that the society's officials have at least six months' time to investigate the applicant's qualifications.</p>
   <p>Assets. (1) The society's assets consist of membership dues, donations, and net proceeds from banquets, lectures, etc. (2) The society's capital, (a) Appropriation for aid to students and (b) this fund consists of monthly dues, donations, and other income. (Notice: The society accepts donations from members and non-members).</p>
   <p>Members. (1) Members may be of either sex. (2) Membership is divided into two classes: first class members pay $5 initiation fee and 50 cents monthly dues, second class members pay $1 initiation and 25 cents monthly dues. The initiation fee may be paid in a lump sum or on time; first class members <pb facs="5423970_3_1003.jpg" n="4"/>may pay it in ten months, second class members in two months' time. First class members paying in full $120, and second class members paying $60, are exempted from further payments. (4) The rights of both first class and second class members, whether men or women, are equal. (5) In addition to the active members of sections I and II, there shall be honorary members. Honorary members shall be those who donate not less than $100 to the society. (6) The Lithuanians of Europe who are willing to join the Aurora Society can pay a ruble (sic), three marks, five francs, or 4 shillings for the American dollar.</p>
   <p>Magistracy. The society's magistracy consists of the president, the secretary and the treasurer. The treasurer must be under a bond of $1,000. (There are) also two trustees of the budget. The bond for the treasurer must be placed by two bondsmen, $500 each. The treasurer cannot keep <pb facs="5423970_3_1004.jpg" n="5"/>more than $100 on him. When he has more than $100, the money must be deposited in the bank by the president, the secretary and the treasurer of the society. (2) The treasurer has no right to pay out money without the knowledge of the society's members. (3) The society's officials are elected by public vote. The officials have no special privilege; they just fulfill the decisions of the society; they cannot by their own will give financial help or a stipend to any student. The majority vote of the society's members decides to whom a stipend should be given. The officials are to get the necessary information about the applicant and fulfill everything that the society tells them to. (5) The central committee shall be elected for three years (It is desirable that the entire committee be elected from one city).</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society is the main branch, but it organizes locals all over the United States and in Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1005.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Any misunderstanding among the members is taken up by the grievance committee of three members. This committee has full right to expel the guilty person from the society.</p>
   <p>Clusters. Clusters of the Aurora Society have full power. The cluster shall send the membership dues to the central treasurer, while the names of the members of the cluster and the account shall be sent to the financial secretary.</p>
   <p>(Translator's note: The sponsor of this Aurora Society is Dr. A. L. Graiciunas. When the first meeting was called, the following members were present: Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, Mr. Giriotas, J. Jancauskas, V. Miseika, J. Adomaitis (Szernas), editor of Lietuva, A. Lalis, author of a Lithuanian-English Dictionary. These men organized the above mentioned society. The society helped ten students in four years, paying $250 a year to each student.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
