<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-09-21">Sept. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Students Hold Convention in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-09-21">Sept. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN STUDENTS HOLD CONVENTION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Students' Association of America held its annual convention on September 14-15 in the Ausra Hall, 29th and Halsted Streets, Chicago, Illinois. Although there were not many delegates at the convention, nevertheless many important decisions were made for the benefit of the organization.</p>
   <p>A motion was made and discussed at the convention to affiliate with the Lithuanian-American Workers' Council, which was recently formed in Chicago by P. Grigaitis, editor of Naujienos (News). It was decided not to affiliate, because the Council is a temporary political organization with unclear aims.</p>
   <p>The issuing of a monthly organ, entitled Banga (Wave), was discussed. However it was decided not to issue an organ on account of the lack of funds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The convention concluded with a big concert, which was given by the Association last Sunday evening, September 16, at Meldazis Hall, 23rd Place and Oakley Avenue. The musical concert netted a profit of $150, which will be turned over to the Association.</p>
   <p>Some of the most talented Chicago Lithuanian musical artists took part in the concert. Among the participants were: F. Jakutis, soloist; Miss Marion Rakauskas, popular singer; Karl Sarpalius; Paul Stogis; Miss A. Radauskas; Miss M. Norkus; and Mr. M. Juozavitas, young pianist.</p>
   <p>Most of the musical artists who took part in the program were members of the famous Biruta Chorus of the Biruta Singing and Dramatic Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
