<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-26">Feb. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">First Meeting of the First Lithuanian National Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-26">Feb. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST MEETING OF THE FIRST LITHUANIAN NATIONAL COUNCIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 10, 1915 at 3 P.M., Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, president of the Temporary National Council, opened the first session of the National Council in the Great Northern Hotel, Chicago, Illinois. The session was attended by: Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas (of the Total Abstinence Alliance), Attorney A. Slakis (of the Knights of Lithuania), Reverend F. Kemesis (of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America), Mr. J. S. Vasiliauskas (of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Federation), Mr. J. Lukosevicius (of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America). The Reverend Jakaitis (of the Total Abstinence Alliance) sent a letter stating that for very important reasons he was unable to attend the meeting. In his letter, however, he made a number of suggestions, in regard to the Council. Nothing was heard from Reverend Misius (of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Federation). A telegram was sent to him, asking that he attend at least the session of the following day. The following were elected as officers of the meeting: Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, chairman; Reverend F.Kemesis, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The session was opened with the Lord's Prayer. This act precipitated a discussion on the subject whether or not this procedure established a binding precedent for all meetings of the Council. It was decided that this precedent would be binding only upon the Christian members of the Council; non-christians were to be at liberty either to participate or not to participate in the saying of the prayer.</p>
   <p>After long and careful deliberations, the following constitution for the National Council in America was adopted:</p>
   <p>I. Definition.</p>
   <p>The National Council in America is the supreme and central Lithuanian-American organization, which unifies, regulates, and dominates all the national activities of the Lithuanians in America.</p>
   <p>II. Purpose and Activities.</p>
   <p>1. The primary and most important purpose of the National Council in America <pb facs="5423970_3_1251.jpg" n="3"/>is to regain political liberty for Lithuania.</p>
   <p>2. Lithuanian-Americans constitute only a limb of the tree of Lithuania. This limb can remain alive only as long as it continues to draw sap--national spirit--from the trunk. For that reason the National Council in America will co-operate and maintain close relations with a similar public, or secret, organization, in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>3. The National Council in America will concern itself with all public affairs of Lithuanian-Americans, such as politics, education, the promotion of national feeling, organizations, etc.</p>
   <p>4. The National Council in America will support and assist in every possible way all important projects of the fatherland, and all activities for the promotion of national culture.</p>
   <p>III. Composition of the National Council in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1252.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>1. The National Council in America as an organization was created by the Lithuanian-American Political Convention, which met on September 21 and 22, 1914 in the Drill Room of the Masonic Temple, Chicago, Illinois. In accordance with the decisions of that convention, the National Council in America shall be composed of delegates from all large and legal Lithuanian-American organizations that possess the right to establish lodges in the United States. Delegates are to be elected for a term of two years. An organization which has no less than one thousand members in the United States is authorized to elect one delegate; an organization with no less than five thousand members may elect two delegates.</p>
   <p>2. The National Council is a nonpartisan organization, and should unite all Lithuanian-American factions. Therefore, organizations of all factions may elect delegates to the National Council.</p>
   <p>3. Organizations may elect delegates to the National Council only at their conventions. An exception to this ruling is made only in case an elected <pb facs="5423970_3_1253.jpg" n="5"/>delegate dies before the expiration of his or her two-year term; then the supreme officers of the organization may elect a temporary delegate until the next convention of the organization.</p>
   <p>5. The officers of the National Council shall consist of a president, a vice-president, and a secretary; for the sake of efficiency and convenience, the president shall also act as treasurer. The officers shall be elected for a term of one year.</p>
   <p>6. The National Council will meet once every year, during the month of February.</p>
   <p>7. Special meetings of the National Council, for important reasons, may be called by the president, but only with the consent of a majority of the members of the National Council.</p>
   <p>IV. Treasury of the National Council.</p>
   <p>1. The National Council shall maintain a treasury to cover the following <pb facs="5423970_3_1254.jpg" n="6"/>expenses: expenses of the secretary; traveling expenses of Council members; rent for convention halls; telegraphic expenses, etc. Every organization which elects a delegate or delegates to the National Council must pay a yearly fee of $25 into the treasury for each delegate.</p>
   <p>2. In case the annual dues prove to be insufficient to cover all the expenses of the Council, then the National Council shall appeal to the conventions or officers of member organizations to donate money from their treasuries to the National Council.</p>
   <p>V. Relations With Lithuanian National Funds.</p>
   <p>1. The National Council is the supreme organization of all Lithuanian-American organizations, and forms the central body of all the important organizations; it enjoys the greatest amount of confidence amount of confidence among Lithuanian-Americans, and is recognized by them as their greatest authority. Therefore, the initial and supreme voice in organizing and conducting important matters <pb facs="5423970_3_1256.jpg" n="7"/>Council. However, an amendment to the constitution can be made only by the votes of at least two-thirds of all the members of the National Council.</p>
   <p>On February 11, during the morning session of the National Council, discussions took place concerning a proposal to present a lengthy petition to the peace congress which is due to assmble at the end of the present European war. The proposal was unanimously adopted. An effort will be made to obtain the largest possible number of signatures of Lithuanian-Americans. A committee of three was elected to prepare the text of the petition. The committee is composed of Dr. Rutkauskas, Attorney A. Slakis, and Reverend F. Kemesis. The committee will publish a large number of copies of the petition and then send them to the various Lithuanian-American colonies with instructions as to how signatures are to be collected.</p>
   <p>The National Council authorized the president and secretary to appeal to those organizations which did not join the National Council to elect delegates to the Council.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1257.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The Temporary National Council, which was created by the Chicago Political Convention to act temporarily, and to organize a permanent National Council, has fulfilled its duty and has transferred all of its business to the permanent National Council in America. An expense account incurred by the first meeting of the permanent National Council--traveling expenses of delegates, rental of the meeting hall, etc.--will be submitted to the officers of the National Fund (who up until now composed the Temporary National Council).</p>
   <p>The following were elected officers of the National Council in America: Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, president; J. S. Vasiliauskas, vice-president; Reverend F. S. Kemesis, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
