<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 1,
<date when="1904-01-01">Jan. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">On the New Year</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 1,
<date when="1904-01-01">Jan. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE NEW YEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On New Year's Day, among Christians of the olden times, there was a custom of sending good wishes to friends and relatives. We also have many wishes for this coming year.</p>
   <p>The first of our desires is peace and mutual understanding between the so-called intellectuals and the newspapers. As long as the disputes and disagreements on minor things exist, we can accomplish nothing good for ourselves, for the society as a whole or for the nation. The most disreputable propaganda is spread by the clergy. The clergy attacks with the dirtiest denunciations, disregarding morals and ethics. The clergymen hold their secret conventions, in which they do not permit laymen to participate. If some loyal layman comes to the secret convention and opens his mouth against the schemes of the clergy, he is denounced as an infidel and is expelled from the convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1639.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The greatest aim of the clergy is to keep under their absolute control the parish schools in order to bring up the young Lithuanian generation as the slaves of the priests. Instead of giving moral and intellectual training in the parish schools, the clergy are trying their best to develop in the schools, fanatics, followers of the clergy, and denouncers of everything that is good for society and the nation.</p>
   <p>In this coming New Year, let us use more sense. Let us have strong workers' organizations, cooperative stores and small factories. Then we will not lack good schools. For this cause we ought to convince our brothers through facts and through logic, but not by denunciations and intrigues. By doing this we shall uplift our Lithuanians morally, intellectually, and economically.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
