<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-03-01">Mar. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Lithuanians Adopt Washington's Birthday Resolutions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-03-01">Mar. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[LITHUANIANS ADOPT WASHINGTON'S BIRTHDAY RESOLUTIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following resolution was passed at each of the seven mass meetings held on Washington's Birthday in different parts of the city and sponsored by the Chicago Lithuanian Council and the Association of Chicago Lithuanian Societies:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We, American citizens of Lithuanian descent, have assembled today to honor the anniversary of the birth of George Washington, the Father of this Country; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, When Lithuania fell in defense of its own freedom and the freedom of other little and weak nations, the Lithuanians found refuge on the hospitable shores of America; the great privilege of American citizenship was bestowed upon them, and freedom and equality have been enjoyed by all; now, therefore, be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, who also understand and believe in the justice of the aims for which George Washington fought, express our deepest respect and esteem for <pb facs="5423970_3_1135.jpg" n="2"/>the Father of our Country and for the men who so nobly sacrificed their lives and fortunes in defense of the American colonies; and be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, American citizens of Lithuanian descent, stand in all our entirety as an integral part of this nation behind the Government of the United States in the struggle against autocracy, and give our fullest support to the high ideals and objectives set forth by George Washington and so ably carried on by President Woodrow Wilson."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
