<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Protestants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN PROTESTANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As it was announced in Lietuva, on October 1st there was organized in Chicago the Evangelical Lithuanian Society. The purpose of this society is brotherly love and love for the fatherland, Lithuania. All Lithuanian Lutherans must unite in one strong organization of brotherly love; to help the unfortunate, to lead a moral life, to visit the sick, to take care of the orphans, to live in peace. When others see that we are leading moral and prudent lives, they join our society. This will be a Lithuanian society. All the society's affairs will be conducted in the Lithuanian language. Therefore all the Lithuanian Lutherans should belong to this society. The initiation fee is only $1.50. Members are accepted from 18 to 45 years of age. The monthly dues are 50 cents. The sick benefit is $5 per week and doctor services. When a member of the society dies, every member donates one dollar. The funeral is taken care of by the society. What is left after the expenses (are paid) is given to the family <pb facs="5423970_3_1708.jpg" n="2"/>of the deceased. We hope to see in other cities Lithuanian Lutherans organize such societies.</p>
   <p>It is time for the Evangelical Lithuanians to wake from their sleep, make efforts to enlighten themselves, read scientific books and good newspapers; not to forget our fatherland, Lithuania, nor our brothers who are suffering under the foreign yoke for trying to enlighten their ignorant brothers, and for uplifting the national spirit.</p>
   <p>Our brothers the Prussian Lithuanians, also Evangelists, are awakening; they do not want the Germans to lead them by the nose and began to work in the Lithuanian field. On November 25, one hundred Lithuanians held a meeting at Klaipeda (Memel), and decided to publish a new Lithuanian newspaper for the Prussian-Lithuanian Lutherans. The newspaper will be nationalistic Lithuanian; it will be the organ of the Lithuanian branch delegates to be sent to the German parliament, <pb facs="5423970_3_1709.jpg" n="3"/>where they will demand the establishment of schools for Lithuanian children, where they may learn how to read and write the Lithuanian language.</p>
   <p>Also, the bishops, pastors, and the preachers must be Lithuanians among the Lithuanian people in Prussian Lithuania. Besides the newspaper, the society will publish educational books for the Prussian Lithuanians in their own language. Publishing of the newspaper will start from the New Year. If anyone of the American Lithuanians would like to get more information about this newspaper, write to the Lithuanian Branch Society, Mr. D. Saunius, per Neukirch, Rokaiten, Ost Preussen.</p>
   <p>Pastor Keturakaitis announces that in nn, Conn., the Lithuanian Lutherans have a society like (the one) we have in Chicago. It would be very essential for those two societies to become closely acquainted and to have mutual relations. This would be very good for <pb facs="5423970_3_1710.jpg" n="4"/>both societies, even the number of their memberships is not large. By uniting the two societies, they could accomplish more and would stand on stronger foundation.</p>
   <p>Anyone who wants to learn more about this Lithuanian Protestant society, call or write to J. J. Razokas, 72 Liberty St., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
