<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 2,
<date when="1906-01-12">Jan. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Destroy the Work Started</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0941</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0941.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 2,
<date when="1906-01-12">Jan. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT DESTROY THE WORK STARTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America, branch 36, at its last meeting, unanimously decided to reply to the sponsors of the Zinycia (Temple) committee, which is trying to establish a Lithuanian colony.</p>
   <p>We see clearly that the committee of Zinycia does not know and does not understand the Lithuanian Alliance of America organization, which has existed for the last 21 years and already has decided to establish a Lithuanian colony and asylum for the orphans and for the old people; this project will finally be decided upon at the coming convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America.</p>
   <p>Why does the Zinycia committee not know this and does not support this project? Why split into two opposed parties? First we must support the project sponsored by the Lithuanian Alliance. It will obtain the desired results much sooner. Why organize new anthills when we have enough of <pb facs="5423970_3_0942.jpg" n="2"/>various societies and alliances? Let us join these societies and promote their aims.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the Zinycia committee does not understand the Lithuanian Alliance, the societies, and in general Lithuanian affairs; therefore the Zinycia came out like Philip from the hemp field. (This Lithuanian expression refers to one who sticks his nose into the affairs of others, but does not know anything about it.)</p>
   <p>Even though we have no Lithuanian colonies in America, we will be able to establish the same without interference from such little masters as the Zinycia committee, which consists of Lithuanians whom we have never met in Lithuanian public activity, and who never worked for the national affairs of Lithuanians. Therefore, we cannot recognize them as nationalists. They are better known to us as servants of the Poles for their past activities. We require nothing from the Poles; we have enough of their benefaction and leadership.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0943.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the Zinycia committee we can expect nothing more than American business, because on several occasions there were present at the Zinycia meetings agents of railroads and real estate firms, offering for sale land for colonies, even though the Zinycia advertised that it will buy a tract of land only when its membership will have increased to one thousand.</p>
   <p>Now then, it is our duty to announce to the public that the Lithuanians should not permit themselves to be misled by the servants of the Poles, who, with their shrewd schemes, are trying to trap us. Let us support the project started by the Lithuanian Alliance of America, which has set aside $1,000. Those who support this project should join the Lithuanian Alliance, and we have no doubt that in a short time the Lithuanian public will join this project, and the Lithuanians will be proud of their accomplishment.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America, Branch 36.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
