<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-06-07">June 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Opening of the Lithuanian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-06-07">June 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE OPENING OF THE LITHUANIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the efforts of the Chicago Lithuanian nationalistic societies and of several private individuals a twenty-one-acre plot of ground was purchased at the southwest border of Chicago, between Bethania and Willow Springs, on Kean Avenue, near Archer Avenue, with the purpose of establishing a Lithuanian national cemetery on this site.</p>
   <p>The formal opening of the aforementioned Lithuanian National Cemetery took place on Thursday, May 30. The following Chicago societies officially participated in the opening ceremonies with their banners:</p>
   <p>(1) Love of Lithuanians in America</p>
   <p>(2) D. L. K. Gediminas (of the Town of Lake)</p>
   <p>(3) Lovers of Truth</p>
   <p>(4) Lovers of the Motherland Number 1</p>
   <p>(5) Concord</p>
   <p>(6) Lithuanian Tailors' Club</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1550.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(7) Simanas Daukantas</p>
   <p>(8) Sons of Lithuania</p>
   <p>(9) Freedom</p>
   <p>(10) Blessed Lithuania</p>
   <p>(11) Lithuanian Social Club of Indiana Harbor</p>
   <p>(12) J. L. A. P. Club</p>
   <p>The program began at twelve o'clock with a speech by F. P. Bradchulis, president of the combined societies which founded the cemetery; Mr. Bradchulis made an appropriate opening address. Then the Lithuania Band, under the direction of K. J. Fillipavicius, played "Lithuania, Our Fatherland," and the Birute Chorus and the public sang. The second speaker, Lee Mathias, was a representative of the mayor. He expressed his gratitude to the Lithuanians for uniting and founding their own cemetery, in which any Lithuanian may be buried without restrictions or religious requirements. He stated that he knows that there are fifty thousand Lithuanians in Chicago who are good citizens....After his speech the Lithuania Band played "America". The Birute Chorus and the public sang.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1551.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. K. Jurgelionis. He affirmed that all nations and all faiths honor the dead and the place where they are buried. The listeners were, it was apparent, altogether satisfied with Mr. Jurgelionis' speech, for it was fundamental, appropriate for so solemn an occasion, and earnest without attacking anybody's personal convictions.</p>
   <p>Then the same band played the "Marseillaise," with the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance's Chorus, Chapter 81, singing the words. After this the public sang while the band played "God Is Our Savior and Strength," a hymn which is known throughout Lithuania. After the program the people walked about, inspecting the burial grounds. As far as could be ascertained, the visitors were all pleased with the place and boasted that the Lithuanians had selected a perfect site for their National Cemetery; it is full of trees, and most of them are oaks, six to eight inches in diameter...About six thousand people were present, possibly more....Donations for the benefit of the Cemetery totaled $226.46.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
