<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Catholic Priest with a Different Outlook</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A CATHOLIC PRIEST WITH A DIFFERENT OUTLOOK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From day to day we hear and see what our priests say and write about Socialism. They call it the most immoral and the most evil thing in the world. With threats of "mortal sin" and damnation they fervently urge all their faithful followers to beware of that "ism" and to avoid any contact with those who advocate it.</p>
   <p>But let our readers acquaint themselves with the opinion of Socialism expressed by an English priest, the Reverend Charles Russell, at the annual Catholic youth congress in Great Britain. He also is a servant of the Church of Rome, like our own priests, but he appears to be by quite a few degrees superior to them in intelligence.</p>
   <p>Here is an extract from an address of his:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"What is the fundamental cause of the present Socialistic movement? We must seek the answer to that question in the present deplorable and ghastly economic conditions of the masses. We all can see how, on the one hand, vast wealth is being steadily concentrated in the hands of the few, and how immorality and despotism are rapidly increasing among the wealthy class, while on the other hand we note among the masses a rapidly rising tide of poverty, misery, and unemployment. These serious abuses of the capitalist system created a great incentive for the origin and the development of the Socialist movement, since it became necessary for the masses to find a remedy for their ills. Although I do not believe for one moment that Socialism is a remedy for these abuses, nevertheless I am forced to admit that apart from Socialism no other remedy has been advanced.</p>
   <p>"Most of our Catholic priests and Catholic lay leaders attack Socialism as a most heinous thing and as something which cannot be supported or tolerated by any Catholic. They even go to the extreme of calling Socialist leaders fools <pb facs="5423970_3_1472.jpg" n="3"/>and swindlers. But I ask you: is such an attitude toward Socialism honest and wise?</p>
   <p>"Socialism is a well-known and recognized theory. It means the nationalization of industry. It stands for a social order in which goods shall be produced not for profit but for use only. The post office is an example of Socialist economy.</p>
   <p>"Furthermore, I wish to emphasize the point that we can easily become convinced that there is nothing in Socialism that is contrary to the principles of Christianity and of Catholicism.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, let us oppose and combat Socialism with intelligent weapons. Let us point out the errors and the impracticability of the Socialist theory; that it ultimately leads to the abolition of the spirit of initiative. We can succeed in combating Socialism only by the use of sound arguments. I strongly oppose <pb facs="5423970_3_1473.jpg" n="4"/>and protest against the use of religious thunder and lightning."</p>
   <p>Here is an enemy of Socialism, but he is very different from the kind that we meet in our daily life here in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
