<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-13">Aug. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Aim and Purpose of the Lithuanian Clerks' Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-13">Aug. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">AIM AND PURPOSE OF THE LITHUANIAN CLERKS' ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Lithuanian Clerks' Association was held on Aug. 4, at 3301 S. Morgan Street. It was attended by four women and thirteen men.</p>
   <p>One of the most important decisions made at the meeting was to affiliate the Association with the Association of Chicago Lithuanian Societies. Mr. F. Eismontas read an essay on the status of clerks in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The membership body of this Clerks' Association consists only of Lithuanian clerks, men and women, who are employed in stores and in offices. The purpose and most important aims of the association are: To unite all Lithuanian clerks; to promote their general welfare; and to find employment for idle members. Besides that, all members receive sick and death benefits.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Association strives to assist members in every possible way and for that reason every Lithuanian clerk in Chicago ought to join it. The chairman of the last meeting announced that there are six vacancies for Lithuanian women clerks. Those who are able to do this kind of work can easily obtain positions by becoming members of this Association. Only those who can write are eligible for membership.</p>
   <p>This Association was organized three years ago. It has thirty members at present--twelve women and eighteen men. The initiation fee is one dollar and twenty-five cents; dues are twenty-five cents per month. The sick benefits are five dollars per week; the death benefit is fifty dollars. Meetings are held on the first Wednesday of every month at 3301 S. Morgan Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0588.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Association was organized by the following Lithuanians: Mr. Bajorinas; Mr. Eismontas; Mr. Masiulis; and Mr. Martinkus. The present officers are: F. Radzivilas, president; J. Zakaras, financial secretary; S. Svolkina, recording secretary; A. Martinkus, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Another important aim of the Association is to promote the educational, economical and national uplift of our people.</p>
   <p>It is noteworthy that all the meetings of the Association are conducted in a very orderly fashion; every member acts in a polite and respectable manner. Such exemplary conduct is a rare thing among our people.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Lithuanian Clerks' Association is a big step forward in the life of Chicago Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
