<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Aurora Society Is Planning to Construct its Own Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE AURORA SOCIETY IS PLANNING TO CONSTRUCT ITS OWN BUILDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Notwithstanding the fact that the Chicago Lithuanian Society League is planning to build a hall for holding meetings, the Aurora Society decided to erect its own building which will be used only for educational purposes. The building which is being planned by the Aurora Society will have a large space for the library or reading room, a school room and a meeting place for Lithuanian students to discuss various educational subjects. This plan is highly approved of by P. V. Misheika, supervisor of the Aurora Society's affairs. He also made the statement that the Aurora Society has a better chance of having its own building much sooner and cheaper than the Chicago Lithuanian Society League's building. The committee of the Aurora Society made an estimate and decided to construct the building for $12,000. The people are in favor of this idea and promise to support it financially as much as possible.</p>
   <p>The committee has already been appointed and the plans have been prepared <pb facs="5423970_3_0747.jpg" n="2"/>for this work. We are all set. The only thing we need now is to start building it immediately without delaying our plans. If we have started something worthwhile we must go to the end and finish it. There is a very good reason why we must build the library and the school for adults. We cannot educate our own people without a school and library. Most of our people here are illiterate, and we must help them educate themselves and develop their desire for reading of good books. We must make every effort to inspire and encourage them to go to our school and prepare for a better future. We cannot help our people educationally if we have no school of our own. Our people cannot go to public schools for the reason that they don't understand the English language and the basic principles of English grammar. The public grammar schools are only for those who understand the basic principles of grammar of their own language. One cannot learn and will never know the English language well if he cannot grasp the principles of English grammar. In order to study and understand the English language well, one must study Lithuanian grammar first. Then the English grammar will be much easier to understand and no time will be wasted. For our people it is best to acquire an elementary education <pb facs="5423970_3_0748.jpg" n="3"/>in our own school before going to the public school. The foregoing statement proves why we need our own school and library. If we had our own school we could prepare our people much better for public school work and that would make it much easier to understand English. At our school we could explain to them the English grammar in the Lithuanian language, if they do not understand English.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian school and the library are indispensable to our people, especially in Chicago. We must have that type of school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
