<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day at the Lithuanian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY AT THE LITHUANIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About five thousand Lithuanians gathered at the Lithuanian National Cemetery on Decoration Day, May 30. A religious service was held at the Lithuanian National Cemetery and a sermon was delivered by Rev. B. Jankauskas of the Lithuanian National Church. After the religious service Mr. P. Grigaitis, editor of Naujienos, delivered a long speech and explained the meaning of Decoration Day and the purpose of celebrating it. In his speech he gave explanations to the people, who had gathered to commemorate Decoration Day, about the Lithuanian National Cemetery and for what purpose this cemetery was organized and established. The purpose of having a national cemetery is one way of freeing ourselves from the Roman Church and the Catholic priests, who were and still are discriminating against our people who don't attend services at the Catholic churches. The Lithuanian National Cemetery is for all our people, whether Catholic, Protestant, or Atheist; no one is discriminated against. In the second part of his speech, he mentioned that Decoration Day is the day for commemorating those who died <pb facs="5423970_3_1155.jpg" n="2"/>for freedom during the American Revolution and those who gave their lives recently for freedom in Colorado, Virginia, Lithuania, and elsewhere.</p>
   <p>Rev. B. Jankauskas in his sermon mentioned those who died fighting for freedom of humanity. He also criticized the Roman-Catholic priests for unfaithfulness and for selling themselves to the Irish bishops. He gave a short talk on the history of mankind and its struggle for freedom.</p>
   <p>The people have been fighting for freedom for two thousand years and they will keep on fighting for another two thousand years. This will be the longest battle in the history of mankind. The sacrifice for freedom is too great. Millions of people have died and a million more people will die fighting for the freedom of humanity. This war for freedom is endless and it is doubtful if it will ever end. Too many people in this cruel world have given their lives for the freedom of humanity. The future generations should always remember those who died for the freedom of the world. They fought for you and me and we must commemorate them on Decoration Day every year. They have done their duty for humanity.Now it is our duty to carry on the fight for the freedom of our future generations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1156.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Besides the sermon and speeches at the Lithuanian National Cemetery there was the young American Lithuanian National choir which sang "Nearer My God to Thee," "National Spirit," "Many of Our People Perished," the national anthem, and the Lithuanian anthem. The last on the program was a Lithuanian band that played five numbers and thus the program ended. Many societies participated in that celebration at the Lithuanian National Cemetery. The members of the societies were dressed in colorful uniforms while others were in their civilian clothes with badges pinned on their lapels. Attorney F. P.Brachulis conducted the program.</p>
   <p>M. M. Juodis, P. Pivarunas, and A. Blinstrupas were the committee who arranged the program.</p>
   <p>After the celebration the people went to Mr. Blinstrupas garden, where they spent the rest of the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
