<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-06">Nov. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Lovers of the Fatherland Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-06">Nov. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LOVERS OF THE FATHERLAND SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The summer months are gone, and now colder weather and shorter days are here; picnics and other summer recreational activities have ceased.</p>
   <p>The beautiful and happy months of summer always diminish indoor social and cultural activities; only a very small percentage of the members of our various societies and clubs attend meetings. Now that the summer season has passed our societies are manifesting greater activity. We all should take full advantage of the colder weather and longer evenings by reading newspapers and educational books, which are available in the libraries of a number of Lithuanian societies that are interested in the educational uplift of our people.</p>
   <p>Therefore, brother Lithuanians, let us become interested in our intellectual development; join a Lithuanian educational society and after a number of months we shall we greatly pleased with the fruit of our efforts.</p>
   <p>One of the outstanding Lithuanian societies in Chicago is the Lovers of the <pb facs="5423970_3_0869.jpg" n="2"/>Fatherland Society. The sole purpose of this society is to promote the intellectual development of our people. Membership dues are only sixty cents per year. The society does not assist the members in sickness or at death; instead, it provides mental nourishment to the healthy, living body. That is, it publishes the literary works of our greatest writers and distributes them without charge to all members, and to Lithuanians who cannot afford to pay for them.</p>
   <p>The society is growing very fast in Chicago. It has three lodges here with about one hundred member each. The 22nd lodge of the society holds regular monthly meetings on the second Sunday of each month at the Ruigis hall, 3301 So. Morgan St. The next meeting will be held on Sunday, November 8. It is very important for all members to be present at this meeting, because the latest publication of the society, a Lithuanian text book on the subject of mathematics, will be distributed to all members in good standing. Any Lithuanian can learn mathematics from this book without the aid of a teacher.</p>
   <p>By Peter Zemaitis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
