<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-03-05">Mar. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lecture to Americans about Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-03-05">Mar. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LECTURE TO AMERICANS ABOUT LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Kleofas Jurgelonis delivered a lecture on Lithuanian history, literature and folklore on March 1 at the residence of Mrs. Charles Hitchcock, 4741 Greenwood Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. The audience was composed entirely of wealthy and highly educated Americans. Mr. Jurgelonis spoke on the history of the Lithuanian people in a very beautiful manner, and pointed out many interesting aspects of the Lithuanian language and folklore. Members of the audience appeared to be surprised to learn of the richness of Lithuanian folklore, and of the fact that the Lithuanian language is a highly developed and very ancient language.</p>
   <p>After the lecture Mrs. Janusauskas sang two beautiful Lithuanian songs. Mr. Janusauskas accompanied her on the piano. The audience was also entertained with a number of Lithuanian national dances by a group of young Lithuanians under the direction of Mrs. M. Damijonaitis. All members of the group were <pb facs="5423970_3_0094.jpg" n="2"/>attired in Lithuanian national costumes. The group was composed of Mrs. M. Damijonaitis, Mrs. R. Slikas, Misses S. Urbis, A. Urbis, S. Staniulis, and A. Zemaitis, and the two little Micevicius sisters (Julia, eight years old, and Wanda, four years old). The audience appeared to be especially thrilled by the Micevicius sisters, who danced very well.</p>
   <p>Refreshments were served at the conclusion of the program. About 140 guests attended. The admission was one dollar. Proceeds from the affair will be donated for the upkeep of the kindergarten at the Fellowship Settlement House, which is active among the Lithuanians of the Bridgeport colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
