<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-04-19">Apr. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The People Are Laughing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-04-19">Apr. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE ARE LAUGHING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After Reverend Maliauskas' evening of execration against the Naujienos in a Chicago Lithuanian church, we have been anxious to learn the present attitude of the people toward our newspaper. We asked our distributor, and he said that "the people are laughing at the priest's denunciation; they are still buying the Naujienos and intend to keep on doing so even if they have to go to hell for it. A record number of copies of the Naujienos were sold on the morning after Reverend Maliauskas' execration!" This is the answer of thinking people to the dizzy priest's fanatical outburst. And this answer hurts that little fanatic more than we at first expected.</p>
   <p>In yesterday's issue we voiced the opinion that the outburst of Reverend Maliauskas would not stop the people from reading working-class newspapers. However, we expected that the people would at least feel somewhat guilty <pb facs="5423970_3_1439.jpg" n="2"/>and to a certain extent stop buying the Naujienos for the sake of the salvation of their souls. But it turned out to be the other way; the people are not only paying no attention to the fool Maliauskas' denunciation leveled against working-class newspapers, but are even laughing at him!</p>
   <p>The people do not intend to worry about the terrors of hell which that apostle of darkness is painting for them as a penalty for reading working-class newspapers. He is execrating against the Naujienos and is tearing himself apart in doing so, but the people only laugh at him. This laughing of the people is an appropriate funeral march for the idiotic ghost of Clericalism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
