<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-12">Dec. 12. 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Delegates of the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0749</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0749.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-12">Dec. 12. 1913</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE DELEGATES OF THE CHICAGO LITHUANIAN SOCIETIES ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the delegates of the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association was held last Friday evening at Aurora Hall, Bridgeport. Fifteen delegates were present at this meeting. The secretary, Mr. M. Duda, did not come, and so Mr. P. Butkus was elected temporary secretary in his place. The chairman of the meeting was Mr. K. Gugis.</p>
   <p>The final report of the recently-resigned general secretary, Mr. J. J. Hertmanavicius, was read. His report gave the reasons why the Association had done nothing during this entire year. He said that there was no "steam" in this organization, that the organization had no leader capable of producing the "steam" that would have given it life. But he believes that the organization will in time elect better leaders, who will place it on the <pb facs="5423970_3_0750.jpg" n="2"/>right road to success. This was the report of the general secretary, Mr. Hertmanavicius, who has already gone to Lithuania.</p>
   <p>All the committees admitted that they had held no meetings, and for this reason had accomplished nothing. The financial secretary reported that the Association had $72.36 in its treasury. Then for about thirty minutes, the Association's president, Mr. J. J. Elias, made a short talk. His speech was the same thing over and over: that the Association had two presidents, too many committees, the general secretary's wife was sick, the weather was too warm, and for these reasons nothing could be accomplished.</p>
   <p>Some of the more important decisions were: Mrs. M. Jurgelionis reported that the Immigrants' Protective League is supporting many Lithuanians who are unemployed and have no means of support; it was decided to donate fifteen dollars from the Association's budget to this League. The Association also decided to write a resolution of protest against the Dillingham-Burnett Bill, <pb facs="5423970_3_0751.jpg" n="3"/>which is already in Congress, and to mail this protest to every Congressman from Illinois. Finally, it was decided to hold the second convention on January 18, 1914, at Aurora Hall. All other decisions and suggestions were deferred to the coming convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
