<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-06-10">June 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Celebration of the Twenty-Fifth Jubilee Convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-06-10">June 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE CELEBRATION OF THE TWENTY-FIFTH JUBILEE CONVENTION OF THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebration of the twenty-fifth jubilee convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America was, it can be said without error, the largest not only in the history of the Lithuanian Alliance, not only the largest in the history of the Lithuanian-Americans, but also the largest in recent Lithuanian history. It showed that we Lithuanians do not lag far behind other nationalities, especially in our concord and unity.</p>
   <p>Almost thirty different societies participated in the parade, comprising from three to four thousand people. Eight bands and four decorated floats were also in the parade, the floats being those of the Birute Society, the Women's Enlightenment Society, the Lithuanian Youth Circle and the Lithuanian merchants. There were also about twenty automobiles and seventy carriages.</p>
   <p>The parade began about 3:00 P.M., June 5, 1910. The weather was very appropriate and therefore everything went well. The parade entered the hall before 4:00 P.M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1330.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Though the hall is vast, with a capacity of six thousand, not all of those assembled could get into it. The hall is located on the most famous of Chicago's streets, Michigan Boulevard, at Sixteenth Street and is called the First Infantry Armory.....</p>
   <p>The program for the jubilee and the stage presentations comprised forty pages and was larger than we had ever seen before.....</p>
   <p>After the parade had entered the hall M. Damijonaitis, chairman of the arrangements committee, called forth the officers of the various organizations and entrusted the chairmanship of the evening to Attorney F. P. Braciulis. The band played the Lithuanian National Anthem, the instrumentation of which was arranged by Mr. M. Petrauskas.....</p>
   <p>In the evening, after the celebration, the first evening affair of the convention was held at the Columbus Theater. The melodramatic opera, "Birute" and the opera, <pb facs="5423970_3_1331.jpg" n="3"/>"Harvest Time", were presented..... The orchestra of fourteen persons was good and was conducted by Mr. M. Petrauskas.</p>
   <p>The singers and actors in the operas were: "Birute", M. Horodeckaite; her father, B. Vaitiekunas; her brothers, K. Kasputis and M. Duda; "Keistutis", V. Vitkevicia; an old priest, a. Zacharevicia; a young lad, A. Bagdanavicia; "Zundestein", K. Strumskis; Knights, K. Raulinaitis and P. Stogis; "Xilli", A. Linkus; "Klaus", J. Buragas; "Lizdeika," J. Juska; "Krive", J. Ilgaudas, and various priestesses and soldiers.</p>
   <p>The following participated in "Harvest Time": "Masiulis", K. Kasputis; "Aldona", M. Jaksevicaite; "Gotautas", V. Brusokas; "Juskus", F. Zachareviciene; a girl, M. Horodeckiute.</p>
   <p>This evening and the artists who participated deserve a place in Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_3_1332.jpg" n="4"/>history. On this occasion, for the first time, the earliest Lithuanian musical works--the first operas in our language, were well-presented. They are the original works of our foremost composer and the originator of our classical music, M. Petrauskas. This was a noteworthy and important moment for our future culture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
