<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians Hold Big Meeting for "Lithuanian Day"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS HOLD BIG MEETING FOR "LITHUANIAN DAY"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On September 13, at St. George's parish hall, about five hundred Chicago Lithuanians met to discuss plans for the coming "Lithuanian Day" (Tag Day) on November 1, 1916. The meeting was called by the editorial staffs of the following Chicago Lithuanian newspapers: Draugas (The Friend), Katalikas (The Catholic), Lietuva (Lithuanian), and Savaitinis Draugas (The Weekly Friend).</p>
   <p>Among those who attended the meeting were delegates from the fourteen united societies of the West Side; delegates from the twenty-five societies that belong to the Association of Chicago Lithuanian Societies; delegates from various parish societies; prominent Chicago Lithuanian leaders; and other individuals who are interested in helping to make the "Lithuanian Day" a great success.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order in the name of the Chicago Lithuanian newspapers by Mr. Bruno K. Balutis, the editor of the Lietuva. He invited <pb facs="5423970_3_0206.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Zaldokas and Dr. A. J. Zimontas to act as chairmen, and Mr. Vitkus and Mr. Giraitis as secretaries.</p>
   <p>Then two orations were delivered; one by Reverend Maliauskas, and the other by B. K. Balutis. They explained the great significance of the "Lithuanian Day". Mr. Balutis reported that two Chicago Lithuanian factions, the Nationalists and the Catholics, have agreed to work in unity for that day. He also stated that a strong effort was made to persuade the other Chicago Lithuanian faction, the Socialists, to join this united front, but without success. He said that no agreement was reached with the Socialists because they demanded more privileges than other factions. Therefore, the Socialists have declined to work in unity with the other factions, at least for the time being.</p>
   <p>Another oration was delivered by Attorney F. P. Bradchulis. He criticized the Socialists for holding partisanship above everything else, and stated that for such a humanitarian cause, as the relief of our war-stricken brothers and sisters, we should forget our partisan differences, forget that we are Socialists, <pb facs="5423970_3_0207.jpg" n="3"/>Nationalists, or Catholics, and remember that we are all Lithuanians. All those who are interested in dividing our forces into partisan factions for such an important cause are not worthy of the name of Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>It was decided at the meeting to elect a Central Chicago Committee, composed of an equal number of members from the Nationalist and Catholic factions. This Committee is to make all necessary plans and arrangements for, and conduct all the affairs of, the "Lithuanian Day" in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The following were elected to the Central Chicago Committee: Reverend F. B. Serafinas, chairman; Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, vice-chairman; Engineer Zaldokas, second vice-chairman; Mr. J. Giraitis, recording secretary; Mr. P. Mulevicius, financial secretary; Dr. A. J. Zimontas, treasurer; Attorney B. K. Balutis and Mr. Paul Baltutis, trustees.</p>
   <p>Besides the above-mentioned officers of the Central Chicago Committee, five advisors from each Chicago Lithuanian colony were elected to the Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0208.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Advisors were elected from Bridgeport, the West Side, Town of Lake, 18th Street, Roseland, etc.</p>
   <p>It is interesting to note that there were delegates at the meeting not only from the Chicago suburbs, but also from Waukegan, Illinois. The latter expressed a desire to work jointly with Chicago Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>The entire meeting was conducted in an orderly and exemplory manner. The delegates appeared to be greatly pleased that Chicago Lithuanians have agreed to work in unity for such a great humanitarian cause.</p>
   <p>The Central Chicago Committee has already held two meetings. Contact has already been made with the Central Lithuanian-American Committee, which was recently formed at the Lithuanian-American Congress at Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania. The officers of the Committee are now very active; they plan to call a meeting shortly of all members of the Committee to make definite plans for <pb facs="5423970_3_0209.jpg" n="5"/>the "Lithuanian Day" in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is planned to have at least two thousand solicitors on the streets of Chicago during the "Lithuanian Day". Although the day is still far away, more than two hundred Chicago Lithuanian women and girls have already offered their services to solicit funds on the street corners of Chicago on "Lithuanian Day". That is a very good sign, showing that the day will be a great success.</p>
   <p>All girls who are willing to act as solicitors on the "Lithuanian Day" (November 1, 1916) are requested to send their names and addresses to one of the two secretaries of the Committee: J. Giraitis, 7941 South May Street, or P. Mulevicius, 1800 West 46th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
