<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 46,
<date when="1903-11-13">November 13, 1903</date><title level="a">Donation to the Aurora Fund</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0976</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0976.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 46,
<date when="1903-11-13">November 13, 1903</date><title level="a">DONATION TO THE AURORA FUND</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the first day of November, several Lithuanians got together at Mr. Joseph Valenta's house, decided to make collections for national affairs, and collected $1.32. The money was divided as follows: seventy cents to the Martyr's Fond, and sixty-two cents to the Aurora Fund, which is to help the young Lithuanian students. We believe that the Lithuanian students, after graduation, will work in the national field, and will repay for this help. In Chicago there are many Lithuanian girls who have no organization among themselves. There are a few Lithuanian girls who are thinking about their education. For this purpose they are attending the churches on Sundays, expecting to find education there, but they cannot find it, because the teachers of the church are themselves without education. They cannot, therefore, aid in the education of the masses. The uneducated masses are exploited by those who should help them.</p>
   <p>As was mentioned in Lietuva, in the Freiheit Turner Hall, there was presented a Lithuanian theatre performance. The public was satisfied with the spectacle, <pb facs="5423970_3_0977.jpg" n="2"/>but the local priest denounced the people, telling them that if they went to this Lithuanian theatre he would give them no absolution. Now, when the people heard of this theatre performance - that there was nothing in it against religion, God or priest, they were sorry they listened to the priest's lie. The priest likes it better when the people go to saloons, get drunk, then fight, instead of going to the theatre where they learn something.</p>
   <p>Barzdinelis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
