<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1906-02-23">Feb. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Rev. Steponavicia Did Not Get Scared</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1906-02-23">Feb. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">REV. STEPONAVICIA DID NOT GET SCARED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the parishioners broke the windows of the rectory last Sunday, everybody said that on the coming Sunday the Rev. Steponavicia would be afraid to come to church. But the priest was not scared. He replaced all the broken windows, all the suspected persons were arrested by the police, and on Sunday the priest brought a large number of policemen and detective and did business in church as usual. The priest's collectors collected the money in the church; the parish collectors did not collect because the bishop got an injunction against them. We are told that the priest's collectors made a very small collection because very few people gave money to them.</p>
   <p>When the priest had celebrated the Mass, had crossed himself, and started to preach the sermon, someone at the door blew a whistle. The people were scared and thinking there would be another fight, started to run outside. The priest also got scared and ran out from the church. The church was emptied and no sermon was preached.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On Tuesday, at the police court, after questioning the people who were arrested during the fight in church on the previous Sunday, thirteen were indicated for criminal offenses and sent to the grand jury. The bond is set at $500 for each offender. The following people were sent to (face) a grand jury: Catherine Macinskiene, Paul Bagvilonis, Anton Peciukaitis, and his wife, Peciukaitiene; John Martinaitis; Peter Vencius, Nikolas Blazis; Joseph Markunas; Aleksander Dargis, and Mary Braziene.</p>
   <p>The names of others were omitted. The grand jury will meet some day in March and the accused will be called for questioning. If the police are able to prove their guilt, they will be investigated by the court. If the police are not able to prove anything, the accused persons will be freed by the grand jury. Besides the thirteen accused, there are twenty people whom the police charge with disorderly conduct and disturbing the church meeting. The cases of less important offenders will be heard at the police station on March 2, at 9:30 A. M., 1906.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
