<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 13,
<date when="1906-03-30">March 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">We Are Complying with the Zvaigzde's Request</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 13,
<date when="1906-03-30">March 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">WE ARE COMPLYING WITH THE ZVAIGZDE'S REQUEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The clerical newspaper Zvaigzde (The Star) published a certain circular and requested other newspapers to reprint it. Therefore we are complying with the Zvaigzde's request and are publishing the circular in full. Here it is:</p>
   <p>"Warning to the Chicago societies! During the coming month of May, on its 28, 29, and 30th days, there will be held in Chicago a convention of a non-Catholic Lithuanian Alliance of America. As a rule such conventions are attended by Lithuanians of liberal views. When they are discussing the organization's problems, they shamelessly attack the Lithuanian clergy, denounce the churches and make fun of the dogma of the Holy Trinity. We, the undersigned, are warning all Chicago Lithuanian church societies not to take part in the parade nor in the convention sessions. Such participation will injure the heart of every Lithuanian Catholic and will bring schism among the Catholics. Let Lithuanian Catholic societies and branches <pb facs="5423970_3_1370.jpg" n="2"/>remain unpolluted in their hearts.</p>
   <p>(Signed)</p>
   <p>Rev. M. Krawczunas</p>
   <p>" N. J. Lukosius</p>
   <p>" A. Skrypka</p>
   <p>" A. Petraitis</p>
   <p>" A. Steponavicia</p>
   <p>" A. Ambrozaitis."</p>
   <p>Editor's note: It seems that the clergy are uneasy when the people do not scold them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1371.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now the priests are scolding their faithful sheep, the parishioners. The Lithuanian Alliance of America forgot the priests entirely as though they do not exist at all. Now the clergy are trying to stir up the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The priests are uneasy when an important organization , like the Lithuanian Alliance of America, says nothing about them.</p>
   <p>The clergy in the circular states that this convention will be held by a non-Catholic alliance, and the good Catholics must not go to this convention, in order "not to pollute their hearts." According to this expression of the clergy, we have the following conception: those who are not too lazy to break the windows of the rectories and of the churches are good Catholics, while those who don't take part in breaking the windows, are not Catholics. It seems to us that it is too late to warn the people about "Catholicism" and "non-Catholicism," because everybody <pb facs="5423970_3_1372.jpg" n="4"/>knows that the clergy's Catholicism is based on the dollar. Where there is no dollar, Catholicism to the clergy is unnecessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
