<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-17">May 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Standing of the Lithuanian Socialists in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-17">May 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">STANDING OF THE LITHUANIAN SOCIALISTS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanian Socialist movement in Chicago is not young--it has been in existence for ten or fifteen years.</p>
   <p>Chicago Lithuanian Socialists are organized into several branches. At present there are seven Lithuanian Socialist branches in Chicago and surrounding territory. The oldest Lithuanian Socialist branches in Chicago are the Fourth, Twenty-second, Thirty-seventh, and Eighty-first. The total membership of all the Chicago branches is approximately two hundred at the present time. By dividing that figure by seven we find that each branch has an average of twenty-eight members. Therefore, it is evident that our forces in Chicago are very weak. Nevertheless, we expend much energy, time, and wealth in our activities. Each branch holds from twelve to fifteen meetings every year. Therefore, <pb facs="5423970_3_0721.jpg" n="2"/>all the branches in Chicago hold a total of about 105 meetings per year. That is unusual activity. However, since only "technical" matters are discussed at these meetings, very little is accomplished, and as a result our membership list is growing very slowly.</p>
   <p>One reason why we are making such slow progress is because we hold our meetings in saloon halls for the most part, and also because our meetings are conducted in a very dull manner. We have many branches in Chicago but no central organization that would make it possible for members of different branches to become acquainted and learn from each other. The lack of such a central organization is also the reason why our influence upon the Chicago Lithuanian public is practically nil.</p>
   <p>We Chicago Lithuanian Socialists should have become organized into a central organization a long time ago. If we were so organized then we would not now be hindered by a lack of good trained workers--agitators; we would not have to <pb facs="5423970_3_0722.jpg" n="3"/>hold our meetings in saloon halls as we would have a hall of our own by now; and we would also be able to establish a Socialist school, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
