<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 10,
<date when="1901-03-08">March 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Alliance Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1014</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1014.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 10,
<date when="1901-03-08">March 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago Mr. Businessman wrote that it is necessary for us to organize a national Lithuanian alliance, because the present Lithuanian alliance does not answer the purpose. The present alliance is under the control of the clergy. They disregard the members, making all kinds of schemes to expel the most active members. The members of the present organizations have no rights, because the clergy are the officials. They have in their claws the destiny of the organizations; inch by inch the clergy are have squeezing out the active and prudent members of the organization.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance now is neither national nor religious, but the tool of the clergy. Later on the clergy will take absolute control. The members will have no rights; the members will only have to pay their dues and obey the orders of the priests. Therefore, we must organize <pb facs="5423970_3_1015.jpg" n="2"/>a new national alliance, and it should be under the civil intelligentsia control. There are many Lithuanians in America. We have enough people for a better and stronger organization, all we need is action. We have a large field for such an organization, because the Lithuanians in America are beginning to realize that they are people with human rights, not the slaves of the clergy. I have no doubt that this new Lithuanian alliance in America, in a few years, will be stronger, larger and will make more progress than the present alliance has made during the past fourteen years.</p>
   <p>J. Suiszergis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
