<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">Feb. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Lithuanian Society Again Active]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">Feb. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[LITHUANIAN SOCIETY AGAIN ACTIVE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After wearing the crown of honor because of its great activity for some time, Chapter 22 of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society, on the West Side, seemed to relax its efforts recently. Now, after a little rest, it is apparent that Chapter 22 is going to become active again, so that the Lithuanians of other colonies will find themselves with some real competition on their hands.</p>
   <p>Soon after the new year started the chapter sponsored a beautiful affair which realized a profit. Besides this, forty-five dollars in donations for Lithuania's independence were collected.</p>
   <p>At the meeting on February 14, it was decided to do the following: to sponsor an affair with speeches and a program during Lent; to purchase about fifteen dollars worth of books published by the Society. These books will <pb facs="5423970_3_0693.jpg" n="2"/>be given away to those new members who join the chapter during the proposed affair.</p>
   <p>Further, the chapter will celebrate its tenth anniversary in October.</p>
   <p>Concerning the matter of publishing the works of J. Sernas, the chapter elected a committee of three members, B. Lenkauskas, M. Juska, and Miss Ona Petkevicius, which will strive to gain the support of other societies in this matter. In the meantime, the chapter has donated twenty-five dollars for this purpose.</p>
   <p>The chapter once had a membership of 200, but now has only 166. This indicates that many of our youths have gone off to the war. It is sad, but not discouraging. Enough Lithuanians remain to double the present membership of the chapter. Older people, also, some of whom pay their dues ten years <pb facs="5423970_3_0694.jpg" n="3"/>in advance, are now joining Chapter 22.</p>
   <p>If Chapter 22 fulfills its program for the year it will have made a great step forward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
