<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-13">Nov. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"Abejotina Ypata" Successfully Staged by Birute Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0865</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0865.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-13">Nov. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"ABEJOTINA YPATA" SUCCESSFULLY STAGED BY BIRUTE SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Birute Music and Dramatic Society successfully presented "Abejotina Ypata" (The Mysterious Person), a two - act comedy, last Sunday evening, at School Hall, 48th and Honore Streets, in the Town of Lake colony. More than 300 Lithuanians witnessed the performance.</p>
   <p>This was the first time the comedy was presented before a Chicago audience. The plot of the play revolves around an illicit love affair; an ardent admirer makes an unsuccessful and embarrassing attempt to win the love of a married woman. It is a very exhilarating comedy and made the audience roar with laughter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0866.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the play the program consisted of a number of Lithuanian songs, executed by the Birute Chorus, under the direction of E. Strumskis, worthy successor of Mikas Petrauskas, who recently left Chicago for Lithuania. The most successful song numbers were: "Oi Motule Maho" (Mother O' Mine); "Sejau Ruta" (I Sowed a Rue); "Motus, Motuse" (Mother, Dear Mother); "Zilvitis" (Little Willow Tree); "Saulele Raudona" (The Precious Red Sun); and "Oi Tu Jieva" (Oh You Eve!). It is very gratifying to note that these songs, which Petrauskas taught the chorus, are still being enthusiastically received by our people. Many encores were requested by the audience.</p>
   <p>It is evident that the gracious personality of Mikas Petrauskas, the founder of the Birute Music and Dramatic Society, is missed by his former pupils and Lithuanian audiences at our music and dramatic functions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0867.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We hope that he will return to Chicago in the near future. Although he is in Lithuania he has not forgotten the Birute Society; he sent two new songs to the society and expressed the hope that the society will continue to flourish under the leadership of Mr. E. Strumskis.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the dramatic and musical program the floor was cleared for dancing, which was enjoyed for several hours. Lithuanian national dances, such as the "Suktinis" (A twirling dance) and "Klumpakojis" (wooden shoe dance) predominated.</p>
   <p>After Christmas the Birute Society plans to arrange several more dramatic presentations, music, and dance programs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
