<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-11-13">Nov. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Cicero Lithuanians Act</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-11-13">Nov. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CICERO LITHUANIANS ACT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of delegates from Cicero Lithuanian societies was held on November 10. The purpose of the meeting was to arrange for the collections of donations for war sufferers and to consider general matters concerning aid to Lithuania. At the meeting, attended by twenty people, it was decided to unite all of the societies for this purpose. The combined societies will be called "The League of Cicero Lithuanian Societies".</p>
   <p>The following societies were represented at the meeting: 1) The Lovers of Lithuania Society; 2) The Strength of Lithuania Society; 3) The Soldiers of Lithuania Society; 4) The Lithuanian Alliance of America, Lodge 194; 5) The Lithuanian Sisters and Brothers Society; 6) The Enlightenment Society; 7) The Women's National Society; 8) The White Rose Club; 9) The Home Owners' Improvement Club; and 10) The Republican Club. The <pb facs="5423970_3_0370.jpg" n="2"/>following were elected officers of the newly created League: M. Gabraitis, president; Anthony Liutkus and Mrs. B. Jonaitis, vice-presidents; F. Strielciunas, recording secretary; J. Praksalis, assistant recording secretary; Mrs. Anna Junkaitis, financial secretary; J. Bigentas, treasurer. Twelve collectors of contributions were also elected. A suggestion was made at this meeting to hold an affair, the entire purpose of which would be to collect donations to aid Lithuania. The Socialist delegate asked to be excused because the meeting was being conducted in a manner contrary to his wishes.</p>
   <p>Donation collections were started at the end of the meeting. The following donated to the Lithuanian Assistance Fund: M. Bartkus, forty-five cents; and M. Gabraitis, fifty cents. (M. Gabraitis also donated fifty cents to the Lithuanian Autonomy Fund.)</p>
   <p>The following donated to the Lithuanian Autonomy Fund: P. Stankaitis, <pb facs="5423970_3_0371.jpg" n="3"/>Mrs. M. Puskis, Mrs. B. Jonaitis and F. Strielciunas, one dollar each; M. A. Sarka, sixty cents; M. Gabraitis (mentioned above), fifty cents; and Mrs. Anna Junkaitis, twenty cents.</p>
   <p>F. Strielciunas, A. Liutkus and M. A. Sarka were elected correspondents. The Lietuva was designated as the official organ of the League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
