<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-22">Aug. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Struggle between Parishioners and the Right Reverend Steponavicius</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-08-22">Aug. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRUGGLE BETWEEN PARISHIONERS AND THE RIGHT REVEREND STEPONAVICIUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 18th Street and Union Avenue Lithuanian community is very well known among Chicago Lithuanians because from time to time a disagreement comes up between the Providence of God parishioners and their parish priest, Steponavicius. Furthermore, this summer's "revolt" of the parishioners against their priest is now reaching abnormal proportions. The parishioners are not satisfied with the conduct of their priest, and the relationship between them for the past several years has not shown a healthy condition. It came to such a point that the co-operation between them was completely broken off.</p>
   <p>The disagreement, as always, started between the parish committee and the Reverend Steponavicius, and now has spread through the entire parish. The committee has accused the priest of not giving an accounting of the parish budget at parish meetings. They accuse the priest of squandering the parish <pb facs="5423970_3_1537.jpg" n="2"/>money for his personal affairs. At these meetings, which are held every so often, they are demanding no more nor less than that the Reverend Steponavicius should resign from this parish.</p>
   <p>So far as we can learn from the "riotous" parishioners, they are very closely bound to Reverend Satkus, who was here as assistant to Reverend Steponavicius, and who was moved to Sioux City, Iowa, as the result of the intrigues of the Reverend Steponavicius. Such is the statement of the dissatisfied parishioners. The supporters of Reverend Steponavicius claim that Reverend Satkus wanted to take the place of Reverend Steponavicius, and for this reason, Reverend Satkus entered into various conspiracies and intrigues against Reverend Steponavicius. No matter how it happened, when Reverend Satkus left, the "riot" of the parishioners became sharper because the followers of Reverend Satkus claim that the parish priest not only moved him (Satkus) out of this parish, but also presented Reverend Satkus to the Archbishop as an undesirable person and a priest whose conduct was questionable. The starting point of this storm came when the Reverend Steponavicius, disagreeing with the old parish committee, dismissed the members who were against <pb facs="5423970_3_1538.jpg" n="3"/>him, and in their place appointed his partisans. The parish committee applied to the Archbishop, although up to the present time they have received no answer.</p>
   <p>The dissatisfied parishioners, who stand by Reverend Satkus have adopted strong resolutions at their meetings against their rector, Reverend Steponavicius, declaring that they "have had enough of his administration." They demand his resignation, believing that they will get in his place a "better leader, with Lithuanian energy."</p>
   <p>"We, for our part," concludes the committee, "will do everything that we can. We will support and join in the plans of a good priest, in order to bring to an end this local struggle." To this declaration are signed the names of : John Kastenas, 670 West 18th Street, Frank Bacevicia, 544 Liberty Street, Andriejus Bruozis, 671 West 18th Street, Juozapas Tverijonas, 1836 South Halsted Street, and Petras Zickus, 1714 South Union Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
