<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-23">Oct. 23, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Educational Society to Resume Evening School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0879</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0879.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-23">Oct. 23, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY TO RESUME EVENING SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Men have been marching forward in the field of intellectual development for a long time and so successfully that they left the women very far behind. In the past, women looked upon the intellectual advancement of men with indifference. However, the women of today have become very enthusiastic over the desire for intellectual development and equality. Lithuanian women are also marching forward. The Lithuanian Women's Educational Society of Chicago has been organized to promote the intellectual development and advancement of Lithuanian womanhood.</p>
   <p>At the first organizational meeting of the society one of the organizers said: "Let the intellectual development of our women always remain the <pb facs="5423970_3_0880.jpg" n="2"/>main and real purpose of the society."</p>
   <p>We have been following the inspired words of the organizer. The society conducts an evening school every winter for Lithuanian girls and women. This year the society is making plans to resume the classes and continue them during the cold months. One of our most distinguished members, Miss T. Andrius, has agreed to conduct the evening classes of instruction this year. The most important elementary subjects, such as reading, writing and arithmetic, will be taught. Classes in cooking and handiwork, such as sewing, knitting, and bead stringing, will also be held. Miss Andrius is a master of the art of cooking; she will teach our young Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_3_0881.jpg" n="3"/>girls and women how to prepare appetizing and healthy meals. Other subjects of instruction will be added upon request.</p>
   <p>This evening school will be opened only to members of the society. Mothers who have daughters, ranging in ages from thirteen to sixteen, may enroll them in the school without charge. It is not necessary for their children to be members in order for them to attend classes. As a means of encouragement, all valuable pieces of handiwork that are turned out by advanced students of the school, will be raffled off by the society for the benefit of the student.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0882.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Therefore, Lithuanian women and girls of Chicago, do not allow this great opportunity to slip by, join the Women's Educational Society and become active members. The initiation fee is fifty cents for women and girls between the ages of sixteen and thirty; for women from thirty to forty the initiation fee is one dollar. The dues for all members are twenty-five cents per month.</p>
   <p>The evening school is open to all members without charge. Furthermore, this is a mutual aid society. Sick members receive three dollars per week; the death benefit is twenty-five dollars.</p>
   <p>All Lithuanian girls, women and their young daughters are invited to attend the next meeting of the society, which will be held on Sunday afternoon, Nov. 1, at 869 W. 35rd Place.</p>
   <p>By Mrs. M. Saskas, sec.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
