<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 46,
<date when="1898-11-18">Nov. 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to the Rytas</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Morning)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1780</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1780.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 46,
<date when="1898-11-18">Nov. 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THE RYTAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(THE MORNING)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On our article, "Where to Sue the Priest," the newspaper Rytas answered as follows:</p>
   <p>"The canon of the church states that it is known and it cannot be private opinion that nobody has the right to strike at the pastor of a church, the right rests in the church itself, to whom God gave the power to rule in all spiritual affairs. In civil affairs the church has as much right, insofar as the civilian law annexes the spiritual law. In other words, how much civil power is necessary to uphold the order and peace among the ecclesiastics? Therefore, if the pope made the law that the priest cannot be sued in the civil court, then only the pope himself can revoke it.</p>
   <p>We are still upholding our old idea that church rule terminates where dogmatic affairs terminate; otherwise the church would have in its power complete control of the people, and the clergy would take not only the rights of the private people, but also the rights of all the nations to suit demands of the church. That some of the clergy are incompetent has been <pb facs="5423970_3_1781.jpg" n="2"/>proven many times by Rytas itself,(as to the incompetency of the priest.) Such a power as Rytas indicates would be a weapon of the improper church leaders, and it would protect them from responsibility for their wrongful deeds, to the public. The wrongdoing of one priest lowers the standing of the good priests and the church itself. We can see that in America today.</p>
   <p>Let us take the situation of our Lithuanian parish in Chicago; not the personal struggle with the Rev. Krawczunas, but the condition of the Parish which is best known to us. About the deficit of many thousand dollars in the parish budget under the control of Rev. Krawczunas, we have written before. Besides that, the rector had wasted thousands of dollars donated by Lithuanians to the church, but our priest with the Lithuanian money is Polanizing our children. In a Lithuanian school they are prohibited from speaking Lithuanian. Our children are forced to speak Polish. If our children refuse to speak Polish, they are expelled from the school. Such conduct of our priest not only humiliates the parishioners, but all the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>We do not care to go into the teachings of the church, but as the parishioners hear nothing good in the church, but slander and denunciation instead of good and moral Christian instruction, then we cannot keep quiet. If such sermon were <pb facs="5423970_3_1782.jpg" n="3"/>to be preached in the English, or in the French churches, such spiritual leaders would be thrown out by the people at once.</p>
   <p>We are asking Rytas when the parish money was wasted by the priests for his personal gains, and the Lithuanians money used for Polanization of the Lithuanians children; when in the church the priest is preaching hate and denunciation, is the priest responsible for all that only to the church government? The church in American cannot be against the Lithuanian national affairs.</p>
   <p>But we have all this. What is the benefit to the church? In Chicago there are over 10,000 Lithuanians, while to the parish belong only 2,000. They belong to the parish because they do not understand that the priest is exploiting them. And even of such people the membership is diminishing.</p>
   <p>The agitation against the priest does not bring as much harm as the fruitless sermons of the priest himself. We hear from the faithful people themselves that they don't want to listen to such sermons because they hear nothing good; only slander and vulgarity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1783.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If the church is under the control of its highest authority, then such a regulation everywhere must be the same. The regulations of the church in Lithuania, Germany or France, are no different than in America. We think that the regulation of the church in America ought to be the same as in Europe. In Europe, when the priest trespasses the civil laws, he is responsible to the civil court. In American also many priests were sentenced to prison for trespassing the civil law. So we see no reason why Rev. Krawczunas cannot be brought to the civil court for his wrongful deeds in the parish.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the Rytas says that the people can go into the ecclesiastical court to punish the priest. We are sorry that the Rytas did not give us the necessary instructions on how to force our rector to give honest account of the parish budget. How to stop the rector from Polanization of our children. How to force the priest so, from mutual hate among Lithuanians instead of Christian solidarity, education and science? We would like to get advice on that point from the Rytas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
