<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Text of President Wilson's Proclamation of Lithuanian Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TEXT OF PRESIDENT WILSON'S PROCLAMATION OF LITHUANIAN DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In designating November 1, 1916 as a "Lithuanian Day" (Tag Day), on which public collections will be made all over the United States for the relief of the war-stricken people of Lithuania, President Woodrow Wilson issued the following proclamation:</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The text of this proclamation appears in the Lietuva in both the Lithuanian and English languages. The following is a transcription of the English text.]</p>
   <p>"Whereas, I have received from the House of Representatives of the United States a resolution, passed July 21, 1916, reading as follows:</p>
   <p>" 'Whereas, in the various countries now engaged in war there are four millions of Lithuanians, the greater majority of whom are destitute of food, <pb facs="5423970_3_0231.jpg" n="2"/>shelter, clothing; and</p>
   <p>"'Whereas, millions of them have been driven from their homes without warning, deprived of an opportunity to make provisions for their most elementary wants, causing starvation, disease, and untold suffering; and</p>
   <p>" 'Whereas, the people of the United States of America have learned with sorrow of this plight of millions of human beings, and have most generously responded to the cry of help whenever such an opportunity has reached them;</p>
   <p>" 'Therefore, be it</p>
   <p>" 'Resolved, that in view of the misery, wretchedness, and hardships which these four millions of Lithuanians are suffering, the President of the United States be respectfully asked to designate a day on which the citizens of this country may give expression to their sympathy by contributing to the funds now being raised for the relief of the Lithuanians in the war zone.'</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0232.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"And whereas, I feel confident that the people of the United States will be moved to aid a people stricken by war, famine, and disease;</p>
   <p>"Now, therefore, I, Woodrow Wilson, President of the United States, in compliance with the request of the House of Representatives thereof, do appoint and proclaim Wednesday, November 1, 1916, as a day upon which the people of the United States may make contributions as they feel disposed for the aid of the stricken Lithuanian people.</p>
   <p>"Contributions may be addressed to the American Red Cross, Washington, D. C., which will care for proper distribution.</p>
   <p>"In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of the United States to be affixed.</p>
   <p>"Done at the City of Washington, this thirty-first day of August, in the year <pb facs="5423970_3_0233.jpg" n="4"/>of our Lord, one thousand nine hundred and sixteen, and of the independence of the United States, the one hundred and forty-first."</p>
   <p>Signed: Woodrow Wilson</p>
   <p>Chicago Lithuanians are now making energetic preparations for that "Lithuanian Day". A big mass meeting of Chicago Lithuanians, called by the editorial staffs of the newspapers Draugas (The Friend), Katalikas (The Catholic), Lietuva (Lithuania), and Savaitinis Draugas (Weekly Friend), took place last Wednesday evening, September 13, at St. George's parish hall. At that meeting a united front was formed by the Nationalist and Catholic factions; the Socialist faction refused to enter into the united front. A Central Chicago Lithuanian Committee, with Reverend F. B. Serafinas at the helm, was elected for the "Lithuanian Day" at the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
