<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1937-12-23">Dec. 23, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Knights of Lithuania Open Chicago Club House</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1937-12-23">Dec. 23, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">KNIGHTS OF LITHUANIA OPEN CHICAGO CLUB HOUSE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1-2.......Climaxing a long and hard struggle to obtain a meeting house of their own, the Chicago District of the K. of L. opened their first central club house on Sunday, Dec.5th, at 2410 Western Ave. in Chicago. Chicago Consul, Petras Dauzvardis cut the ribbon and formally opened the rooms.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Urbonavicius presided as master of ceremonies and after the singing of the Lithuanian national anthem, various guests voiced their approval of the new K. of L. central home. The speakers were Consul Dauzvardis, Editor Leonard Shimutis of Draugas (The Friend), Dr. A. Rakauskas, President of the Lithuanian-Catholic Federation of America, Editor J. Poshka of Jaunimas (The Youth) , Attys. A. Lapinskas, J.J.Grish and J.P.Rakstis - all rendered encouraging words to the occasion.</p>
   <p>Since it was a house warming party every one was obliged to drop a piece of coal from the bin into the stove fire. Following this, Mr. Shimutis wrote a short and well-meant proclamation that was signed by guests and members alike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0661.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Refreshments concluded the formal proceedings and the general feeling of the group was reflected in the following statement of one of the members:</p>
   <p>"Give Father Urbavicius credit. What if the rooms are a little small, it is a beginning, isn't it? That is what counts!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
