<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America</title>, in Possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America, Dist. of Chicago

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America</title>, in Possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America, Dist. of Chicago
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America of the Chicago district was organized in 1914. At the beginning, the district consisted of four states: Illinois, Indiana, Wisconsin and Michigan.</p>
   <p>The first administration of this district was: M. Kadzenskis, president; K. Varanaviciene, vice-president; K. Pahastas, secretary; Rev. F. Kemsis, trustee; H. J. Luthus and Miklas, organizers.</p>
   <p>In the first years the district organizer's activity was to organize the new branches to obtain charters for them and to get all the existing branches into the district organization.</p>
   <p>In the year of 1916 in the districts minutes we find: That Mr. S. Kibaratas, member of the 101st branch appealed to the districts' delegates maintaining that "the freethinkers and the socialists in their fight against the Alliance and all the Catholic <pb facs="5423970_3_1090.jpg" n="2"/>organizations are severely attacking the Rev. F. Kemesis and are mailing letters to him, even demanding that he disclose the secrets of confession." In other minutes we find: "A resolution expressing sympathy was brought in favor of the Alliance Branch 85 of Chicago, which was assaulted by the Grand Duke Vytautas of Lithuania Knights Society, because of Catholic parish affairs."</p>
   <p>In the year of 1919 there was held in Chicago a yearly convention of the district; the convention was a great financial loss to the district. To cover the expenses, the branches were assesed at the rate of $11. for each branch.</p>
   <p>In 1927, the Chicago district brought forth a protest against the Central Administration for demanding that the branches pay the past membership dues which had not been paid to the former Central Administration; it also protested because members were not allowed to join those sections of the mortuary fund to which they wanted to belong. One branch admitted seven new members, and the Central Administration placed them in a different section than that to which the members were originally assigned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The district had disputes with its treasurer because he wasted the district's funds, and at the general convention of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance the delegates wasted the districts funds; and the delegates of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance general convention refused to give a report of what was done at the convention.</p>
   <p>In 1933 there occured in the Chicago district another scandal: One member, who was district vice-president, began to support the Communists. In the beginning in the district there was much trouble, but it does not pay to five attention to it.</p>
   <p>From 1934, the district of Chicago was, and still is under the leadership of J. A. Mickeliunas; the most atcive members are A. Bacevicius, A. J. Zviblis, K. D. Rubinas, B. Grybas, J. Mikolainis, J. P. Aukstaitis, A. J. Sutkus, P. Cizauskas, L. Simutis, Dr. Rakaukas, Dr. Poska, Atty. Grisius and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1093.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At the present time (1937) the district of Chicago is endeavoring to organize the branches where more have existed heretofore, also much energy is devoted to increase the funds of the district. For that purpose the district is arranging picnics, banquets and other festivals.</p>
   <p>The present administration of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America, District of Chicago, consists of the following persons: Rev. A. Baltutis, spiritual leader; J. Mickeliunas, president; A. A. Bacevicus, vice-president; I. Lakalas, secretary; K. Rubinas, treasurer; A. Kazlanskas and J. Mikolanis, trustees; Doctor Poska, health inspector; attorney J. Grish, legal adviser; Cizanskas, organizer.</p>
   <p>Ig. Lakalas, secretary,</p>
   <p>6747 S. Artesian Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
