<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-12-22">Dec. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians to Participate in Allied Bazaar</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-12-22">Dec. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS TO PARTICIPATE IN ALLIED BAZAAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Lithuanians are making extensive preparations to participate in the Allied Bazaar, which will be held in the Coliseum for ten days, beginning January 10, 1917.</p>
   <p>The Bazaar is to be held for the purpose of raising funds for the relief of the war-stricken people of the Allied nations in Europe. In addition to the Lithuanians, the following nationalities will participate: French, British, Russian, Belgian, Serbian, Japanese, Montenegrin, Portuguese, Czech, Polish, etc.</p>
   <p>The sponsors of the Bazaar's Lithuanian section are the Central Chicago Lithuanian Committee, which was organized to promote Lithuanian Day (Tag Day), held <pb facs="5423970_3_0167.jpg" n="2"/>on November 1, and the Federation of Chicago Lithuanian Societies, which was organized a few months ago for the purpose of raising funds for Lithuanian war relief and in which more than fifty Chicago Lithuanian organizations are members.</p>
   <p>Mr. Paul Baltutis has been appointed manager of the Lithuanian section. Jonas Sileika, popular Lithuanian art painter, will be in charge of the art work of the Section.</p>
   <p>The fee for each nationality section in the Bazaar is five hundred dollars. However, taking into consideration the limited financial means of the Lithuanians, the Allied Bazaar Committee has granted a section to Chicago Lithuanians free of charge. Mr. J. Patten, president of the Committee, and his brother have donated fifty dollars each to help defray the expenses of erecting the Lithuanian section. The Lithuanians have been alloted a space of <pb facs="5423970_3_0168.jpg" n="3"/>eighteen by twelve feet.</p>
   <p>The idea of holding the Allied Bazaar originated with Mr. J. Patten, who is a millionaire.</p>
   <p>All that remains for Chicago Lithuanians to do is to assemble various items that are to be sold in the Lithuanian section. A strong effort is being made to gather typical Lithuanian goods, such as waistbands, aprons, handicraft, towels, wood carvings, table cloths, etc. A group of Chicago Lithuanian women, meeting in the home of Mrs. J. Zimontas, are making up a number of dolls in typical Lithuanian national dress; these will be offered for sale in the Bazaar's Lithuanian section.</p>
   <p>By participating in the Bazaar, it is believed that a few thousand dollars, at least, will be raised for Lithuanian war relief. At the same time, the <pb facs="5423970_3_0169.jpg" n="4"/>political aspirations of the Lithuanian nation will be advertised and advanced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
