<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 51,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Assembly of Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 51,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">ASSEMBLY OF LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thanksgiving Day several Lithuanian societies of Chicago held a meeting. At this meeting was discussed the uniting of all the Chicago societies into one Lithuanian society.</p>
   <p>The first object of such an organization should be to build a Lithuanian national home with a hall, where we could hold concerts, theatrical performances, meetings, etc. Such a project is not only to be approved, but should be supported.</p>
   <p>Because of the lack of such a Lithuanian national building in Chicago, the forty thousand Lithuanians of this city have no place where they could improve themselves culturally. This project should inspire all the Lithuanian societies to take action. The erection of a Lithuanian building would be the starting point of a good Lithuanian movement.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, Lithuanians have not taken advantage of American freedom. During all the past years of their life in this country, the Lithuanians have not taken part in their national affairs. They can not be <pb facs="5423970_3_0112.jpg" n="2"/>blamed. They came from a despotic country without education and enlightenment; they know nothing about unity among themselves; or about the value and benefit of such a union. They do not understand that in unity can be accomplished great deeds.</p>
   <p>The establishment of many churches and fraternal societies, the publishing of newspapers, books, and the upkeep of book stores, proves that Lithuanians in America have worked hard to maintain all this. We see that the activity in churches and fraternal organizations is growing stronger, but this is not enough. We must unite all the Lithuanian societies into one strong organization in order to gain material benefit.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians have spent hundreds of thousands of dollars for churches, but what benefit did they gain? They are still as ignorant as they were before. In order to uplift themselves, the Lithuanians must look for material gain; establish factories and commerce; build their own industry and business to improve the material standard of living, instead of the spiritual which leads nowhere.</p>
   <p>To uplift Lithuanians materially, several years ago we organized "Zinicia". We must have our organization in every branch of industry and commerce; and <pb facs="5423970_3_0113.jpg" n="3"/>by having such unity in business, we could compete with other industrial and business institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
