<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 25,
<date when="1901-06-21">June 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Hunters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 25,
<date when="1901-06-21">June 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In America, Dr. Szliupas is known as the best Lithuanian speaker and agitator. Of this honor to Dr. Szliupas the Lithuanian clergy are very envious. At last the clergy decided to attack Dr. Szliupas, to start an agitation in order to disgrace the reputation of the said doctor. So the clergy elected as their agitator the Rev. Milukas. The clerical agitator arrived in Chicago. He delivered long speeches here, but he explained nothing well. He tried to plant the seeds of disturbance among the Chicago Lithuanians as he had done in Pennsylvania, but we doubt very much whether he will succeed in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In his speech he praised the Rev. Krawczunas for upholding the Polish school in the Lithuanian parish. He even denounced those priests who raised voices of protest against the Rev. Krawczunas' Polanization of the Lithuanian children.</p>
   <p>Further, the priest urged the people not to read newspapers, but he <pb facs="5423970_3_1649.jpg" n="2"/>did not name the newspapers. According to the agitator's instructions, the people must not read even the Catholic newspapers, such as Katalikas and Dirva (The Field). What benefit would this have? I doubt whether the priest knows.</p>
   <p>He spoke on various questions but from his speech came nothing good; a mixture of cabbages and peas.</p>
   <p>When the agitator comes to Chicago again, we will have a stenographer copy his speech, so the public can read it and find out for themselves. It is not enough to have the material in the speech, how to use the material is another question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
