<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-03-12">Mar. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Englewood Lithuanians Raise $300 for War Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-03-12">Mar. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLEWOOD LITHUANIANS RAISE $300 FOR WAR RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee for the purpose of raising funds for the relief of war victims in Lithuania was recently organized by the Lithuanians who reside in Englewood. This committee is composed of delegates from various Lithuanian organizations in Englewood.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians of Englewood are very generous in their contributions for Lithuanian war relief. During the past three months they raised about $280. It is believed that this sum will be increased to $300 before it is sent to the Lithuanian Relief and Autonomy Fund. Fifty dollars of this sum will be designated for the autonomy section of the Fund, and the balance for the relief of our brothers and sisters in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>At a meeting of the Committee on March 6, at Baubkis Hall, there were discussions as to which of the three Lithuanian war relief funds the committee should send the money which it has raised. After a short discussion it was <pb facs="5423970_3_0348.jpg" n="2"/>decided to send it to the Lithuanian Relief and Autonomy Fund, which was set up by the Lithuanian nationalists. The members of the Committee are certain that all the money that is sent to this Fund will be honestly used for the relief of Lithuanian war victims and for the liberation of our fatherland.</p>
   <p>There are about seventy Lithuanian families and about one hundred and forty single Lithuanians living in the Englewood district. In view of that fact, it must be admitted that the Lithuanians of Englewood have contributed very generously for the relief of Lithuanian war victims.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Socialists of Englewood are also raising funds for this cause. It is reported that they have raised twenty dollars, which they will send to the Lithuanian Assistance Fund, set up by Lithuanian-American Socialists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
