<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Chapter 22 of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF CHAPTER 22 OF THE LOVERS OF THE FATHERLAND SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chapter 22 of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society held a special meeting at Milda Hall on Sunday, January 27. The meeting was opened by A. D. Kaulakis, last year's vice-president, who, after a short speech, invited the newly elected president, Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, to assume his office.</p>
   <p>The new president outlined the officers' plans for 1918. It was apparent that the new officers, at their first meeting, have instilled fresh spirit into the organization. A program was held in conjunction with the meeting.</p>
   <p>The secretary read the minutes of the last meeting, which were accepted. The program followed. First, Mr. Stankauskas read B. K. Balutis' essay "On Patriotism," which was well received by everyone. Attorney F. P. Bradchulis then made an earnest speech on the present status of Lithuanian independence. He pointed out that Lithuanian independence is being thwarted by the Poles, who are carrying on intrigues among the English, French, Americans, and Russians <pb facs="5423970_3_0696.jpg" n="2"/>The Lithuanians, he said, must become active and show the world who they are and what they demand.</p>
   <p>Later a motion was made to support the appeal of the Lithuanian-American Council calling for "a general Lithuanian-American political convention" on March 13-14 of this year. The meeting discussed the advisability of holding the convention in either Pittsburgh, Cleveland or Detroit, so that the convention site would be midway between the Chicago, New York, and Boston Lithuanian colonies. The motion was passed. The members admitted the need for a general convention of Lithuanian-Americans at this moment.</p>
   <p>Another matter of equal importance was also discussed. This concerned the voluntary pledges of monthly donations to war sufferers. It was decided that each member pledge five cents or more each month for Lithuanians who are suffering because of the war. It was decided to inform the Supreme Board of the Society of this decision concerning monthly pledges, so that it could instruct all chapters of the Society to take similar action. In this manner we would collect more donations for war relief and for political purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0697.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After the political discussions Mrs. Damijonaitis spoke on child training. She pointed out that children who attend the public schools do not want to speak Lithuanian with their parents at home. She further stated that parents make a big mistake when they permit very young children to attend all kinds of theaters and parties for these very often corrupt the children. Parents believe that they should not go where their children go; they are wrong in believing this. It would be better if parents accompanied their children everywhere. Then they could observe how their children conduct themselves, and should the latter misbehave, the parents could restrain them.</p>
   <p>Later, after several less important matters were discussed, the meeting was adjourned. All those attending were favorably impressed by the meeting. More than ten new members joined the chapter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
