<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-21">May 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Socialists Invite Nationalists to Combat Clericalism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-21">May 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISTS INVITE NATIONALISTS TO COMBAT CLERICALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A suggestion has originated in the press of the Lithuanian Socialists that a united front be formed with the Lithuanian Nationalists for the purpose of combating the ever-growing danger of clericalism among our people in America.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that clericalism is dangerous, and its spread among our people should be fought. The history of Lithuania during the past few decades serves to demonstrate how intolerable the power of clericalism can become to the masses. Besides Lithuania, there are many other examples which show how undesirable and damnable is the power of clericalism.</p>
   <p>However, there are a number of points to consider in connection with the proposal to form a united front between the Socialists and Nationalists to <pb facs="5423970_3_1463.jpg" n="2"/>combat the spread of clericalism. It is quite true that clericalism is dangerous to our people; but no less dangerous is that dire debauchery which predominates in that section of our press from which the proposal for a united front has originated. The press of the middle (Nationalist) faction always upheld and still upholds the belief that the prime requisite for making progress in public life is decency. In public as well as private life it is impossible even to think of progress when vulgar language and indecent behavior are countenanced. Therefore, as long as the Socialists endanger the moral foundations of our people by tolerating and promoting debauchery, the Nationalists cannot talk of forming any kind of united front with them; they must clean house first before any united front proposals can be considered.</p>
   <p>The Nationalists are waging a fight against clericalism (not against Catholics). But the Nationalists are likewise opposed to the indecency and debauchery of the Socialist faction. The Nationalists believe that our people are endangered by both of these elements. Therefore, a united front cannot be formed between factions with such widely divergent aims and principles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
