<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 15,
<date when="1908-04-10">Apr. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">What I Have Noticed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 15,
<date when="1908-04-10">Apr. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT I HAVE NOTICED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are certain phases of Americanization such as public schools, settlements, public parks and other places of recreation. One observes that these places are centers for the "civilizing of foreigners". This "Americanization" scheme, however, is without bloodshed and killing. The modern methods are different from those used in civilizing the Indians with sword and cross. At present the Americans are civilizing the foreigners with scorn and humiliation.</p>
   <p>I have noticed at the park playgrounds that the recreational directors are watching closely so that children of foreign parents do not play their beautiful national games. They see to it that the children do not speak their parents' language. When the directors hear the children talking in their own language, they stop them at once and give them to understand that if they do not speak English, they will not be permitted to play at the park playgrounds.</p>
   <p>This is not all. At Davis Park, Lithuanians got permission to place their books in the park library for the general Lithuanian public to read. At first, the books were placed on the shelves close to the entrance so that <pb facs="5423970_3_0613.jpg" n="2"/>Lithuanians could find the books without difficulty, as they do not know the English language and are unable to ask for the books they want. Thus it was very easy for them to get the books they wanted. The books were on scientific subjects. Many Lithuanians began to read these books. The girl or woman at the desk in the library noticed that the Lithuanians were eagerly reading the books, and by reading such books increased their knowledge. So the librarian had the books removed from the front shelf, where it was very easy to reach for them, to a shelf in the rear where they were inaccessible. Since then, even those Lithuanians who can converse in English have trouble getting the books they want,and those who can not speak English are unable to get Lithuanian books.</p>
   <p>Such mistreatment of foreign people, no one has ever seen, not even in Russia. This is the American ideal - to Americanize foreigners. The Americans do not want the Lithuanians or people of other nationalities to read scientific books, to gain knowledge and culture.</p>
   <p>The American libraries are packed with trashy literature, but when classical or scientific books are requested, the answer is that such books are not available.</p>
   <p>A. K. Rutkauskas, M.D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
