<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 7,
<date when="1907-02-15">Feb. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The 36Th Branch Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 7,
<date when="1907-02-15">Feb. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE 36TH BRANCH BANQUET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America, branch 36, had its banquet in the same hall where the twenty-four Lithuanian Alliance convention was held. The crowd was large. It seems that the Lithuanians begin to realize that it is their duty to support the national activity. The banquet was a success and gave a fair profit. The money will be used for sending delegates to the twenty-second convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, which will be held in Cleveland.</p>
   <p>I must mention that the 36th branch is the most active and has organized several branches of the Lithuanian Alliance of America in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On February 10th the 122nd branch of the Lithuanian Alliance of America held lectures and a banquet in the district of the Town of Lake. At this banquet Mr. F. Eismontas spoke on the affairs of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The second speaker was Mr. F. Golubickas.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0919.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The people are saying that when the Lithuanian priest of Town of Lake heard that the Lithuanian Alliance was going to have a banquet, he warned the people from (the neighborhood) not to go. Yet, there are some persons who say that the clergy are not against the enlightenment of the people. The Lithuanians of Town of Lake are more under the control of the priest than any other Lithuanians of Chicago, and these Lithuanians in Town of Lake district are the most ignorant people. In Chicago there are over 40,000 Lithuanians, a majority of them are oppressed by the priest. The Lithuanians are so ignorant that if Christ could see them he would cry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
