<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 19,
<date when="1914-07-01">July 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Teacher of Morals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 19,
<date when="1914-07-01">July 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TEACHER OF MORALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Draugas (Friend), the Catholic newspaper, is shrinking from its own false statement
 which it made against the Naujienos (News). Moreover, Draugas does not want to admit
 that it made such a hypocritical statement against the News. Draugas made a
 reference especially to one article which was published in the News just recently.
 This article was misinterpreted to the people by Draugas, and its meaning was not
 explained as it was written originally in the News. Draugas, in order to hurt
 Naujienos' good standing in the community, took excerpts from some Socialistic
 sources, which they claim to be genuine, and published them in their paper as
 follows: "The Socialists are organizing the proletariat and will lead it into bloody
 battle when the zero hour comes." Then Draugas made the following statement:
 "Naujienos says that arms will be used only then, when the ruling class will try,
 with armed force, to subdue the proletariat.</p>
   <p>"However, we know that the Naujienos' editor and other Socialist <pb facs="5423970_3_1491.jpg" n="2"/>leaders understand that the ruling class will
 not give up without a fight and the Socialists will not accomplish their task
 without using armed force."</p>
   <p>One thing we would like to know, how does Draugas know, and where did they get the
 information that the Socialist party and its leaders are planning to use armed force
 against the ruling class? A man who is well read and has studied the principles of
 the Socialist party knows very well that the Socialists don't believe in
 overthrowing the government and the ruling class by armed force. This idea of using
 armed force, as Draugas states it, is nothing more than fantasy and excogitation by
 the editor of Draugas, who is ignorant and does not understand the principles of
 Socialism. To write of certain things of which you have no idea shows that a man has
 a mental weakness, and he should be sent to the hospital immediately for mental
 observation. We have already mentioned in the newspaper a famous living Socialist,
 who is a real authority on the principles <pb facs="5423970_3_1492.jpg" n="3"/>of
 Socialism and we explained his opinion about social revolution, but there was not
 mentioned anything about that which Draugas said about the Socialist proletariat and
 its armed force. The people who are feeble-minded as a rule imagine very queer
 things in the world we live in; very seldom they see the world as it is, and they
 live in a world of hallucination and see devils flying around like angels. It is a
 pitiful thing to see people in that state of mind, especially when their mental
 faculties cease to function properly. Under such conditions these people cannot see
 and cannot understand the facts as they really exist. We cited in our article a few
 sentences on social revolution from a famous living authority on Socialism, Mr. K.
 Kautsky, and we explained his opinion on Socialism and the principles of the
 Socialist Party. But we never made a statement that the Socialist proletariat is
 organizing to use armed force against the ruling class, and neither did Mr. K.
 Kautsky mention in his book on Socialism anything about using armed force against
 the ruling class. According to the Socialists' understanding, social revolution will
 manifest itself in various countries and in various forms, but <pb facs="5423970_3_1493.jpg" n="4"/>we cannot say that social revolution should and
 must happen through a means of a bloody battle, this is impossible. There is no
 Socialist who really believes in using armed force and waging a bloody battle
 against the ruling class. Even if the Socialists did suspect that the ruling class
 all over the world are planning to subdue the Socialist proletariat by means of
 armed force, the Socialists would never resort to armed force and wage a bloody
 battle against the ruling class. So Draugas and its editor are far from being
 correct about the principles of Socialism and the social revolution. If anybody uses
 a weapon to defend himself in case of attact, one cannot say that he wants a bloody
 battle and is waiting for an hour of opportunity to strike. That idea is absolutely
 wrong, incorrect and antiquated. It is easier for some people to lie than to tell
 the truth, and they cannot get away from that bad habit, because to lie is almost
 inborn in them.</p>
   <p>Draugas, the Catholic newspaper, failed a second time in its investigation to prove
 that the followers of Karl Marx are purposely increasing <pb facs="5423970_3_1494.jpg" n="5"/>the workers' misery in order to effect social
 revolution sooner and accomplish their purpose. The question that started this
 argument between Naujienos and Draugas was the question of morality. Draugas
 expressed its opinion that the workers' living conditions can be improved only when
 their morals are raised to a higher level; and in addition, a dissolute people would
 never live in peace under the Socialist system. Draugas, the Catholic newspaper,
 call those people dissolute who are not members of the Catholic Church and don't
 attend the church services on Sunday morning. Draugas' opinion of morality and
 immorality is, as we understand it, that all Catholics have a high standard of
 morality and all other people who are not Catholics, especially the Socialists, are
 very immoral people. This is the definition of morality and immorality as given by
 the editor of Draugas, which is the leading Catholic newspapers in America. It is
 pitiful that the editor of Draugas has not learned the definition of morality and
 immorality as yet. He should make every effort to look up these two words in the
 Webster's International Dictionary, <pb facs="5423970_3_1495.jpg" n="6"/>and he will
 find there a correct meaning of these two words, morality and immorality. We
 answered his question before, but he failed to understand our answer. We answered
 that the workers are waging the battles for Socialism and full expansion of
 morality, which is essential in order to effect the idealism of the Socialist
 proletariat, and this can happen only in the era of Socialism, when the capitalists'
 exploitation of the people and ignorance will disappear from all the world. Draugas,
 the Catholic newspaper, for some reason did not mention private ownership and the
 effect of exploitation upon the morality of the people. Draugas speaks about the
 relationship between morality and enlightenment. The quotation from Draugas is as
 follows: "The editor of Naujienos made a big mistake by saying that knowledge or
 enlightenment can bring about a real morality. The life of the people shows us that
 morality cannot be separated from religion. In life itself, there are many people
 who are very well educated, understand the philosophy of life and yet they lead an
 immoral life. So, what does this means to them. What does enlightenment or knowledge
 mean to a man who has bad inclinations? Does knowledge <pb facs="5423970_3_1496.jpg" n="7"/>or enlightenment help him to lead a moral life? knowledge or
 enlightenment to a man who leads immoral life is just the same as the flashlight to
 a burglar who robs homes at night. Religion can only teach morality and faith can
 give a man power to resist temptation, and to lead a clean moral life." We did not
 confirm that enlightenment alone can bring about morality. But under no
 circumstances can we agree with Draugas that morality comes from religion and faith.
 Draugas repeated its statement about twenty times in each edition, and each time its
 argument appeared weaker and without logic. According to their argument, all
 Catholics are moral and the others are immoral. Lithuanian Catholics who are strong
 believers are those who set the example of hate and create disturbance among
 peace-loving people. There is a good example of Montreal, Canada, when happened in
 Hoosick Falls, N. Y. , and Montreal, Canada, when a Catholic priest organized the
 mob which attacked the speaker and people in Hoosick Falls, N. Y. Mr. John Perkunas
 was the main speaker that evening when he was attacked and beaten by the mob, which
 was organized by the Catholic priest, the teacher of morality. And religion is
 supposed to teach morality. A second example of the Catholic priests' morality: when
 <pb facs="5423970_3_1497.jpg" n="8"/>the priest killed the girl who was to
 become a mother through his fault, in Montreal, Canada. He took the girl's life to
 save himself and his so-called morality. The third incident was in Cracow, Poland,
 when a priest, Macoch, fell in love with his brother's wife and then he killed his
 own brother because he knew too much about his reverend brother's relationship with
 his wife. He was afraid to murder his brother, especially when his brother was
 sober, so he made him drunk first, then he murdered him with an ax by chopping his
 head off. The fourth and the last incident we all remember happened in New York,
 when a Catholic priest by the name of Schmidt murdered a young girl who was to
 become a mother; he cut up her body and threw it into the Atlantic ocean. These
 facts cannot be denied by the Catholic priests because they are known all over the
 world. We have one outstanding example in the world, which shows that Catholic
 priests are the coldest murderers that had ever existed. We have historical facts
 which prove what happened in Spain during the period of the inquisition. How many
 innocent people were murdered by the Spanish monks. Those people were tortured with
 greatest pain-producing <pb facs="5423970_3_1498.jpg" n="9"/>instruments that could
 be conceived by the brains of the Spanish Catholic church. Is that the morality the
 Catholics teach? What is the morality of religion? We found from historical records
 and proved by historical fact that the heads of the Spanish church were the cruelest
 of murderers. These people were well educated and in addition they were very
 religious, and yet, they committed immoral deeds and committed cruel murders by
 burning people alive and torturing them with the cruelest instruments which produced
 the greatest pain and suffering. We believe that Draugas will admit that the Spanish
 Inquisition was the moral deed of the Catholic Church. Religion and faith do not
 help to bring about morality and idealism.</p>
   <p>The editor of the Catholic newspaper, Draugas, failed to prove his theory about
 religion and morality. Moreover, he contradicted himself by saying that Socialists
 are immoral. We gave him very good historical examples as to what type of people are
 most immoral in their actions. We cited five good examples, which show that the <pb facs="5423970_3_1499.jpg" n="10"/>Catholic priests have committed more immoral
 deeds and cruel murders than any other leaders of any organization. By this we refer
 to the Spanish Inquisition. Now let us take for example free thinkers such as
 Voltaire, Karl Marx, Frederick Engels, Bebel, Kautsky, Mirabeau, and Savanarola who
 was a Catholic priest and was actually burned on a pile of wood for criticizing the
 priests' immorality.</p>
   <p>Let the editor of Draugas scrutinize the famous Socialist leaders and let him see for
 himself what murders and immoral deeds these famous Socialist writers have
 committed, as compared to the famous leaders of the Spanish Inquisition. Let us see
 how many immoral men and murderers the editor of Draugas can find among the
 Socialist leaders whose names we mentioned above. The Socialist writers and leaders
 have fought and will fight in the future against the elements that bring about
 immorality. We may enumerate the three main factors that increase immorality and
 they are as follows: Ignorance, Misery and various exploitations by capitalists and
 political parasites.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1500.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Bad conditions and starvation are most dangerous to morality. There is nothing that
 can save the morality of the people under the bad conditions. What causes immorality
 if not bad conditions and starvation? This situation can be remedied only by social
 revolution and social reforms and other remedies will not help, especially religion.
 Religion has thwarted social and economic progress for many years, and will thwart
 it for many more years to come. And morality itself depends upon social reforms and
 more justice to humanity. In order to eliminate immorality, we must first improve
 living conditions by eliminating ignorance, misery and exploitation by the
 capitalists, then the world will be happy and moral.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
