<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 14,
<date when="1906-04-06">April 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Remark to the Chicago Lithuanian Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 14,
<date when="1906-04-06">April 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">REMARK TO THE CHICAGO LITHUANIAN SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been told to you from the pulpit and in the printed circulars, and also through confession, that you must not participate in the twenty-first convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, which will be held in Chicago, because this convention is conducted by enlightened and intelligent people who are not afraid to tell the truth.</p>
   <p>The church societies agreed to participate in the parade, but when they heard the warning of the priests they obeyed like sheep. It is time to shed your sheepskin and to become human beings, to demand human rights, to rule yourselves by your own reason, not to be ruled always by the morally inferior priests, who are leading you to the swamp where destruction is awaiting you.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian Alliance of America is not an anti-religious organization. The Rev. J. Zebrys of New Britain, Conn., when the convention of the Lithuanian Alliance was held there, not only was not against the convention, but he urged all the Lithuanian societies of New Britain and from all other towns to participate in the parade of the convention.</p>
   <p>By belonging to the Lithuanian Alliance of America, the Lithuanians can improve themselves materially and culturally, so that we shall be able to show Americans that Lithuanians are a cultured people. We pay no attention to the low cultured priests for their attack on culture and progress, against the enlightenment of our brother Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>At this convention the governor of Illinois and the mayor of Chicago will be present. They are curious to see the activity of the Lithuanians. The greater the number of Lithuanians that will participate in this parade, the stronger will be the impression which we shall make on the <pb facs="5423970_3_1368.jpg" n="3"/>American public and the officials. There will be reporters of American newspapers who will write broadly about our parade. The better they write about this convention, the better it will be for the Lithuanians. And yet, the ignorant Lithuanian priests of Chicago warn Lithuanian societies not to participate in this parade. The clergy wants to obstruct as such as possible the grand showing of the Lithuanians before the American public. All the Chicago Lithuanian societies must pay no attention to the priests, but must go forward with their preparations for the grand parade.</p>
   <p>On April 6th, branch 36th of the Lithuanian Alliance of America will hold a meeting at 3301 S. Morgan St. We are inviting all the Chicago Lithuanians to this meeting. Come and hear for yourselves the discussion as to why we must take part in this parade of the convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The societies which have decided to participate should send delegates to this meeting. Let us prepare for this rare Lithuanian festival in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
