<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-25">Sept. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Political Convention of Lithuanians in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-25">Sept. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLITICAL CONVENTION OF LITHUANIANS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The political convention of Lithuanians in America, which was called by the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Federation of America, was held in the drill hall of the Masonic Temple in Chicago on September 21 and 22.</p>
   <p>The chairman was Dr. A.K. Rutkauskas. The vice-chairmen were Joseph J. Elias (Chicago), B. Vaisnora (Pittsburgh), and Miss Jakaitis (Worcester, Massachusetts). The secretaries were Mr. Kaupas (Chicago), and Mr. Vasiliauskas (Baltimore).</p>
   <p>More than 270 delegates, many of whom represented several societies, participated in the convention. Many branches of the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance, the Lithuanian Alliance of America, and the Lovers of the Motherland Society were represented. There were about fifty priests present.</p>
   <p>The convention sent President Wilson a telegram in which he was petitioned to <pb facs="5423970_3_1301.jpg" n="2"/>support the Lithuanian demands.</p>
   <p>The following resolutions were passed: (1) A demand for autonomy for Lithuania and the union of Lithuania Minor with Lithuania Major. (2) A demand for the separation of the Suvalki province from Poland. (3) An expression of the hope that an autonomous Lithuania would arrive at federation with an autonomous Latvia. (4) An expression of the hope that Lithuania's neighbors, the Poles, the White Russians, and the Ukrainians would also gain autonomy.</p>
   <p>It was decided to establish a timely National Fund for the purpose of providing relief to Lithuanians who will suffer because of the war, and to aid in obtaining autonomy for Lithuania. In connection with this, it was decided to proclaim a "Lithuania Day" throughout the United States. The profits of this day will go to the fund. Thanksgiving Day, November 26, was selected for that purpose for the present year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1302.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was also an expression of the desirability of founding a national council which would be composed of the delegates of the largest organizations, selected according to these regulations: organizations having not less than one thousand members would have one delegate; organizations of not less than five thousand members would have two delegates; the delegates would be elected for two-year terms.</p>
   <p>Five sessions were held; four regular ones, and an extra session. The regular sessions were held on September 21 and 22, from 9 A. M. to 12 noon, and from 2 P. M. to 5 P. M. The extra session was held on September 22, from 5 P. M. to 9 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
