<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-23">Apr. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Hold Benefit Wrestling Show for War Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-23">Apr. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">HOLD BENEFIT WRESTLING SHOW FOR WAR RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A wrestling show for the benefit of war victims in Lithuania was held last Saturday evening, April 17, in St. George's (Lithuanian) parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn (now Lituanica) Avenue.</p>
   <p>There were two matches. The first match was between Blendow and Billy Lynn, both lightweights. The latter won by scoring two falls, in eighteen and in ten minutes respectively. The second match was between Charley Cutler, the American heavyweight champion, and Peter Zilinskas, well-known Lithuanian wrestler. This match ended in a draw after a half-hour of wrestling; neither scored a fall. Zilinskas was never in danger, but Cutler was twice in danger of being downed. Both men appeared to be well trained and experienced wrestlers; it is difficult to decide who is the better.</p>
   <p>During an intermission period Mr. Norkus, famous Lithuanian "strong man", <pb facs="5423970_3_0336.jpg" n="2"/>demonstrated his strength. He bent several heavy iron bars, drove a nail through a maple board three inches thick with his fist, and broke a heavy piece of stone with that same fist.</p>
   <p>Mr. Norkus and the wrestlers participated in the program without remuneration. Therefore, Lithuanians ought to be very thankful to them, because the compensation for such services usually amounts to hundreds and even thousands of dollars.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that there was insufficient time properly to advertise the show. For that reason the attendance was not large.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
