<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 19,
<date when="1903-05-08">May 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">From the Aurora Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0984</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0984.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 19,
<date when="1903-05-08">May 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE AURORA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday a meeting was held by the Aurora Society, whose purpose is to help the Lithuanian young students who are seeking to obtain the higher education. The Aurora is giving a stipend to one Lithuanian girl student who is attending a university in Europe. The society is paying $20 per month to that girl student. The amount is small. We were unable to give more help because at that time the society had no money. At present the society has $300 in its budget, now we can give a stipend to another good student. Of course, if Lithuanian society will support us as they did in the past, we can afford to give the second stipend.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society decided to give stipends as follows: One stipend to whomever is seeking to get a higher education in natural science; the other to anyone studying sculpture, architecture, painting, music <pb facs="5423970_3_0985.jpg" n="2"/>and singing, for such a student from whom in the future the Lithuanians may get benefit.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society announces that only those who help the stipend will be given, because we are obtaining appeals from students who write letters of a Polanized nature. Such degenerates will get no help from this society, because they will bring no benefit to the fatherland! Those who appeal to us must show their recommendation that they are not degenerates, but good Lithuanians, who are active in the Lithuanian field, and may be good workers in the future for the benefit and honor of our nation.</p>
   <p>As we have stated above, Aurora's budget at present has money, and we are able to give a second stipend. Therefore we have decided to give help to art students. At present we have no such candidate student and we know no one. Now then if anyone has ability in music or the <pb facs="5423970_3_0986.jpg" n="3"/>arts and wants to go to the conservatory of music or to the academy of arts, let him appeal to the Aurora Society with a recommendation from the national workers for Lithuanianism, and he will get the stipend.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
