<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 8,
<date when="1901-02-22">Feb. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">It Seems That the Lithuanian Alliance Will Split</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1016</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1016.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 8,
<date when="1901-02-22">Feb. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">IT SEEMS THAT THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE WILL SPLIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of Tevyne (Organ of the Lithuanian Alliance of America) it is stated that the central committee will strike out from the organization members Damijonaitis and Tareila for infidelity. We ask whoever investigated those members, were they guilty or not? No court will punish the accused party without permitting him to defend himself. Even in Russia the accused have rights to be defended. Our clergy is upholding a different principle. Now we see that in the last convention the decisions were made purposely to make it easier for the clergy to strike out the undesirables from the alliance before the coming convention. That means that the last convention gave full power to the clergy to enslave the alliance. Now that another convention is coming we believe that the clergy will strike out more members from the alliance, so the clergy at the convention will have more power to do what it pleases. The alliance cannot be one-sided. It cannot uphold the rights of the clergy and disregard the rights of others. It looks as if the alliance will be <pb facs="5423970_3_1017.jpg" n="2"/>forced to split as the Polish alliance did. We should not accuse the clergy alone, we must accuse those who, at the convention, gave full power to the clergy by trespassing the rights of others.</p>
   <p>The priests are accusing those who do not consent to the aims of the clergy. The clergy sheds tears because the Lithuanians are divided into parties. The present president of the alliance writes under various pseudonyms in the alliance's organ all kinds of denunciations. Who, then, we like to know, is the propagator of the various parties among Lithuanians? With such an action that the clergy has taken at the last convention of the Lithuanian Alliance, we cannot avoid having different parties. Such immoral conduct of the clergy we find everywhere. We know it is impossible to expect anything good from the clergy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
