<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 20,
<date when="1908-05-15">May 15, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians Need Unity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0103</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0103.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 20,
<date when="1908-05-15">May 15, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS NEED UNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We feel a lack of unity among the Lithuanian societies of Chicago. We know that in order to accomplish anything beneficial to the public, we must have unity, so that all of us together may establish some project for the good of all the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>It seems that we have enough national and church societies, and that we are well protected during sickness and in case of death. Also, we have enough churches.</p>
   <p>Let us look closer at our daily lives; we see that we are lacking much. We are still separated in small branches and societies. They have among them no closer relations or cooperation, except one common word, 'Lithuanians." Although our affairs are mostly alike, our projects are not much different, we have something (which prevents) a close relation to each other, no faith in a common <pb facs="5423970_3_0104.jpg" n="2"/>purpose. We see good cooperation among other nationalities.</p>
   <p>If we want to accomplish something good for ourselves, we must take care of ourselves. Let us consult, unite for the benefit of our national affairs; let us start some worthy activity. It seems that all of us are wishing to have one public building in common, or a hall where we can hold our festivals, celebrations, concerts, etc., instead of being beggars and seeking refuge with strangers. Can we not have such halls like Germans, Poles, etc.?</p>
   <p>We have never been and we will not be less than they (are) if we work together. In recent times, to discuss and to establish the project several of the church and nationalistic societies have organized an alliance among themselves. They elected an administration, and the treasurer is placed under $5,000 bond, and the association already has a few hundred dollars in the bank. The most essential affair of ours is to build the hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0105.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We have confidence that other Lithuanian societies will not refuse to join this worthy project and that they will elect their delegates and send them to the meeting which will take place on May 31, at 5 P. M., in T. Radavicius Hall, 942 W. 33rd St.</p>
   <p>The Alliance of the Lithuanian Societies of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
