<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-09-15">Sept. 15, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Lithuanian of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-09-15">Sept. 15, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE LITHUANIAN OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2....The Lithuanian Alliance of America held its semi-annual meeting Saturday evening Sept. 9, at Mildazis Hall on the West Side. The speakers of the evening were as follows: Mr. M.J. Damijonaitis, F. Eismontas, A. Kuema, and J. Girijotas, who explained the aims and purpose of this organization, stating that the Lithuanian Alliance of America, as a beneficiary society, is the most important organization of Lithuanian people in America. Mr. Eismontas explained the subject further and went on to say that the Lithuanian Alliance of America is a national organization and is organized for the purpose of helping and uniting all the Lithuanians in the United States. One can derive many benefits by belonging to the national organization.</p>
   <p>L.L.A. is an organization from which we benefit in many ways from a material and cultural point. If this organization has not yet accomplished its original aims, it will in the future,as it grows stronger and larger. Then we can expect <pb facs="5423970_3_0946.jpg" n="2"/>something from this organization because its membership will have increased.</p>
   <p>The second speaker, Mr. M.J.Damijonaitis urged those who agreed with the aims of the organization to join the organization as soon as possible. One man from the audience stood up and made the motion that a separate chapter of the Lithuanian Alliance of America be organized on the West Side for those people who live too far and cannot attend the meetings regularly. That motion was carried and so it was then and there decided to organize a new chapter on the West Side.</p>
   <p>The decision was unanimous; not a single person in the audience was opposed to the idea. Soon after discussion, twenty-one new members signed up, and the new chapter was organized.</p>
   <p>The executive board was elected the very same evening as follows: President, Peter Yakstas; secretary, Vincas Makaveckas; cashier, M. Mildazia. There is hope <pb facs="5423970_3_0947.jpg" n="3"/>that the new chapter of the Lithuanian Alliance of America will grow bigger and stronger in the future. The Chicago Lithuanians will begin to realize the value of the Lithuanian Alliance of America and will join in greater number, if we launch a lively campaign.</p>
   <p>Fellow-countrymen, let us work together in unity, so that we can be proud of our work and show at the next convention that we are doing our part well as can be expected. Let us talk to the people and persuade them to join the Lithuanian Alliance of America society which is the largest beneficiary organization in the United States, organized for the sole purpose of helping the people who are sick and unable to work any more. It is much better to belong to one large beneficiary society such as the Lithuanian Alliance of America than to many small beneficiary societies which are not even interested in our national affairs or working for the benefit of our people.</p>
   <p>Now is the time to get busy before the 21st convention of the L.A.A. next May in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_0948.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Members of the alliance in Pennsylvania are protesting against holding the convention in Chicago. They state that Chicagoans do not deserve that honor, because they have attracted very few members to the Alliance. Therefore, let us strive to obtain a few hundred members before the 21st convention. In that way we will demonstrate that the 20th convention did not err in deciding to hold the first convention in twenty years in Chicago. Therefore, every one of us who are Lithuanians join the SUSIVIENYIMAS LIETUVIA AMERIKOJE (Lithuanian Alliance of America).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
