<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 3,
<date when="1902-01-17">Jan. 17, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Let the 21st Day of May Be a National Holiday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1006</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1006.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 3,
<date when="1902-01-17">Jan. 17, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">LET THE 21ST DAY OF MAY BE A NATIONAL HOLIDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the question as to who obstructed the growth of the Lithuanian Alliance of America during the past sixteen years, briefly we can say: the clergy did it. This can be seen today by every Lithuanian who watches the national movement. Now when the Lithuanian Alliance of America is freed from the tutelage of the clergy, it is going forward with gigantic strides. Having a free road, we have no doubt that the alliance will bring the desired results. Even though the clergy, under the name of Catholicism, was trying to deliver the death blow to the Lithuanian Alliance, their aim was seen and their plans were frustrated. The intriguers became ashamed when the Lithuanians heard the voice of truth and gave the death blow to the conspirators. True, the clergy succeeded in taking the alliance's money, but this did not weaken the alliance; it only strengthened it. It opened the eyes of the Lithuanians,who saw that the grabbers had put on their foreheads an indelible mark. We can boast that the Lithuanian Alliance has 1,200 members, who have joined the alliance in the last seven months. What can the pseudo-leaders boast of? What! of nothing but stealing the alliance's money and thus earning the people's aversion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1007.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the last sixteen years the Lithuanian Alliance has had to bear a heavy load of spiritual misery and was unable to do any good for the nation, even though its national name rang loud among the Lithuanians of America. The men of good will among the Lithuanians learned by experience that the bad people are continually tearing the house from its foundation in order to obstruct the road leading to progress. There is a Lithuanian saying that the man who has one hundred friends is more fortunate than the one who has one hundred dollars. So it is with the obstructors of the alliance. They are accustomed to grabbing the money and giving nothing, but they forget that dollars will not make a man happy. By destroying the alliance, the clergy believed they could make profits for themselves, while they were ignoring the rights and the needs of the people. The Lithuanian Alliance of America won the sympathy of all the American Lithuanians, and that is why the alliance is growing. Therefore, let me suggest that the day on which the trap set by the clergy was broken, should be proclaimed as a national holiday. The day is the 21st day of May, 1901. Therefore, the alliance should consider it as its yearly anniversary to celebrate the victory of light over darkness. I must</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
