<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. S. Linkus</title>, Pastor of St. Mary's Mission Church, 3501 S. Union Avenue.
(<date when="1937-02-02">Feb. 2, 1937</date>)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. S. Linkus</title>, Pastor of St. Mary's Mission Church, 3501 S. Union Avenue.
(<date when="1937-02-02">Feb. 2, 1937</date>)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Interviewer's note: This is the continuation of the schism in the Roman-Catholic Church. When the Polish priest, Kozlowski, by inducement of A. L. Graiciunas, established the Independent Catholic Church, the movement of the Independent Church at that time spread throughout the United States among Poles and Lithuanians, like fire. In many cities Lithuanian and Polish churches were established. There was one priest, Mickevicius, in the New England states, very active. He organized in Lawrence, Mass., Providence, R. I., etc., the Lithuanian National Catholic Church. This priest later became Bishop Mickevicius. He was a terror to the Roman-Catholic priests. He was a good speaker and good organizer. As soon as he came to the city where the Roman Catholic Church dominated the Lithuanians, Bishop Mickevicius always succeeded in organizing Independent Catholic churches. One of these churches he organized in Chicago. He was very successful in his church <pb facs="5423970_3_1423.jpg" n="2"/>activity because there were no price set for his services).</p>
   <p>St. Mary's Mission Church has the distinction of being the home of Rev. Stanley Linkus, founder of the mission. During the past several years Rev. Linkus has been very active in providing food and clothes to thousands of destitute people, irrespective of religious belief or race.</p>
   <p>About 100,000 Lithuanians reside in Chicago and vicinity. Of these about 10,000 belong to the Chicago Lithuanian National Church of America. The church was established in Chicago in 1916 by the Rt. Rev. S. Mickevicz, as is stated in a publication of the Department of Commerce, United States, of America, Religious Bodies, Part II, page 347, published in 1916.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian people are lovers of liberty. The Roman-Catholic <pb facs="5423970_3_1424.jpg" n="3"/>religion was forced upon Lithuanians by sword and fire. In the year 1250 A. D., Pope Innocent IV and the people of Rome presented the crown to Mindangas, Duke of Lithuania, but the moment he realized what monarchy implied, he passed it aside and trampled it under his feet. He became again a simple Lithuanian, a knight of freedom and a follower of the democratic virtues.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians defended their liberty for 300 years against the Roman Catholicism. After 300 years of wars, Lithuania was exhausted of man power, and through the intrigues and conspiracy of Poland's demoralized nobility, Lithuania by force and fraud accepted the Catholic religion, and liberty and independence were lost. In other words, upon Lithuania was pronounced the sentence of death. Her name was blotted out, the language was forbidden, and all the printing was prohibited by the Russian government with the help of the Roman-Catholic clergy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1425.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the United States, for the last fifty years, in many cities there had been many bloody battles in Lithuanian Roman-Catholic churches for the control of the parishes and members of the Lithuanian parishes. The situation was aggravated in some cases by placing of other than Lithuanian priests in charge of Lithuanian churches. The result was that disturbances arose which developed at times into riots. In Chicago a popular Lithuanian priest was removed, and a protest made against the installation of his successor resulted in a general decree of excommunication. The congregation laid claim to the church property, but the claim was disallowed by the courts. The congregation then purchased ground, put up a new edifice of its own and declared itself absolutely independent of the former ecclesiastical leaders.</p>
   <p>During the panic 1930-1935, the Lithuanian National Catholic St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1426.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mary's church gave many concerts and dance balls to raise money for the needy.</p>
   <p>One spectacle, "The Gates of Paradise," by Lorado Taft, was presented on June 23, 1934, at Coliseum, 15th and Wabash Avenue. "The Orphan of Faith," was presented by St. Mary's church, Oct. 29, 1935, at the Lithuanian Auditorium, 3133 S. Halsted St.</p>
   <p>Relief.</p>
   <p>An audit of the St. Mary's Mission church relief provision has just been completed which gives an accurate and interesting picture of the relief work carried on during the five years, from April 5, 1930, to April 6, 1935.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1427.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>During this period 2,235 families or 9,527 persons were helped with food, clothing, fuel and other necessities, irrespective of race or creed.</p>
   <p>The distribution of the following commodities and their quantities: Bread, 355,785 loaves; Cakes, 200,325 pieces; Rolls, 25,575 bushels; pies, 28,650 pieces; milk, 15,576 galons; eggs, 10,250 dozens; Fruits and vegetables, 11,502 bushels; candy and nuts, 650 pounds; meat, 1,478 pounds; coffee, cocoa, sugar, etc., 2,650 pounds.</p>
   <p>Coats and trousers, 1,225 pairs; Women coats and dresses, 1,110 pieces; Boys and girls clothes, 12,455 pieces; stoves, 52; beds, complete, 65; sewing machines, 1; shoes, 1,551 pairs.</p>
   <p>St. Mary's Mission church, 3501-09 S. Union Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1428.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Board of Trustees and honorary officers:</p>
   <p>Wm. Zukowski</p>
   <p>A. Raslavicz</p>
   <p>J. Kirby</p>
   <p>J. Bogus</p>
   <p>J. Martin</p>
   <p>Attest:</p>
   <p>A. Raslavicz, Secretary.</p>
   <p>(Seal)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
