<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-04">June 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Observe Decoration Day at Cemeteries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_3_1144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-04">June 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN OBSERVE DECORATION DAY AT CEMETERIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Non-Catholic Chicago Lithuanian observed Decoration Day on Sunday, May 30, with appropriate exercises at the Lithuanian National Cemetery, which is located on Kean Avenue in Justice Park, Illinois. In spite of inclement weather, about two thousand people came to the cemetery.</p>
   <p>Mass was celebrated by Reverend B. Jankauskas (a National Catholic). Addresses were delivered by Attorney F. P. Bradchulis and Pius Grigaitis. The body of Mrs. Skinderis of Bridgeport was interred in the cemetery on that day.</p>
   <p>After the program in the cemetery was over, the people went to Leafy Grove, which is only a short distance north of the cemetery, to attend a picnic given by those Lithuanian organizations which founded the cemetery. The people enjoyed themselves there until late in the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_3_1145.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A well is being sunk in the cemetery at a cost of about one thousand dollars. Many improvements have been made in the cemetery during the past year. A number of burial lots were sold during the commemoration program.</p>
   <p>Chicago Lithuanian Catholics celebrated Decoration Day at the St. Casimir's Lithuanian Roman Catholic Cemetery, located at 11100 South Crawford Avenue (now Pulaski Road), on Monday, May 31. A large crowd, which filled the cemetery grounds, attended the exercises. High Mass was celebrated at the cemetery, and a sermon was also heard. The people sang "Diena Rusti" (It is a Wrathful Day) as they marched into the cemetery. Under the direction of Anthony Pocius, the combined choirs of all Chicago Lithuanian churches participated in the celebration of the High Mass.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
