<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1907-10-18">Oct. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Clerical Speeches</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1907-10-18">Oct. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE CLERICAL SPEECHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 6th speeches were made in the St. Michael Archangel Church hall. Rev. Steponavicia called the meeting to order, saying that on that day we had a speaker from Pennsylvania, Rev. Milukas, whose mission was to get more members for the Lithuanian Roman-Catholic Alliance of America. When the public heard such a statement, many laughed at it. Rev. Steponavicia did not like that, and said: "Do not laugh, you know what happens in my Jerusalem. Now if someone dies and they come and beg me to perform the funeral services, at once I give them the parish book, for which they must pay $25." This is really true; Rev. Steponavicia named his parish "Second Jerusalem." The difference is that Christ alone has chased out from the church hundreds of priests and grafters, while hundreds of honest Lithuanians cannot chase out only one swindler from their church.</p>
   <p>Rev. Milukas said that Lithuanians are good Christians, and how good <pb facs="5423970_2_1572.jpg" n="2"/>Christianity is. He blamed Lithuanians for denationalization, for loving a strange language, and for neglecting their own. The priest did not forget to praise himself for having attended the gymnasium for eight years. He jumped in his speech from point to point without conclusion or final statement. He denounced the Socialists for revolting against the Russian tsar's despotism. He said that the Russian government is all right, etc. Now the same hotheads come to this country, establish a newspaper, Kova (The Struggle), and fight. Fight against whom? Why, to fight against the workers themselves, because Lithuanians have no millionaires. The Jews, said the priest, can fight among themselves because they have millionaires. And the priest delivered himself of many more absurdities. Further the priest said that he would speak only to those who would join the Lithuanian Roman-Catholic Alliance; those who did not want to join the organization were asked to leave the hall. Upon leaving the hall we heard the Marseillaise. Many people outside the hall stated <pb facs="5423970_2_1573.jpg" n="3"/>that the priest was the agent of the capitalists, etc.</p>
   <p>The priest denounced his own compatriots, although this priest and every priest do not care to enlighten his ignorant patriots. The more ignorant the people are, the easier to exploit them. Why then do not the priests at such meetings discuss the opening of a good school for Lithuanians, to educate and to clear the people's mind of the hypocrisy of the clergy?</p>
   <p>Anti-Clerical.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
