<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-05-20">May 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[King Mindaugas Club Sponsors Benefit]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-05-20">May 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[KING MINDAUGAS CLUB SPONSORS BENEFIT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian King Mindaugas Club sponsored an affair with a play and a ball at the St. George School Hall on May 15, for the benefit of the same school. Dr. Pietaris' four-act drama, "The Battle of Gruenwald" was presented and songs were rendered. The drama was presented by the theatrical Birute Society; the songs were rendered by the chorus of the same Society, under the direction of Mr. M. Petrauskas.</p>
   <p>This drama can be called, without error, one of the best in our language. It portrays, beautifully and vividly, the political policy and villainy of the Poles and of Jagaila toward the Lithuanians. The drama is based on historical facts.</p>
   <p>The first and second acts present Jagaila's rooms in Cracow. Jagaila, the Lithuanian traitor, is portrayed as a half-wit and a schemer. Often, as he paces the floor, he mutters prayers and is a firm believer in the omnipotent power of his relics, of which he always carries a small sack <pb facs="5423970_2_0532.jpg" n="2"/>and which include Judas' whiskers, a murderer's nail, the skin of a rat, a piece of wax, some kind of St. Phillip's fingernails, etc. He is always thinking of them and discusses them with the Bishop. The Poles "honor" their king for such piety though they really laugh at him and despise him. But he was their only chance for success in intrigues against the Lithuanians. Since he could understand nothing and did not even know how to read, his assistant and minister, Zbignievas, performed everything and controlled everything just as he wished. As for Jadvyga (Hedwig), she abhorred and hated him dreadfully. But Zbignievas convinced her that she was the best foundation for the political fate and destiny of the Polish nation and that, without her, Poland would fall to the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>With the Knights of the Cross attacking Poland, the latter decidedly needed the assistance of the Lithuanians. But they tried to get that assistance in such a way that the Lithuanian's Vytautas' army would fight the Knights for them and that the Poles, with as little loss to <pb facs="5423970_2_0533.jpg" n="3"/>them as possible, would receive all the benefit and glory. After the two nations agreed to fight the Knights, Vytautas arrived with his army to find that the Poles were not preparing at all for battle, claiming that there was still plenty of time. Zbignievas and Jagaila had agreed to put the Lithuanians in the first lines so that they would be utterly destroyed. If, however, Vytautas were to conquer the Knights, then they too would attack the defeated Knights and would proclaim themselves the victors. Then they would be able to take a weakened Lithuania into their own hands. But Vytautas was cunning. Observing what the Poles were planning, he aroused the Knights and withdrew his army. The Knights attacked the Poles who, whether they wanted to or not, were forced to defend themselves. Later Vytautas attacked the Knights from the rear and utterly defeated them. Therefore in that manner the Lithuanians defeated the German Knights at Gruenwald, with the Poles unwillingly assisting them. (Today, however, the Poles advertise them-selves as the conquerors of the Knights.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0534.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The actors were: V. Brusokas as "Jagaila"; M. Damijonaitiene as "Jadvyga," his wife; P. Moskiene as her friend; P. Butkus as "Abignievas"; A. Zacharevicia as the Bishop; P. Stogis as "Magnatas"; A. Liutkus as "Vytautas"; J. Babicas as "Marma," his messenger and several others, Bakutis, Z. Stogis, Praninckas, Valiukas, and Grikienis in minor roles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
