<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Socialists Stage "Pirmi Zingsniai"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN SOCIALISTS STAGE "PIRMI ZINGSNIAI"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dramatic Circle of the Lithuanian Socialist League successfully staged the drama "Pirmi Zingsniai" (The First Steps) on October 17 at the Hull House theater. The plot of the play was as follows:</p>
   <p>Zvirblis, tenant farmer on the estate of Murinskis, has a daughter, Ona, with whom Enrikas, son of Murinskis, in love. Ona repulses the advances of Smitke, German foreman of Murinskis' estate. In retaliation, Smitke makes various attempts to harm the Zvirblis family and their youthful farm hand, Jonas, who is a bookworm. Jonas has been taught to read by Enrikas, who also supplies him with books.</p>
   <p>Smitke is a cruel foreman; he persecutes, exploits, and defrauds the farm workers. Murinskis subscribes to the old bourgeois theory that workers have no rights, that they must be oppressed and made to tremble in the presence of their superiors. However, he is a rather easygoing man. His son is a convert <pb facs="5423970_2_0565.jpg" n="2"/>to the new progressive ideals. He looks upon the peasants as his equals, and endeavors to help them as much as possible. Madame Murinskis subscribes to the views of her son.</p>
   <p>The drama depicts a scene from an uprising of the peasants against their masters. Slapas, a student on vacation at the home of Zvirblis, urges all the peasants to demand certain rights that have been won by peasants elsewhere, and, if necessary, to refuse to work until their demands are met. Smitke informs Murinskis of the plans of the peasants, and advises the banishment of the Zvirblis family. Murinskis learns from a neighbor that the peasants on the surrounding farms are already on strike. The landowners invite the Cossacks to suppress the peasant uprising.</p>
   <p>With Zvirblis as their spokesman, the peasants demand concessions from their master. Smitke enters the home of Murinskis through a window and steals his master's money. He blames this crime on Zvirblis, who is jailed. Murinskis <pb facs="5423970_2_0566.jpg" n="3"/>learns that the farm of his neighbor, Frick, has been ruined by the Cossacks, the buildings burned, and Frick severely beaten. Thoroughly frightened, Murinskis decides to flee, intending to leave Smitke in full charge of his estate. However, the latter resigns, and takes to flight after receiving two hundred rubles in back salary. As Smitke leaves the farm, he carries all his money in his hands and boasts to himself of his villainous deeds. His words are overheard by Jonas, who is hiding in the shrubbery with a gun, ready for the Cossacks. Jonas becomes angered, shoots Smitke, and takes all his money.</p>
   <p>The Cossacks arrive; they plunder and destroy everything, and severely beat Murinskis. His son admonishes his father for his mistakes, and succeeds in persuading him to release Zvirblis. Finally, Enrikas receives his father's permission to marry Ona; his father deeds the farm to him, and the drama ends with the following words of Enrikas: "Long live the brotherhood of man, of understanding, and of liberty!"</p>
   <p>The drama had a pleasing effect upon the audience. It is really a very <pb facs="5423970_2_0567.jpg" n="4"/>beautiful and intelligently written play. It is entirely free from superfluous expressions, and everything is properly timed and arranged to suit each character. Every character honestly adheres to his or her ideals, and departs from them only when forced to do so by unfavorable circumstances. The theme and plot of the play are carefully based on real life, and are developed with properly selected and well-conceived characters. In a word, the whole drama is very vivid and effective.</p>
   <p>Most of the players performed their roles well, and were well fitted for them. Mr. Strazdas (who played the role of Frick) and Miss Pakas (who played the role of Mrs. Zvirblis) were unsuited to the parts they played. The following players rendered splendid performances: B. Vaitekunas (Murinskis), Mr. Briedis (Zvirblis), J. Levanas (Smitke), A. Zagaras (Enrikas), J. Stankunas (Jonas), Miss K. Makas, J. Bruzas, and Miss A. Zemaitis. The most outstanding players were B. Vaitiekunas, Mr. Briedis, and Mr. Levanas. A. Zagaras lacked enthusiasm where it was mostly needed. Mr. Vaitiekunas is unquestionably a real dramatic artist.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0568.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The prompter spoke so loudly that at times it was possible to hear him even in the balcony. It is hoped that in future performances the Dramatic Circle will avoid this mistake. Furthermore, the intermissions between acts were entirely too long.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the performance, Bruno Vargsas, the author of the drama, was greeted by the audience with great enthusiasm; he answered two curtain calls.</p>
   <p>The Dramatic Circle will stage another drama, "Alkani Zmones" (Hungry People), on November 1, at the same theater. This drama was written by K. Jasukaitis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
