<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 44,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Socialist Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 44,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN SOCIALIST ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago there is a large number of Lithuanians who carry on various activities. Societies consisting of enlightened members arrange lectures for the benefit of mankind; societies, consisting mostly of ignorant members, have as their aim banquets and drinks. Such societies give a medal to anyone who can dance the best; the church societies give a medal to the one who kneels the best in church. Such societies and their donated medals make no progress.</p>
   <p>It was announced that the Aurora Society has arranged a number of lectures to be delivered this fall. Those who attend these lectures will learn something.</p>
   <p>No matter what activities are there, we are lacking one thing: a Lithuanian library. Branch 4 of the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance for the last six months has been discussing the necessity of a Lithuanian library. I must mention that branch 4 of the Lithuanian Socialists already has $75 for a Lithuanian library.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0789.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On November 10, 1907, at Freihet Turner Hall, 3417 S. Halsted St., there will be a banquet for the benefit of the library. Therefore, the Lithuanians are invited to come to this banquet to help us make some profit, which will be used for establishing the library.</p>
   <p>Before the library is established it will take time, although we need at present to discuss the problems of Socialism. Branch 4 of the Lithuanian Alliance of America has decided to have discussions two times a month: on the first and third Sundays of the month. The lectures will be held at Radavicius Hall on 33rd Street near the St. George's church. Those who will have a Socialist pin will pay no admission; without the Socialist pin, socialist or not, one must pay five cents admission.</p>
   <p>A. Zimontas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
