<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">They Talk about it Everywhere</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0995</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0995.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THEY TALK ABOUT IT EVERYWHERE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Naujienos reporter informed us that lively talk about Naujienos is going on all over Chicago. No matter where he went, he heard the people talking about his paper, and it seemed that it is the most important subject in daily conversation. Draugas (Friend), a Catholic daily, and its followers became inflamed recently over the Naujienos. Our newspaper is being studied very carefully and is closely followed by all Lithuanian newspapers, especially Draugas, which is interested mostly in Naujienos' policies and its attitude towards the Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>Draugas does not like the title of Naujienos (News) because this Catholic paper has a column called "News." The editor of Draugas will have to change the name of this column to something else, so that it will not look like Naujienos.</p>
   <p>The editor of Lietuva, Mr. Balutis, and his staff are talking and arguing <pb facs="5423970_2_0996.jpg" n="2"/>about the Naujienos and its followers. At one of the regular meetings Mr. Balutis, editor of Lietuva, was shedding tears whenever the name of Naujienos was mentioned.</p>
   <p>He did not have much use for the Naujienos, because it is a Socialist paper. He is a strong nationalist. As such he supports the national movement and for that reason strongly opposes Naujienos and its supporters.</p>
   <p>The editor of Katalikas (Catholic) and his staff told one another not to mention the name of Naujienos. It seems that everybody is afraid of Naujienos for some unknown reason. It is not clear whether they are afraid of Naujienos or whether they are jealous because Naujienos is a better newspaper and has a better staff of writers, and even a better manager. This may be the reason why they are raising so much rumpus against the Naujienos. The only reason we see for raising this rumpus <pb facs="5423970_2_0997.jpg" n="3"/>is that they are afraid of clean competition. They have a fear that Naujienos may kill all other papers. We believe that able writers and the managers of the papers shouldn't be afraid of a little competition. All editors, the enemies of Naujienos, are wrathful; they are planning to get together and console each other by calling all the professional people to discuss some things which haven't been yet discussed at previous gatherings. The main topic of discussion, as we understand, will be the Naujienos. What their decision will be we don't know; but we feel that they will put up a big fight against us.</p>
   <p>At the labor meetings, the people were speaking with great joy about their newspaper Naujienos, while editors of other papers and their supporters are mourning about the doom of their newspapers, for they have outlived their time and the end is coming soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
