<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-05-11">May 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Biruta Society Stages Melodrama</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-05-11">May 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTA SOCIETY STAGES MELODRAMA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been a long time since the Lithuanians of Chicago have had such a treat for their emotions, their eyes, and their ears as they enjoyed last Sunday. The Biruta Music and Dramatic Society staged one of the finest Lithuanian plays, the well-known two-act melodrama "Biruta" [name of a fourteenth-century Lithuanian duchess and mother of Vytautas the Great], under the direction of Mikas Petrauskas.</p>
   <p>The performance was a success in every respect. The players, singers, and musicians did not disappoint the public, and the public, in turn, did not disappoint the sponsors of the program, since a capacity crowd witnessed the performance.</p>
   <p>The leading role was enacted by Miss Marion Rakauskas, who has been entertaining Chicagoans with her beautiful voice for the past three years. She was exceptionally good in this role, which she performed with such meticulous care and with such feeling that the audience literally went wild with enthusiasm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It probably would not be an exaggeration to say that this performance of the melodrama "Biruta" was the best ever given in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The supporting cast consisted of the following Chicago Lithuanians: K. Sarpalius and J. Stankus as the brothers of Biruta; J. Vaitekunas as the father of Biruta; J. Jakutis as Zundsteinas; Misses L. Zilvitis, A. Zemaitis, and S. Stanulis as the vestal virgins.</p>
   <p>The songs of the vestal virgins and the ceremonies around the sacred fire created a very deep impression upon the audience. Many remarked that the scenes made them feel as though they were really witnessing and living the history of Lithuania five hundred years ago. It was not a long play, and when it came to an end the audience was so pleased with the performance that everyone felt like seeing it all over again, and was reluctant to leave the hall.</p>
   <p>For such a wonderful performance, the Biruta Society and its director, Mr. P. Sarpalius, deserve a real word of thanks. The Biruta Chorus has made great <pb facs="5423970_2_0367.jpg" n="3"/>progress, and is now unquestionably one of the best Lithuanian choral groups in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
