<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Notice to the Chicago Lithuanian Business and Professional Men</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. J. Baciunas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NOTICE TO THE CHICAGO LITHUANIAN BUSINESS AND PROFESSIONAL MEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. J. Baciunas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are preparing to publish the Lithuanian Business Guide. The purpose of this publication is to put the names of all Lithuanian business and professional men of Chicago in one book. Even though the number of Lithuanian businessmen of Chicago is larger than that of any other Lithuanian colony in America, for some reason they have no guide book of their own. When the need arises, a person can find the names and addresses of Lithuanian business or professional men and could go to one of his own nationality for business or advice, whereas often he now goes to a stranger. Frequently a Lithuanian asks a Lithuanian saloon keeper where he might find a Lithuanian doctor, drug store, real-estate man, bank, store or another saloon, only to find that the saloon keeper himself does not know. The person <pb facs="5423970_2_1208.jpg" n="2"/>seeking information might have heard or might have a vague idea that the one he is seeking lives somewhere around a certain corner. Then, willy-nilly, he must go for advice to a stranger, with whom he can hardly hold conversation for lack of knowledge of the English language. It is to fill in this gap that the guide will be published.</p>
   <p>In order to make the guide complete, every Lithuanian business and professional man should submit his name. The advantage will be not only to Lithuanian workers but also to professional and business men as well. In addition, the guide will include a section on general information wherein every Lithuanian will be able to find many valuable hints for which he may have need in his daily life. When published, the guide will be given to every Lithuanian free, and businessmen will distribute them among their customers. The guide will be published in the latter part of December. For any information, call J. J. Baciunas, 2511 West 45th Place, Chicago, not later than the first of December.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
