<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 13,
<date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Aurora's Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 13,
<date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE AURORA'S CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Aurora Society held its concert last Saturday evening, May 16, at the Meldazis Hall on the West Side. Five well-known Lithuanian choirs participated in the concert that evening: The Lithuanian National Choir Birute, the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance Local 81st Choir, the Progressive Youth Choir, the Ruta (Rue) Choir, and the Lithuanian Socialist Men's Choir. The Lithuanian band Lietuva furnished the music at the concert.</p>
   <p>Various prizes were given to the best students from the Aurora School, located at 30th and Halsted Sts. The concert was followed by an entertainment and dance. The audience, which was unusually large, was well pleased with the program.</p>
   <p>We want to mention the names of the students who received prizes for their good work at school. Seven men and two girls received prizes at the concert.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The names of the students who received prizes are as follow: Theodore Daugenas and Zenonas Stogis received a prize for mechanical drawing; George Ziuzda received a prize for being the best student in algebra. T. Daugenas, Miss Salome Stasiukyte and Miss Elizabeth Petronyte received prizes for being the best students in arithmetic; Anthony Zilvitis, John Viackis, Charles Baltas, Victor Balciunas and Miss Elizabeth Petronyte received prizes for being the best students in the English language.</p>
   <p>Thus the Aurora School ended its session.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
