<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"Wreath of Myrtle" on the Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"WREATH OF MYRTLE" ON THE STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the night before last A. Vitkauskas' theatrical company presented J. Zulavskis' four act drama, "Wreath of Myrtle," on the stage of the Hull House Theater.</p>
   <p>It had been advertised that the play would be presented "according to the system of the Moscow Theater." Though the presentation was far from that, the acting was wonderful. A. Vitkauskas, himself, and other distinguished Chicago artists were in the cast. The acting was better than Chicagoans have ever had an opportunity of witnessing before.</p>
   <p>The most important characters in the play are Vladas and Janina. A. Vitkauskas played the role of Vladas and performed it beautifully. Miss Zilvitis performed the role of Janina perfectly. She entered into the character which the role demanded and did not leave it during any part of the play.</p>
   <p>The other actors also played well. S. Valancauskas gave a good performance in <pb facs="5423970_2_0212.jpg" n="2"/>the role of Edward, though he is new to the stage. The mother (Miss I. Aleksandravicius) was well acted, as were the parts of old laborer (Sirvinskas) and the father (B. Vaitekunas). Robert, played by J. Sankunas, was somewhat less convincing.</p>
   <p>If there were shortcomings, they disappeared in the acting in general, and the whole play left a very good impression. Only the make-up was bad.</p>
   <p>During the intermissions Mr. A. Pocius played the organ.</p>
   <p>The audience was small--much smaller than had been expected. Perhaps the system of advertising does not meet with the approval of the public. But the audience which did attend was a select one. Almost all the [Lithuanian] businessmen and professional men of Chicago were present.</p>
   <p>A. Vitkauskas' visit to Chicago will not go for naught. He will give the <pb facs="5423970_2_0213.jpg" n="3"/>Lithuanians something new, and perhaps will be successful in reviving the recently dormant theater of the Lithuanians in Chicago. It is to be hoped that he will succeed in accomplishing this. Lovers of the theater should help him in this work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
