<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Book of Naujienos</title> Vol. I, No. 6, 6:1, Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>,
<title level="a"/>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0993</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0993.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Book of Naujienos</title> Vol. I, No. 6, 6:1, Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1914-04-01">April 1, 1914</date>,
<title level="a"/>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There won't be any more young Lithuania editor even before the paper had started to exist. The death of this paper is due to the poor management of the man who succeeded me as editor of the young Lithuanian. This newspaper could have existed if it were managed by a capable editor who knows something about the news business and knows the psychology of the people who read the newspapers. Moreover, an editor must be a broad minded individual who understands the philosophy of life and not a fanatic who looks at the world through the key-hole and sees only a very small portion of the world in which we live. An editor must widen the horizon of knowledge, and enliven the spirit of the people and at the same time he must be a civic leader in the community in which he lives. Instead of widening the spiritual field of the people, the present editor was narrowing it and keeping the people in a state of ignorance. It is a deplorable situation which exists at the present time among our people. The people, as yet, cannot differentiate between two different editors; one who has not made any spiritual progress and the one who has made such spiritual and has a clear understanding of the world's progress and knows the philosophy of life. At the present time, we cannot even dream of uplifting the courage of our spirit and deepening our thoughts, because, the time has not come for a young spirit to take its <pb facs="5423970_2_0994.jpg" n="2"/>place in this world, because the old spirit of the world is still predominating. Therefore, we cannot have an editor with a young spirit at the present time and we have to be contented with an editor of the old spirit.</p>
   <p>It appears that the Young Lithuania newspaper will continue to be called Young Lithuania, as I understand. This newspaper has a very small number of readers and its name reminds me only of bitter memories. As a past editor of the Young Lithuania I feel deeply hurt to see such a fine newspaper go out of existence. I am fulfilling my last duty and recalling all invitations from writers and those who co-operated with me while I was editor of the Young Lithuania. I hope that in the future the world will become more idealistic and will understand each other mush better.</p>
   <p>Kleofas Jurgelionis, past editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
