<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-19">Dec. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Birute Is Waiting for You</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Pranas Butkus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-19">Dec. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTE IS WAITING FOR YOU</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Pranas Butkus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his article "Concerning Our Theaters" in a recent issue of Lietuva, S.F.Z. writes about Chicago Lithuanian theatrical societies. He made the suggestion that all the Chicago Lithuanian theatrical societies should organize themselves into one strong organization; and he says further that sooner or later this will come about because the public, and the art and the business affairs of the theatrical societies are all forcing them to do it.</p>
   <p>Sorry that Mr. S.F.Z. did not appear three years ago with his honest suggestions. At that time the musical and dramatic society Birute of Chicago was trying its best to organize all the Lithuanian theatrical societies into one Lithuanian theatrical society, not simply of Chicago, but of the United States. The Birute society not only spent several dollars at that time, but also much time and energy in that cause. It called two meetings of the theatrical societies of Chicago, and also prepared the rules for the Drama Societies Association. But all this work has gone for nothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0431.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the first meeting we noticed that our youth is not yet ready for such an achievement. I remember very well that there came to this meeting some people who were not simply representatives of organizations; these people came to do harm, or to mock. But the Birute Society did not give up the idea. At many other meetings this problem was discussed. A committee was even selected so that, if the opportunity came, it could bring up the question publicly.</p>
   <p>When the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association was organized two years ago, the Birute Society thought that many Lithuanian theatrical societies would join this organization. It would then have been possible to organize within this Association a nationalistic art branch, and the results which Mr. S.F.Z. seeks in his article would have been secured. In such an organization, as in the arms of a real mother, it could have been understood that we are brothers and sisters of one and the same idea--that we are workers in the field of national culture, working cordially together to help each other for the benefit of the national cause in order that this important work of art should be of benefit, not only to ourselves, but to the public as well. Therefore, the Birute Society is waiting <pb facs="5423970_2_0432.jpg" n="3"/>for you,--you that are of the same idea--to come to our Association! Here among us, you will find that our, and the national idea are the same.</p>
   <p>It is known from the newspaper announcements that the second convention of the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association will be held on January 18, 1914 in Aurora Hall. Therefore, Lithuanian theatrical societies of Chicago, elect your delegates and send them to this convention. By joining the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association, we will with open arms to work with you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
