<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Jaunimas Lithuanian Basket-Ball League Flooded with Entries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1585</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1585.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">JAUNIMAS LITHUANIAN BASKET-BALL LEAGUE FLOODED WITH ENTRIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4...........Our announcement in the last issue of the Jaunimas about the Chicago Lithuanian Basket-Ball League met with unexpected interest on the part of leading Lithuanian teams from all over the city. The interest shown in this league proves that the young Lithuanians are willing and ready to make themselves known, but have had no one to champion their cause. Jaunimas is taking upon themselves this great responsibility of furthering the cause of our Lithuanians American youth in the field of sports. What response we will get from the older Lithuanians in the way of support remains to be seen. Whether the present existing Lithuanian American Sports Committee, Lithuanian radio hours, and the daily Lithuanian press will go along with the Lithuanian-American youth or continue to ignore the urgent need of Lithuanian sponsorship remains to be seen.</p>
   <p>All entries for the basket-ball league definitely close on Wednesday, Dec. 23, 1936. On this date a managers meeting will take place at the home of Jaunimas sports <pb facs="5423970_2_1586.jpg" n="2"/>editor, Jack L. Juozaitis, 6822 South Rockwell Street. A list of players along with the $5.00 fee must be in the hands of the committee on or before 9:00 P.M. that evening.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt Furniture Company, John T. Zuris Boosters and the Bridgeport Knights of Lithuania were among the first teams to enter. Later requests for entering were received from the West Side Lithuanian Club, Brighton Park Knights of Lithuania, Chicago Lithuanian Youth Society, Holy Name and five other teams whose entries will be considered.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
