<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, Vol. VI,
<date when="1925-01-13">Jan. 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Proletarian Art Appearing in Vilnis Every Second Tuesday from Central Bureau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, Vol. VI,
<date when="1925-01-13">Jan. 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">PROLETARIAN ART APPEARING IN VILNIS EVERY SECOND TUESDAY FROM CENTRAL BUREAU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The time set for the election of the officers of the Central Bureau of Administration is at its close. Have all branches, such as choirs, dramatic clubs, circles, and "The Bud of Flower Society," voted in this election? If not, do so, as the Central Bureau wants to publish the correct and actual report.</p>
   <p>The new songs are ready. Each choir affiliated with the Arts Alliance, which paid its annual dues for 1924, will receive these new songs entirely free. Distribution of these songs will start within two weeks, but if secretaries of choirs, etc., have given their correct addresses to the Central Bureau and the songs are not received by January 24, write to the Central Bureau about it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Budding Flower of Youth Society" members belonging to the American-Lithuanian Alliance of Proletarian Art, will receive free a copy of the theatrical play, "The Winner is Labor." They will also receive a few copies of the new songs. This theatrical play is not hard to learn. Additional books of this play are 30c each.</p>
   <p>To theatrical clubs or dramatic circles we can give nothing at present. We have tried hard to prepare some plays, but for certain reasons we were unable to publish them.</p>
   <p>For the following season we will have a whole line of very good and nice plays, as friends of "Letpropoets" (Lithuanian Proletarian Poets) have sent us a whole bunch of dramas and comedies in Russian, part of which the Central Bureau has decided to translate, and about mid-summer we will try to publish them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0251.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Central Bureau was unable to function properly because last year was a year of organization. The program for the year of 1925 will be published later. The Central Bureau is ready with new plays and a better fundamental study of proletarian art for the year of 1925. It is also ready to bring proletarian art into life, and by this to wage a bitter struggle against the "white" art. The Bureau anticipates the increase of membership in our Alliance.</p>
   <p>The next issue of Vilnis will be very interesting. Everyone should read our publications. In this issue will be published articles of prominent writers, such as V. Zalionis and P. Aushrotas, from Russia. Other friends of our Alliance are invited to write to our publications.</p>
   <p>(signed) J. Pakaushis</p>
   <p>10831 Indiana Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
