<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-04-25">Apr. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[History of Lithuania Published]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-04-25">Apr. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[HISTORY OF LITHUANIA PUBLISHED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. J. Sliupas has written a book dealing with the age of the rule of Polish nobility in Lithuania (1569-1795), and the statutes of King Zigmontas I. The book was published by Lietuva and is very important for Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>It is essential that everyone should know the history of his country. Many of us do not know the history of our own fatherland; we do not know the great men, the generals, and the political events of the past. For example, a stranger may ask a Lithuanian about his nation's past history, about the time when Lithuania was independent, how large the country was, etc. In such a case, a Lithuanian could not answer the questions because he does not know his own history. Even when his children ask about the past history of Lithuania, the father cannot give the information to his children, because the father does not know himself. Every Lithuanian should know who were the "Washingtons" and "Lincolns" in Lithuanian history.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1212.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In this book, the reader will find many facts of great importance. He will find that the Catholic religion was one of the basic causes of the downfall of Poland and her province, Lithuania. He will read about the greatness of Lithuania when she was under the rule of her own dukes.</p>
   <p>It has been stated that Lithuania became practically a province of Poland. At the Lublin (city) convention it was stated, that "free with free, equal with equal"--Lithuanians and Poles have united.</p>
   <p>But during the past two hundred years, the Lithuanian statutes vanished. And at last, at the fourth convention, the administrative statute of Lithuania was abolished, and Lithuania was taken over under absolute Polish control. This is a critical period of the history of Lithuania. The people of Lithuania had no voice, the clergy and nobility were "polanized," and at last they repudiated their own (Lithuanian) nationality. This was one of the great causes of the downfall of the independence of Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1213.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the end of the book, you will find the Lithuanian Statute of Zigmontas the First. It is very important to know the rights and the laws that Lithuanians had at that time. The book contains 552 pages, 6x9; paper covers--$1.50; cloth covers--$2.00.</p>
   <p>A. Olszewski</p>
   <p>3252 South Halsted Street</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
