<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-06">Jan. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Conservatory of Music Students' Concert</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0311</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0311.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-06">Jan. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN CONSERVATORY OF MUSIC STUDENTS' CONCERT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday the students of the Lithuanian Conservatory gave a concert at St. George's Parish Hall. The program consisted of twenty-eight numbers. One was especially interesting and highly effective. It was given by the children, whose ages ran from five to twelve years. Their technique was excellent. The instructor, Mr. Mikas Petrauskas, has devoted much time and energy to teaching these children, as is shown by their fine musical technique. The young pianists were Miss Anna Mazeikis, Anton Olszewski, Alex Bijanskas, and the children of Dr. A. L. Graiciunas.</p>
   <p>Kazys Jakubkas played two violin compositions of Mr. Petrauskas, "Zilvitis" (The Willow) and "Oi Tu Jieva" (O, Bird-Cherry Tree). Miss Sophia Olsevskis and Miss Antigona Dundulis also played well. Mr. Bigelis played the andante <pb facs="5423970_2_0312.jpg" n="2"/>and presto movements of one of Bach's masterpieces.</p>
   <p>The instrumentalists were Mr. H. Mockus--trombone, Petras Grazulis and Juozas Balakas--clarinet. Mr. Juozas Balakas played Moszkowski's "Serenade", and Vienazindis' (pen name of Mikas Petrauskas) "Polka" excellently.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stogis has a splendid bass voice. If he does not neglect his training, he should became a fine singer. Mr. Mikas Dudas has a fine baritone voice, and he had a good opportunity to show the quality of it.</p>
   <p>Miss Anna Balaiciute sang the "Flower Song" from Faust beautifully.</p>
   <p>Miss Malvina Horodeckis was the star of the evening. She sang only one song, Schubert's "Serenade". I have heard the same song sung by Sembrich and by Schumann-Heink, but when I heard it sung in Lithuanian, I found new beauty in it. Miss Horodeckis is the rising star among Lithuanian singers. The final number was given by a quartet, composed of Miss Jaskevicius, Miss O. Balcaitis, Mr. Kasputis and Mr. Dudas. They sang an aria from Verdi's "Rigoletto".</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0313.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Some Lithuanians are bringing honor to the name of Lithuania in science, politics, literature and art--but Mr. Mikas Petrauskas, the foremost Lithuanian musician, brings the name of Lithuania into the musical world. It is a great honor to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
