<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Newspaper Organ</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1001</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1001.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEWSPAPER ORGAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every progressive society ought to have its own organ, which would contain all important society's decisions, proposals and the addresses of the officials. The people could thus find the necessary information when needed. The organ is as important to a society as the blood is to the body. The organ gives life to the society just as blood gives life to the body. A society without a newspaper is like a body without a head. A newspaper helps a society to expand and grow larger. It binds the members of the society into one body and helps to maintain harmony among its members. It enlightens the members and reports to them daily events; helps arouse their interest and inspires them to work more ardently for the benefit of the society.</p>
   <p>Let us have a lesson from the past in the tailor strikes. Let us see what happened. The unions were organized for the benefit of workers in the tailoring industry, helping them fight for better working <pb facs="5423970_2_1002.jpg" n="2"/>conditions and better wages. The tailors' union organization movement was great, interesting and beneficial to the workers. It concerned not only the tailors but workers in other industries as well. The tailors at the time had no newspaper of their own. What happened then? The local newspapers did not help workers in their struggle for bettering conditions; did not make favorable reports on their activities, as to whether they gained or lost their battle in the struggle for existence; never gave a single word of encouragement.</p>
   <p>Not only did these local newspapers fail to help the workers, but they presented things in a different light from what they really were.</p>
   <p>If the tailors' union had had its own newspaper organ, this paper would not only have defended them but it would have made suggestions for winning sooner and with much less expense.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1003.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Today the tailors have realized the importance of having their own newspaper, and all the members of local unions decided to accept Naujienos as their official organ. The Naujienos will make every effort to help and defend the cause, not only of one union, but of all unions. The Naujienos is the first Lithuanian weekly newspaper which will help the Lithuanian workers' union in its struggle for bettering working conditions and demanding better wages.</p>
   <p>Looking at this situation from the business standpoint, we may explain it as follows: The Naujienos will accept in its organization those unions which have accepted Naujienos as their official organ and will give them cheaper rates on the advertisements, and may be for nothing to its members, and will not neglect the affairs of other societies.</p>
   <p>We advise those societies which have no newspaper of their own to accept the Naujienos as their official organ, and the Naujienos will take good care to help those societies that belong to Naujienos organization. The societies that are willing to join our organization may <pb facs="5423970_2_1004.jpg" n="4"/>apply at the Naujienos printing establishment which is located at 18th St. and Halsted St.</p>
   <p>The News Administration Department.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
