<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Evening School of Women's Educational Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-02-12">Feb. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">EVENING SCHOOL OF WOMEN'S EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The evening school of the Lithuanian Women's Educational Society is progressing very satisfactorily. The school is being conducted in the field house of Mark White Square, which is located on the corner of 29th and Halsted Streets.</p>
   <p>The following subjects are taught at the school this year:</p>
   <p>Sewing: Every Tuesday evening. This class is divided into three branches: Fundamentals of sewing, fancy sewing, and all kinds of knitting work. The class is being attended by about thirty women and girls. The teacher of this class is a specialist with long experience in this line of work.</p>
   <p>English language: Classes in reading and writing in the English language are held on Wednesday and Friday evenings of every week. About twenty students attend this class. The teacher of this class is a famous authoress of textbooks for immigrants, for the study of the English language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1310.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Home economics: On Thursday evenings there is a class in cooking, now to keep a home clean and healthy, etc. More than forty students attend this class.</p>
   <p>Non-members as well as members of the Society can join and attend the classes free of charge. More details about the classes can be had by applying at the school or from any member of the Society.</p>
   <p>All the students are showing a great interest in their studies. The number of students is constantly growing. The school offers an excellent opportunity for Lithuanian women and girls to obtain valuable knowledge about important matters pertaining to their daily life without charge. We should not ignore this opportunity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
