<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-29">Oct. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">First Lithuanian Theatrical Company Goes into Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-29">Oct. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST LITHUANIAN THEATRICAL COMPANY GOES INTO ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recently organized Lithuanian Theatrical Company will present its first vaudeville show on Saturday, October 30, at the Lithuania Theater, 3214 South Halsted Street. This Company is probably the first Lithuanian theatrical company in America. It was organized several weeks ago. Members of the Company are Mr. H. Mockus, Mr. I. Pakalniskis, and Mr. V. Kundrotas. This Company differs from all other Lithuanian-American theatrical or dramatic societies in that it is organized entirely on a business basis for profit. Its purpose is to organize and conduct a permanent and continuous Lithuanian vaudeville theater.</p>
   <p>The first show of the Company will consist of a play entitled "As Numiriau" (I Died). Besides this play, the program will include songs, monologues, and other numbers that are usually seen in vaudeville shows. As an added attraction a motion picture entitled "Brolis Pries Broli" (Brother Against Brother), which pertains to the present European War, will be shown to the <pb facs="5423970_2_0217.jpg" n="2"/>audience between acts. On the following day, Sunday, the stage show will be the same but there will be a different motion picture.</p>
   <p>Various departments of the Company are now being organized. Mr. B. Vaitekunas, popular Lithuanian-American actor, has been placed in charge of the dramatic department; Mr. Peter Sarpalius, Lithuanian-American musical composer, has been placed in charge of the music department; Mr. Vincent Brusokas, popular Lithuanian-American comedian who has been entertaining Chicago Lithuanian audiences in the role of "Stepukas" (Little Stephen), has been placed in charge of the department of monologues and other short subjects.</p>
   <p>For the time being the Company plans to give only two shows per week, on Saturdays and Sundays. Later, after Thanksgiving Day (November 25), it is planned to give four shows per week if the Company is showered with success. The main worry of the Company is a shortage of good Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_2_0218.jpg" n="3"/>actors and actresses. Mr. Mockus stated that if a sufficient number of Lithuanian actors and actresses could have been found the Company would have decided to open the theater with four shows (four days) per week.</p>
   <p>The members of the Company are confident that Lithuanian-Americans will appreciate and support the efforts to establish the first Lithuanian theater in America. Mr. Mockus, who is the president of the Company, stated that the success of the theater depends entirely upon the support of the Chicago Lithuanian public. Mr. Mockus also stated that he does not see any reason why a Lithuanian theater should not be as successful as the American theaters. He believes that Lithuanian theaters in America can reach a high state of development.</p>
   <p>The Company will make an effort to locate and enlist all the best dramatic talent among Lithuanians in America. It is believed that this is a good opportunity for a number of talented Lithuanian-Americans to develop into highly paid theatrical artists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0219.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Lithuanian theatrical artists, and those who know of such talent, are invited to write to the Company. Address all communications to Mr. H. Mockus, Lithuania Theater, 3214 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
