<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 17,
<date when="1901-04-26">April 26, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Forgotten Project</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 17,
<date when="1901-04-26">April 26, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE FORGOTTEN PROJECT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago Mr. Sabonis announced a proposition in Lietuva that while the Lithuanians are celebrating their name day, it would be very good to donate or make a collection of funds for national affairs. Even though the proposition was brought up a long time ago, it has very few supporters and it is very important. If the Lithuanians at their name day banquets would use less beer, say one glass of beer, and donate the money for national affairs, this would uplift the Lithuanians culturally. For lack of money, the Lithuanian culture is lagging behind. Here in America nobody stops us from having our own national schools, and yet we have made no effort to have such schools. True, there are a few Lithuanian schools, but these schools make more damage than good for the national cause. The Lithuanian schools in America are our most important national affair. If at the name day banquets, each of us would donate five cents for the schools, we would collect enough money to establish not one, but many. To establish the Lithuanian schools, it is the duty of every Lithuanian to join this great cause!</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1383.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides that we must not forget our brothers in our Fatherland, especially the Lithuanian martyrs who are exiled in the depths of Russia for the cause of Lithuanianism and for spreading enlightenment among the ignorant people. Do not forget that many of the exiled Lithuanians are starving, living in misery, while we are celebrating our name day. We should not forget to make collections for our exiled brothers, to show them that we are remembering their great deeds for the cause of Lithuanian culture. When they will come back from exile to the Fatherland, they will work again with greater energy in order to uplift our brothers from lethargy. The proposition of Mr. Sabonis ought to be supported by all: by worker, priest, lawyer and doctor. Because the Russian government disregards classes and professions it exiles everyone who wants to enlighten his ignorant brother.</p>
   <p>I am supporting the project and my birthday being on the 19th of April,</p>
   <p>I am donating 50 cents for our martyrs. Who will be the next?</p>
   <p>Jurgis Tumosa.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
