<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-12">Jan. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal in Behalf of Lithuanian Library</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0761</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0761.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-12">Jan. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL IN BEHALF OF LITHUANIAN LIBRARY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3....We all have heard many times about the existence of the Lithuanian Library and Reading Room in Roseland, Ill. Many of us have visited the library and derived more or less benefit from it.</p>
   <p>Hence, it should be important for us to learn with what purpose and under what conditions the library was organized and sustained.</p>
   <p>It will soon be two years since the library was established under the name of "Ausra"(The Dawn), at 10090 S.Michigan Ave., on top of Baker's Pharmacy. The idea was originated by a group of young Lithuanian men and businessmen with the most lofty intentions. They hoped that the establishment and maintenance of this idea would become an obligation of local organizations and individuals.</p>
   <p>Much time has passed, but local organizations have shown very little interest in the library. The library, having many expenses, allowing readers to read the <pb facs="5423970_2_0762.jpg" n="2"/>books gratis, and without support from organizations, was unable to maintain itself. Therefore, in order to provide at least some income for the continuance of the library it was decided to conduct evening classes of instruction in the study of the English and Lithuanian languages. The classes attracted a large following and provided sufficient income to pay all expenses and conduct a splendid library. But with the advent of the present hard times the number of students has greatly diminished and the income is now insufficient to cover expenses. Therefore, the library cannot exist any longer, because it is unable to make ends meet.</p>
   <p>The founders of the library, those who have established it on non-partisan lines for the benefit of all Lithuanians, hereby make another appeal to local organizations and individuals to come forward and make a united effort to save the library. All societies are requested to discuss this important matter at their meetings and select delegates to attend a general conference which will be called shortly to decide whether or not the library is to remain open. It is hoped that the heads of our organizations will not fail to heed this appeal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
