<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 24,
<date when="1905-06-16">June 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Lithuanian Businessmen of America of the Lithuanian Company Zvaigzde (The Star)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 24,
<date when="1905-06-16">June 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE LITHUANIAN BUSINESSMEN OF AMERICA OF THE LITHUANIAN COMPANY ZVAIGZDE (THE STAR)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the Lithuanian businessmen will be held on June 18, 1905, at Joseph Kuzsleika Hall, 4558 S. Paulina St., Chicago. The meeting will begin at 4 P. M.</p>
   <p>There will be speeches. Among the speakers will be not only famous Lithuanians, well known among their own people, but Lithuanians considered eloquent businessmen by Americans. This convention will show the position occupied by business and commerce in human affairs; also that we Lithuanians must participate in them for the welfare and advancement of our people. The commercial standard of the nation is judged by the ability of the people to conduct the business of the nation.</p>
   <p>This meeting is called by the Lithuanian corporation The Star, which <pb facs="5423970_2_0098.jpg" n="2"/>has a capital of $50,000 and has the largest Lithuanian store in Chicago, located at 4605-07 South Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Besides the speeches at this convention, the general condition of this corporation and its assets will be presented to its members. We invite all Lithuanians to come to this meeting. Those who wish to join this corporation will have a chance to buy shares.</p>
   <p>In the name of the corporation,</p>
   <p>J. Varkala,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
   <p>Extracts from the by-laws of the corporation, Star: Lithuanians only and those of Lithuanian descent who speak Lithuanian may be stockholders of this corporation. All mutual affairs and meetings must be conducted in the Lithuanian language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The price per share is $10. Every member of this corporation can buy not more than $5,000 worth of shares. The corporation guarantees from 5 to 25% or more profit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
