<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Radio Tantrums</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">RADIO TANTRUMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Margutis (Easter Egg) finally got that afternoon hour on WIND Station Sundays. The time is 2:15 P.M.</p>
   <p>Now for a little lambasting:</p>
   <p>First to be dragged over coals is Charles Stephens. His English accent certainly ruins our beautiful mother tongue, while his program's Kalbancios Zinios (Speaking News) has deteriorated to something between a news broadcast and the march of time. The irritatingly sung theme songs also drag their weary way before and after each program. How about trying a little humming of the tune? On the whole, the program, instead of improving, has at times slipped below the average of the first new programs.</p>
   <p>Next on the pan is our young M.C. Paul Saltimieras. Instead of shedding tears over his elegant reading of the death-notice, listeners laugh with <pb facs="5423970_2_1258.jpg" n="2"/>glee. You have heard of professional mourners being hired for funerals, haven't you? We nominate Saltimieras for first place in the professional mourners' ranks. Boy, how Vytantas Farutis has been affected by his professional standing! You should hear the sacrilege he commits by singing Lithuanian folksongs swing style and with his own variations. Recommended: Keep the simple Lithuanian folk-songs simple.</p>
   <p>A little praise:</p>
   <p>To "Margutis" for the variety on his programs. Legal advice, medical advice, various speakers, and the better recordings all go to make a better Lithuanian radio program.</p>
   <p>To Paul Saltimieras for keeping up the quality of the musical portions of his programs. Although the "ensemble" at times sounds as though it needs a good deal of practicing, it is still a pleasure to know that musicians are actually being employed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1259.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To Sophie Barcus for her early morning broadcasting on WGES. The other programs are still so-so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
