<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians Participate in Anti-Tuberculosis Drive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS PARTICIPATE IN ANTI-TUBERCULOSIS DRIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Chicago Tuberculosis Institute has completed arrangements to hold a gigantic educational exhibit on tuberculosis, from January 15 to January 29, at the Mark White Square field house, which is located in Bridgeport, at 29th and South Halsted Streets..... The importance of this anti-tuberculosis drive lies in the fact that during the year 1914 as many as 3,895 people died from the disease in Chicago."</p>
   <p>"Two of the days of the exhibit, namely, Thursday January 21 and Friday January 22, have been allotted to the Lithuanians. A Lithuanian committee has been selected to take charge of the exhibit during the above-mentioned two days. The committee consists of the following Chicago Lithuanians:</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Zimontas (chairman), Mrs. K. Jurgelonis, Dr. K. Drangelis, Mr. J. A. Chmieliauskas, Rev. P. Lapelis, Mr. P. Baltutis, Mr. M. Zaldokas, Mr. A. <pb facs="5423970_2_1450.jpg" n="2"/>Petraitis, Mrs. A. Nauseda, Mr. and Mrs. Damijonaitis, Mr. Casimir Gugis, Mrs. Zimontas, Dr. A. J. Tananevicz, Mr. St. Tananevicz, Dr. S. Rutkauskas (Mrs. Slakis), Rev. F. M. Kemesis, Dr. A. L. Yuska, Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, and Mrs. J. Slakis.</p>
   <p>"The above-mentioned committee will be in charge of the following program during the two Lithuanian days:</p>
   <p>"On January 21, at 3:15 P.M. all Lithuanian pupils of the public schools will march directly to the exhibit at Mark White Square. Dr. Jonikaitis will deliver a lecture entitled 'How Children Can Avoid Tuberculosis! Dr. A. J. Zimontas will lecture on 'The Proper Care of the Mouth and Teeth.' A motion picture on the subject of 'Toothaches' will be shown to the children. Mrs. K. Jurgelonis will be in charge of this program.</p>
   <p>"Mr. A. Petraitis will have charge of the program during the evening of <pb facs="5423970_2_1451.jpg" n="3"/>January 21. Dr. A. L. Yuska will deliver a lecture on 'Hygiene and Health.' Dr. K. Drangelis will lecture on 'Mouth Hygiene.' The St. George's Parish chorus and Mrs. Pocius will furnish musical entertainment for the audience. The motion picture 'Toothaches' will be shown. Members of Lithuanian women's societies are especially invited to attend.</p>
   <p>"The afternoon program of the second Lithuanian day, January 22, will be in charge of Mrs. J. Slikas. Lithuanian pupils from parochial schools will attend. Dr. S. Rutkauskas (Mrs. Slakis) will deliver a lecture on 'How Children Can Avoid Tuberculosis.' Dr. K. Drangelis will lecture on 'The Care of the Mouth and Teeth.' A motion picture entitled 'Bacteria" will be shown.</p>
   <p>"The evening program of the second Lithuanian day will be in charge of Attorney F. P. Bradchulis. Dr. J. Kulis will deliver a lecture on 'How Tuberculosis Spreads.' Dr. A. J. Zimontas will lecture on 'The Gate to Health.' Dr. A. J. Tananevicia will lecture on 'The Anti-Tuberculosis Movement.' Entertainment <pb facs="5423970_2_1452.jpg" n="4"/>for the evening will be provided by the Biruta Chorus and by Mr. F. Jakutis (a solo tenor). The motion picture 'Bacteria' will also be shown.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
