<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Socialists Stage "Audra Giedroje"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN SOCIALISTS STAGE "AUDRA GIEDROJE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dramatic Circle of the Lithuanian Socialists League staged a comedy, "Audra Giedroje" (A Storm in Fair Weather), on Sunday evening January 9, at St. George's parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn (now Lituanica ) Avenue. The Play was staged for the benefit of the Ausra (Aurora) Society, which is a students' aid and general educational society. A fairly large crowd attended. It is estimated that a profit of about twenty dollars was realized.</p>
   <p>We will not discuss the plot of the Play because it is well known to the Lithuanians in Chicago. It has been staged here several times before.</p>
   <p>The cast of players is as follows: "Kupetis"--Mr. Briedis, "Agne"--Miss Cepaitis, "Katre"--Miss Zemaitis, "Bartasius"--Mr. Vaitiekunas, "Magdalena," the old maid--Mrs. M. Dundulis, "Barbe," the daughter of "Bartasius"--Miss Pakatis, "Jonas," son of "Bartasius"--Mr. Levanas, "Grigaitis," the young <pb facs="5423970_2_0543.jpg" n="2"/>doctor--J. Svermickas, "Raulas," the servant of "Kupetis"-- Mr. J. Sankunas.</p>
   <p>The best acting was done by "Bartasius" (played by Mr. Vaitiekunas). He created much laughter in the audience. Others who rendered satisfactory performances were: Miss Cepaitis, Mr. Briedis, and Mrs. Dundulis. The acting of the other players cannot be praised. However, this fact should be overlooked because it was their first appearance on the stage. Mr. Briedis became ill prior to the performance, but did not fail to carry out his part, having in mind the good cause for which the Play was staged.</p>
   <p>We heard rumors to the effect that the profit from the Play was rather small because many Lithuanian Socialists boycotted the affair. The reason given for the boycott is the very good reason why the Play was staged--for the Ausra Society, which society is a rival of the Socialists Student Loan Circle. However, we are inclined not to believe this absurd charge, because the Ausra Society aids students of all views, even Socialists. At present, the <pb facs="5423970_2_0544.jpg" n="3"/>majority of the students who are being aided are Socialists. Then why should the Socialists possess an unfriendly attitude toward the Ausra Society?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
