<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Farmers of Lithuania Society Marks Tenth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-09-22">Sept. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">FARMERS OF LITHUANIA SOCIETY MARKS TENTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Farmers of Lithuania Society, of the West Side colony, is planning to commemorate the tenth anniversary of the Society next Sunday at Meldazis Hall, 23rd Place and South Oakley Avenue. The program of the commemoration will consist mainly of musical numbers.</p>
   <p>The Society, which is a sick and death benefit society, has decided at a meeting held last Sunday to add a higher sick benefit table for the benefit of its members.</p>
   <p>The Farmers of Lithuania has shown that it is one of the most cultured Lithuanian-American societies in Chicago. It not only aided many Lithuanians in the hour of their greatest need, but has been very active in various Lithuanian activities in Chicago since its inception ten years ago. It is doubtful if any other Lithuanian society in Chicago has accomplished so much in the field of Lithuanian nationalism as did the Farmers of Lithuania Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1661.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The editorial staff of the Lietuva heartily congratulates the Farmers of Lithuania Society on its tenth anniversary, wishes the Society still greater success in the future, and hopes that the Society will continue its praiseworthy activities for the benefit of Lithuanian nationalism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
