<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Vilnis Campaign</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">VILNIS CAMPAIGN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign to raise funds for the Vilnis is now started and will continue through June. Our comrades in all the Lithuanian colonies in America will arrange mass meetings, canvass Lithuanian homes, and employ other methods to sell subscriptions and obtain donations for the Vilnis fund. Our comrades will work in a united manner all over the country in order to increase the circulation of the Vilnis and increase its influence among the Lithuanian working class.</p>
   <p>The Vilnis is a newspaper of the workers, for the workers, and by the workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0835.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The future of our press and the strength of the Lithuanian working class movement depends entirely upon the degree of success which these workers will have in approaching and convincing the Lithuanian masses to subscribe to the Vilnis.</p>
   <p>The Vilnis is now going on its seventh year. During the past six years the circulation of the Vilnis has been growing steadily. As a result of these years of prosperity the paper has reached a healthy financial dondition. Today themanagers of the Vilnis are figuring, not how to make ends meet for the upkeep of the Vilnis, but how to convert it into a daily newspaper. Although the present annual <pb facs="5423970_2_0836.jpg" n="3"/>campaign for funds is not a drive to make the Vilnis a daily, nevertheless, the success of this campaign will play a very important role in bringing closer the hour when our newspaper will become a daily.</p>
   <p>We will draw the logical conclusions from the results of this campaign and will guide ourselves accordingly in our plans for a daily Vilnis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
