<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-06">Sept. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">$20,000 for the Daily Already in the Bank!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0854</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0854.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-06">Sept. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">$20,000 FOR THE DAILY ALREADY IN THE BANK!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Well men--and all of you very active girls--let's all give three cheers!</p>
   <p>After a long offensive, the fort barring the way to the daily fell--on the last day of the time limit! For three months the brave troops of the nationalists stormed that fort. Last Tuesday they crushed the remaining opposition and ran up the flag of the daily on the fort which many of our enemies said we would never take.</p>
   <p>We took it! Twenty thousand dollars lie in the Universal State Bank of Chicago, waiting for the conclusion of all of the formalities and the beginning of the daily.</p>
   <p>Man, but it was work! September 1 was a Sunday, Monday was "Labor Day," a legal holiday. Therefore, the last day for accumulating the desired amount of money for deposit in the bank was Tuesday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0855.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That gave the storming battalions two extra days, Sunday and Monday.</p>
   <p>If "Labor Day" was a day of rest for you, dear reader, it was a day of real labor for the committee members of the daily. They were out shelling the city with the shares of the daily, while the Lietuva office was being crowded all day by people coming in with reports.</p>
   <p>The Chicagoans were working hard and so were all of our supporters in other colonies all over America.</p>
   <p>Tuesday, when a count was made, it was revealed that already the army of the daily was composed of more than nine hundred shareholders, but that the required goal of twenty thousand dollars was not yet reached. Many people had applied for shares, but not all had come through with their pledges on time. Not all of them could: one had become ill; another had met some other kind of misfortune; a third had asked for a day-or-two's extension of time. A couple of thousand dollars were thus <pb facs="5423970_2_0856.jpg" n="3"/>promised. But the money had to be in the bank by Tuesday.</p>
   <p>Well, what should be done?</p>
   <p>"How much is in the bank and how much are we short?" somebody asked.</p>
   <p>We have so much, and so much is short, somebody else replied.</p>
   <p>"All right! Go ahead until tomorrow! I will take all the shares that are needed to make twenty thousand dollars, because, men, we need the daily. But here are three conditions: you must help me resell some of these shares, for I already have some and these would be too much for me; you must strive to increase the army of the daily to an even thousand shareholders; and you must not reveal my name. Do you agree?"</p>
   <p>"Sure!" everybody shouted. "Now that we have got into the swing of things, it will be easy to sell your extra shares later. We'll all help."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0857.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In that way all of the necessary capital was put into the fund of the daily on time.</p>
   <p>Now we must help to lighten the burden on that one man by selling his extra shares to others. We will thus finish the matter and will keep our promise.</p>
   <p>THOSE WHO PROMISED--HURRY!</p>
   <p>All those who have pledged to purchase shares and those who have already made down payments are urged to send their money as soon as possible. All of you who have supported the proposed daily up to the present are urged to continue to do so until the very end.</p>
   <p>PREPARATIONS</p>
   <p>A shareholders' meeting was called at the Milda Hall last Tuesday. At this meeting a committee of three people was elected from among the shareholders <pb facs="5423970_2_0858.jpg" n="5"/>to appraise the value of the present Lietuva property, in co-operation with a committee of the old Lietuva shareholders. They will hire an expert who once more will take an inventory of the property in the Lietuva press and evaluate it.</p>
   <p>Not one cent of the money placed in the fund for the daily will be used for purchasing the present Lietuva press. The old shareholders are investing their property in the daily and will receive as many shares as the committees and the expert decide are due to them according to the appraised value of the property.</p>
   <p>The following were elected to the above-mentioned committee: A. Zemaitis (a printer), M. Dudas (a former printer), and Attorney J. A. Ambrosius.</p>
   <p>At this time we cannot predict the definite date for the first issue of the new daily. In the meantime the personnel of the daily must be organized. Its editorial and administrative staffs will require more workers than are <pb facs="5423970_2_0859.jpg" n="6"/>needed in publishing a weekly. Other preparations, which may take some time, have been begun. It is expected that the preparations will be completed by the end of this month. When they are completed, the publishing of the daily will begin.</p>
   <p>Many people were active in the organizational work for the daily, but most of the work was done by those who not only purchased shares themselves, but also sold them to others. They have won the gratitude of the new daily.</p>
   <p>We beg all of those who sold ten or more shares to send us their photographs to be published in the daily. Besides that, we want to make a large photograph of all of these people to remind us of our brave army of organizers. This photograph will hang in the office of the daily. Also it has been suggested that we send copies of these photographs to all people who have sold more than ten shares.</p>
   <p>All of those who have purchased or sold nearly ten shares are urged to reach the ten mark. The more "ten-men" we have, the better it will be. There are <pb facs="5423970_2_0860.jpg" n="7"/>several tens of these "ten-men" now.</p>
   <p>So, get to work, men!</p>
   <p>If we had published a list of all the names of those who purchased shares this week, the space required would have been half of this newspaper.</p>
   <p>Our "strategist" (the person who organizes and spaces the columns and prepares them for publication) looked at the great pile of letters, booklets, greetings, articles and other "war" material, threw his arms into the air and shouted, "Kamerad! I give up! I fought all summer, but this pile is too much for me! I'd rather surrender and become a prisoner!"</p>
   <p>Therefore, all the articles, greetings, and lists of names remain on his desk for the time being. They will be used later.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
