<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-11-26">Nov. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lovers of Fatheriand Society Publishes Another Great Book</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Mikas Pakrasenis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-11-26">Nov. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LOVERS OF FATHERIAND SOCIETY PUBLISHES ANOTHER GREAT BOOK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Mikas Pakrasenis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another great book, Sirdis (The Heart) by de Amicis, has been published by the Lovers of the Fatherland Society. Members have been impatiently waiting for this book a long time. This is the first time the Society has issued a great and important book since the publication of the works of Vincas Kudirka several years ago.</p>
   <p>Members of the Society are receiving copies of the new book with great interest and enthusiasm. This book is also very popular among many other nationalities. In some languages it was published in several editions. These facts alone reveal the great value and importance of the book. It is only regrettable that our people did not have an opportunity to get acquainted with this book years ago. Now that it has been finally published in the Luthuanian language it will undoubtedly greatly enrich Lithuanian literature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1188.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One very important feature of Sirdis is that it will be read with equal interest by the young and the old, by the uneducated as well as the educated person.....The book contains innumerable passages of deep, pure, and lofty pathos. It is capable of arousing man's most dormant emotions, and it reveals to us the most lofty and most important qualities of the heart of man. The book is a great fountain of learning to its readers; and everyone who reads it will unquestionably learn more than one lesson, even unknowingly. The many lessons this great book is capable of teaching are of especially great importance to Lithuanians. We can hardly find anywhere else so much humanitarianism and great respect for one's fellow man as are shown in this book. And we Lithuanians are greatly in need of such qualities of character.</p>
   <p>It is the great hope of the writer that this book will be read not only by the members of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society but also by all other Lithuanians of the world; and it would be an excellent idea if those who cannot read will ask others to read the book to them. If any book really deserves these fulsome compliments, that book is Sirdis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1189.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The book has a very beautiful and attractive appearance. It is printed on very good paper, in attractive type, and contains about two hundred interesting illustrations. The writer has noted only one typographical error in the book--one line on page thirty-two is printed upside down.</p>
   <p>The book was translated into the Lithuanian language by Mr. M. Griginis. The translator summarized some parts of the original book; in other parts the translator was forced to employ his own ideas in order to make the book more suitable to the Lithuanian people. However, on the whole, the translator adhered to the original very faithfully.</p>
   <p>This book, copies of which are distributed free of charge to all members of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society, is indeed a very good Christmas gift. It also would be a very suitable Christmas gift for all other Lithuanians--nonmembers of the Society. Copies of the book are now available at the home of Mr. Damijonaitis, Chicago, Illinois, who is the chief librarian of the Society. Dr. A.J. Zimontas is the supreme president of the Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
