<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. III, No. 1,
<date when="1901-01-03">Jan. 3, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">National Field</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. III, No. 1,
<date when="1901-01-03">Jan. 3, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL FIELD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We started our third year of work for the benefit of Roman-Catholics in America. We consider our native language and religion as the greatest fortune which we brought from our fatherland to this strange land called America. Religion and language is our entire fortune, which we received from our fathers and which we must keep as a sacred relic. The fatherland is our second mother, our country in which we grew up, made our livelihood and spent the best days of our lives. It is heartbreaking for everyone of us to think how we spent our days of youth in Lithuania. How happy we were there with no worry at all. Our childhood days in Lithuania are glorious memoirs of the past. It makes one feel happy to think of our childhood days when we played our games with a great joy and never dreamed of our future, for we were well contented with the present. We were just like any other children, never worried about tomorrow or the next day; we had not the slightest shade of worry on our faces; we never thought of facing future problems and we had no idea that we would face our <pb facs="5423970_2_1071.jpg" n="2"/>problems somewhere in a strange land of which we never dreamed in our childhood days.</p>
   <p>Many of us suffered injustice and hardship in Lithuania under the Russian government; yet, there were many happy days in our childhood when we lived in our native land. Even those who lead an easy life in America think with envy about the happy days of youth spent in Lithuania. It is hard to forget a beautiful meadow in the month of May, especially when flowers are blooming and birds are singing.</p>
   <p>We cannot forget our language, religion and fatherland. Language, religion and fatherland are sacred things to us, which we must always carry in our hearts.</p>
   <p>Therefore, Katalikas, has a difficult problem to solve in order to help their Catholic brothers in America. Katalikas will make every effort to help brothers in their needs and will help to enlighten them in their lives.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1072.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We hope that all disagreements will end among our brothers during the 19th century and solidarity will prevail among our people who are living in America. It would be much better to put aside all unnecessary quarrels and separating into many groups, instead of maintaining a strong national unity. We cannot accomplish much if we split into many groups.</p>
   <p>In order to accomplish something worthwhile we must unite and work together for our fatherland and our brothers who are suffering hardships across the sea.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
