<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 19,
<date when="1901-05-10">May 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Is it Time to Have a Daily Newspaper?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 19,
<date when="1901-05-10">May 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">IS IT TIME TO HAVE A DAILY NEWSPAPER?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week Katalikas proposed to establish a Lithuanian daily newspaper, and asks the opinion of others on this project.</p>
   <p>That the Lithuanian daily newspaper is essential and beneficial, no one can dispute. If the majority of nationalities in America have their daily newspapers, even in recent times, the Slovaks started to publish their daily newspaper, the Poles already have five daily newspapers, why then can't the Lithuanians have their daily newspaper? The question is, could we uphold such a newspaper? Would it bring the results we are seeking? It looks to us as if the present weekly Lithuanian newspaper does not have many subscribers because, among the Lithuanians there are not many who want to read the newspapers. The Lithuanians work at hard labor. When a man is tired from hard labor, does he care to read the newspapers? A majority of the Lithuanian newspaper readers read <pb facs="5423970_2_1067.jpg" n="2"/>the newspapers on Sundays only because they are not used to reading the papers daily. Those who are reading the dailies in foreign languages will read them when the Lithuanian daily newspaper is issued. To have such newspapers as the American, we need literary force and financial power.</p>
   <p>In America there are ten times as many Poles as Lithuanians, but the Polish daily newspapers are hardly existing. The Polish newspapers are better provided for, and are published mostly by the priests. Everybody thinks that it is easier for the priest to donate a hundred dollars for a newspaper than for the workingman to donate 25 cents. We must not forget that the parish budget is in the priest's hands and under his sole control. Only in Milwaukee the Polish daily, Kurjer, is not under the control of the parish. It stands on a stronger basis; this is the oldest Polish newspaper; before, this daily newspaper used to have highly paid advertisements.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1068.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It would not be easy to get a group of writers for the newspaper. The editor himself prepares the literature without outside help. Yes, we receive correspondences, but in order to make it fit to be put in the newspaper, the editor must re-write such a correspondence. On such conditions one editor for a daily newspaper is not enough. Even though the editor would be of the greatest ability, he could not produce enough literature for the daily newspaper.</p>
   <p>No one will say that literary ability is developed by writing. In reality it is different: the newspapers are killing the literary men, they do not develop them. The newspaperman has no time to prepare the literary work properly, because he is always in a hurry. We see in our newspapers that literary preparation is far behind that of the European newspapers. The American writers have no time to prepare their articles in the right manner. When they <pb facs="5423970_2_1069.jpg" n="4"/>get used to making sketches, it is a very hard (thing) to regain literary ability. Even though the writers of other nations are standing on a higher standard, we see that the newspapers have the great effect of stopping the development of their literary ability. In America we have more newspapers than in any other country in the world, but the literary value of these newspapers is very low, for instance, the literary value of the American newspapers is far behind the newspapers of the three million people of Switzerland. Nobody will deny the literary ability of the American writers, but this literary ability is destroyed by the daily newspapers, and the best literary writers are ruined.</p>
   <p>It looks to us as if daily newspapers among the Lithuanians could not exist, and it will not bring the benefit we desire. When more Lithuanians will get used to reading the weekly newspapers, we can prepare them for the daily newspapers. At the present time we have not enough readers to support the daily newspaper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
