<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 48,
<date when="1900-11-30">Nov. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">On Oppressed Nations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Russian)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 48,
<date when="1900-11-30">Nov. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">ON OPPRESSED NATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sometime in the past the Rusini (Russians speaking a somewhat different dialect from the Russian language) raised the question in the paper Swoboda, that in order to gain freedom all the oppressed nations by the Russian government, should unite and publish a newspaper in one of the international languages. Among the Lithuanian newspapers, the Lietuva and Vinybe approved of the idea, and for that purpose they have collected a couple of dollars.</p>
   <p>We do not expect the clergy to support this publication, because there would be no pecuniary gain for them. Ateitis (The Future) does not favor the idea. The editor of Ateitis replied that in order to gain freedom, the people must get enlightenment; then they will find their way to freedom by themselves. No one objects to the fact that the enlightenment of the people is most essential, but the editor of Ateitis did not explain how to spread enlightenment among Lithuanians in Russia, where even the Lithuanian language is prohibited. To wait until the government <pb facs="5423970_2_1077.jpg" n="2"/>enlightens the people would be too long. The union among the oppressed nations and the proposed newspaper is the most important aim if we are to gain freedom and spread enlightenment.</p>
   <p>Among the Polish newspapers, the Zgoda favors this idea and published Dr. John Szliupas' article on the matter. The Polish daily, Dziennik Narodowy, gave an analysis on this problem, and we think that the other Polish liberal newspapers will uphold this idea. Of one thing we are sure: neither the Polish nor the Lithuanian clergy will support this idea because there is no business for them in it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
