<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-01-06">Jan. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">J. Sileikis Farewell</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-01-06">Jan. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">J. SILEIKIS FAREWELL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 2, at the Chicago University Settlement in the Town of Lake, Miss McDowell arranged a farewell party for our young artist, Mr. Sileikis, who is going to Europe to study. There were about one hundred people present. Miss McDowell, speaking to the guests said, "We came here because we like him." She hoped that Mr. Sileikis might become an artist even though not as great a one as Raphael, or Michelangelo. She stated that in America there were many opportunities for artists. Since Mr. Sileikis has great artistic ability, he should go abroad to study under the great European masters. Furthermore, she stated, paintings should not hang in the palaces of the rich, but should be placed in public places where the common people may see and enjoy their beauty.</p>
   <p>Dr. Graiciunas said that it was through the efforts of Miss McDowell, that our <pb facs="5423970_2_0186.jpg" n="2"/>artist Sileikis could go to Europe to study. Mr. K. Sliupas, in his talk expressed his best wishes for the success of our young artist. Mr. Jurgelionis, delivered a very enthusiastic speech. In his short talk he revealed the value of and the need for art. His talk made a great impression upon the audience.</p>
   <p>The concert was given by the students of Mr. Petrauskas. Mr. K. Kasputis, Miss Jaskeviciute, Miss M. Horodeckaite, Miss Krikscioniute, Mr. M. Duda and the violinists, Mr. Sarpalius, and Mr. K. Sliupas. We owe a debt of gratitude to Mr. Petrauskas for arranging such a splendid program. Mr. Petrauskas played several violin solos beautifully.</p>
   <p>Then the Lithuanian national dances were performed. Miss McDowell and several Americans took part in the dances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
