<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Incorporation of Lietuva</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">INCORPORATION OF LIETUVA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspaper Lietuva, the Consolidated Printing Company (Lietuva printing shop), and the Lietuva Library up to the present time were separate institutions, but now have merged into one large corporation under the name of Lietuva Publishing Company. This new corporation has bought $30,000 worth of stock from the Consolidated Printing Company, and has started its new life in business with an incorporation capital of $100,000.</p>
   <p>While announcing this event to our readers and friends, at the same time, we feel it our duty to offer our heartiest thanks for their sympathy and support during our hard labor. It is through the sympathy and support of its <pb facs="5423970_2_1022.jpg" n="2"/>readers ever since its inception twenty-two years ago, that this newspaper has been able to grow and to become one of the largest Lithuanian newspaper corporations.</p>
   <p>In this new corporation, the workers will have the right to become stockholders. This is the first time, among Lithuanian corporations, that workers will be given an opportunity to become stockholders, and will be able to share in the profits.</p>
   <p>Having relied upon our readers, co-workers, friends, and public sympathy for the past twenty-two years, we believe that we will get the same support and protection in the future for the good of Lithuanianism. By working together with our sympathizers and supporters we will be able to continue our fight against the ignorance which exists in our midst. Our readers <pb facs="5423970_2_1023.jpg" n="3"/>will help us chock the exploitation of our people, and will support us in our struggle by spreading enlightenment among our brothers--a pure light (sic) is the key that opens the door to a better future and fortune.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
