<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 50,
<date when="1907-12-13">Dec. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Science Is Power</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 50,
<date when="1907-12-13">Dec. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">SCIENCE IS POWER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That science is power is no empty phrase. Where can we go without science? Nowhere. What can we accomplish without science? Nothing. A man without education is a slave closed in a dark den. He sees nothing. Life to him is a martyrdom, "The Vale of Tears," and he always dreams about the quickest way to free himself from this unhappy condition of martyrdom. The man of science is entirely different. He sees life from a different point of view. The educated man sees further and more broadly. A man without education is a slave; the educated man is free and independent. Only the educated man enjoys life, not the ignorant slave.</p>
   <p>On November 24th there was a third lecture arranged by the Aurora Society. The lecture was delivered by a student of Valparaiso University, Mr. St. Safranauskas. The subject was, "Air Elements <pb facs="5423970_2_1564.jpg" n="2"/>and its Agency." At the beginning of his lecture, he made several experiments with air. Then after the lecture there were questions, the lecturer answering and making clear to everyone the action of the air. The audience understood that science is power.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday, December 15th, there will be the fourth lecture of the Aurora Society at the Fellowship House hall, 869 33rd Place. The subject of this lecture will be, "What we Need," by Dr. Butkevicius. The lecture will start at 3:30 P. M. Admission 10 cents.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society gives help to the poor Lithuanian students. By arranging the lectures it not only helps the students but at the same time gives education to the people, to make them broad-minded. By attending the Aurora's lectures, you help the society help the poor Lithuanian students. The Aurora Society has arranged for an eight-lecture course after New Year.</p>
   <p>J. Ilgandas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
