<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">To the Katalikas and its Boss</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE KATALIKAS AND ITS BOSS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Rev. Krawczunas' newspaper, Katalikas, for the last year has warned the people against Olszewski. The Reverend Father has been writing in his newspaper shameful lies about the latter; that Olszewski with his henchmen are attacking the people on the streets; that Olszewski has a lot of debts; that he is on the verge of bankruptcy, etc. The priest believes that with such lies he will force Olszewski into brankruptcy. (To wit: the Rev. Krawczunas is angry because Lietuva dared to disclose his improper acts, and the priest firmly believed that the life of Lietuva is in his hands; to destroy Lietuva the priest established his own newspaper Katalikas. When the priest had established his newspaper he said to everybody that Lietuva will exist only for two months; that he will leave Olszewski without a shirt).</p>
   <p>The dog's voice does not reach heaven. During the past year Katalikas poured out the dirtiest lies about Olszewski in order to persuade the people that they should not go to Olszewski with any business; <pb facs="5423970_2_1083.jpg" n="2"/>but unfortunately for Katalikas, all the people were not listening to it. More than twelve months ago the priest started his attack on Olszewski, but up to the present time the spiritual father failed to destroy Olszewski. What, then, remains for the spiritual father to do? The priest quit the financial attack on Olszewski; now he took up the religious malice to pour on Olszewski's head. The priest picked up from his drawer letters in Polish and Latin, the damnations of the Independent bishop Kozlowski in the year 1895. The Rev. Krawczunas added the ficticious signature of Olszewski, and in number 50 and 51 of Katalikas, he published the shameful lie, telling all the people that Olszewski has joined the Independent Catholic Church Parish Committee, that in 1898 when he went to confession he declared that he belonged to the Independent Catholic Church, and that he took sacrilegiously the sacrament of the Roman-Catholic Church. He sold his soul to the devil, etc. Now the priest believes that with such lies he will kill Olszewski's business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1084.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even though our spiritual father upholds lying as his principle, such a lie is too thick. He has some of my letters; if he will compare the signatures he will see, if he wants to see, that my signature is different from the one he published in the newspaper Katalikas.</p>
   <p>To these lies of the Rev. Krawczunas I reply: That I have never belonged to any Polish parish committee of the Roman-Catholics nor of the Independent Catholics. Therefore, I am asking Katalikas to repudiate the shameful lie about me. If in the following issue the Katalikas will not repudiate that lie, I will be forced to seek justice in court. The same repudiation I demand from the newspaper Saule (Sun), whose publishers seem to have made an agreement to repeat the lies that were printed in Katalikas.</p>
   <p>A. Olszewski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
