<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. II,
<date when="1900-02-01">Feb. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Our Opinion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. II,
<date when="1900-02-01">Feb. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">OUR OPINION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the help of God and with the good will of the people today we are sharing our happiness with our readers because Katalikas becomes larger. Beside this, in the future we will constantly improve Katalikas, not for profit but to serve our brother Lithuanians who came to this strange country and who succeeded financially, sometimes very rapidly, forgetting they are people, forgetting they have sincere and worthy parents, brothers, sisters, relatives and friends.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we repeat again, not for the purpose of increasing our profit but for love to our brothers, so that they get back on the good road of life; all who became lost on account of belonging to immoral organizations, reading of provocative newspapers and ungodly books. Therefore, we are not after profits, but only wish that most of our brothers start to read this newspaper. Naturally, we ask this in order that we would not ask big contributions. Even building the famous church of Solomon was stopped for a short time on account of shortage of labor and material. On that <pb facs="5423970_2_1081.jpg" n="2"/>account, brother Catholics, don't stop your work; contribute everything you can by reading, by propagating and writing important news about Lithuanian life in America. We all must stick to the work. If we stick to the unity God will bless us. Many who are lost we will bring back to moral life. Those who are doubtful in holy religion, we will strengthen. Those who have inclination for prostitution, drunkards, swearers, we will bring them back to salvation.</p>
   <p>Therefore, let every Lithuanian read Katalikas, in the reading of which you will find happiness in your sorrows and hope to salvation. For there is only one road to reach eternal happiness,for our deal souls are suffering here in this vale of tears. At the end, we repeat again, let's stick to our work that will bring fruitfulness a hundredfold.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
