<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-31">Dec. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Vincas Kudirka Society to Hold Annual Affair</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-31">Dec. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">VINCAS KUDIRKA SOCIETY TO HOLD ANNUAL AFFAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual affair of the Vincas Kudirka Society will be held on January 1, at the Meldazis Hall, 2242 West 23rd Place. The doors will be opened at 4 P. M., and the play will begin promptly at 5 P. M. Admission will be thirty-five cents and up.</p>
   <p>A great play, "Two Roads", a three-act drama by G. Gejerman, will be presented. This play depicts the lives of two priests in a small coast town of Holland. They have been the best of friends in school but, having attained priesthood, each chooses a separate road to travel. One devotes himself to an ideal; obeying the teachings of Christ, he opens the doors of his home to an unfortunate woman, and provides her with Christian assistance during her serious illness. Finally the privileges of priesthood are taken from him through the treachery of his boyhood friend, the second priest, who cares <pb facs="5423970_2_0355.jpg" n="2"/>nothing for brotherly love and the teachings of Christ; but serves only the Roman trust.</p>
   <p>So, honored readers, you will have a wonderful opportunity to hear the bitter arguments of the priests. You will learn from the story of the woman in the play how a modern, enlightened worker, such as the priest who assisted her, defends his rights and his liberty.</p>
   <p>The best available talent has been gathered for the various parts of this play. Among the actors will be Stasiunas, Buragas, Mrs. M. Dundulis, Miss Novikas and others. Therefore, we assure you that you will be fully satisfied if you attend this affair.</p>
   <p>There will be dancing after the play. The music will be furnished by the Sarpalius Brothers' Orchestra.</p>
   <p>P. S. Those who want to see the play are urged to be on time, for the <pb facs="5423970_2_0356.jpg" n="3"/>curtain will rise at 5 P. M. sharp. Those who do not wish to see the play and are interested only in dancing, can come about 8 P. M. By that time the performance will have ended.</p>
   <p>The committee invites everybody to attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
