<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-02-25">Feb. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Activity of the Lovers of the Motherland Society's Local Brarches</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-02-25">Feb. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITY OF THE LOVERS OF THE MOTHERLAND SOCIETY'S LOCAL BRARCHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local branches of the Lovers of the Motherland Society have begun to work in earnest. They are planning to revive the Chicago district of local branches of the Lovers of Motherland Society, in order to secure more activity on the part of the branches. Almost all the branches are getting new members, and the publication of new books is bringing more energy to the activities of the local branches.</p>
   <p>On February 27, the Lovers of Motherland Society, Branch 22, of Bridgeport, will hold its meeting at Aurora Hall, 3001 South Halsted Street, at 2 P. M. At this meeting the new book, The Mother, will be given to the members, and the previously published book The Heart, will be given to those members who have not yet received it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0680.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On February 27, the Lovers of Motherland Society, Branch 27, will hold its meeting at A. J. Bierzinskis Hall, 4602 South Paulina Street. At this meeting the same books will be given to the members of Branch 27.</p>
   <p>On February 28, the Lovers of Motherland Society, Branch 28, will hold its meeting at M. Meldazis Hall on the West side at 8:P. M. At this meeting they will have a discussion on the newly published books. Previously they had such a discussion on the book, The Heart; now they will discuss the literary works of Mr. Strazdas and Mr. Jonila. The new book, The Mother, will be given to the members at this meeting.</p>
   <p>Persons who do not belong to this literary organization may come to these meetings. Old members should bring new members to these meetings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
