<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-05">June 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Ausra Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-05">June 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE AUSRA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Guided by the belief that action is better than words, I wrote as little as possible in our newspaper about the first branch of the Ausra (Dawn) Society, of which I am the chairman. However, a large number of members have criticized me for my reticence and urged me to engage in some occasional publicity, in an effort to attract more people into our movement. Therefore, I am making this effort to acquaint more people with the aims and activities of our society. I hope I will succeed in arousing a greater interest in our movement among the Lithuanian public of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Ausra Society was organized recently by a group of leading Chicago Lithuanians, along non-partisan and non-sectarian lines, for the purpose of assisting Lithuanian students financially and to promote in a general way the educational uplift of our people.</p>
   <p>In order to meet a long felt need for professional people of our own nationality, <pb facs="5423970_2_0696.jpg" n="2"/>the society is now assisting a number of worthy and talented Lithuanian students to complete their college education. We all know that the realization of our dreams for a greater and brighter future, both as individuals and as a group, depends to a large extent on an ever increasing number of college graduates.</p>
   <p>An important part of the activities of the Ausra Society are the evening classes, which are being conducted for the benefit of adult Lithuanian men and women. Various elementary subjects, such as arithmetic, reading, and writing, in both the Lithuanian and English languages, are being taught under the able direction of Vincent Maseika. He is a graduate of the Ryga Polytechnic Academy, and came to America only recently from Latvia, where he was employed as a railroad engineer.</p>
   <p>A rapidly growing Lithuanian and English library is also maintained by the society. Books are available free of charge to all Lithuanians of Chicago <pb facs="5423970_2_0697.jpg" n="3"/>and vicinity.</p>
   <p>The hearts of those who have been following the activities of Chicago Lithuanians during the past twelve or eighteen months, are being comforted with unmistakable signs of a greater and brighter for our people in America.</p>
   <p>The membership of the Ausra Society is composed of the very best element of Lithuanian men and women of Chicago. The realization of the aspirations of our talented youth depends largely upon them.</p>
   <p>The Ausra Society is a piplar of education, not for political agitation or religious fancies, but a pillar of real education and knowledge. It is a solid and reliable foundation, upon which we can safely build our national hopes and individual welfare.</p>
   <p>The next monthly meeting of the Ausra Society will be held on June 7, 3:30</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0698.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>P.M., at the Fellowship House, on 33rd Place, near Halsted Street.</p>
   <p>A. Rutkauskas, M.D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
