<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Equality</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">EQUALITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new book in the Lithuanian language, entitled Moteris Pries Teisybes Ir Logikos Teisma (Women Before the Court of Justice and Logic), has been published last month by the Pirmyn Press, Minersville, Pa. It was written originally in German by Carl Federn and translated into Lithuanian by A. Antonas.</p>
   <p>The book explains in detail the present position of women in the various spheres of life, with suggestions for their emancipation. A strong appeal is made not only for equal rights with men, but also for additional privileges, because women are members of the weaker sex.</p>
   <p>It is true, we should be more lenient with people who are weak and less fortunate. However, the whole world abhors privileges. Even now mankind is engaged in a bitter struggle to abolish the privileges which are being enjoyed and abused by the wealthy class. If, in addition to equality, society would grant special privileges to women, they also would abuse them.</p>
   <p>We agree that women should be granted equal rights with men, but only under <pb facs="5423970_2_1253.jpg" n="2"/>the condition that they will accept equal responsibilities. If we grant them equal rights without equal responsiblities, we will set up another parasitical class in society. This, in turn, would give birth to another bitter movement, such as the labor movement, against privileges and exploitation. We must remember that the world does not give anything for nothing to anyone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
