<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Biruta Society Stages Melodrama "Nastute"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTA SOCIETY STAGES MELODRAMA "NASTUTE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Biruta Musical Society has started its New Year activities by staging "Nastute" (Nastute, a feminine name), a two-act melodrama, on January 10, at Meldazis hall. The play was written by Mr. Grigonis; the music for the play was adopted by the famous Chicago Lithuanian musician Anthony Pocius.</p>
   <p>The Biruta Society is generally famous among Chicago Lithuanians for its presentation of the more important musical plays. Thanks to the Biruta Society, Chicago Lithuanians have had an apportunity to witness the staging of a long string of great musical plays. To its many accomplishments over a large number of years, the Biruta Society has now added another, the staging of "Nastute."</p>
   <p>The play deals with the love of "Nastute", a peasant girl, for her lover "Petras," who has gone abroad. Much time has elapsed since "Petras" left. He has not been heard from. He has either perished or forgot his "Nastute."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0225.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The situation appears hopeless. However, "Nastute" does not forget her "Petras." She thinks and dreams about him day and night.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, penniless "Nastute" gets an opportunity to marry a rich baron. Her mother and others strongly advise her to take advantage of the opportunity. "Nastute" struggles with herself and is unable to make up her mind. She finds it impossible to forget the man to whom she has promised her heart and soul. Later, during a very critical moment when the earth appeared to be moving under her feet, "Petras" returns, and faithful love rejoices over its victory.</p>
   <p>The play is very appropriately embellished with music. The music undoubtedly adds much color and makes the play more effective.</p>
   <p>The Biruta Society has been surprisingly successful in selecting a very suitable cast of players. The following Chicago Lithuanian theatrical artists took part in the play:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0226.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Nastute," by Miss E. Rudauskas; the mother of "Nastute" by Miss E. Urbis; "Petras," by Mr. S. Kvietkauskas; the baron by Mr. A. D. Misevicius.</p>
   <p>The acting was splendid. The audience behaved unusually well and appeared to be deeply impressed with the play. Many members of the audience were moved to the point of tears during the most dramatic moments of the performance.</p>
   <p>If we would have such splendid performances more often, then it would not be necessary for us to complain that our people do not take sufficient interest in our theatrical affairs. We cannot blame our people for the fact that many seats remain unoccupied at our theatrical performances; the blame rests with those who present the plays.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
