<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with a representative of the Casimir the King Lithuanian Roman Catholic Society in Marquette Park</title>, Chicago, Illinois, by Theo Kucinskas,
<date when="1937-06-08">June 8, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with a representative of The Casimir The King Lithuanian Roman Catholic Society in Marquette Park</title>, Chicago, Illinois, by Theo Kucinskas,
<date when="1937-06-08">June 8, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Casimir The King Lithuanian Roman Catholic Society in Marquette Park was organized on May 17, 1914. It was incorporated on April 7, 1917.</p>
   <p>The St.Casimir The King Society upholds its unity with the Roman Catholic Church. The spiritual and public affairs must be conducted according to the Roman Catholic faith. Every brother-member must uphold the Roman Catholic religion and their children must be sent to a Catholic school No one should read or keep in his home, books, or any kind of literature which is inimical to the Roman Catholic religion.</p>
   <p>The society's flag will bear on one side the picture of St.Casimir, and on the other, the picture of the Holy Mother of the Vilnius Aurora Gate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1629.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Society of St.Casimir the King will be liquidated when there remains only five members. If this society should be liquidated, all the money shall be given to the orphans, the Roman Catholic Church and the schools.</p>
   <p>The Spiritual Affairs.</p>
   <p>The Society of St. Casimir the King, will have its yearly holiday on its patron's, St.Casimir's Day which is on the 4th day of March. On this day, all the members of this society must attend confession and take the holy sacrament. The donations for performing the mass on that day every year must be given to the parish church, the amount being according to the society's decision.</p>
   <p>Every member must attend the Easter confession and for not attending it, will <pb facs="5423970_2_1630.jpg" n="3"/>be expelled from the society.</p>
   <p>The membership dues are 25 per month. The sick benefit is $5 per week. At the death of a member the society pays $50 from its budget, and every member pays one dollar.</p>
   <p>The membership is about seventy. The assets are $1,000. The meetings are held at the Birth Parish Hall, 6812 So. Washtenaw Ave.; R. Andeliunas, president, 6324 So. Western Ave.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
