<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-19">Jan. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Socialists Commemorate Bloody Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-19">Jan. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISTS COMMEMORATE BLOODY SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... The 22nd chapter of the Lithuanian Socialist League commemorated Bloody Sunday with a varied program of songs, declamations and orations on Jan.17, at Meldazis hall.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. Grigaitis, editor of Naujienos (The Lithuanian Daily News), and who was a student in St.Petersburg during that Bloody Sunday, delivered the main address. He described in detail how a large group of innocent workers were slaughtered by the Russian army on Bloody Sunday in St.Petersburg on Jan. 9, 1905. He explained how a group of workers from all over Russia marched to the Czar's winter palace, carrying religious ikons and singing patriotic songs, to deliver a petition to the Czar, asking for redress of their grievances. The procession was led by Father Gapon. The Czar answered the peaceful delegation with bullets, killing many participants. Mr. Grigaitis explained the various reasons for that brutal massacre, and pointed out what demands the workers should make.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1443.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the address the Lithuanian Socialist Male Choir sang a few songs, followed by declamations and more songs by the Mixed Choir of the 81st chapter of the Lithuanian Socialist League.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grigaitis spoke to the audience a second time on the present war situation in Europe. He explained the cause of the war and what must be dong to abolish all wars in the future. He also touched upon the war situation in Lithuania and appealed for relief of Lithuanian war refugees.</p>
   <p>More than three hundred people attended, and all were pleased with the orations and program.</p>
   <p>It is advisable that all Lithuanian colonies in Chicago make arrangements to commemorate Bloody Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
