<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 1,
<date when="1908-01-03">Jan. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Kensington Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 1,
<date when="1908-01-03">Jan. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE KENSINGTON LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this suburb of Chicago there are a large number of Lithuanians, mostly Catholic, and very ignorant. Drunkenness among them is very common. They do not want to read books or newspapers; they spend all their hard-earned money in saloons; their children are badly nourished, half naked, and yet when one asks them to subscribe to a good newspaper, they answer that they have no money, or that the priest have told them not to read books or newspapers. What will the future generation from such a Lithuanian community come to, whose chief aim is to pray, drink and fight? Their future is very dark.</p>
   <p>Among these ignorant Lithuanians there are several enlightened Lithuanians who have organized a Lithuanian Socialist branch, which at present has thirty members. This branch is very active already; it has arranged two lectures before, and on December 22, 1907, it <pb facs="5423970_2_1559.jpg" n="2"/>arranged lectures at the Visnevski Hall. The first speaker was Mr. J. K. Vasiliauskas. He spoke about drunkenness and its bad effect on the workers. The speaker urged the people to read scientific books, newspapers and other good literature, that the workers must have unity.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was Mr. Svirmickas; the third speaker, Sederevicia, spoke about the workers' duties. Mr. Ambraziejus read a poem, "Tsar and Worker." The hall was packed with people. The people were satisfied with the lecture. A collection was made and $4 were collected for the expense of the hall, and the balance ($2) was sent to the literary fund of the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance of America's newspaper, Kova (The Struggle), Philadelphia, Pa.</p>
   <p>Seven new members joined the local branch of the Lithuanian Socialists after the lecture.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1560.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian socialists are planning to establish a Lithuanian library in this district for the Lithuanian public. On account of the industrial slack, many Lithuanians are out of work, so our plan to open the library has had a set-back.</p>
   <p>The Echo of the Poor One.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
