<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 23,
<date when="1893-06-17">June 17, 1893</date><title level="a">Editorial about the American Lithuanian</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Dennouncing the Lithuanian Science Society)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 23,
<date when="1893-06-17">June 17, 1893</date><title level="a">EDITORIAL ABOUT THE AMERICAN LITHUANIAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Dennouncing the Lithuanian Science Society)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not only in all the Lithuanian newspapers, but everywhere in Chicago, they are discussing how to educate Lithuanians, how to improve their living conditions, how to raise the standard of Lithuanians among other nations, etc.</p>
   <p>John Grinius, former editorof Lietuva is writing letters to newspapers and privately, urging Lithuanians to take up education, etc. The same John Grinius says that here in Chicago the Lithuanian Science Society has three or four schools, where they are teaching history, geography, English; that they have libraries with all kinds of books.</p>
   <p>Here is what one man told us about how they are educating our Lithuanians. This man went to investigate such schools and what they were teaching there. This man tells us that in one of those schools, the teacher began to tell his listeners that the Catholic religion is the worst enemy of education,that the Catholic priests are the exploiters of the common people, etc.</p>
   <p>This man tells me that the speaker said nothing good about our Catholic faith.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, dear readers, is the Catholic faith no good? Are not our Catholic churches the most beautifully decorated? The Catholic faith the best? We need more faith, we must believe our priests, we do not need such libraries where there are no prayer books.</p>
   <p>A man without religion is like a beast; he will steal, rob and kill just because he has no religion.</p>
   <p>Good Lithuanians will not go to such a school where they do not teach about the good of our faith and what benefits the Catholic faith brought to Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
