<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. II, No. 36,
<date when="1894-09-08">Sept. 8, 1894</date><title level="a">To the Lithuanian Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1756.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. II, No. 36,
<date when="1894-09-08">Sept. 8, 1894</date><title level="a">TO THE LITHUANIAN SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our societies have for a principle "love thy friend." Let us look closer, do they live up to their watchword "love thy neighbor as thyself?" Let us look to their by-laws, it says that the society takes in young and bealthy people only, but no others. Now the question arises, where can the sick and the old people lay their heads? If a society does not accept the sick and the old, then where is the beautiful watchword "love thy friend?"</p>
   <p>Of course, the sick ones and the old ones, we must put into the two different categories: One who is unhealthy from accident, and the old ones who were persecuted by Russia in Lithuania. They were forced to take refuge in other countries in order to escape their prison.</p>
   <p>And the others who have an incurable disease from dissolute living and drunkenness, who had been living in this country for many years, did not care to belong to societies when they were young and healthy. Now such persons are not acceptable by our societies.</p>
   <p>Such people ought to be accepted by our societies on the following basis:</p>
   <p>(1) The initiation fee and the monthly dues must be the same as of good and healthy persons, but the sick benefit ought to be only from $2 to 3 a week <pb facs="5423970_2_1757.jpg" n="2"/>instead of $5 or more. But, if such person were sick for a long time, then the society must make arrangements to take him to the city hospital. (2) If any such old or sick person cared to go back to Lithuania, the society ought to buy him a ticket. (3) If such a person died, the society ought to pay his funeral expenses. Of course, the expenses must be as small as possible.</p>
   <p>Let our societies take this suggestion into their consideration. One more suggestion: that the presidents of our societies ought to be great lovers of Lithuanianism and to know the purpose of it; that the presidents of our societies ought to be great lovers of Lithuanianism and to know the purpose of it; that the presidents must look not only for the benefit of a society, but he must take into consideration the enlightenment of his brothers, in order to uplift the Lithuanians into a higher culture. That the presidents of our societies must be educated persons, they must be readers of several Lithuanian newspapers. The presidents must know how dear the Lithuanianism is. Such presidents must tell the members of the society what are the activities among Lithuanians in other cities. The presidents of our societies must not be like senators and dictators to their members, they ought to be as enlighteners, to show their own good deeds to the members of society and to all the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>Chicagoan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
