<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Printers' News - the Mirror</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PRINTERS' NEWS - THE MIRROR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lithuanian readers have a special paper called The Mirror which is being published now. This paper will be exclusive in the field of art and the only paper of its kind in Chicago. It will contain only news pertaining to the theater and the scenes. This kind of paper is very desirable to have in Chicago. Most of our people don't understand the English language well enough to appreciate the news in American papers. Therefore, it is necessary for us to have this kind of paper in our own language.</p>
   <p>The theatres are playing an important part in the life of the Lithuanian people. The Lithuanian people love the music and the plays. The theater gives them pleasure, satisfaction, consolation, and helps them to forget their troubles when they come home tired from work.</p>
   <p>Today we have many theatres in almost every Lithuanian colony in Chicago, working ardently and organizing their own theatrical groups, writing their own plays, which deal with their national life in America <pb facs="5423970_2_1006.jpg" n="2"/>and Lithuania. Those who are organizing theatrical groups now are ordinary people and with no knowledge or understanding of art. They need instructors and advisers who know and understand the art of acting and who know the music which goes along with acting.</p>
   <p>Now we are very fortunate in having The Mirror, which will make every effort to improve our theatres and actors in the future. The first edition of The Mirror, according to our conditions in Chicago, was very good and quite an interesting paper.</p>
   <p>However, we cannot expect the first edition to be absolutely satisfactory and successful, but as time goes on the paper will improve little by little. We have to admit that we haven't any good writers in that field, those having a knowledge of art and music. Of course, some of us have a better knowledge than others, but those who have a better knowledge and who are more capable of doing things are not <pb facs="5423970_2_1007.jpg" n="3"/>interested in the field of art. We have to wait for some time until we will have more and better writers who will be interested in that line of writing.</p>
   <p>I think it would be much better for The Mirror to go along with the greater number of art and theatre lovers and to use the language or writing that can be understood by the general public, especially those who are interested most in art and music.</p>
   <p>This little paper has excellent plans and aims for developing our young artists and musicians and will arouse a greater interest among the youth in the field of art and music. The first edition of The Mirror was very good and we hope it continues to grow and improve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
