<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-02-09">Feb. 9, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Birute Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-02-09">Feb. 9, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTE PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Birute Society presented Rudolph Blauman's "The Evil Spirit," a three-act drama at St. George's Hall on February 4. The following actors participated: A. Stankauskas as "Jonas Vieversius," a farmer; P. Kriksciokiute as "Ona," his wife; B. Bernotaitiene as his mother; K. Vicas as Ona's brother, "Andrius"; Joana Miseviciute as "Jieva," a maid; A. Misevicia as the miser; R. Rudzikiute as "Lize," a neighbor; A. Siuksta as "Jurgis," a young man; H. Mockus as "Vilkas," a drunkard; S. Pronickas as "Vapsa," a farmer ; L. Miezinis as "Jankus," son of Ona and Jonas; B. Vaitiekunas as "Abraham," a Jew.</p>
   <p>The best performances by the actors were those of Bernotaitiene, J. Miseviciute, Vaitiekunas, and H. Mockus. The weaker acting was by Vicas, Stankauskas, Sileika, and Kriksciokiute. In the role of the miser, A. Misevicia was weak, <pb facs="5423970_2_0501.jpg" n="2"/>and it was apparent he was not in the spirit of his role. He could not put himself in the character of the miserly and insane person who was to be portrayed here.</p>
   <p>Kriksciokiute had a good role in which she could have displayed her talents and distinguished herself, but it proved to be beyond her scope. She could not in any way enter into the characterization and did not succeed in expressing the haughtiness, the arrogance in putting the maid, Ieva, in her place, enough to distinguish her and set her apart from her brother, Andrius, who is in love with Jieva.</p>
   <p>Vicas played his role better this time than usually, but it still was not good enough. He lacks sincerity and feeling, especially in love scenes. Miseviciute, who appeared on our stage for the first time, was very emotional. Her bearing on the stage is sympathetic and free, and a very good actress can be expected of her. She feels what she says; she lets her role absorb her. That is what our artists so often lack.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0502.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Vaitiekunas appeared as a Jew for the first time in Chicago, it seems. He is as successful in portraying a Jew as he is in other, especially comical, roles. P. Mockus portrayed the drunkard well. Though P. Stankunas fits into farmer roles it cannot be said that he gave a good portrayal this time. He was lacking in action, in sincerity, especially when he returned from a journey with the news that he had not won the two thousand rubles, as he had previously read in a newspaper. He should have shown more emotion, worry, frustration, but he just sat and calmly related the news. The others had shorter and weaker roles.</p>
   <p>After the drama, the Birute Chorus sang "To War," by Fred Beidel (formerly director of the V. Kudirka Singers' Society); "Fly, Falcon!" by C. Sosnauskas; and "The Chimes," by Fred Beidel. All three were sung by the Birute Chorus for the first time. They sang the first song, "To War," very beautifully; the second and third were not sung as well. The director of the Chorus is P. Sarpalius.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
