<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Dr. V. Kudirka Theatrical Singers Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 10,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE DR. V. KUDIRKA THEATRICAL SINGERS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the city of Chicago there are many Lithuanian societies. Among these societies there are the Aurora Society, the Lithuanian Alliance of America branches, the Lithuanian Socialist Labor Party, and the Lovers of Fatherland Society. But the most important society of all of them is the Dr. V. Kudirka Theatrical and Singers Society. No other society brings such a benefit to humanity as this society. Every member of this society has a chance to train his voice. At the same time when this society sings at the banquets it gives pleasure to the listening people. Up to the present time we, Lithuanians, of Chicago, have no large chorus; with over 30,000 Lithuanians in Chicago it is a disgrace not to have a large Lithuanian chorus. We are no worse than other people; why then should we stay behind them? Therefore all the Lithuanian youth who have good voices, come and join this singers' organization; help us build the best Lithuanian singing society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0333.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The saying is that Lithuania is the country of songs. Now then, let us join this society; let us bring back the beautiful Lithuanian songs and singing.</p>
   <p>The practice of the chorus is held every Sunday at 2 P. M., 869 33rd Place. All the young Lithuanian men and girls who want to exalt the spirit of the beautiful Lithuanian songs, come and join the only Lithuanian theatrical singing society in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Z-tes Boy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
