<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Statistical Survey of Chicago Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">STATISTICAL SURVEY OF CHICAGO LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The results of statistical surveys of individual Chicago Lithuanian colonies were published in previous issues of the Lietuva (Lithuania). Today, we are publishing the combined results of all these surveys, which cover all the Lithuanians of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>Altogether, there are one hundred nineteen Lithuanian organizations in Chicago. They are located in the following Lithuanian colonies: twenty-five in Bridgeport; eighteen in the 18th and Halsted Streets colony; twenty-two in the West Side or McCormick colony; twenty in Town of Lake; eleven in the North Side colony; seven in the Roseland and Kensington colonies; four in South Chicago; three in West Pullman; two in Melrose Park; and two in Grant Works (Cicero, Ill.). These figures include lodges and branches of national Lithuanian organizations.</p>
   <p>These one hundred nineteen organizations are divided as follows: sixty-two <pb facs="5423970_2_0074.jpg" n="2"/>are non-Catholic; forty-one are Catholic; ten political; two Lutheran; three are mixed; and two are Polish-Lithuanian societies.</p>
   <p>The character of these societies is classified as follows: seventy-four are benefit societies; twenty lodges and branches of national Lithuanian organizations; eleven clubs; seven building and loan associations; six educational societies; eight commercial organizations; five women's societies; three skilled workers societies; three musical societies; two dramatic societies; and two companies. [Translator's note: -- The total of these figures amounts to one hundred forty-one. Apparently, the twenty lodges and branches and the two companies are not included in the one hundred nineteen figure given above].</p>
   <p>The lodges and branches of national Lithuanian organizations are classified as follows: Eight lodges of the Lithuanian Alliance of America (fraternal); four lodges of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance of America (fraternal); four branches of the Lithuanian Socialist League; three branches of the <pb facs="5423970_2_0075.jpg" n="3"/>Lovers of the Fatherland Society (cultural); and one branch of the Auskra (Dawn) Society (students' aid and general educational society).</p>
   <p>Only five of the clubs are of a political character.</p>
   <p>The largest number (fourteen) of non-Catholic societies are located in the West Side or McCormick colony. The largest number (ten) of Catholic organizations are located in the Bridgeport colony. The largest number (three) of political organizations are in the 18th Street colony.</p>
   <p>The number of public Lithuanian institutions and professionals are as follows: Seven churches; one convent; eight schools (one non-Catholic, and seven Catholic); three halls (one non-Catholic, and two Catholic); one astronomical observatory; one library; four periodicals. Eight medical doctors; one dentist; one attorney; twelve priests; one commercial artist; four building contractors; seven mid-wives; one judge; six policemen; and one constable.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0076.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There are four hundred forty-three Lithuanian business men in Chicago. They are located in the following colonies: one hundred twelve in Town of Lake; one hundred ten in Bridgeport; seventy in the 18th Street colony; twenty-one on the North Side; thirty-seven in the West Side or McCormick colony; fifteen in the 47th Street and Wentworth Avenue colony; fifteen in South Chicago; eleven in Melrose Park; eighteen in Kensington; nine in West Pullman; six in Roseland; and nineteen in Grant Works (Cicero, Ill.).</p>
   <p>Thirty of the Lithuanian business men own two or more business establishments. Altogether, there are five hundred four Lithuanian business establishments in Chicago. They are classified as follows: one hundred eighty saloons; eighty-eight food stores; thirty-two barber shops; seventeen tailor shops; fourteen steamship agencies; ten printing shops; eleven cigar and confectionary stores; eleven dairy stores; eleven wagon renting services; thirteen real estate agencies; ten photo studios; nine clothing stores; six book stores; six cleaning and dyeing shops; five musical instrument stores; seven shoe-repair shops; <pb facs="5423970_2_0077.jpg" n="5"/>six shoe stores; five men's furnishings stores; seven insurance (fire) agencies; six undertakers; seven bakery shops; four plumbing shops; four cigar factories; five bath houses; four furniture stores; two watch and jewelry stores; three hardware stores; two general stores; two livery stables; four drug stores; one bank; one postal sub-station; six notaries public; one coal yard; one ice cream parlor; one picnic grove; one baseball park; and one blacksmith.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
