<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. III, No. 7,
<date when="1895-02-16">Feb. 16, 1895</date><title level="a">The Society of Simonas Daukantas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. III, No. 7,
<date when="1895-02-16">Feb. 16, 1895</date><title level="a">THE SOCIETY OF SIMONAS DAUKANTAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have in Chicago seven Lithuanian societies of men and two societies of women. Each and every one of those societies are alike. But the society of Simonas Daukantas is entirely different. The main principle of societies is to pay five dollars per week to their sick members and nothing more. But the society of Simonas Daukantas has a different purpose. It does not care much about an expensive funeral, but the society's main duty is to give more to its members than five dollars per week when you are sick. Such a sick benefit always expires with the funeral.</p>
   <p>Our society's aim is to educate and uplift from misery the poor Lithuanians who had no education, who cannot even read or sign their names. Our effort is to educate Lithuanians so that they can go forward with other oultured nations, that they would not be behind other nationalites. For this reason this society has its library, and though the library is small we believe that we are doing a great educational work among our brother Lithuanians. The library will be improved. We are getting more books and Lithuanian newspapers. Later on we will establish a school to teach the Lithuanians the English language and other educational subjects. Education <pb facs="5423970_2_0727.jpg" n="2"/>never dies. Parents will leave their education to their children. Only through education. we can put our Lithuanians on a solid ground. Therefore, we are saying that the education is more important than the five dollars per week of sick benefit, and the expensive funerals. This is the purpose that our society stands for.</p>
   <p>We are asking our Lithuanians to join this educational society. Through enlightenment and education we will uplift ourselves and our children for a better life. Before, many Lithuanians objected to joining our society. They said that there were many infidels. We had a few infidels, but now they are stricken out of our society. Now all members are good Catholics. No danger in joining our society now.</p>
   <p>Officials of Simonas Daukantas Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
