<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Keistutis Benefit Club</title>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Keistutis Benefit Club, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1777</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1777.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian Keistutis Benefit Club</title>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Keistutis Benefit Club, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This club was organized on October 6, 1911.</p>
   <p>The sponsors of this liberal club were John Alex Androvicius, Stanislavas Pabedinskas and Leonas Strogis. The first meeting of these sponsors was held at the home of Mr. L. Strogis, 38th Place and Kedzie Avenue. Mr. Stogis was the first to give one dollar for the organization of this new club. He was followed by J. Alexandravicis, S. Pobedinskis and others. A total of $7.00 was donated.</p>
   <p>The first meeting of this club was held on October 15, 1911 at L. Strogis.</p>
   <p>John Alexandravicis was the chairman at this meeting and Felix Bieliauskas the secretary; he entered the names of those who joined this club. Seventy-two members joined. F. Pobedinskas suggested for this new club the name of "Strazdas" - The Robin, while S. Pobedinskas suggested "Kleistutis." For the name of "Strazdas" there were two votes, for "Keistutis", ten votes.</p>
   <p>The Club's Accomplishments:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1778.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the year 1919, a ball was held for Br. Vargses - (Laucevicia) to build for him a monument. The profits were $120. The club donated $15. (Trans. Note: - poor ocie, was his literary name. His real name was Laucevicuys. He was a great writer of comedies and tragedies. He died at thirty-six years of age in 1915.)</p>
   <p>In March, 1921 there was donated to the Szernas Fund, $30. (Szernas, - his real name Joseph Adomoitis. He was the editor of the newspaper Lietuva. He wrote many scientific books.)</p>
   <p>In November, 1921 donated $50.00 to the starving people of Russia.</p>
   <p>November, 1921 joined the Friend's of Soviet Russia with monthly dues of $2.</p>
   <p>March, 1922 it held a banquet for the benefit of the starving people of Russia. The profits were $100.68.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1779.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In July, 1922. Donated $10. for the monument of Zemaite (Trans. note: Zemaite was her literary name. Her real name was Julia Zymontas. She was a great story writer. She wrote about the life of the peasants. Died December 7, 1921 over seventy years of age).</p>
   <p>In july, 1922. Donated $25. for the Szernas monument fund.</p>
   <p>In December, 1922. Donated $5. for the Zemaite monument fund.</p>
   <p>In January, 1923. The union with the Friend's of Soviet Russia was dissolved.</p>
   <p>In July, 1922, and February, 1924 the club joined the protest against the discriminations against the rights of foreigners.</p>
   <p>In July, 1926 it donated $32. for the Textile strikers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1780.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In August, 1926. A resolution was adopted aginast the Massachusetts government, demanding the freedom of Sacco-Vanzetti.</p>
   <p>In February, 1927. A protest was sent to the representatives of Lithuania in Washington, D.C. against the overthrowing of the legal government in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>In February, 1927. There delegates were sent to the anti-fascist's council of the Chicago Lithuanian societies.</p>
   <p>In December, 1927 it donated $25. for the monument fund of Szernas.</p>
   <p>In January, 1928. A protest resolution was brought forth against the restriction of the rights of foreigners.</p>
   <p>In August, 1928 it donated $13.75 for the striking miners.</p>
   <p>In September, 1928. The Anti-Fascist Committee was dissolved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1781.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In December, 1930 there was organized a fund to help the unemployed. The club donated $10. The members contributed $40.00 for the cause.</p>
   <p>In March, 1933 the unemployed fund committee was dissolved.</p>
   <p>In April, 1934 a banquet was held for the benefit of the A.L.T.Assn. for the second flight to Lithuania and for the Darius-Girenas monument fund. The profits made were $68.</p>
   <p>To the Keistutis Club were joined the following societies and clubs:</p>
   <p>December, 1927. The Liberty Club (formerly the All Saints Society) with eighty-four members, and the assets of $1,481.</p>
   <p>July, 1931. The society of the Sons of Lithuania, with sixty members.</p>
   <p>June, 1933. The The Theatrical Society of Simonas Daukantas, with ninety members and assets of $ 3,125.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1782.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>February, 1933. The Society of the Grand Duke Algirdas of Lithuania, with one-hundred members,and assets of $1,580.</p>
   <p>February, 1933. The Society of the Workers' Union with, seventy-five members, and assets of $2,431.</p>
   <p>1933. The Society of the Love of Lithuania, with sixty-eight members, and assets of $700.</p>
   <p>1933. The Lovers of the Fatherland Society, No. 1, with fifty members, and assets of $620.</p>
   <p>1933. The First Division of the Grand Duke Algirdas of Lithuania, with seventy-five members, and assets of $1,000.</p>
   <p>1933. Simonas Daukantas Society Theatrical Youth Club.</p>
   <p>1933. The Society of the Grand Duke Vytautas of Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1783.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>1933. The Society of Men and Women, with eighty members, and assets of $700.</p>
   <p>To the Lithuanian Keistutis Benefit Club the members pay fifty-five cents per month. The sick benefit is $5 per week. To the deceased heirs $300.00 is paid from the treasury of the club.</p>
   <p>The total membership is about $1,350. The assets are $28,000.00, good accounts are $22,000.</p>
   <p>The books kept during the early period of the club are lost; so the income and the expenses will be given from 1920 to 1936.</p>
   <p>During the last fifteen years the total amount of membership fees paid was $62,865.68. From banquets the profits were $2,299.25. From picnics -$2,849.40. From interest -$2,393.41. Total income $70,407.78.</p>
   <p>The Expenses were as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1784.jpg" n="8"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Death benefits paid were</cell>
     <cell>$30,065.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sick benefits " are</cell>
     <cell>22,976.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Coffin bearers</cell>
     <cell>1,478.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Automobiles</cell>
     <cell>1,395.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Flowers and wreaths</cell>
     <cell>1,075.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Salaries</cell>
     <cell>2,989.55</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Rings (presents)</cell>
     <cell>1,629.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For the By-laws</cell>
     <cell>$987.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Press and Postal cards</cell>
     <cell>825.55</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For inspection of the books</cell>
     <cell>130.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To Lawyers</cell>
     <cell>452.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donations</cell>
     <cell>445.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Stamps</cell>
     <cell>60.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Presents to the Park Authorities</cell>
     <cell>45.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$63,832.53</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>During this time the profits were $6,575.25.</p>
   <p>The club's officers of this year (1937):</p>
   <p>J. Kundraska, president, 2841 W. 40th. P1.</p>
   <p>B. Kiler, secretary, 5332 S. Long Ave.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
