<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-15">Oct. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Activities in Roseland, Illinois</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Vitkauskas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-15">Oct. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN ACTIVITIES IN ROSELAND, ILLINOIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Vitkauskas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The directors of the Ausra (The Dawn) Library in Roseland, Illinois, opened an evening school for Lithuanians on September 21. Sixteen students enrolled on the first day of the school. Two-hour classes in the study of the English language were held three evenings each week. Later, on October 6, it was decided to hold classes six evenings each week and, besides English, add the study of arithmetic and, if possible, the study of the Lithuanian language. This decision became effective on October 11. Mr. Zigmas Vitkauskas is the teacher. Now the Ausra Evening School has about thirty-two students of both sexes.</p>
   <p>The Ausra Library and School are supported by eight progressive (liberal) Lithuanian organizations of Roseland, Illinois. None of the Catholic organizations contribute to the support of these two educational institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the benefit of the uninformed, the Ausra Library of this colony is not connected in any way with the Ausra Library and Ausra Society in Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>A benefit affair for the Ausra School was given on September 26 by the eight supporting organizations in Stancikas Hall. A two-act comedy entitled "Nuo Degtines" (Effects of Intoxicating Drinks) [sic], written by L. Tolstoy and translated into the Lithuanian language, was staged by a group of Lithuanian actors and actresses. The program also included an oration, recitations, a dialogue, and two solos with a cornet and guitar. Herman's orchestra entertained the audience with a few musical numbers. The Aidas (Echo) Chorus was also scheduled to participate on the program. However, Mr. J. Karalius, director of the chorus, failed to arrive and for that reason the chorus was unable to perform. About five hundred people attended the affair, which was, generally speaking, a success.</p>
   <p>A committee of the above-mentioned eight organizations is making plans to <pb facs="5423970_2_1306.jpg" n="3"/>launch an educational campaign among the Lithuanians of the colony during the coming winter season. It was decided to hold lectures, orations, debates, and discussions twice each month in the Ausra Library, which is located at 10900 South Michigan Avenue. Plans have also been made for a group visit to the Field Museum of Natural History. An arrangements committee of three members was elected for the above purpose.</p>
   <p>Employment has slightly increased in this district. For that reason the people are happier.</p>
   <p>There are several hundred books in the Ausra Library. These books can be read by anyone free of charge. The following Lithuanian-American newspapers and periodicals come to the library and are available to visitors: Lietuva (Lithuania), Vienybe Lietuvninku (Unity of Lithuanians), Amerikos Lietuvis (The Lithuanian-American), Draugas (The Friend), Keleivis (The Traveller), Laisve (Liberty), Kova (The Struggle), Ateitis (The Future), <pb facs="5423970_2_1307.jpg" n="4"/>Naujienos (News), Jaunoji Lietuva (Young Lithuania), and Saule (The Sun).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
