<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-25">Dec. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A. Olszevskis' New Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-25">Dec. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A. OLSZEVSKIS' NEW THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A. Olszevskis' new theater, at 3138-3142 South Halsted Street, near 32nd Street, is already completed and will be opened on Christmas Day, December 25, 1914, at 2:15 p.m., with vaudeville and motion pictures.</p>
   <p>From Christmas Day on, excellent shows will be presented here at very low prices every evening. On Saturdays, Sundays, and other holidays there will be so-called "matinees" in the afternoons.</p>
   <p>The prices of tickets: Saturday and Sunday evenings the main floor and loges will be fifteen cents; the balcony, ten cents.</p>
   <p>On all other evenings, and for the matinees, the main floor seats will be ten cents; balcony,five cents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0047.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A Lithuanian name, Milda, has been given to this theater.</p>
   <p>Milda, as you know, is the goddess of love and art in Lithuanian mythology. Therefore, this is an appropriate name for a theater.</p>
   <p>The Milda Theater is the most beautiful in the southern part of Chicago. Built according to the newest regulations of the Chicago Building Code, it is constructed of steel and cement (absolutely fire-proof), with the best sanitary conveniences, ventilation, and a large, fully-equipped stage.</p>
   <p>It is as beautifully decorated as the large theaters downtown and it cost no less than the downtown theaters.</p>
   <p>In this building, besides the theater, there are also two beautiful halls suitable for parties, banquets, dances, and meetings. Beneath the theater there <pb facs="5423970_2_0048.jpg" n="3"/>are large rooms with billiard tables and bowling alleys. There is a Lithuanian buffet on the main floor, in front.</p>
   <p>This theater building is seventy-five feet wide and a hundred and thirty-five feet long. It takes up almost half a block. It is the biggest, most beautiful, and most expensive building in this part of the city. It is most conveniently located, and can easily be reached from all parts of the city because the Halsted Street cars run every minute.</p>
   <p>It was built by the A. Olszevskis Bank.</p>
   <p>If you wish to pass an hour of your free time gaily, come to the Milda Theater and you will not regret having spent five cents for a ticket. Here you will see a better show for five cents than you would downtown for fifty cents.</p>
   <p>It will open Christmas Day, December 25, 1914, at 2:15 p.m.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: An illustration of the building is included in this advertisement.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
