<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-05-09">May 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Lithuanian Girl Artist at the Chicago Art Institute</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-05-09">May 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A LITHUANIAN GIRL ARTIST AT THE CHICAGO ART INSTITUTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the near future, at the Chicago Art Institute, there will be an art exhibition. According to the statement of the newspaper Draugas (Friend), the Lithuanian girl artist Miss E. B. Grigaitis, will participate in this art exhibition.</p>
   <p>About this Lithuanian girl artist, we find more information. The newspaper Draugas states:</p>
   <p>"Miss Grigaitis is working at the Chicago Portrait Company. Her most important piece of work is her water-color painting in the Lithuanian parish at New Philadelphia, Pa. of the parish hall curtain depicting a Sunday scene in front of St. Peter's Church, in Vilnus, Lithuania.</p>
   <p>"Miss Grigaitis was born in Griskabudis parish, Lithuania. She was a little girl when her parents brought her to America. They settled in Grand Rapids, Mich., where that little girl attended school..... She studied art <pb facs="5423970_2_0184.jpg" n="2"/>with the Sisters of the Innocent Heart at Scranton, Pa., and later at the Chicago Art Institute.....</p>
   <p>"Miss Grigaitis is not the only Lithuanian student who obtained her art education at the Chicago Art Institute. Miss Viensiutis attended this institution as did Mr. J. Aleksandravicius, who at present has an art school in Kaunas, Lithuania; also Messrs.J. Kodis and J. Sileikis, who are now attending the King Academy, an art school in Munich, Germany.</p>
   <p>"We wish the greatest success to our young girl artist. At the same time we urge our Lithuanians, when they need some artistic work done, as curtains, scenery, decorations, etc., to give orders to Miss Grigaitis."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
