<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Lietuva Readers and Friends</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO LIETUVA READERS AND FRIENDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We hereby notify the readers and friends of the newspaper Lietuva (Lithuania) that on June 1, 1917, we, the undersigned, purchased Lietuva.</p>
   <p>"During the past few weeks, because of the reorganization of the bank of A. Olsauskas (Olszewski) into the Universal State Bank, a bank coming under governmental regulations, the administration of the newspaper was neglected to a great extent. This neglect, though unavoidable and unintentional, caused various inconveniences to readers of the paper. Since we have taken over the affairs of the newspaper, our immediate concern has been to take care of all unfinished business with the thought of giving our readers and friends quick and conscientious service. Already Lietuva has honestly and usefully served the Lithuanian-American public for twenty-five years. During all those years of faithful service the newspaper has earned the respect and honor of the Lithuanian-American public of Chicago and elsewhere. This newspaper will continue to serve its readers and the Lithuanian-American public as faithfully as it did in the past. As far as we will be able, we <pb facs="5423970_2_0939.jpg" n="2"/>will strive constantly to improve the paper and make it still more useful to our people. On the other hand, we believe that all Lietuva's old friends and supporters, of which there was always a large number, will continue to remain friends and supporters of Lietuva now, and will boost Lietuva always and everywhere with their good words, advice, subscriptions, etc.</p>
   <p>"The office and the printing plant of Lietuva remain in the same place; however, the entrance to the office has been changed. Whereas it used to be through the bank at 3252 South Halsted Street, the entrance will now be at 814 West 33rd Street. Therefore, the new address of Lietuva is 814 West 33rd Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>"Joseph J. Baciunas</p>
   <p>"John P. Pajauskas."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
