<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-03-01">Mar. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">"For Love"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jo. Vis-Kas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-03-01">Mar. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">"FOR LOVE"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Jo. Vis-Kas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dramatic Circle of the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance presented Togobocni's drama "For Love" at the Hull House Theater on February 25. It is an important and educational classical drama. It is only regrettable that the resources of the Dramatic Circle were too poor for the presenting of such a play. Short-comings in characterization were apparent everywhere. For example, Sarah (M. Dunduliene) should have been younger, not of so husky a build (she would have fitted in the role of an old widow); Leiba (J. Sankunas) looked too young, compared to his daughter, Sarah, but he did play his part exceptionally well. John (U. Zuktveris) did not look at all like the type whom girls would love blindly. He should have been a special sort of character instead of an ordinary peasant type. As it was, it looked very odd, unnatural. What kind of half-wits would those girls have to be if they chased after, fought, and committed suicide over such an ignorant, repulsive character--who, <pb facs="5423970_2_0497.jpg" n="2"/>furthermore, was poor! Danute (Algminaviciute) played her part well but, just the same, she did not impress one as being blindly, madly in love, nor as a vindictive person, nor as a villain demanding a child's blood.</p>
   <p>The characters in this drama are so unusual that their correct portrayal requires great talent, experience, study, and general understanding. The actors must fit their roles not only physically, but especially in spirit and in mind. Lacking these requirements, the performance did not make a great, tragic impression because the players did not posses the necessary spiritual and mental qualities. The audience occasionally laughed. Why did they laugh? There was nothing to laugh at. Perhaps the audience was too ignorant? Did it not understand the play? Perhaps many did not understand it, but the most ordinary man can understand emotions if they are presented to him faithfully. The common people give way to emotions even more willingly than the learned. Let us take that one moment when Leiba tragically damns his daughter. It made a great impression on everybody. If Sarah had not appeared so fat when he was <pb facs="5423970_2_0498.jpg" n="3"/>grieving for her because she was so thin and stunted by work it would not have been funny. Sarah's elopement is also a tragic situation, but as she squirmed through the window, exclaiming: "Oh, it is so difficult!"--it was funny, for it really looked difficult for her to climb through a window, because of her weight. Such statements apply also to Uktveris who, God knows with what, fascinated the Jewess and Danute.</p>
   <p>Buragas and Juska portrayed the roles of drunken peasants excellently. The townspeople and beggars were also excellent, appearing natural. Such roles are familiar to, and understood by Lithuanians. Our actors cannot go far in their portrayals of roles which are unfamiliar and which must be studied.</p>
   <p>Sankunas had an unusually difficult role, but he managed to distinguish himself in it. Algminaviciute showed that she has talent and can act, but she is still lacking in experience. A good actress can be expected of her if she will strive to work more and gain experience on the stage.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0499.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Others, having smaller roles, were: M. Kriksciokiute, Kalvaiciute, J. Prusinskas, Vilnaite, Augustinavicius. We cannot avoid especially mentioning Prusinskas, one of our foremost actors, who conscientiously enacts all the roles he accepts.</p>
   <p>The attendance was so large that many could not be seated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
