<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian School in Englewood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN SCHOOL IN ENGLEWOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 12, two speeches were given by Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, a student of medicine, and Mr. Vinips, who spoke in English, for the purpose of securing more members for the Lithuanian Y.A. Club (What do these letters mean?--Editor of Lietuva) in order to help it to grow. The aim of this club is to establish a school for Lithuanian youth, but the financial conditions of the club do not permit it to have a school. Last winter this club did have one but this year, because of lack of money, the school cannot be continued.</p>
   <p>The existence of such a school is very essential because we are living in this country, and we must learn the English language. That is the purpose of this school. To be sure, there are public schools but they are not accessible to us; they are too far away and the transportation expenses are too high. It is very difficult for a tired workingman to take long trips to school. In the place of the public schools, we must <pb facs="5423970_2_1333.jpg" n="2"/>have a school nearer to us. Although such a school could not continue its existence because of lack of funds, we hope that these speeches will help to improve its situation for the speakers stressed the necessity of supporting such a school, and the benefit of knowing the English language by those who live in this country. After the speeches, several new members joined our club.</p>
   <p>Last year, the teacher was an American, but this year we want to have a Lithuanian instructor in his place. Thereby it would be much easier to study the English language, because he could explain in Lithuanian the meaning of the English, and it would help us to learn more quickly.</p>
   <p>Especially those Lithuanians who recently came to America should attend such a school. It would be much better if every Lithuanian would join this club. The meetings are held on the first Saturday evening after the fifteenth of the month, at 8 P.M. in J. Baukus hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
