<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-28">May 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Press Conference</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0971</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0971.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-28">May 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN PRESS CONFERENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>V. K. Rackauskas, secretary of the Lithuanian Press Society, officially announced that the fifth conference of the Society will take place this year on June 11, 12, and 13, in Chicago, Illinois. The Lithuanian-American intelligentsia are also officially invited to participate in the conference "so that it will be possible jointly to discuss not only matters pertaining to our press, but also questions of general interest to all Lithuanians in America."</p>
   <p>The following Chicago Lithuanian publications are members of the Society: Lietuva (Lithuania), Jaunoji Lietuva (Young Lithuania), Laisvoji Mintis (Free Thought), and the Katalikas (The Catholic).</p>
   <p>Unquestionably, the participation of our intelligentsia in that conference is <pb facs="5423970_2_0972.jpg" n="2"/>no less important than that of the representatives of our press. At present, outside of the Lithuanian Press Society, we do not have any other organization or institution within which it is possible freely and independently to discuss the national interests of Lithuanian-Americans.</p>
   <p>It is true that some of our large organizations occasionally discuss at their conventions questions of common interest to all Lithuanians in America. However, the activities of these organizations are confined to certain specialized fields. For that reason, they discuss various public matters only insofar as they are related to the interests of the organizations. Furthermore, organizations which are over-burdened with their own activities have very little time to discuss matters foreign to the interests of their own groups.</p>
   <p>The press conference presents an excellent opportunity for a broad discussion of our public problems and interests. There are a number of problems pertaining only to our press. For example, the question of standardizing the spelling <pb facs="5423970_2_0973.jpg" n="3"/>of the Lithuanian language is of utmost importance. Almost every editor or writer in America, and even in Lithuania, spells Lithuanian words differently..... This problem was discussed at previous conferences of the Society, but it is still unsolved.....</p>
   <p>The question of decency in our press was widely discussed in our publications a short time ago. It was also discussed at previous conferences of the Society, but without any definite results.....This question is important; it should be discussed at the coming conference and a definite decision should be made on the matter.</p>
   <p>Another important question is the problem of raising funds for the relief of war victims in Lithuania, At present there are three different Lithuanian war relief funds in America; one has been set up by each of the three Lithuanian-American factions: Nationalists, Socialists, and Catholics. If this work is unified and better organized it will unquestionably produce much better results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0974.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Closer relations should be established between our press and the Lithuanian public. Such unity would result in greater efforts for our general welfare. Press conferences, with the participation of our intelligentsia, present the best opportunity for establishing and maintaining closer ties between the press and the public.</p>
   <p>It is hoped that the coming conference will not fail to consider the above suggestions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
