<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Reaction of Lithuanian Lecture to Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Kleofas Jurgelonis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">REACTION OF LITHUANIAN LECTURE TO AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Kleofas Jurgelonis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.... My lecture before the exclusive Chicago Woman's Club on Lithuanian Renaissance literature was a great novelty to the"high society"women. An account of various reactions to the lecture ought to be interesting.</p>
   <p>A large group of club members and their friends attended the lecture. I was told that it was the largest audience attending a literary lecture in the history of the club. That is most probably due to the fact that the present world war has popularized the question of "self-determination" for minority groups. For that reason many wished to get acquainted with one of these minority nationalities. It is highly probable that before the war very few people would have attended such a lecture.</p>
   <p>The audience, which was composed entirely of aged women, listened with attentive interest and displayed great interest.</p>
   <p>The fact that only aged women attended is not at all surprising, because that <pb facs="5423970_2_1446.jpg" n="2"/>is typical of American life, that is, only wealthy aged people are interested and engaged in various cultural activities. In Lithuania, or Russia such a lecture would attract young people. But here the young people are engaged only in play, such as baseball, football, and dancing. The middle aged people are deeply engaged in business. Only the old people remain to look after the cultural interests of the nation in science, art, literature, and music.</p>
   <p>However, many women in the audience appeared to possess youthful spirits. Some were thrilled by Lithuanian poems; many enjoyed the "Dainos," Lithuanian folk songs. Edith Wyatt, famous author, was especially delighted by the "Dainos" before a gathering of Chicago writers and authors where the famous American poet Amy Lowell of Boston was an honored guest.</p>
   <p>After I finished my lecture I was interviewed by many members of the audience. I noted that the Irish were especially interested in the Lithuanian language, songs, and struggle for national independence. They informed me that Irish history and literature were in many respects similar to that of the Lithuanians. The intonation of folk songs too was considered as another mark of similarity <pb facs="5423970_2_1447.jpg" n="3"/>Some of the women, who are collectors of folk lore material, asked for more detailed information about Lithuanian folk songs and strongly urged their publication in the American press. Others asked: "What is the reason that the magazine of the Geographic Society of America never publishes a story on Lithuania? That should be done, because it would be extremely interesting.</p>
   <p>I had dinner with several members of the club, where the interview continued. I was asked and in return answered many questions. One woman said:"I live in St. Charles,Ill., where there is a large Lithuanian colony. I would be very glad to do something for them." She finally decided to purchase a few Lithuanian books for the St. Charles Public Library.</p>
   <p>The members of the Chicago Woman's Club especially impressed me with their loveliness, which appears to be a genuine characteristic. They were very generous with compliments.</p>
   <p>However, I was most pleased to see how well they all enjoyed my lecture. I am very thankful to Mrs. Jerome, who used her influence to make it possible for me to <pb facs="5423970_2_1448.jpg" n="4"/>deliver a lecture on Lithuanian literature before the most exclusive Chicago Woman's Club.</p>
   <p>The favorable reaction of the lecture proves that a book of Lithuanian folk songs in the English language would be well received by the American people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
