<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-14">May 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Is There a Need for a Lithuanian Women's Periodical?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-05-14">May 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IS THERE A NEED FOR A LITHUANIAN WOMEN'S PERIODICAL?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A suggestion to establish a Lithuanian women's periodical has been made in our press. The suggestion is supported by the following points: There are sections that deal with the affairs of women in many of our publications; women are equal to men; it is probable (but not certain) that women have as many interests as men; periodicals for the discussion of women's affairs are as much needed as those dealing with the interests of men; Lithuanian-American women do not have a periodical of their own. Therefore, one should be established.</p>
   <p>The above arguments, with the little loophole "if," form the basis of the proposal. However, the author kills his suggestion with further arguments. He asks himself the question: Who conducts the sections for women's affairs in our press? He finds that these sections are conducted by male editors with the aid <pb facs="5423970_2_1130.jpg" n="2"/>of a few women. In some publications the women's sections are conducted entirely without the aid of women; these sections are often filled with articles written by men using feminine pen names, because of the scarcity of Lithuanian women writers.</p>
   <p>If women do not write for the women's sections in our press, then it is apparent that they are not interested in them. Another possible explanation is that our women are not sufficiently "mature" and "cultured" to understand their "feminine" interests. Evidently they are not even aware of any "feminine interests" if it is necessary for men to substitute for women in order to create the impression that there is a Lithuanian feminine movement in the United States.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding other arguments, a conclusion against the proposal to establish a women's periodical must be drawn from the fact that our women are not interested in the women's sections of our publications. If our women are unable to conduct, or to show an appreciable degree of interest in, the present women's sections of our publications, and if men are forced to substitute for women in <pb facs="5423970_2_1131.jpg" n="3"/>order to supply reading matter for these sections, then how will our women be able to conduct and maintain a periodical of their own?</p>
   <p>Furthermore, if there is really a need for a women's periodical, in spite of the above arguments, then the proposal for such a periodical should at least originate among the women. The author of the present suggestion is not a woman, but a man.</p>
   <p>In the fifty-ninth number of the Laisvoji Mintis (Free Thought) the author of the proposal asks and answers the question: Can our women support a periodical of their own? He gives an affirmative answer, stating that "if our men, who are only slightly more intellectually advanced than our women, can support and maintain as many as twenty-four publications in America, then why cannot our women issue and support one publication devoted to their own interests?"</p>
   <p>The author is slightly mistaken. Those twenty-four publications are supported not by men alone, but equally by men and women. Furthermore, our publications <pb facs="5423970_2_1132.jpg" n="4"/>are not specifically devoted to the affairs of men; they are devoted to the interests of all Lithuanians, men and women alike. We do not have even one publication devoted solely to the interests of men. Therefore, the fact that twenty-four Lithuanian publications are able to exist in America cannot be used as an argument that it would be possible for one women's periodical to exist.</p>
   <p>There is no foundation for the belief that a group of Lithuanian women with various political and religious convictions would be able "to discuss and promote the welfare of all Lithuanian-American women". If men are unable to act impartially then how can we expect women of various political and religious convictions to act in harmony? Women are divided in their opinions in the same degree as men; this is evident among American women of other nationalities. It is quite true that a woman likes a man of her own convictions far better than [she likes] a woman of opposite convictions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
