<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1927-01-03">Jan. 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Starting the New Year</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1927-01-03">Jan. 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">STARTING THE NEW YEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once again we say good-by to the old year - 1926 - and say hello to the new year-1927. The Vilnis is greeting a new year for the first time as a daily working class newspaper.</p>
   <p>The Vilnis had been faithfully serving the cause of the Lithuanian working class movement in the Middle West for over five years. The first issue of the Vilnis appeared on April 8, 1920, as a weekly newspaper. Later it was converted into a semi-weekly. On <pb facs="5423970_2_0818.jpg" n="2"/>Sept. 18, 1926, thanks to the courageous and untiring efforts of our working class organizations and individuals, the Vilnis became a daily. The Lithuanian-American labor movement now has two daily newspapers -- the Laisve (Liberty), in the eastern states, and the Vilnis (The Wave), in the Middle West.</p>
   <p>The Vilnis is the first Lithuanian working class newspaper published in Chicago. The two extinct Lithuanian dailies that were published in Chicago -- the Lietuva and the Katalikas -- were not working class newspapers because they were mainly in the service of the Lithuanian bourgeoisie. The same is true with the other two active Lithuanian dailies in Chicago -- the Naujienos and <pb facs="5423970_2_0819.jpg" n="3"/>the Draugas. The Vilnis is the only Lithuanian daily in Chicago exclusively in the service of the Lithuanian working class movement.</p>
   <p>Just as we had predicted the Daily Vilnis has caused a great increase in activity and power among the Lithuanian-American working class. No other Lithuanian newspaper in America has such a large army of contributors, correspondents, and friends.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in starting another new year, the Vilnis, promises not only to remain in the service of the working class, but also promises to make an effort to improve the contents of the Daily Vilnis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0820.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The old year is dead, a new year has been born, but our trials and tribulations are old. Beginning with the new year, we must labor with new energy, and with renewed determination to make the new year more successful than the past year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
