<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-10-04">Oct. 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Lithuanian Newspapermen's Conference</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-10-04">Oct. 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE LITHUANIAN NEWSPAPERMEN'S CONFERENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following newspapers were represented in the third Lithuanian newspapermen's conference: Vienybē Lietuvninku, Katalikas, Lietuva, Tevynē, Darbininku Viltis, Laisvoji Mintis, and Dagis.</p>
   <p>The conference was held in Chicago. The meetings began Friday, September 27, at the Bismarck Hotel.</p>
   <p>After the meeting of the Press Society had been called to order, it was brought to president J. M. Tananevičius' attention that the following newspapers were participating in the conference:</p>
   <p>1. From the editorial board of the Lietuva: L. Šernas and B. K. Balutis; representing the publishers: A. Olševskis and J. Hertmanavičius.</p>
   <p>2. From the editorial board of the Katalikas: P. Brandukas and J. Viskoška; <pb facs="5423970_2_1030.jpg" n="2"/>representing the publishers: J. M. Tananevičius and S. Tananevicius.</p>
   <p>3. Representing the editors and administration of Vienybē Lietuvninku, J. Širvydas.</p>
   <p>4. From Laisvoji Mintis, the editor and publisher, Dr. J. Šliupas.</p>
   <p>5. From the editorial board of the Tēvynē, its specially authorized correspondent, K. Jurgelionis.</p>
   <p>6. From the Dagis, P. Brandukas.</p>
   <p>A. Kvederas, reporter for the Kova, also presented his credentials at this time.</p>
   <p>The editorial office of Draugas announced that, because of various reasons, Draugas could not participate, but asked that the resolutions of the conference <pb facs="5423970_2_1031.jpg" n="3"/>be sent to it.</p>
   <p>The following were elected as officers of the conference: J. M. Tananevičius, president; J. Viskoska, and K. Jurgelionis, secretaries.</p>
   <p>The question of discussing by-laws, a project which had been put off until this meeting, was postponed to the end of the conference. A discussion of various problems followed, in the following sequence:</p>
   <p>1. It was decided that, to put our scientific and technical terminology in order, the newspapers would use the international terminology, after making it suitable to the Lithuanian language. To put in order the American-Lithuanian terminology (names of institutions, officials, and the political field) a special committee was elected, including Dr. J. Šliupas, L. Šernas, and K. Jurgelionis (with Šliupas acting as the responsible committee chairman)....</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1032.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. The matter of miraculous doctors and misleading advertising. The thought was expressed that the most successful way of abolishing these advertisements would be: a) to have the government forbid the printing of such advertisements, and b) to strive as much as possible to explain to the people, more often, that they should not believe such advertisements. Since the National American Medical Association is at present working on both these suggestions and since the Lithuanian doctors have already made a beginning in organizing a branch of that Association with their Lithuanian Doctors Alliance, this matter was relegated to our doctors' organization. The newspapers promise to aid them and print their articles in reference to this matter.</p>
   <p>3. The desire that all newspapers and publishing houses would exchange copies of their publications was expressed.</p>
   <p>4. Problems regarding enlightenment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1033.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>5. Statistical matters.</p>
   <p>The members of the Statistics Committee, K. V. Račkauskas, with a written report, and J. O. Širvydas, verbally, announced that they had collected much material from various sources in their effort to put in order the statistics regarding Lithuanians and their activities in America but that it is insufficient as yet and, therefore, too early to be compiled. K. Jurgelionis also announced that he had collected much statistical material for the proposed encyclopedia, which could be used in compiling the statistical reports.....</p>
   <p>6. The centralization of various organizations.</p>
   <p>7. It was decided that the officers of the Press Society continue their efforts to draw to this newspapermen's organization those newspapers which, up to the present time, have not belonged to it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1034.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>8. Problems of the theater.</p>
   <p>Since the presentation of theatrical plays is a large influence in educating the people, it is desirable that our newspapers turn as much attention as they can to theatrical matters. It is advisable that the lovers of the stage associate themselves with the Teatras, a periodical devoted to theatrical matters, in which better theatrical plays could appear. In the meantime, a special committee was elected to make up a list of all the better plays which it would be advisable to present on the stage and to publish that list in the newspapers. J. D. Širvydas and K. Jurgelionis were elected to the committee.</p>
   <p>9. The establishment of evening schools.</p>
   <p>The meeting advises the newspapers to explain to the people from time to time, and especially in the fall, how they can secure such schools from the city government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1035.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>10. On the matter of temperance.</p>
   <p>The newspapers are in accord with the propagation of temperance and express the desire that the Lithuanian doctors help the newspapers in this matter by the preparation of suitable articles.</p>
   <p>11. The conference is in accord with the movement that Lithuanians settling here concern themselves with procuring citizenship papers and that they participate in the political activity of this country.</p>
   <p>12. The question being raised as to how much the Lithuanian newspapers should concern themselves with this country's politics, it was decided that the newspapers, each according to its convictions, should concern themselves with politics as much as space permits.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1036.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>13. The opinion was expressed that it is desirable to support Lithuanian commerce and industry and to urge and accustom Lithuanians to them as much as possible.</p>
   <p>14. It is advisable to support the learning of trades and to explain their benefits to the people.</p>
   <p>15. For elevating and caring for our literature and authors, it is desirable that Lithuanian writers would join into one organization, which would be similar to a section of the Press Society.</p>
   <p>16. The meeting expressed the general opinion that it is advisable to support a Lithuanian colonization movement if such a colonization plan is conducted honestly by conscientious individuals.....</p>
   <p>17. The conference happily observed that the desire expressed at the last newspapermen's conference in regard to organizing Lithuanian students is <pb facs="5423970_2_1037.jpg" n="9"/>being at least partially fulfilled.....</p>
   <p>20. The question of a Central Library.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that a place be found where there could be stored all the newspapers, writings, books, and publications--not only in the Lithuanian but also in other languages--which in one way or another concern the Lithuanian nation and life. In other words, to found a Lituanica Library which could be used by Lithuanian-American writers, researchers, etc. The founding of a Lituanica in Lithuania is inaccessible to Lithuanian-Americans.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
