<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">New Owners of Lietuva</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0936</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0936.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-08">June 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEW OWNERS OF LIETUVA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 1, 1917, the newspaper Lietuva passed into the hands of new owners. The newspaper was purchased from Mr. A. Olsauskas (Olszewski) by Mr. Joseph Baciunas and John Pajauskas, who some time ago had purchased the printing plant of the Lietuva.</p>
   <p>Both of the new owners of the Lietuva learned the printing trade in the Lietuva plant, where they have been employed since their youth. They are recognized now as being among the best Lithuanian-American printers.</p>
   <p>The change in ownership has caused many people to wonder about the future editorial policy of the Lietuva. Readers are hereby assured that the editorial policy will remain what it was before. In the political field, the Lietuva has been adhering to a middle-of-the-road policy, without favoring either of <pb facs="5423970_2_0937.jpg" n="2"/>the two extremes. This policy will be adhered to. The paper will continue to defend our national interests against all enemies, be they Lithuanians or non-Lithuanians. The paper will also continue in its efforts to create unity--and not further dissension--among all Lithuanian-American factions, so that all will work in harmony for the benefit of Lithuanian nationalism.</p>
   <p>Now that a change in the ownership of the Lietuva has taken place, we wish and hope that the Lietuva will continue to be the torch of enlightenment among Lithuanian-Americans that it has been in the past.</p>
   <p>If we support the new owners, their good intentions, their sound and energetic efforts, and their industry, there can be no doubt that the Lietuva will enjoy a very prosperous future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
