<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-08">Oct. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Catholic Press League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0965</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0965.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-10-08">Oct. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CATHOLIC PRESS LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to newspaper reports the Catholic Press League, an association whose purpose is to organize all Lithuanian-American Catholic newspapers and periodicals, was established at the recent congress of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Federation of America in Brooklyn, New York. It is said that there are ten such publications in America, although two of them, the Pittsburgo Zinios (Pittsburg News) and the Vytis (The Knight), organ of the Knights of Lithuania, have not appeared yet.....</p>
   <p>It is noteworthy that the daily Katalikas (The Catholic) is not mentioned as a member of the League. Has the Katalikas become a non-Catholic newspaper? We can hardly believe that. In our opinion, the Katalikas has a greater right to call itself a Catholic newspaper than all the other so-called Lithuanian Catholic newspaper put together.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0966.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We believe that there is another reason, the real reason, why the Katalikas is not considered as a Catholic newspaper by the Catholic Federation. It appears that all those publications, which are mentioned as members of the Catholic Press League, are either published by priests or strongly influenced by them; these priests are all of the same caliber as the Reverend F. Kemesis. The latter, as we all learned from experience, is making a strong effort to organize a powerful force of Clericals (priests and their followers who take an active part in worldly as well as religious matters) for the purpose of dominating the public life of Lithuanian-Americans. That force can be formed only with the aid of a sufficiently large number of publications that are controlled by the apostles of Clericalism. The weekly Draugas (The Friend) was established for that purpose. The Darbininkas (The Worker), recently established in Boston by Reverend Kemesis, also has the same goal; it was not established to promote the interests of the workers, but as a bait for the workers, who comprise an overwhelming majority of the Lithuanian-Americans. All other Lithuanian Catholic publications are established and issued for the same purpose; all of them must comply with the dictates of the leaders of Clericalism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0967.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, the Katalikas is not in the hands of priests and their efforts to control that newspaper were not successful. The publishers of the Draugas, especially, made a strong effort to force the Katalikas to become their servant, but failed. For that reason the Katalikas has been labeled as an "insufficiently Catholic" newspaper, although non-Clericals believe that it is more Catholic than all other Lithuanian Catholic publications put together.</p>
   <p>All the shouting which our Clericals are making about Catholicism is a great humbug, which can influence only big fools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
