<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-05">Feb. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Proletarian Art Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-05">Feb. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PROLETARIAN ART CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago chapter of the Lithuanian-American Proletarian Art Society gave its annual concert, Jan. 24, at Meldazis Hall. A large crowd attended the concert in spite of the fact that on the same evening many of our people went to the celebration at the Coliseum, commemorating the second anniversary of the death of Lenin.</p>
   <p>A long and pleasant program was enjoyed by the audience at Meldazis Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0127.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was opened with the singing of the Internationale, international anthem of the working class, by the Kanklu (Lithuanian guitar) Chorus, under the leadership of the famous Lithuanian music leader, A. P. Kvedaras. This chorus also sang a number of other songs, such as "Brothers Let us Unite," and "Listen Millionaires".</p>
   <p>The North Side chorus, of the children's Little Society of the Blossom of Hope, entertained the audience with a number of songs and dances. This chorus, consisting entirely of Lithuanian children and led by Miss P. Bigelis, pleased the audience immensely. Miss Bigelis must be complimented for training the children so successfully.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0128.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A newly organized violin orchestra, under the able leadership of B. Kalkis, rendered a few numbers. This orchestra consists of 25 young Lithuanians from the Bridgeport colony. Judging from their initial efforts the orchestra appears to have promising future.</p>
   <p>The Englewood chorus, of the children's Little Society of the Blossom of Hope, also sang a few songs. This group was lead by Miss P. Peciukas.</p>
   <p>A violin and piano number was rendered by the youthful Radaukis <pb facs="5423970_2_0129.jpg" n="4"/>sisters. These girls appear to possess great musical talent and are endowed with excellent stage personalities. They should be encouraged to continue their musical training.</p>
   <p>One of the outstanding artists on the program was Genevieve Sidiskis, famous Lithuanian soprano. She pleased the audience immensely with her lovely voice. Miss Sidiskis is developing into a great star.</p>
   <p>The Brighton Park chorus, of the Children's Little Society of the Blossom of Hope, sang a number of songs. A group of girls from <pb facs="5423970_2_0130.jpg" n="5"/>the chorus entertained the audience with a short play, "Spnas" (The Dream). This chorus consists of over one hundred Lithuanian children and appears to be well disciplined. Miss V. Bigelis is the leader.</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with a number of songs rendered by the Aidas (Echo) Chorus from Roseland.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the program J. D. Bendokas, chairman of the evening, delivered a short talk. Among other things, he outlined <pb facs="5423970_2_0131.jpg" n="6"/>the purpose of the newly organized American Labor (Communist) Party and appealed to the audience for contributions to assist the party. A collection netted sixteen dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
