<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-10">Oct. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Liquidation of the Zinycia Colonization Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-10">Oct. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LIQUIDATION OF THE ZINYCIA COLONIZATION SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Zinycia Colonization Society, which was organized in Wisconsin in 1905, came to the end of its existence on September 16, 1913, by paying off all the stockholders in full with interest. The land which it owned was sold to the members. Profits had been satisfactory, but because of the lack of public support, the stockholders decided to liquidate this society.</p>
   <p>Six stockholders remain unpaid because the board does not have their addresses. When they demand it, everything will be paid to them, down to the last cent. The board of this organization will continue for three more years. Its president is Povilas Rumkevicius, 318 East 116th Street, Kensington, Illinois; and its secretary is M. D. Cinikas, 2727 West 22nd Street. The other member is Niceforas Zilevicius 2533 South Spaulding Avenue, Chicago.</p>
   <p>The principal sum and dividends will be paid in full, with interest, to those stockholders who have subscribed for several shares but have been unable to pay <pb facs="5423970_2_0058.jpg" n="2"/>in full; and also to those who began to buy stock on a payment plan--which required a down payment of not less than ten dollars--but later stopped their payments. Their money will be returned with ten per cent interest.</p>
   <p>The active members of this organization will receive thirty per cent dividends on their investments in the stock. Therefore, this organization came to the end of its existence, not because of a lack of profit, but because of the lack of public interest in it. For lack of members, this organization was unable to accomplish its object. Upon my departure for Lithuania, therefore, all the members have agreed to liquidate it.</p>
   <p>J.J. Hertmanavicius</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
