<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-27">Oct. 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Olszewski Bank to Be Known as Reserve State Bank</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-10-27">Oct. 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">OLSZEWSKI BANK TO BE KNOWN AS RESERVE STATE BANK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An attempt was made to cause the same kind of trouble for the bank of A. Olszewski as was experienced by the bank of J. Tananevicius. Three depositors of the A. Olszewski Bank instituted a suit against the bank, despite the fact that it is being reorganized into a state bank.</p>
   <p>However, the three depositors did not succeed in their efforts. On learning that the bank is being reorganized into a state bank, Judge Landis withheld action in the suit and gave Mr. Olszewski until October 30 to complete the reorganization of his bank.</p>
   <p>The new name of the bank will be shorter than was stated in the last issue of Lietuva (Lithuania). The bank will now be known as the Reserve State Bank.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0037.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The officials of Mr. Olszewski's bank have assured us that it definitely will become a state bank, and that in a few days all the work necessary for its establishment as a state bank will be completed. They also report that a license for the new bank has already been received from the state government.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: A full page advertisement, offering shares of the new Reserve State Bank at $112.50 per share, appears in this issue of Lietuva. It is stated that the bank will have a basic capital of $200,000,and a surplus of $25,000.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
