<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-09-15">Sept. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Birute Musical and Dramatic Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-09-15">Sept. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTE MUSICAL AND DRAMATIC SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... Melodic voices, harmonic renditions, elusive notes - all go into producing the prospective debut of Birute's musical season. Lights, Curtain, Action!! - and Drama sweeps into the limelight to blend harmoniously in a bewildering, swirling climax of a musical triumph.</p>
   <p>With the opening of the 31st season, preparations for an operetta are going full force. It will be something to be anticipated as the selections were secured by Mrs. Byanskas during her very recent visit to Lithuania. But stay! That is not all. Dancing feet gliding to the strains of tantalizing music, delectable refreshments to tempt the most fastidious of palates- Birute's social life is not supressed by her musical ambitions.</p>
   <p>The members are a gay lot of alert, vitally alive young people - true adherents to the age of old adage "a little nonsense now and then is relished by the best of men." Attending guests, once having witnessed Birute's rehearsals find them <pb facs="5423970_2_0350.jpg" n="2"/>magnetic and return each week as regular members. Why don't you?</p>
   <p>At eight P.M. Sandara Hall, 814 West 33rd St. is dimly lighted, where one finds upon entering the rendezvous, groups discussing and reviewing eagerly the possibilities of the evening, Much is anticipated of Thursday evenings, and seldom are they disappointing.</p>
   <p>Mr. Byanskas, the director is acclaimed with enthusiasm upon his arrival, for his presence-besides meaning that rehearsals are about to begin - radiates a warm friendliness so desirable in gathering. Nothing is too little to escape his notice and receive attention. Humor is an inborn quality with him, for no occasion affording a sheltering nook for wit, will find him off guard. Besides being "the life of the party" before and after rehearsals, he becomes a strict disciplinarian while at work, making the chorus an integrity ready for work.</p>
   <p>Rehearsals last approximately two hours - two hours of sheer delight; when music lovers delve into melodious selections, brimful of ecstatic harmony. To each <pb facs="5423970_2_0351.jpg" n="3"/>and every member, Thursday evening means an escape from the realm of realism into a beautiful aesthetic world so dear to his heart. Once each month Birute holds a business meeting, where plans are made for social gatherings, outings and family "get-togethers", as well as decisions as to the acceptance and refusals of invitations to participate in the presentation of other organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
