<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 34,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date><title level="a">Lithuanian Musicians, Take Notice</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0179</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0179.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 34,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date><title level="a">LITHUANIAN MUSICIANS, TAKE NOTICE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>September 3, Sunday, 4 P. M., at St. Kokosz Hall, 749 W. 18th St., Lithuanian musicians will hold their second meeting. All Lithuanian musicians from all parts of Chicago should not fail to come, as at this meeting there will be organized a band of Lithuanian musicians only.</p>
   <p>Brothers, this band is an excellent project! Remember that there are in Chicago many good Lithuanian musicians who served in the Russian army musicians' band and they are very good players.</p>
   <p>All of you know that nobody can beat the Russian Army Band. And with such musicians we can make one of the best bands in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian musicians, today play in German, Polish, and other bands, from which they derive no national benefit as they simply are helping to make good bands for other nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0180.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For instance, when the Society of the Province of God had its ball, who were the players at this ball? Why, the Poles! If we could have had our Lithuanian band, this society would not hire Polish musicians.</p>
   <p>Same thing with the Society of Duke Gedeminas. This society, once in a while, has its banquets and hires musicians of other nationalities. Would it not be very nice if we Lithuanians had our own band? Would Lithuanians not be proud that in parades with other nations, Lithuanians would have their own band.</p>
   <p>We are telling you, that we Lithuanians, with our band could beat any band in America. You must remember that many of us Lithuanian musicians served in the Russian Army Band. Who can beat the Russian Army Band? Nobody!</p>
   <p>No matter what instrument you play, come to this meeting, here, and we will organize a Lithuanian band and orchestra.</p>
   <p>Lithuanian Musicians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
