<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">To Establish Lithuanian Library on North Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0785</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0785.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">TO ESTABLISH LITHUANIAN LIBRARY ON NORTH SIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The North Side (81st) branch of the Lithuanian Socialist League invites all the local Lithuanian organizations to a get together for the purpose of establishing a Lithuanian library. Well established public Lithuanian libraries for Lithuanians are very necessary. They play a very important role in the general educational uplift of the people.</p>
   <p>There are several rather wealthy Lithuanian organizations on the North Side. One of the aims of these organizations, according to their by-laws, is to promote the intellectual advancement of our people. With the assistance of these organizations, it would be an easy matter to establish a library and a suitable home for it. The library must not be located in a saloon hall so that it would be freely accessible to women and children.</p>
   <p>The desire for a Lithuanian library is constantly increasing among the Lithuanians of the North Side, and attempts to establish one are likewise increasing. These <pb facs="5423970_2_0786.jpg" n="2"/>facts are very good indications, and something of which every Lithuanian can be proud.</p>
   <p>All the Lithuanian organizations of the North Side are asked to elect delegates to a conference which will be called soon to discuss ways and means of establishing a Lithuanian library. Send the names and addresses of the delegates to Mr. J. Mickevicius, 1400 Dickson Street, and he will notify the delegates the time and place of the conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
