<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Educational Society Re-Opens Evening School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S EDUCATIONAL SOCIETY RE-OPENS EVENING SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ever since the Lithuanian Women's Educational Society has been established it has endeavored to engage in some useful activities. During the last winter season, the Society conducted an evening school for the purpose of teaching sewing, knitting, writing, etc. The school was supervised by a well-known artist, Miss Theodora Andrus. I do not believe that the Lithuanian women and girls who attended the school regret their decisions in this direction.</p>
   <p>Now that another winter season has arrived, the Society is again conducting an evening school for Lithuanian women and girls. In response to a large number of requests, a class in cooking and home economics has been added to the school. All Lithuanian women or girls, who are eighteen years of age or over, are eligible to attend the school and learn how to prepare delicious and healthy meals. All expenses, except for the provisions used in cooking, are paid by the Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1370.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every Lithuanian woman and girl should take advantage of this wonderful opportunity to become more useful in the home. It is not necessary to be a member of the Society in order to attend the school. Every member of the cooking class contributes an equal share of money to pay for the provisions which are used in cooking. The class now consists of twelve members; the cost to each member is about two or three cents per evening. Surely, everyone can afford to pay such a small sum. There are no other expenses. The food which is prepared during the class period is served to the members, and they all enjoy a pleasant evening.</p>
   <p>Now that the Lenten season is here, and entertainment affairs have decreased to a minimum, we have more time to devote to our intellectual development. Every one who attends the cooking class learns how to avoid many bodily ills and discomforts by preparing delicious and healthy meals. It is very important to know the kinds of foods and in what proportions our bodies require them. All these matters are taught in the cooking class.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1371.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These classes are conducted in the Fellowship House, at 831 West 33rd Place, every Wednesday evening, beginning at 7:30 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
