<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 23, 7-3,
<date when="1914-07-29">July 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Aurora School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 23, 7-3,
<date when="1914-07-29">July 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">AURORA SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The foreign born Lithuanians of Chicago have long felt the need of a Lithuanian school for adults who can not speak English well. This is the first Lithuanian school of its kind in the United States, where grown-up people will have the golden opportunity of preparing themselves for a better future.</p>
   <p>This kind of school is indispensable to our people, especially, to those who came to America without any education and want to acquire it, and learn how to speak the English language correctly.</p>
   <p>Our people can not go to American schools at the beginning for a few reasons. First of all, a man may be entirely illiterate; or, if he is not, he can not speak English, nor can he understand the English language. There are some people who have some education, but they can not go to public school because they have no knowledge of the English language. It is obvious that no American can teach a person or explain anything to him, if that person does not understand the English language at all. In that event, we are much better prepared to help our people, especially whose who can not speak the English language correctly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1320.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have observed that our people, especially those who do not know the grammar of their own language, have much trouble grasping the English language. We know this from our own experience, and we have proof that the people who go to public school from our school, become very good students. About seventy-five per cent of our students have become professional men today. We give them a very good foundation and prepare them for higher education; in addition, we encourage them to continue their education. We are making every effort to arouse the interest of our adults in education, and we will help them to understand and appreciate the value of education and its importance in human life.</p>
   <p>Our school is divided into two departments - the Lithuanian department for beginners, and the English department for advanced students. The Lithuanian department teaches only two subjects:- Lithuanian grammar and arithmetic. The English department is the largest department in the school, where many subjects are being taught at the present time. The subjects which are being taught are as follows: English language, arithmetic, book-keeping, stenography, typewriting, commercial law, general history, geography, algebra, geometry, trigonometry, and mechanical drawing.</p>
   <p>Mathematics and mechanical drawing is taught by Mr. V. Misheika, mechanical engineer. Mr. Misheika graduated from the technical institute in St. Petersburg, Russia, where he received his degree as a mechanical engineer. Now he is instructor <pb facs="5423970_2_1321.jpg" n="3"/>and principal of the Aurora School, which is located at 3149 S. Halsted St.</p>
   <p>Every Lithuanian man and woman should take advantage of this opportunity, which is being offered by the Aurora School. There is nothing more important than education, which is the greatest asset to any man or woman. Education offers many advantages in life; it helps one to appreciate better things in life; it helps one to discriminate between good and bad, and between right and wrong; it helps one to meet better people and to make friends with them; and it helps one to get a better position and makes life more pleasant to live. It opens your eyes to the world and its beauties.</p>
   <p>Teaching hours are as follows: day school from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., and evening school from 7:30 to 9:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>Don't miss this golden opportunity; enroll right now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
