<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth Lithuanian Newspapermen's Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1024</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1024.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH LITHUANIAN NEWSPAPERMEN'S CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fourth Lithuanian Newspapermen's Convention was held on October 8 and 9, 1913 in Tillman Hall at Shenandoah, Pennsylvania. The following newspapers sent these delegates to the convention: Lietuva, Editor J. Sernas; Katalikas, Editor P. Brandukas and Publisher S. Tananevicius....</p>
   <p>The various committees that were appointed at last year's convention did not carry out their duties. Some of them, like the Central Library Committee for instance, have accomplished very much, while the Terminology Committee has done nothing. This year the convention decided to undertake fewer projects, and to try to complete them.</p>
   <p>Among the new projects, it should be mentioned that the Lithuanian Press Society decided to publish a yearly Almanac, the first issue of which is to <pb facs="5423970_2_1025.jpg" n="2"/>appear at the end of the coming year. The purpose of this publication will be to reflect the course of life of Lithuanian-Americans. After long discussions the convention drew up several resolutions, which express the views of the newspapers on certain manifestations of our life. Thus, it was decided to fix attention on the struggle against drunkenness, which--to tell the truth--is one of the worst blots on Lithuanian life. The newspapermen at this convention expressed their greatest sympathy with the delegates of the Lithuanian Science and Art Society, Dr. J. Basanavicius and M. Ycas, who are at present in this country collecting contributions for the erection of the National Museum in Vilnius [Vilna].</p>
   <p>It was also found necessary to point out from time to time in our newspapers the value of physical culture. Much time was devoted to a discussion of "miraculous" medical advertisements. Dr. J. Sliupas, who last year was elected chairman on the Committee on Quack medical advertisements, had not succeeded in accomplishing anything. The convention adopted a resolution, <pb facs="5423970_2_1026.jpg" n="3"/>which condemns detestable advertisements like, for example, "Girls Wanted," and other matrimonial advertisements.</p>
   <p>This convention also decided to participate in the Lithuanian Press Convention which will be held next year in Vilnius, Lithuania. It was decided to hold the next convention in New York City. The following officers were elected: J. M. Tananevicius, president; J. O. Sirvydas, vice-president; V. K. Rackauskas, secretary; and Dr. J. Sliupas, treasurer. Dr. J. Basanavicius and M. Ycas and many local Lithuanians were visitors at the convention.</p>
   <p>The Shenandoah Lithuanians received the newspapermen very cordially at a good concert and a banquet. This celebration was arranged by the Lithuanian women of Shenandoah.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
