<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-06">Nov. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Oppose Liquidation of Sernas Music Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-11-06">Nov. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">OPPOSE LIQUIDATION OF SERNAS MUSIC FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After reading in Lietuva, of October 30, about the liquidation of the Sernas Music Fund by the treasurer, Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, a meeting of all organizers of the fund was called by the secretary, J. Laukis. The meeting took place in the home of Dr. A. L. Graicunas, 3312 S. Halsted Street, and was attended by fifteen founders of the fund. The decision to oppose the liquidation of the fund, was agreed upon unanimously.</p>
   <p>It was explained at the meeting that Dr. Rutkauskas, who is the treasurer of the fund, decided to liquidate it when he became angered at a request of the secretary to deposit the money of the fund in a bank in the name of all three members of the committee. He resented this as an unfair reflection upon his honesty and character.</p>
   <p>It was argued at the meeting that the meeting for liquidating the fund, which Dr. Rutkauskas held at his home, was insufficiently advertised and called at <pb facs="5423970_2_0165.jpg" n="2"/>a very inconvenient time and place. On the day of the meeting nearly all the founders of the fund attended the Daukantas commemoration exercises. For this reason none of the founders of the fund attended the meeting; and Dr. Rutkauskas had no right to liquidate the fund without the consent of a majority of the founders of the fund. His action and decision to merge the Sernas Music Fund with the Ausra (Aurora) Society, a student aid society, on the grounds that both societies have a common purpose, is unjustified and worthy of condemnation.</p>
   <p>The Sernas Music Fund (named in honor of Joseph Sernas-Adomaitis, editor of the Lietuva and famous Lithuanian writer), is a music aid society. Its purpose is to develop and promote musical and theatrical talent among Lithuanian-Americans.</p>
   <p>It was decided at the meeting that Dr. Rutkauskas should transfer all the money of the fund, $132.25, not to the Ausra Society but to Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, the newly elected treasurer of the Sernas Fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0166.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The old committee of the Sernas Fund was replaced at the meeting with new officers. The new officers are: Dr. A. L. Graicunas, chairman; attorney F. P. Bradchulis, treasurer; J. Laukis, secretary. These officers were authorized to reorganize the affairs of the fund and to make recommendations for future action at the next monthly meeting of the society.</p>
   <p>The Sernas Music Fund will continue to exist and flourish. The Lithuanian public is asked to continue their generous support of the fund with contributions.</p>
   <p>By J. Laukis, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
