<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Semi-Weekly Vilnis to Be Daily Soon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">SEMI-WEEKLY VILNIS TO BE DAILY SOON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.5................The campaign to raise a fund for converting the semi-weekly Vilnis (The Surge) into a daily newspapers is constantly gaining in support from Lithuanians all over the country. Comrade F. Audaitis of Helen, W.Va., writes: "Enclosed you will find $8.00 - three dollars is for a subscription to the Vilnis and five dollars is a Christmas gift to the Vilnis Daily Fund. Before the holidays people spend a lot of money on various gifts, but I am spending my money for something useful by subscribing to a newspaper and donating monty to assist the Vilnis to become a daily newspaper."</p>
   <p>Besides giving financial assistance to the Vilnis, comrade Audatis also gives a good example on how to buy "Christmas gifts," A subscription to a working class newspaper for a friend, or the financial support of the press is the best kind of Christmas present.</p>
   <p>Contributions to the Vilnis Daily Fund are steadily flowing in from all parts of the country. Comrade F. Mason from the North Side of Chicago, sent in $25.00. That sum <pb facs="5423970_2_0839.jpg" n="2"/>was collected at a dinner given at the home of the Peciukas family. Another $25.00 collected at a dinner given by the Vesius family, was recently sent in from the same colony. It appears that the Lithuanian colony on the North Side in Chicago is very anxious to see the Vilnis become a daily. They are supporting their desire with real deeds.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian colony in Roseland, Ill., is making plans to give a benefit musical program for the Vilnis Daily Fund. The Cicero, Ill., chapter of the American-Lithuanian Workers Literary Society has donated $17.00 to the fund, and is determined to fulfill its quota in the Vilnis drive for 2,000 new subscribers. $20.00 was received recently from Comrade K. Svirskis of Milwaukee, Wis. He stated that the Lithuanians in that colony are planning to present various musical and theatrical programs to raise funds for the Vilnis Daily Fund. Comrade V.Yaken of Pittsfield, Mass., sent in $5.00.</p>
   <p>Judging from the wonderful support we are now receiving it will be possible to convert our semi-weekly publication into a daily within the next few months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
