<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Two New Proletarian Plays</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TWO NEW PROLETARIAN PLAYS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comrade C. Biuras, prominent member of the Lithuanian-American Proletarian Art League, is about to issue another proletarian play, a one-act drama, "For A Soviet Lithuanian," written in the Lithuanian language.</p>
   <p>The play deals with the period in Lithuanian history immediately after the World War, when the Lithuanian proletariat, in our mother country, fought bravely on the battlefields against the White Guardists in an effort to establish a Soviet government in Lithuania. The play is very interesting and full of action. It <pb facs="5423970_2_0189.jpg" n="2"/>is simple and easy to present even in the smallest Lithuanian colony. Orders for copies of the play are now being accepted by the Lithuanian-American Proletarian Art League.</p>
   <p>Comrade C. Biuras is also the author of another proletarian play, a four-act melodrama, "Priesai" (Enemies), which is now being published. This play received very high praise when it was reviewed at a recent meeting of the Lithuanian-American Proletarian Art League. The play is 80 pages long and will cost about $200 to be published as a book.</p>
   <p>"Priesai" is a very pleasant play, based on a beautiful romantic <pb facs="5423970_2_0190.jpg" n="3"/>plot. However, it is very different from bourgeois love plays. It has a strong proletarian character. A bourgeois love play usually revolves around a tempting kiss, which either separates or unites two people who are in love. In a proletarian love play, idealism is the motivating force.</p>
   <p>These two plays will greatly enrich Lithuanian proletarian literature. During the past few years Lithuanian-Americans have made remarkable progress in proletarian art and literature. Less than a decade ago proletarian art was practically unknown among our people in this country. Now we are proud of a large <pb facs="5423970_2_0191.jpg" n="4"/>number of Lithuanian proletarian artists and their works.</p>
   <p>Comrade C. Biuras is also the author of a number of proletarian songs. He recently published a collection of his songs in a book, "Proletaru Dainos" (Proletarian Songs). This book is meeting with astonishing success in all Lithuanian colonies in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
