<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-14">Nov. 14, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">West Side News</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Aesculapius</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-14">Nov. 14, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WEST SIDE NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Aesculapius</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More beautiful events have been presented on the West Side than any other place, but up to the present time the Lithuanians here have not had their own permanent group of artists. Now the Lovers of the Motherland Society, Branch 28, has decided to have its own dramatic group, which all of the West Side artists have promised to join. For proper arrangements, a committee of three has been appointed: R. Zauras, Miss K. Surniute, and B. Lenkauskas. This new dramatic circle has promised to show the people what it can do. On November 16, at Meldazis Hall, it will present a three-act drama, "On the Brink of the Abyss." The artists are working hard, and they have promised that this presentation will be a good one.</p>
   <p>November 9, at Meldazis Hall, the Holy Mary Society, presented two one-act <pb facs="5423970_2_0445.jpg" n="2"/>comedies: "The Bridegroom" and "A Servant Becomes Entangled". We must mention that in the play "The Bridegroom," Miss S. Kaupiute as "Natalie" showed her artistic ability. She is one of the best actresses of all among West Side Lithuanians. Mr. M. Jokubka, in the role of "Jonas Lamas" (the bridegroom), was also very good.</p>
   <p>The second comedy, too, was performed excellently. Nothing can be said against the artists. In this play, Mr. A. Springis as the servant is worthy of mention.</p>
   <p>It was disappointing that the Our Lady of Vilna Parish Choir did not sing, even though they had promised to do so. In the place of the choir, S. J. Darguzis, student, delivered a short speech. He urged the audience to support the Lithuanian students and their periodical, Jaunimo Sapnai, (The Dreams of Youth).</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0446.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is very seldom on the West Side that a program can be complete without the appearance of the comedian Stepukus (Mr. V. Brusokas); a program without him would be like eating your dinner without dessert. Stepukas brought the program to a close in such a way that even a sick person would have laughed. The conduct of the audience during the entire evening was very orderly, thanks to the supervisors of the evening. Dancing followed the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
