<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 49,
<date when="1893-12-16">Dec. 16, 1893</date><title level="a">The Purpose of Simonas Daukantas Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 49,
<date when="1893-12-16">Dec. 16, 1893</date><title level="a">THE PURPOSE OF SIMONAS DAUKANTAS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>December 10, a meeting was held by the society of Simonas Daukantas, the constitution was adopted, and after many discussions the meeting decided upon the following principles:</p>
   <p>1. To spread education among Lithuanians, to teach the Lithuanian language, to propagate Lithuanian literature.</p>
   <p>2. To establish a library, to keep all kinds of Lithuanian books and newspapers, and also books in other languages.</p>
   <p>3. The society will celebrate all national holidays, and will present theatrical plays.</p>
   <p>4. The society will take part in spiritual and material activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. The society will take part in American and European politics.</p>
   <p>6. The society will collect relics for the Lithuanian Museum.</p>
   <p>7. The society will help those Lithuanians who are seeking higher education.</p>
   <p>8. The society will join the Lithuanian Catholic Alliance of America, and will never participate in any action against the Catholic religion. (Trans. note: - The society still exists, now as a liberal society, and does not participate in nor supports any religious activities.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0734.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Any Lithuanian of good morals and manners, and who is over sixteen years of age, can join this society.</p>
   <p>All money from dues and donations will be used for the library of Lithuanian literature. The initiation fee is fifty cents. Monthly dues are fifteen cents.</p>
   <p>Any member of this society may be fined or expelled from the society for any bad manners or bad activities.</p>
   <p>Sick members must be visited by society members, and given spiritual and material aid.</p>
   <p>At every meeting of this society scientific questions must be brought for discussion and for proper explanation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0735.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>J. Kolesinskis gave one book, History of the Church; the Lithuanian Catholic Alliance of America gave one book, History of Europe, and another, The Manners of Ancient Lithuanians, of Samogitians and Mountaineers.</p>
   <p>Also Mr. M. Nomeskis, who has a large book store in Tilzen Ost, Germany, donated sixteen copies of various books.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
