<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-06">Aug. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Biruta Society Prepares for Return of Petrauskas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-08-06">Aug. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">BIRUTA SOCIETY PREPARES FOR RETURN OF PETRAUSKAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the previous number of the Lietuva (Lithuania) it was announced that the rehearsals of the Biruta Music and Dramatic Society will begin on Wednesday evening Aug. 4. The next rehearsal will take place on Saturday evening, Aug. 7. Hereafter the rehearsals will take place twice a week, on Wednesday and Saturday evenings. All rehearsals will be held at the hall of the Church of Our Lady of Vilna, 23rd Place and Oakley Avenue. If a sufficient number of singers enlist from the Bridgeport colony, the place of rehearsals will be changed as follows: Wednesday evenings on the West Side, in the above mentioned hall, and on Saturday evenings in a hall at Bridgeport.</p>
   <p>Mikas Petrauskas, former Chicago Lithuanian musical artist and composer who is now attending a conservatory of music in Paris, France, has <pb facs="5423970_2_0315.jpg" n="2"/>promised to return to the United States before the 25th annual convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, which will take place this month in Chicago. Mr. Petrauskas has agreed to assist in every possible way in all the commemorative exercises of this important convention. He is scheduled to arrive in Chicago on Aug. 15; a big reception for him is being planned on the evening of the above date by the Biruta Society at our Lady of Vilna hall.</p>
   <p>Immediately after Mr. Petrauskas returns to Chicago he will resume leadership of the Biruta society; he will give half-hour classes on the theory of music at every rehearsal of the Biruta chorus. Besides that, he will immediately start organizing his own orchestra, which will participate in all his musical concerts and theatrical presentations. It is absolutely necessary for every prospective orchestra member to <pb facs="5423970_2_0316.jpg" n="3"/>attend all rehearsals of the Biruta chorus.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petrauskas will give musical concerts and stage important theatrical plays in all the principal Lithuanian colonies of America.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petrauskas hopes that by the time he returns to Chicago, the organization of the Biruta chorus will have been completed; he wants to see at least one hundred singers in the chorus. Shortly after his arrival the chorus will be closed to new applicants. Therefore, all young Lithuanians who plan to join the chorus are advised to do so immediately. Those who attend the rehearsals will not only spend their time in a pleasant way, but will also receive valuable instruction in the art of music.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0317.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Members of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, who wish to celebrate their 25th convention in Chicago in a most memorable fashion, should not only join the Biruta chorus themselves, but also urge other singers to do so.</p>
   <p>By J. Ilgaudas, chairman of the Biruta Society.</p>
   <p>P. S. The officers of the Biruta Society have decided to present musical and theatrical entertainments in the Lithuanian colonies situated not too far from Chicago, but only in those colonies where it is possible for the members of the Biruta chorus to leave Chicago on Saturday and return early on Monday morning. Entertainments will be held only in those colonies where local residents will guarantee at least a moderate financial profit for the society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0318.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Address all communications in regard to this matter to Mr. J. Ilgaudas, president, 3252 So. Halsted St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
