<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-04-14">Apr. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Our Youth and the American Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Petrukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-04-14">Apr. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">OUR YOUTH AND THE AMERICAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">BY Petrukas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As far as I have been able to learn, our young people are taking very little interest in real American art. They attend only the vaudeville theaters. Very few of our youths witness any of the legitimate theatrical productions. For that reason, they form the mistaken impression that the American stage has nothing better to offer than jig dancing.</p>
   <p>Thus, many good productions come and go, and our young people never see them; they will probably never get an opportunity to see them on the Lithuanian stage because we lack artists and money to produce such plays. Since we are unable to place our own theater on a high level, and since we do not witness the productions of other nationalities, we are unable to follow the progressing stages of humanity. We can learn much from the theater, because the theater always was and probably always will be an expression of the ideas of humanity, a reflection of our every-day life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0194.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At present, one of the most important productions that pertain to our daily life is being shown at the Garrick Theater under the title "Experience". We can see much truth in this production. It depicts the entire life and faults of youth, and enables one to obtain a true understanding of life, its meaning, its value, etc.... Everyone should see this production. It would pay our young people to take a greater interest in real art, which furnishes more food for the spirit than our own theater. It is not necessary to know the English language well to understand these productions, because they are acted so realistically that they can be understood even without words.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
