<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"The Chimney Sweep and the Miller" on the Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"THE CHIMNEY SWEEP AND THE MILLER" ON THE STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Birute Society presented the operetta, "The Chimney Sweep and the Miller," at the St. George Parish Hall last Sunday. The music for this operetta was written by M. Petrauskas. The presentation of the operetta came off better than expected since very little time had been spent rehearsing it. But, nevertheless, the inadequacy of preparation was evident. It can be expected that the Birute Society, the strongest and probably the largest dramatic organization in Chicago, will overcome the deficiencies which are still to be seen here and there. It is easily possible for the Society to do this, for it has the resources for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the presentation can be called successful. Only one fault made a bad impression on the audience. That was the inadequacy of the orchestra. It is difficult to say whether this was due to an assembly of poor musicians, or to a poor selection of instruments. Most likely it was both. It is <pb facs="5423970_2_0283.jpg" n="2"/>necessary that orchestras play softly for such operettas as "The Chimney Sweep and the Miller," especially if the singers' voices are not very strong. In this case even a trombone was included in the orchestra (and more necessary instruments were omitted). The trombone was very evident because the musician apparently does not know the difference between "forte" and "pianissimo." Because of this the music sounded somewhat strange in spots.</p>
   <p>Of course, this does not apply to the actors themselves. The musicians, we were told, had been hired only for that evening. Nevertheless, sponsors of programs should devote more attention to orchestras and demand more from them. In musical presentations, orchestras are extremely important and, if they are not capable, all of the efforts of the sponsors go for naught. The Birute Society undoubtedly will do away with such shortcomings in the future. A large audience was present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
