<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 20,
<date when="1901-05-17">May 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">From the Lithuanian Newspapers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Review)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 20,
<date when="1901-05-17">May 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE LITHUANIAN NEWSPAPERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Review)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last week's issue, the Saule (The Sun, Mahanoy City, Pa.) gives a suggestion on how to stop the polemics among the Lithuanian newspapers. That newspaper suggests that the publishers and editors of the newspapers hold a convention.</p>
   <p>That the wrangle of our newspapers and their personal disputes have nothing to do with the public affairs, no one will deny. But would a convention of publishers and editors stop the wrangle? To make an agreement is very easy, but to fulfill it is another matter. Among the American-Lithuanian newspapers there are many detestable controversies, and especially the Saule which, with its polemics, has left all other newspapers behind. The clerical newspapers say that the liberals are criticizing the clergy too much. Yes, we do. But the clericals are using the most detestable polemics against the liberals. Take the clerical newspaper Zvaigzde (Star) for instance. You will <pb facs="5423970_2_1161.jpg" n="2"/>find (in it) such dirty, detestable nicknames for their opponents that one wonders how the spiritual leaders can use such low language for the expression of their ideas. If the liberal newspapers would have followed the clerical press, it would have been necessary to invent new words in the dictionary of the American-Lithuanian newspapers.</p>
   <p>Would a convention of publishers and editors be able to stop the clergy from denouncing the liberals in their newspapers, pulpits and on lecture platforms? What remains for the denounced person to do but to answer with the same words the clergy uses?</p>
   <p>We must state that among our newspaper men there is too much hypocrisy. Newspapermen use the worse slanders in order to harm their opponents.</p>
   <p>Rev. Kaupas in last week's issue of Tevyne (The Fatherland. Organ of the Lithuanian Alliance of America) announced to the Lithuanian public that he has found the cause of the present disputes in the Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_2_1162.jpg" n="3"/>Alliance. The cause is that the censure of the Lithuanian Alliance's president makes it impossible even to breathe. The priest says that in order to stop such polemics the organ Tevyne should be issued monthly instead of weekly. Then, according to the priest, the wolf and the sheep could drink from the same spring. This is really a good invention; the priest ought to patent it.</p>
   <p>As Krilov says, there are in this world some people who can see only the small bugs, so they let the big bugs fly into their eyes. For the real cause of these polemics Rev. Kaupas must look to the other side, to his brother priests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
