<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Open Forum Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN FORUM ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of the more progressive Lithuanians in Town-of-Lake, Lithuanian colony of Chicago, has established an open forum, which is to be held every Thursday evening in the Cesna hall. The first forum, an organization meeting, was held last Thursday evening. Comrade V. Andrulis, editor of the Lithuanian semi-weekly working class newspaper, Vilnis, was the principal speaker. After his talk, the meeting was opened to free discussions, <pb facs="5423970_2_1405.jpg" n="2"/>questions, and answers. Comrade Andrulis offered a few suggestions on how to conduct the forum.</p>
   <p>The group of Lithuanians who have established this forum are active members of the progressive Lithuanian organizations of that colony. The purpose of the forum is an attempt to raise the intellectual level of Lithuanian workers, and to recruit members for working class organization.</p>
   <p>Town-of-Lake has one of the largest Lithuanian colonies in <pb facs="5423970_2_1406.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago. It contains the largest Lithuanian Catholic church and parish in America. However, the workers of that neighborhood are living under the Most poverty stricken conditions. Most of them are employed in the Stock Yards. And everybody knows how Stock Yard workers are brutally exploited by the capitalists. These workers are in great need of education on the principles and problems of the working class movement.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian workers of that colony have been under complete domination of Catholic priests for many decades. That is the <pb facs="5423970_2_1407.jpg" n="4"/>reason why these workers lack class-consciousness and have very little knowledge of the American working class movement for higher wages and better working conditions. However, since the progressive workers became active in that colony, the workers are steadily becoming more progressive and class-conscious.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
