<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Raise Funds for Lithuanian Library in Cicero, Ill</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0759</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0759.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">RAISE FUNDS FOR LITHUANIAN LIBRARY IN CICERO, ILL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A social for the benefit of the recently established Cicero Lithuanian Library was held on January 16 in Cicero, Ill. In spite of the inclement weather, a fairly large crowd attended. Intoxicating drinks were not sold or served at the social, and it appears that the people did not even miss them. That is a very good sign!</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians in Cicero are showing much interest in the Library, which is still in the process of organization. The Cicero Lithuanian orchestra, under the leadership of Mr. J. Balakas, furnished the music for the above-mentioned social without charge. In this matter, the members of the orchestra indirectly donated a large sum of money for the Library.</p>
   <p>A collection for the Library fund was made among those who were present at the social. Mr. Brazauskas donated six dollars; others donated smaller amounts. The collection netted a total of $21.65. Besides these donations, a net profit of $21.40 was realized from door receipts and from the sale of <pb facs="5423970_2_0760.jpg" n="2"/>refreshments at the social.</p>
   <p>A large and valuable donation was made by Mr. Lemontas, who donated ten dollars worth of books to the Library.</p>
   <p>Members of the Library committee are very grateful to all those who have contributed in any way to the Library Fund. Plans are being made to hold another benefit social in the near future.</p>
   <p>All those who wish to join the Library Society can do so by paying an initiation fee of fifty cents; dues are ten cents per month.</p>
   <p>It is believed that it will be possible to open the Library to the public in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
