<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">New Lithuanian Publication</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">NEW LITHUANIAN PUBLICATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first number of the new Lithuanian weekly Pazvalga (Review) has appeared. It is published by the newly organized Lithuanian Publishing Company, which also publishes the Jaunoji Lietuva (Young Lithuania) at 4611 South Paulina Street, Chicago, Illinois. The new company was created by a merger of the publishers of the Laisvoji Mintis (Free Thought) and the publishers of the Jaunoji Lietuva. The monthly Laisvoji Mintis has been discontinued and is being replaced by the weekly Pazvalga. However, the Pazvalga will be issued regularly as a weekly only from the latter part of the month of August. It will be issued in magazine form and will contain sixteen pages. The subscription price of the new publication has been set at three dollars per year.</p>
   <p>In the first number of the Pazvalga an outline of the aims, attitudes, and policies of the new publication and the bylaws of the Lithuanian Publishing Company are published.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The new publication will strive to promote the following ideals: abolition of the "exploitation system"; public control of commerce and the means of production; a new world order that will guarantee equal rights to all nations and nationalities; freedom in the use of language, guarantees of equal rights, and proportional representation in the government and public institutions for all minority foreign-language groups in every country; arbitration commissions and international courts to settle disputes between nations; the democratic order; abolition of capital punishment; prohibition of child labor; protective legislation for working minors and women; a minimum wage and a standard eight-hour working day; equal pay for equal work to men, women, and minors; the right and freedom for workers to organize and strike; control of farm lands in accordance with industrial principles; a systematic suppression of the sale of intoxicating drinks; the municipalization and nationalization of public utilities; social insurance against disease, accidents, and unemployment.</p>
   <p>From the above-mentioned principles it is apparent that the Lithuanian Publishing Company and the Pazvalga will be closely allied with socialism.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
