<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview, with Dr. A. L. Graiciunos, of the Lithuanian Theatrical Group</title>, Chicago Ill. by Alex Ambrose,
<date when="1937-01-29">Jan. 29, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[The Lithuanian Theatrical Group]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview, with Dr. A. L. Graiciunos, of the Lithuanian Theatrical Group</title>, Chicago Ill. by Alex Ambrose,
<date when="1937-01-29">Jan. 29, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[THE LITHUANIAN THEATRICAL GROUP]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of this Theatrical Group were: Dr. A. L.Graiciunos, John Grinius, Alex Szidlauskas, Antenas Stephonavice, Frank Braczulis, Miss Urszula Waranka, Miss Magdelena Waranka, Miss Anna Waranka, Mike Waranka, Anthon Waranka.</p>
   <p>This Theatrical group first staged the play, "Genevieve," and later, in the month of October, 1894, the play, "The Assassination of Alexander II of Russia" was staged.</p>
   <p>This last performance was not advertised at that time in the newspaper Lietuva. A. Olszewski at that time was a fanatical Catholic, while the Theatrical Group consisted of liberals and freethinkers. For this reason the publisher of <pb facs="5423970_2_0347.jpg" n="2"/>Lietuva,A. Olszewski, refused to advertise it in his newspaper. He did not want to have anything to do with the 'infidels', as the Theatrical Group was called at that time.</p>
   <p>Later on, this Lithuanian Theatrical Group was reorganized under a different name, that of the Aurora (Ausra) Society. The purpose of this society was to establish libraries and evening schools for Lithuanians and also to help the Lithuanian students who escaped from Russia and wanted to go on with their studies in other countries.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Society donated $800 to Vincas Mickevicius (Kapsukas). Later Mr. Mickevicius became a Bolshevik; and he died three years ago in Russia. He also donated to A. Halis $300. Mr. A. Halis later wrote the Lithuanian English and English Lithuanian Dictionary. Mr. Halis at present lives in Lithuania where he is writing and enlarging the dictionary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0348.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of this Lithuanian Theatrical Group only two members are still living, Dr. A. L. Graiciunas and Frank Bracziulis who is an attorney now. Dr. A. L. Graiciunas says that, when Mr. Upton Sinclair was in Chicago investigating the stock yards for his novel, The Jungle, Mr. Graiciunas took Mr. Sinclair and showed him how the Lithuanians were living at that time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
