<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 47,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Mikas Petrauskas' Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 47,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">MIKAS PETRAUSKAS' CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On November 17th the Chicago Lithuanians showed themselves to the Americans in deeds, but not with noise! On this day the concert was given by our honorable singer and composer, Mr. Mikas Petrauskas. He is the first singer that has proved to the world that even an oppressed nation has its geniuses, that under its straw roof great men are born.</p>
   <p>The concert was held in the Music Hall, where all the world's famous artists give their concerts. A majority of the public was Lithuanian.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was a duet, violin and piano, suite number 2 in E major, Eduard Schuett, by Mrs. and Mr. Frederiksen. Then Mr. Petrauskas came on the stage. The public received him with a great ovation,flowers were thrown under his feet, it was several minutes before the public became calm. Petrauskas was moved by this <pb facs="5423970_2_0171.jpg" n="2"/>ovation. The first song was Italian, "Per Pieta," by Mozart. The singer was moved by such a reception, so that he was unable to sing very well. The second song was in Lithuanian, "Thanks to God," his own composition. This song brought a greater impression on the Lithuanian public because they can understand the words. After this song the public demanded more. He sang another Lithuanian song of his own composition.</p>
   <p>The third number on the program was the violin solo "Romance et Finale," for violin by Wieniawski, was played by Frederick Fredericksen.</p>
   <p>Fourth, (a) was a song in the Russian language, "Osen," by Tschaikowski; (b) Russian song, "Ditiatko," by Pashalov. These songs Mr. Petrauskas sang very well. The last sorrowful song brought tears in the eyes of the public. Further Mr. Petrauskas sang Lithuanian songs of his own composition, "The Birds," and "Give us heat, Oh Sun." In these two songs the singer reminds our fatherland, <pb facs="5423970_2_0172.jpg" n="3"/>the singing of birds in the fatherland's forests. The following two songs were in English, "Cradle Song," by Tschaikowski, and "By the Murmuring Stream," by Tschaikowski. The last song was in Lithuanian, "Kiela," by Tschaikowski. This song Mr. Petrauskas sang very well. Number 5 was a piano solo, played by Mrs. Frederiksen, "Serenade," and "La Fileuse," by Sig. Stojowski. Mrs. Frederiksen is a very good pianist.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petrauskas sang very well the aria from Pagliacci, "Pionska Stacha," by Moniuszko; and the aria, "The Fierce Maidens," by Gounod. The best one was when he sang the last aria from the opera "Rigoletto."</p>
   <p>At the beginning of the concert Mr. Petrauskas was moved by the tremendous ovation the Lithuanians gave him. By and by the artist came to himself and performed his duty perfectly as an artist should do on such occasions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
