<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">"The Thieves" Presented by Youth Circle</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Juodvarnis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">"THE THIEVES" PRESENTED BY YOUTH CIRCLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Juodvarnis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 26, at St. George's Hall, the Lithuanian Youth Circle presented "The Thieves." The play itself has nothing special in it; its plot is taken from the life of the rich class of people. The most important roles in this play are those of the three thieves, who although they are professional robbers, pose in society as well-educated, enlightened persons; children of good parents. They commit robberies among their friends, but when they are caught in a clever manner, they convince their captors that they are innocent.</p>
   <p>But enough of the play, the performance, after all, is the important thing. The Lithuanian Youth Circle, does less exaggerated advertising than any other Lithuanian dramatic society in Chicago, but its performances surpass all of them. I should mention that the Circle pays much more attention to scenery; it is always in keeping with the play.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The performance of this drama was very good, except for the first act. It seems that the actors in the first act were beginners, and did not know their roles well. The last two acts were done artistically; much better than we can expect from people, who, after long hours of hard labor, devote their time to art. Of the actresses, Miss Sofija Urbaite and Miss Sofija Urbanaviciute were noteworthy. Those who have seen them act before, no doubt, will attend the second performance in order to see them again. Among the men, we should not forget to mention the three thieves: J.J. Zolpis, J. Gestautas, and P. K. Strzineskis. V. Valentinas as the policeman should also be mentioned. In the last act, the thieves sang a trio which was so fine, that one seldom hears such singing. The attendance was large, but could have been larger; the cause--heavy rain. If the Lithuanian Youth Circle continues its theatrical activity, it will not only have the support of the people, but other Lithuanian theatrical societies will take example from its action. As was announced in the hall, the Lithuanian Youth Circle will present another play, "Who is Guilty".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
