<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 21,
<date when="1914-07-15">July 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. J. Elias' Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 21,
<date when="1914-07-15">July 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MR. J. ELIAS' POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Elias is exploiting the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, and using their names for political purposes in order to accomplish his desires.</p>
   <p>The United Societies for Local Self-Government is well known as a Chicago politicians' nest, where they gather and discuss politics, instead of discussing the society's affairs. This society has been turned into a political organization, since Roger Sullivan and his Democratic mob joined the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago. In addition to Roger Sullivan's gang, there are various Republican factions that belong to this society. The United Societies of Chicago held a meeting last Thursday and the politicians discussed how to make a better arrangement for the coming election, and how to divide the patronage among the members of the organization who are active in the political campaign. At this meeting they selected a committee <pb facs="5423970_2_1691.jpg" n="2"/>to handle the affairs of the coming election. This committee consisted of one vice-president from each nationality, and Mr. Elias was elected as vice-president to represent the Lithuanian group. We inquired at the office of the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, what societies Mr. J. Elias represents, and the man at the office told us Mr. Elias is representing the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago. This time we ascertained for sure that Mr. J. Elias is representing the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago. Mr. J. Elias was the president of the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago some years ago. Now he is no longer the president of this society, but he is still playing politics, as he did before when he was president of this society, and he is still exploiting the name of this society for political purposes. He had no right before to use the name of the United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago, and he has no right now to use the name of the society merely for political purposes in order to accomplish his desires.</p>
   <p>The United Lithuanian Societies of Chicago should make a protest against Mr. J. Elias' conduct and misrepresentation of our societies, <pb facs="5423970_2_1692.jpg" n="3"/>which are not organized for political purposes. This society is a benevolent organization, not a political one. No one has any right to use its name for political purposes, and its name should, by all means, be kept out of politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
