<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-03">May 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Study English at Home!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-03">May 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">STUDY ENGLISH AT HOME!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thirty lessons, a full correspondence course, now for two dollars. The same course formerly cost ten dollars.</p>
   <p>We correct all homework.</p>
   <p>We return your money if you are not satisfied.</p>
   <p>There is no better method than taking this course to learn to speak, read, and write English. It is the easiest, fastest, and best method to learn the whole English language at home. Each lesson of this course deals with different matters in such an understandable and certain way that a student not only can, but is forced to remember everything. The lessons present different matters so clearly and practically, with so much interest in each line, that each word forces itself into the student's mind, so that he cannot raise his eyes from the lesson without having learned it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This course consists of thirty lessons, beautifully printed on good paper. The first lesson is of eight large pages; the others are of four pages each. At the end of each lesson is an exercise which the student does according to the instructions and with the advice of the teacher, and sends to the school for correction of mistakes. There is no charge for making corrections. The corrected exercises are sent back to the student. Instructions concerning the sending of exercises for corrections will be sent by us with the lessons.</p>
   <p>Here is what one of our students, who has learned English, says about the course:</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen: I beg you to accept my sincere gratitude for your responsible teaching and the popular lessons of your method. I am satisfied with your teaching in all respects. Thanks also for your advice. Your course is surprisingly inexpensive <pb facs="5423970_2_1291.jpg" n="3"/>....</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"Joseph Kijauskas</p>
   <p>"Norristown, Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>"July 11, 1917."</p>
   <p>We have hundreds of similar letters from our students. If, having paid ten dollars for the course, they are satisfied, you, now paying only two dollars for the same course, will also be satisfied. But order it immediately-- now. Later it might be too late. Remember, we will send out only five hundred courses at this price of two dollars. After that the price will again be ten dollars. Therefore, be the first. Send two dollars today. Add fifteen cents worth of postage stamps for mailing the course. You risk nothing. If you are not pleased, send the course back to us within three days after receiving it and we will return your money. This course is worth thirty dollars. Our price is only ten dollars, but you now have the opportunity to obtain it for two dollars <pb facs="5423970_2_1292.jpg" n="4"/>and fifteen cents, including postage. Take advantage of this opportunity now, and help us to circulate this practical method.</p>
   <p>Order today from the "L" American College Preparatory School (formerly the American School of Languages), 3103 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
