<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-07-07">July 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Second Annual Concert of Beethoven Conservatory of Music</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-07-07">July 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND ANNUAL CONCERT OF BEETHOVEN CONSERVATORY OF MUSIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 28, Anthony Pocius and his wife, Ona, conducted a concert by the students of their school, the Beethoven Conservatory of Music. The concert was held at St. George's parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn [now Lituanica] Avenue. Both children and grownups participated in the program; there were about eight children, mostly girls, and sixteen adults.</p>
   <p>The program consisted of simple piano, violin, and vocal selections. All participants in the program gave excellent performances. The pianists and singers received bouquets.</p>
   <p>Of the children, Vytautas Briedis, a ten-year-old Lithuanian boy, made the best impression; he distinguished himself not so much by good technical delivery as by his courage and self-reliance. He gave the impression that he felt entirely at home, like an old trouper, as he played a number on the piano...He did not receive any flowers, but the great applause of the audience brought him out on the stage a second time; this is really worth more to <pb facs="5423970_2_1296.jpg" n="2"/>him than any bouquet of flowers.</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with a number of songs by a mixed chorus of sixteen singers under the direction of Mrs. Ona Pocius. The chorus sang Mikas Petrauskas' composition "Dega Ugnis" (The Fire Is Burning) and Rossini's aria "Inflammatus"; Miss Ona Rudauskas, a soprano, sang the solo. The chorus made a fine impression on the audience.</p>
   <p>After the program, Mr. Pocius, director of the Conservatory, distributed medals of distinction among the younger pupils of his school, which is located at 3259 South Halsted Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
