<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-30">Oct. 30, 1908</date><title level="a">Sernas Musical Aid Fund Merged with Ausra Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-30">Oct. 30, 1908</date><title level="a">SERNAS MUSICAL AID FUND MERGED WITH AUSRA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sernas Musical Aid Fund was liquidated on Oct. 25, and merged with the Ausra (Dawn) Society. This change was made by forty members of the Sernas Fund Society in a meeting at the home of the treasurer Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas, 8829 Commercial Ave. The merger was made for economical reasons at the suggestion of Dr. Rutkauskas. The aims and purpose of the Ausra Society are the same as that of the Sernas Fund; to assist worthy Lithuanian students.</p>
   <p>The Sernas Fund was established four months ago, on June 19, 1908, by the Lithuanians of Chicago to assist talented and worthy Lithuanian music students. The fund was named in honor of Sernas (pseudonym of <pb facs="5423970_2_0323.jpg" n="2"/>Joseph Adomaitis, editor of Lietuva, and famous Lithuanian writer) as the Sernas Musical Aid Fund. The fund was raised and maintained by collections and contributions from the Lithuanian public.</p>
   <p>According to a financial statement prepared by Dr. A. K. Ruthauskas, treasurer, in the Aug. 14 issue of the Lietuva, the fund now consists of $132.25. This money was raised as follows: $100.00 donated by the twenty-third convention of the Lithuanian Alliance of America: $14.40 collected at the commemoration of the thirtieth anniversary of Sernas literary career; the balance of the fund was raised by individual contributions and from collections at Lithuanian gatherings.</p>
   <p>The $132.25 of the Sernas Fund was transferred by Dr. Rutkauskas to Dr. J. Sliupas, treasurer of the Ausra Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
