<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Aurora Gate Mother of God Society</title>, 1644 Wabansia Ave.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of The Aurora Gate Mother of God Society</title>, 1644 Wabansia Ave.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In neighborhoods where there were many Lithuanians there also Lithuanian societies were organized. But the Lithuanians having been stifled so long by the Poles and Russians, were not able to separate themselves from the Poles. For that reason, they were often drawn by the Poles into their parishes; not only the people separately but also the Lithuanian organizations. The Poles were able to get hold of such organizations and to use them for their own aims.</p>
   <p>During these dark times the Aurora Gate Mother of God Society was organized. On Aug. 17, 1907, six Lithuanians decided to meet at A. Jasinskas' home, at 2830 Cornelia Ave. and they organized this society. The first members of the society were: J. Sakavicius, president; his assistant C.Gasinskas, secretary; J. Karabavicius, Tamasinavicius, A. Stanevicius and others.</p>
   <p>This society, when organized, made as its aims: - to help and benefit the sick <pb facs="5423970_2_1772.jpg" n="2"/>members, to give the final services to the dead members, and to help the orphans. In this society each member had to pay twenty-five cents a month, getting $5 a week benefit in care of sickness. In case of the death of a member the beneficiary gets from the society $50, and each member pays $1.</p>
   <p>As many other Lithuanians thought, so also the members of the society held that the Lithuanian nationality was dying. Polish propaganda had denationalized the Lithuanians. With their society these members went to the Poles and served them for nine whole years. Denationalized Lithuanians and Poland's promises pulled the Lithuanian Society to the Polish Holy Trinity Parish, where the Lithuanians stayed until Dec. 18, 1915.</p>
   <p>In this new country, the Lithuanians put their hard-earned dollars into the Polish churches, rectories, schools and other institutions. If this is not true, then witness this Lithuanian society's history, which shows that for nine years the Lithuanians contributed to the Poles for remodeling the church, <pb facs="5423970_2_1773.jpg" n="3"/>press, hall and other things.</p>
   <p>At the present time you will find very few misunderstandings among Lithuanians, few who would work for the benefit of foreigners.</p>
   <p>The Aurora Gate Mother of God Lithuanian Society, until 1915 used the Polish language. Its constitution was written in Polish and often the meetings were conducted also in Polish. But during the time of the World War Lithuania's awakened mind affected the Lithuanians in all parts of the country and shook even those Lithuanians who had remained in the Holy Trinity Polish Parish. It dawned on the Lithuanians, that the time had come for them to break from the Poles. Leaving the Polish constitutions and all writings, the Lithuanians abandoned their foreign place and on January 2, 1916 transferred their society from the Polish Holy Trinity Parish to the Lithuanian St.Michael Parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1774.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian society now joined the Lithuanian parish, selected a new board in which the following were members; M. Randeliunas, president; L. Vasiliauskas, vice-president, J. Lapitavicius, secretary.</p>
   <p>The Rev.F. Kudirka swore them in, blessed them, and invited them to work for the good of the nation, their fellowmen, and the church.</p>
   <p>Having broken from Poland's net, these members of the society showed themselves to be good Lithuanian national patriots. When Lithuanian Liberty Bonds were being sold this society bought $50 bonds. They donated $10 to the Lithuanian gold and silver fund; $100 was donated to the Benefit League. For miscellaneous benefits and needs $85 was given. The St.Michael parish has donated $300.</p>
   <p>There are thirty-eight members now.</p>
   <p>A. Andriuskeircin, president, 1734 Wabansia Ave.</p>
   <p>Fr. Andriuskevicis, secretary, 1620 Winchester Ave.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
