<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Naujienos Eliminates Advertisements of Quack Doctors</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0917</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0917.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NAUJIENOS ELIMINATES ADVERTISEMENTS OF QUACK DOCTORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For several days now, we have seen no advertisements of quack doctors in the Naujienos. That newspaper has eliminated them quietly without saying a word to its readers. These parasites have been advertising in the Naujienos for a long time, but at last this greatest source of income to the Naujienos has collapsed.</p>
   <p>For more than three years the Lietuva has carried on an uninterrupted fight in its editorial pages against the Naujienos for accepting advertisements of quack doctors. At last, the Naujienos has given in. For that we wish to thank the Naujienos. We also wish to thank all those who have assisted us with documents, affidavits, and news items to carry on the crusade against the Naujienos successfully.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0918.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, only two Lithuanian newspapers remain that still accept advertisements of quack doctors. They are the Keleivis (The Traveler) and the Laisve (Liberty); the former is published in South Boston, Massachusetts, and the latter in Brooklyn, New York. There are reports to the effect that the Laisve will soon eliminate the fraudulent advertisements. When the parasites [ads of quack doctors] disappear from these two newspapers, the Lithuanian press will be one of the cleanest in America in regard to advertising policy.</p>
   <p>We promise to help both the Kelevis and the Laisve in ridding their pages of fraudulent advertisements if they do not do so themselves in the near future --in just the same way that we have so successfully aided the Naujienos in this regard.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
