<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-02-11">Feb. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Socialists Stage Two Comedies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-02-11">Feb. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN SOCIALISTS STAGE TWO COMEDIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dramatic Circle of the Lithuanian Socialists League staged two comedies, "Amerika Pirtyje" (America in the Bath), and "Dede Atvaziavo" (Uncle Has Arrived), on February 6, at the Hull House theatre. These two comedies have been presented here several times before, and are well known to Chicago Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>The comedy,"Amerika Pirtyje," is an original Lithuanian play, written by Keturakis. It is a historical play, because it was the first theatrical play to be staged by Lithuanians, and therefore, marked the beginning of Lithuanian drama. The historical presentation took place in Palanga, Lithuania, on August 8, 1899.</p>
   <p>The cast of players in the latest presentation of "Amerika Pirtyje" was as follows: "Bekampis"--Mr. B. Vaitiekunas, "Mrs. Bekampis"--Mrs. M. Dundulis, "Agota"--Miss M. Simoska, "Vincas," the tailor--Mr. J. Sankunas, and "Gaspadorius," the landlord--Mr. M. Kazenas. The performance was very successful, as the cast of players was composed of the best Lithuanian theatrical artists in Chicago. The best character performance was rendered by "Vincas," the tailor, which was played by Mr. J. <pb facs="5423970_2_0540.jpg" n="2"/>Sankunas; it was also the leading role. Others who rendered satisfactory performances were Mrs. Dundulis and Mr. Kazenas. Miss Simoska lacked the required enthusiasm for her part.</p>
   <p>The cast of players of the other comedy, "Dede Atvaziavo," is as follows: "Vingyra"--Mr. T. Dundulis, "Jurgis Spurgis"--B. Vaitiekunas, "Garniene"--Mrs. Dundulis, "Tarnaite," the maid--Miss O. Cepaitis. This performance was also successful. All the players rendered very satisfactory performances.</p>
   <p>Both comedies were so successfully staged that it is doubtful if any other Lithuanian theatrical troupe in America could have rendered better performances. The audience was in a very gay mood from beginning to end. The attendance was not large because many Lithuanian theatrical fans did not wish to witness the performances a second time.</p>
   <p>If the Dramatic Circle will continue to present such wonderful performances, it <pb facs="5423970_2_0541.jpg" n="3"/>will undoubtedly receive the proper support from the Lithuanian public, and will probably develop into a professional Lithuanian theatrical troupe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
