<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-10-14">Oct. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Song and the Birute Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. M. Dudas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-10-14">Oct. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SONG AND THE BIRUTE SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. M. Dudas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not necessary to argue broadly and to scrutinize thoroughly in order to realize what a part songs (and music) play not only in the awakening and improvement of the senses of the individual, not only in the cultural uplift of a whole nation, but also in the development and progress of our entire humanity. Everybody, especially Lithuanians, can feel that, if not while they are living here then at least in our Motherland, where, in the hills, forests, and fields--most often in the gardens of Rue--our sisters sing our pleasant and beautiful songs. Song, in truth, has great power and is the real ruler of a person's soul. It awakens every feeling in a person to activity and it also keeps them from too great activity; it holds them back from sadness, from too great surrender to pleasures, from violence, etc. For instance, according to tradition, Cain, having <pb facs="5423970_2_0305.jpg" n="2"/>killed his brother, sought peace from a troubled conscience in music; making a whistle out of bark, he played it and thus found at least a moment of peace for his conscience.</p>
   <p>In olden times songs and music were given priority in everything. They are even regarded as the most fitting mediums in the adoration of the Highest Being, as the Bible states: "The angels adore their Creator with songs." The Walls of Jericho fell, thanks to the mournful notes of the trumpets which were played while encircling the city's walls. Many other miraculous incidents are credited to the power of music and song, as stated by tradition and in myths.</p>
   <p>Therefore, such playing was honored in ancient times and was used in the enactment of solemn and holy ceremonies. But today they are degraded and stepped on by many, even by our brothers who, dizzy from alcoholic drinks, begin playing all kinds of instruments and sing such songs in which their basest desires and bestiality are let loose. Such music, even though it <pb facs="5423970_2_0306.jpg" n="3"/>cannot be called music, has, by its imitation of music, its own power and works the opposite from the summons of real music, that is, against virtue and the improvement of man. It becomes apparent that the people do not turn as much attention to songs and music in these times as they did in the past, although songs and music have, thanks to a few persons who are wholly devoted to that art, reached the highest degree in their perfection. But, just the same, music does not make itself heard to the soul without moving the deepest emotions. A song of the Motherland, especially, scores deeper in a man's heart and its consequences are much greater. It can be no other way. Those melodies which our mothers hummed as they swung the cradles and which induced us to shut our eyes in sweet slumber, which, in a word, were like a balsam calming our hearts, should be embraced by the souls of all of us. They should be our most important occupation; we should perfect them and promote them among our nationals and among all of humanity.</p>
   <p>The tunes of our national melodies, created by the inspiration of our <pb facs="5423970_2_0307.jpg" n="4"/>ancestors and beautified by them, make an unearthly, noble impression on each one of us and even on foreigners. All of our past, with its troubles and good fortune, with its sadness and joy, with its glory and suffering--in a word, everything, is reflected in them; even what has not been recorded by historians has been put into song by our noble, old Kankler. [Translator's note.--The Kankles is the ancient Lithuanian national instrument. Kanklers, like the English bards, are credited with the composition of the majority of the ancient folk songs.] To say it briefly, a song of the Motherland is one of the truest friends in everything and everywhere. You might be in the depths of sadness or confined by shackles, when, unexpectedly, comes the thought of a melody, for instance, "The willows sway on the hill...." or "The sun is red...." and others, of which we have many.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to express the power that such a song has in a few words, and it is not necessary to argue the matter more fully with our nationals who know it well. But I will only remind you that it is the duty of everyone to strive, as much as they can, to promote and to improve this <pb facs="5423970_2_0308.jpg" n="5"/>branch of our art. We have here the widely known Birute Society, whose highest aim is vocal training. This is accessible to all, especially Chicagoans, who have an hour of free time. There are more of such societies; however, the attention of all should be turned to the Birute Society because it is supported by all of the resources of our composer, Mikas Petrauskas. His only joy, his only good fortune is when he sees a crowd of song lovers who desire training. He is satisfied only when he sees the fruits of his labors, in the full sense of the word, for the good of his nation.</p>
   <p>It is true that at present the Birute Society has more than two hundred members. However, the number should be several times greater from such a huge throng of Lithuanians as there is in Chicago. Though we expect to realize the desired number it is hoped that this will happen as soon as possible so that art can be propagated at once and raise the spirits of our brothers. In order to avoid interruptions in the training of singers and the obtaining of results, it is necessary that as many Lithuanians as possible throng to the Birute Society. New members are being accepted <pb facs="5423970_2_0309.jpg" n="6"/>this season. Even though they do not know music at all they should join the Birute Society without delay and become co-workers in the Lithuanian field. New members will be accepted until October 15 of this year. Rehearsals and auditions of new members are held every Friday at 8 P. M. in the public hall of Mark White Park, Halsted and 29th Streets.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that chapters of the Birute Society be organized in other towns also, as has been done in Scranton, Pennsylvania and in South Chicago. They were the first to react to the activity of the Birute Society and became an example for other Lithuanian colonies, proving that we can work in common in that branch of art, even though we are scattered throughout the wide world. Only good desire and devotion are necessary and we can attain anything.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
