<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 49,
<date when="1898-12-09">Dec. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Empty Dispute</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0796</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0796.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 49,
<date when="1898-12-09">Dec. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE EMPTY DISPUTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All of our newspapers, no difference what principles they are upholding, are writing about the ignorant Lithuanians, of their drunkenness and fights. Not one newspaper denies the evil and sorrowful habits of Lithuanians, it is impossible to deny it. Yet, we do not agree on the causes of these bad habits, and on the remedy. The ignoramus does not care for nor does he respect human honor. The cause of bad habits among our Lithuanians is ignorance. The ignoramus cannot see the benefit of enlightenment. Even if one wants to enlighten himself, he can hardly do that because we have no places where one could get enlightenment.</p>
   <p>In our time, we brought up the question of establishing libraries. All the newspapers raised the question of who must undertake the job of establishing the libraries. Of course, the clergy did not take the trouble to open libraries, although in few places libraries were established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0797.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to take the people from saloons, having libraries is not enough. Besides libraries we must have amusement places, hold concerts, theatres, dances, etc. Who will take the privilege of doing it? It looks to us that it is the privilege of every one who loves Lithuanianism. While our priests are materially the best provided, it ought to be their duty to make the start, then other Lithuanians would join with their help. From this empty dispute we will reap no benefit, if we will not work and not come with our donations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
