<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-10-04">Oct. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Concert Presented by the Birute Chorus</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. K. Drangelis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-10-04">Oct. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT PRESENTED BY THE BIRUTE CHORUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by DR. K. Drangelis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After M. Petrauskas left the Birute chorus, the initiative of the organization was not very strong. It would force itself to work, would sponsor some sort of an affair, and would again become quiet. It could have been compared to an old man sitting by a stove: He would take a pinch of snuff, sneeze, and feel better for a while. But after a moment, he would be coughing and moaning again. It seemed that the enthusiasm and youthful energy had died.</p>
   <p>But Birute is again active. Once more echoes a mighty song; once more the youth are active. This is so because we have another composer, Stasys Simkus, among us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Birute chorus made its first appearance under the leadership of its new director on September 29. The members of Birute once more lined up in orderly fashion and entertained us with many songs. One had but to listen to be thrilled.</p>
   <p>It is easy to learn the tune of a song, and to read the written lyrics. That much can be done by almost anybody. But to give a song its correct interpretation, to create through a series of tones a power which is capable of elevating a soul and smoothly, calmly soothing it--the divine spark of a true artist is necessary.</p>
   <p>The hand of the director could be felt in every number of the Birute concert.</p>
   <p>In "Vazavau Diena" (I Rode All Day), "Vakarine Daina" (Evening Song), from Simkus' new opera, "Pagirenai", and "Lietuviais Esame Uzgime" (Lithuanians We Were Born), as well as in other songs, one could feel the true interpretation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: The three songs mentioned are compositions of Stasys Simkus.] You would be astounded to learn, and probably would not believe, that the Birute chorus had only two weeks to prepare for this concert.</p>
   <p>I was pleased personally with everything that was sung at the Birute concert. Miss Rudauskas, with her pleasant voice and calm, beautiful appearance; Miss Rakauskas, with her voice of a nightingale and smiling (perhaps sometimes out of place) expression; and Miss Stanelius pleased me. Mr. Kasputis, with his high-pitched, beautiful voice and a severe cold in the nose, was accompanied by Miss Rakauskas. Mr. Stogis, with his thunderous voice, was also good. Everything, everything pleased me! Where there were shortcomings in voices or something else, the deficiency was remedied by the beautiful interpretations of the songs by the artists.</p>
   <p>But, most of all, I was pleased with Mr. Simkus' new song, "Vakarine Daina", <pb facs="5423970_2_0136.jpg" n="4"/>which was heard for the first time. Even now it rings in my ears:</p>
   <p>"It is time to go home, brothers;</p>
   <p>The sun is already low.</p>
   <p>The dark night will come quickly.</p>
   <p>The mothers await us there.</p>
   <p>So, home, home, home!</p>
   <p>The sun is already low.</p>
   <p>"In the evening, in the orchard,</p>
   <p>The nightingales begin to sing.</p>
   <p>The rue in the garden</p>
   <p>Must be watered and weeded.</p>
   <p>So, home, home, home!</p>
   <p>The sun is already low.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0137.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"In the embrace of the dark night,</p>
   <p>Our labors will rest.</p>
   <p>In the hills and by the wood,</p>
   <p>Only our songs will ring.</p>
   <p>So, home, home, home!</p>
   <p>The sun is already low."</p>
   <p>What an opera that will be, since the individual songs leave such an impression! One can understand why Mr. Baciunas has already promised to donate fifty dollars toward renting a big hall when "Pagirenai" will be presented.</p>
   <p>It is up to us Chicagoans to strengthen the Birute Chorus, which is becoming active again.</p>
   <p>Wearied by the labors of the day, thirsting for art, we now have something <pb facs="5423970_2_0138.jpg" n="6"/>with which to cleanse and refresh ourselves.</p>
   <p>A long life to our Birute Chorus!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
