<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-11-25">Nov. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Folk Dance and Music</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1936-11-25">Nov. 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN FOLK DANCE AND MUSIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3...The Lithuanians are an ancient people whose language is related to the Sanscrit. Lithuania is a land that has given Poland good rulers, heroes, and men of letters, for it was during the reign of the Lithuanian royal house of Jogello that Poland enjoyed her Golden age, and such men as Kosciusko and Michiewicz-Mickus brought renown to Poland's name. But we shall not devote our time to Lithuania's history, rather to her folk dance and song.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians are a singing people, with a treasure of folk lore and song that is distinct, rich and colorful. The ploughman sings of his plough and rye fields, the shepherd of his sheep and verdant pasture lands, the maiden of her lover, her flower garden and rue wreath, the swain, of his maiden and fast steed, the mother of her children, of the daughter who is to be married, or bemoaning the son, who leaves for war. Even with tears in his eyes, the Lithuanian sings. In his saddest moment he will sing. He has songs to fit his moods and whims, expressed by the rich store of Lithuanian folk songs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0633.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Russian tzars persecuted the Lithuanian inhumanly. So not always did the Lithuanian laugh; often in his song he cried, and only the goddess of song and the speckled cuckoo, the bird of omen and sorrow in Lithuanian love, could feel with him. At night, when free of the Pan's (rich land owners ) whip, the youths went to the forests, lit bonfires and there with only the verdant grass, the slender firs and the smiling moon to see- did they reveal their true selves. It was during these Geguzines (May time) that the spirit of song and dance reigned supreme.</p>
   <p>In olden days there were many joyful songs and game dances and combinations of both ritualistic,and festive in character, dances with candles in the hands, and dances to which "Laumes" (fairies) were invited. Today circle song and game dances still exist, one known as "Agoneli"(The Little Poppy), particularly dainty and charming. The dancers inquire of the dove if she knows how the poppy grows. Naturally she knows, and tells them how.</p>
   <p>The whole process, from the time it was planted until the moment it is eaten, is told and acted out in dance and song form.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0634.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another often seen in Lithuanian communities is a song and dance called "Norin Miega" (I wish to sleep), but how can a young man sleep, when he knows that in the flower garden there is a beautiful maiden braiding a rue wreath with a song on her lips.</p>
   <p>What could her song be? He goes to the garden and what he hears will serve him as a lesson if he wants her for a spouse.</p>
   <p>The Polka occupies a very important place in the Lithuanian life as represented by the folk dance. It has become as national dance in Lithuania as in many other European nations. Mikas Petrauskas, composer and singer has introduced many folk dances borrowed from other nations - the tempo of which is similar to that of the Lithuanian dances "The Klumpakojis" (wooden shoe) dance, taken from the Bohemian national dance the "Besepa", is the most popular of these. It resembles the Scandinavian and other Teutanic "clap dances." There are many adaptations, with or without Lithuanian coloring, of the dances of foreign countries which are very popular in Lithuania, <pb facs="5423970_2_0635.jpg" n="4"/>such a "Vengierka Kokiekta" (German-Kreuz Polka) and many other dances danced at any Lithuanian entertainment.</p>
   <p>A great many Lithuanians are still dancing their native dances in Chicago and in many other Lithuanian communities in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
