<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Lietuva's Extra Supplement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">LIETUVA'S EXTRA SUPPLEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A big, awful war has started in Europe. Our motherland, Lithuania, is in the very whirlpool of that war. Being situated between the real Germany and Russia, she is like a finger caught in pliers. We do not even know what awful news each hour might bring us. But we do know that there is such news, that there will be much more, and that the Lithuanians are waiting for it impatiently.</p>
   <p>Our newspaper is prepared, and our readers will find in each number of the Lietuva a condensation of the most important news items of the week. However, there are so many news items from the battlefield that they cannot all fit into a regular issue of the Lietuva. Besides this, the readers would be able to get this news only once a week.</p>
   <p>For this reason, since last Sunday, the Lietuva, besides its regular issues, began publishing a daily extra supplement, consisting of two <pb facs="5423970_2_0986.jpg" n="2"/>pages of the same size as the Lietuva.</p>
   <p>The latest telegrams and articles from the battlefields are published daily in this supplement. The Lietuva Supplement is illustrated, and all readers can receive it by paying an additional fifty cents a month.</p>
   <p>The daily extra supplement will be published every evening, except Sundays. The supplement will not be published on Sundays and holidays unless something very important happens.</p>
   <p>Individual copies of the Lietuva Supplement are sold for two cents each in Chicago--three cents elsewhere. Subscriptions to the Supplement, however, must be for at least a month and must be paid for in advance.</p>
   <p>When ordering this war supplement, readers must, at the same time, send fifty cents or more (according to how many months they wish to pay for) and must give their full name and address clearly [written]. Address your <pb facs="5423970_2_0987.jpg" n="3"/>orders to Lietuva Supplement, 3252 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>In undertaking much work and a large financial expenditure in publishing this large supplement, we expect to thus satisfy the desires of our readers and the Lithuanian public. We believe that they will know how to evaluate our efforts.</p>
   <p>The editors and the administration of the Lietuva.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
