<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-11-30">Nov. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">New Publication of Lovers of the Fatherland Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-11-30">Nov. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEW PUBLICATION OF LOVERS OF THE FATHERLAND SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long-awaited new publication of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society, Kulturos Istorija (History of Culture), has appeared in a three-volume edition. The volumes contain more than five hundred pages and are profusely illustrated.</p>
   <p>Readers of this work may judge its worth for themselves, but it may be said here that Lithuanians will read The History of Culture with greater interest than they have read any kind of fiction.</p>
   <p>The author of the book is J. A. Chmieliauskas, formerly a member of the editorial staff of the Lietuva. Every member of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society will receive all volumes of the book free of charge....</p>
   <p>Before the end of the year members of the Society will receive another <pb facs="5423970_2_1179.jpg" n="2"/>important book entitled Ten Years of National and Cultural Activities in Lithuania. The Society is also preparing for the press several other interesting works, including a historical novel dealing with the history of Lithuania and written by M. Salcius, prominent Lithuanian author, and the literary works of J. Sernas [Joseph Adomaitis].</p>
   <p>It is apparent, therefore, that the present officers of the Society are the most active and productive that the Society has ever had in its long history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
