<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Simanas Daukantas Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1668</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1668.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE SIMANAS DAUKANTAS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspapers have written more than once about the Simanas Daukantas Society, making both complimentary and uncomplimentary statements about it. It is well known that our people sometimes get excited and say all sorts of things. But that is only half the trouble--after all, everybody makes mistakes. The sad thing is that these hot-headed people are afraid to sign their real names to the articles they send to the newspapers.</p>
   <p>An article insulting our Society appeared recently in the Lietuva. What reason the correspondent had for writing such an article, no one knows. The Society naturally wanted to investigate the lie, and demanded that the Lietuva reveal the name of the correspondent. This the Lietuva refused to do. (Editors generally do not divulge the names of their correspondents--Editor.) Similar uncomplimentary articles have appeared in another newspaper, the Keleivis, but the Society has paid no attention to these articles and has continued to carry out its necessary functions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1669.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Simanas Daukantas Society was organized on November 12, 1893. It can be said that it was the first independent [i.e., unaffiliated with any religious or political group] society in Chicago. During its short existence, it has experienced much persecution at the hands of our less enlightened brothers. Nonetheless, it has grown and prospered. The Society sponsors an annual celebration of the birthday of our great historian, Simanas Daukantas. It also has its own library, valued at five hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>I shall now speak of the income and expenditures of the Society during 1915. The amount received by the treasury was $2,497, and expenditures were $2,149.74. At the end of the year (1915), the Society's assets amounted to $3,907.82. The Society has 361 members. For purposes of comparison, I shall also mention the financial status of the Society during the last three years. Here are the figures: in 1913, the treasury had $3,267.10; in 1914, $3,581.86; in 1915, $3,907.82.</p>
   <p>The following were elected officers of the Society for 1916: I. F. Aleksandravicius, <pb facs="5423970_2_1670.jpg" n="3"/>3427 West 37th Place, president; A. D. Kaulakis, 1840 South Halsted Street, vice-president; Frank Kenutis, 3238 South Halsted Street, secretary; I. Sonikas, 937 West 32nd Place, financial secretary; A. Martinkus, 3223 Auburn Avenue, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The Society holds its meetings in the beautiful and spacious Mark White Square Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
