<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date><title level="a">Why a Daily Vilnis Is Necessary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_0831</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0831.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-02">Feb. 2, 1926</date><title level="a">WHY A DAILY VILNIS IS NECESSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A daily newspaper, for the Lithuanian working class, is very essential in Chicago. The daily Naujienos (News), has become an obnoxious anti-working class newspaper, and for that reason does not deserve our support. Nevertheless, we are contributing to the maintenance of that paper. Why? Because we have no other alternative. We want to read the latest news everyday. Furthermore, many of us by the newspaper to glance over the classified advertisement section, in search of a room, job or other needs. As a semi-weekly newspaper, the Vilnis is unable to satisfy all these needs. However, when the Vilnis becomes a daily, we will have no further use for the Naujienos, and we will attempt to persuade every Lithuanian worker to read the daily Vilnis. We are confident that our aspirations will meet with success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0832.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Lithuanian-American Workers Literary Society, has decided to take an active part in the drive to make the Vilnis a daily. At the last Chicago district conference of the society, a decision was made to secure 2,000 new subscriptions for the Vilnis. That is a highly commendable decision. However, besides a large circulation, we are in need of new printing presses and other costly equipment necessary to publish a daily newspaper. It is, therefore, necessary to raise a sufficient amount of money for this equiment. This can be done by donations and the sale of shares.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian-American Workers Literary Society has about a thousand members in the Chicago area. There is no doubt that each member desires to see the Vilnis become a daily. We can depend upon all members to do their share of the work in this important campaign. Every member should purchase at least one share; the price of the stock is only $10.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_0833.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those who have purchased one share, should buy another. It is true that some members will be unable to purchase any shares. However, many members will buy two, three, and even more shares. In so doing, they will make up for those members who are unable to buy even one share. Accordingly, we should have no difficulty in raising a fund of $10,000, in the Chicago area alone, during the next two months. In the same manner, an additional $20,000 can be raised in other parts of the United States.</p>
   <p>All branches of the society should make the necessary preparations for the drive. Huge mass meetings should be called to reach as many of the Lithuanians in Chicago, as possible. If all members will do their share of the work then it will not be very long before the daily Vilnis will become a reality. When the Vilnis become a daily, our working class activity, especially in Chicago, will double in intensity, a thing every Lithuanian worker would like to see. Therefore, let us get busy:</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
