<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-01-14">Jan. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Second District of the Lithuanian Alliance of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_2_1673</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_2_1673.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1916-01-14">Jan. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE SECOND DISTRICT OF THE LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday in Town of Lake, a convention was held by the second district of the Lithuanian Alliance of America. The purpose of this convention was to discuss the election of suitable candidates for the central board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, and to suggest to other branches of the Lithuanian Alliance what candidates should be elected as officers of this organization. The most important nominees of this district were Attorney F. P. Bradchulis and Mr. K. Jurgelionis. Although Mr. Jurgelionis' candidacy was strongly recommended, the delegates were not sympathetic and decided to choose as candidate, Attorney F. P. Bradchulis.....</p>
   <p>The convention adopted the following resolution: The third convention of the Second District of the Lithuanian Alliance of America was held on November 28, 1915; and it was unanimously decided that the Second District should suggest and recommend to all the branches of this district that suitable persons should be elected to the central board of the Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_2_1674.jpg" n="2"/>Alliance of America. In accordance with this decision, the Second District of the Lithuanian Alliance of America called this special meeting of January 7, 1916, at 8:30 P. M. The president of the Second District opened the meeting and explained the purpose of the meeting. The officials of seven branches of the Lithuanian Alliance of America participated in this meeting, and six branches sent letters with statements that they would approve and abide by the decisions of the Second Districts' convention. It was recommended and unanimously approved that every delegate at this meeting should write down the names of seven persons whom he thinks qualifies for election to the central board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, and should also indicate to what official position such persons are recommended.</p>
   <p>After a comprehensive discussion of the qualities of every candidate, it was decided by secret ballot that the Second District of the Lithuanian Alliance of America heartily recommend to the central board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America the following persons: for president, Attorney F. P. Bradchulis, Chicago; for vice-president, Pranas Kibartas, Chicago, Ill.; for secretary, A. B. Strimaitis, the present secretary of <pb facs="5423970_2_1675.jpg" n="3"/>the Lithuanian Alliance of America; for treasurer, A. J. Bierzinskis, Chicago; for doctor, Dr. A. L. Graicunas, Chicago, Ill.; and for trustees, M. J. Damijonaitis and S. T. Tananevicius, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>F. K. Strzineskis, secretary of the Second District of the Lithuanian Alliance of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
