<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-11">Dec. 11, 1918.</date><title level="a">Lithuanian Alliance Lodge Donates to Cause of Liberty</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0442</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0442.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>II D 1</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-11">Dec. 11, 1918.</date><title level="a">LITHUANIAN ALLIANCE LODGE DONATES TO CAUSE OF LIBERTY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Last Sunday, Lodge 55 of the Lithuanian Alliance of America held its meeting.
After the official business of the Lodge had been transacted, a letter from
the Supreme Board of the Lithuanian Alliance of America was read. It urged 
all lodges of the Alliance to give all possible help to the cause of
Lithuanian independence.</p>
      <p>The members unanimously agreed to comply with this request. How could they 
refuse when such a noble project faces them?</p>
      <p>This Lodge is still very young. It was organized only last April and has
fifty-one members; therefore, it is not yet strong financially.</p>
      <p>On the motion of the financial secretary and organizer of the Lodge,
<pb facs="4223970_4_0443.jpg" n="2"/>
Andrew Statkus, the members of the Lodge voted to donate ten dollars from
their treasury, and the members present donated $19.26, thus making a
grand total of $29.26. But the Lodge does not intend to be satisfied
with this contribution. It elected a committee composed of five men and
women, who will visit every member of the Lodge and other local Lithuanians
to solicit donations for the cause of Lithuanian freedom. It is expected
that a large sum will be collected in this manner because the Lithuanians 
of Chicago will not lag behind those of other cities who are donating
thousands of dollars. Don't we want Lithuanian liberty?</p>
      <p>Well, we will see what the outcome will be. In the meantime, we wish to

announce that the following members of the Lodge have donated the following

amounts as a beginning:</p>
      <p>J. Gruzdis and P. Raisutis, five dollars each; K. Koncius, two dollars;
J. Repsas, K. Lape, A. Mikalauskas, A. Rentauskas, and A. Pocevicius,

<pb facs="4223970_4_0444.jpg" n="3"/>

one dollar each. Smaller donations totaled $2.26.</p>
      <p>For the time being, these donations will be kept in the treasury of the

Lodge and will be sent [to the Lithuanian Council] with other donations 

later.</p>
      <p>Twenty new members joined the lodge that same day; a fact which proves 

officers of the Lodge are active.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
