<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1912-01-19">Jan. 19, 1912.</date><title level="a">Immigrants and Yankees </title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0331</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>II E 2</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1912-01-19">Jan. 19, 1912.</date><title level="a">IMMIGRANTS AND YANKEES
</title><title level="a">
(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>A large percentage of the inhabitants of America is made up of immigrants.
And thanks only to immigration this country was enabled to develop, to reach
the high degree of material culture of which it boasts today. That is admitted 
by the Americans themselves--those who can see beyond their noses.
However, there is a small number of "real" American Yankees who look cockeyed 
at the so-called foreigners, the element arriving from foreign countries,
and demand more and more severe laws to curb immigration. As a motive for
their demands, they make the assertion that only the most ignorant element
with the smallest degree of spiritual and moral culture, all kinds of dregs
of society seeking prey, are entering America. They bring nothing good here
but only their harsh natures, wantonness. Therefore crime--robberies, murders--is 
the fruit of unlimited immigration. All bad deeds-- the deeds of
immigrants.</p>
      <p>Is it so?</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0332.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>Police reports of all cities, including those in which an especially high
percentage of immigrants live, show that the greatest number of all kinds of
misdeeds, including the most vicious, are committed not by immigrants but by
those who call themselves real Americans.</p>
      <p>A newspaper published in Grand Rapids gives this kind of an account of crimes

committed in that city. It mentions the nationality of the transgressors.

mere it states:</p>
      <p>According to nationality, of all the arrested transgressors there were: "real"

Americans, 2511; Hollanders, 175; Poles, 137; Germans, 95; Russians, 60; Irish,

50; Canadians, 41; Lithuanians, 38; Swedes, 34; Syrians, 21; Italians, 20;

Englishmen, 15; Austrians, 13; Scots, 11; Greeks, 10; Hungarians, 9; Danes, 8;

Norwegians, 7; Rumanians, 7; Finns, 5; Swiss, 3, French, 2; Turks, 1; Belgians,

1.

We see then that of 3291 persons arrested for all kinds of misdeeds, there were
<pb facs="4223970_4_0333.jpg" n="3"/>

2511 Americans and only 780 of all other nationalities. It should be pointed

out that the larger part of the population of Grand Rapids is made up of

immigrants, not Americans. It is made apparent that those unwanted immigrants,

the "most ignorant element," who are so hard pressed and persecuted by the

"cultured" American Yankees, are not at all the criminals it has been attempted

to make them. It would not is beside the point to point out that the immigrants,

those "foreigners," are arrested in most instances for minor offenses: for

intoxication, for disturbing the peace, for family fights, etc. The greater

criminals, robbers, murderers, etc., are mostly the Americans themselves.

Undoubtedly there are instances among the foreigners, but the percentage is

much smaller than the Yankees'. Therefore there is no reason for the Yankees

to press the foreigners. Not criminals seeking prey, but people, pressed by

one or another circumstance, have come here, seeking the opportunity by honest

initiative and sweat to earn a crust of bread in a foreign land.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
