<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-05-31">May 31, 1918.</date><title level="a">"Convention" of Polish Sympathizers Starts in Polish, Ends in Lithuanian</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0504</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I G</item>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>III B 2 (Polish)</item>
          <item>III H (Polish)</item>
          <item>I G (Polish)</item>
          <item>I C (Polish)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-05-31">May 31, 1918.</date><title level="a">"CONVENTION" OF POLISH SYMPATHIZERS STARTS IN POLISH, ENDS IN LITHUANIAN</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>According to a well-planned scheme of the Poles, a group of 
Polanized Lithuanians, calling themselves Polish barons and 
acting as such, called a mass meeting in the name of the Lithuanians at 
Pulaski Hall on May 26.</p>
      <p>The Lublin Union Society was the sponsor of the affair. The active members 
of the arrangements committee were Dr. Szumkowski, Kraszewski and Bielinski. 
The purpose of the meeting was to protest against the occupation of
Lithuania by the Germans and to show the world that "the Lithuanians, like 
their forefathers, want to live in unity with their brothers, the Poles."</p>
      <p>In the resolution prepared in advance by the Polish sympathizers, they
appealed "to all the nations which, before the Polish Partition, composed
the Polish 'Rzeczepospolita', in other words, the Poles, Lithuanians and
<pb facs="4223970_4_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
Ukrainians.....They urge them to avoid disharmony and to attempt to regain
the Polish 'Rzeczepospolita' , with the same nations and the same boundaries
as existed before the Partition." The resolution stated also that if,

after this was realized, nations in this Polish kingdom wished to establish

self-government, they could do so, but must consent to a defense agreement

by which each nation would aid the others to protect themselves from
enemies.</p>
      <p>Having planned everything in detail, the Polish sympathizers began their

mass meeting. Though they call themselves children of Lithuania and

Lithuanians, their program was arranged to contain only Polish music.

poems, etc.</p>
      <p>The hall was full of people when the program began. A Polish orchestra

played the American anthem and than the Polish. The Polish sympathizers

never even thought of the Lithuanian anthem. But Dr. Drangelis, interrupting 
the master of ceremonies, Mr. Kraszewski, announced that the Lithuanian



<pb facs="4223970_4_0506.jpg" n="3"/>

anthem would be sung. when the Knights of Lithuania chorus and the

Lithuanian public began to sing our hymn, the walls shook. The Poles were 

surprised. They rose and the orchestra played the Polish anthem. Though 

this hymn at a meeting of Lithuania's children is like the fifth wheel

on a wagon, the Lithuanians all rose, out of politeness. They did not want 

to insult even these Polish sympathizers.</p>
      <p>But the Polish-minded Lithuanians repaid this courtesy with piggishness.
After the speeches, which were delivered by "an officer of the Polish army" 

and Kodis, a Lithuanian who spoke in English, the orchestra began to play

a medley of Polish tunes. When the musicians inserted the Polish anthem into 
this medley, the master of ceremonies again signaled the audience to rise.

When some of the Lithuanians refused to do so, Kraszewski called them "fools

who do not know how to honor our Polish hymn."</p>
      <p>That was like a spark in a keg of powder; it started a near-riot.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0507.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>"Recall that statement! Apologize!" people shouted from all parts of the

hall. The audience forced the master of ceremonies to apologize to the

Lithuanian for the insult. He also had to kiss the American flag.</p>
      <p>That brought the Polish program to a close. The Lithuanians, who until

then had sat patiently and listened to the Polish cooing, demanded that an

end be put to the comedy. Mr. K. Kasputis asked for permission to address

the public from the stage. It was denied to him but, after the audience

demanded it, Kasputis went up on the stage and, without dodging the issue,

flatly stated what the Poles wanted and what these Polish-minded Lithuanians

were leading to.</p>
      <p>"Let Poland be free," said Kasputis. We do not begrudge her liberty; we hope

for it. But Lithuania also wants to be free--and it will be free. The Poles

will not get Lithuania!" The audience applauded wildly and many shouted,

"Yes, we don't need Poland!"</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0508.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>Kasputis read a resolution written in English, which demanded full freedom 

for Lithuania and expressed the Lithuanians' loyalty to this country and 

the Allies. The resolution was adopted.</p>
      <p>The Polish-minded sponsors of the meeting refused to sign their names to the 

resolution even though it contained nothing against Poland. Then the people 

recalled the chairman and the secretary or the meeting, Kraszewski and

Dr. Szumkowski, respectively, and in their places elected Dr. K. Drangelis

and K. Kasputis. Thus the meeting ended.</p>
      <p>After the Lithuanians left, thirty or forty Poles and Polanized Lithuanians

remained in the hall to hold a discussion on the general theme of "A To

Psiakrew Litwini" (those Lithuanians of dog's blood).</p>
      <p>The Poles wanted to know how the Lithuanians react to their intrigues in

regard to Lithuania. Now they know.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0509.jpg" n="6"/>
      <p>The next day the Polish newspapers printed the lie that a group of Lithuanian

bolsheviks and socialists invaded the hall with clubs under their coats and 

broke up a meeting or "good Lithuanians."</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
