<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909.</date><title level="a">Mikas Petrauskas Receives Lively Welcome on Return to Chicago</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0766</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0766.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II B 1 a</item>
          <item>III A</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909.</date><title level="a">MIKAS PETRAUSKAS RECEIVES LIVELY WELCOME ON RETURN TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Mikas Petrauskas, noted Lithuanian musical and theatrical artist, was enthusiastically 
welcomed back to Chicago at a reception which was arranged in his
honor by the Biruta Singing and Dramatic Society on August. 15, at the Our Lady
of Vilna church hall, 23rd Place and Oakley Avenue. The reception was attended 
by about one hundred and ten Lithuanians, including the Biruta chorus, which
is now composed of seventy members---thirty ladies and forty men. Many prominent 
Chicago Lithuanians attended.</p>
      <p>The following is a list of some of the guests: Anthony Pocius (who graduated
earning a gold medal from the first course of the Chicago College of Music),
K. Strumskis (ex-director of the Biruta chorus), V. Dauksa, B. Janusauskas, A.
Limontas, Dr. A. Rutkauskas, Dr. L. Graiciunas, attorney F. P. Bradchulis, A.
Olsevskis (publisher of the Lietuva), J. E. Bagdziunas, M. J. Damijonaitis,
B. Vaitiekunas.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0767.jpg" n="2"/>
The hall was decorated with a number of wreaths of oak leaves and white and 
blue paper ribbons. On the table on the stage were five flower bouquets.
The members of the chorus and the guests awaited the arrival of our composer,
singer, and leader, with some kind of unusual mental tension. Some girls, who
saw him coming into the hall, rushed to the choral group and in great excitement 
and joy said: "He is here!....I saw him come in. Mr. Petrauskas has arrived."</p>
      <p>The choral group greeted their beloved guest with a song, specially written for
the occasion. Mr. Petrauskas greeted the members of the chorus, whom he had

missed very much, with enthusiastic handshakes.</p>
      <p>After the greeting ceremonies, the first part of the program followed. Miss

O. Balsis, who is American born, recited a poem, written by the poet Vaicaitis;

a quartet of Chicago Lithuanian organists, with A. Pocius at the piano, sang

"Gamta Grazi" (Beautiful Nature), composed by Mr. Petrauskas; J. Uktveris recited 
a poem entitled "Yra Salis" (There is a Land), by Vaicaitis; J’. Uktveris

<pb facs="4223970_4_0768.jpg" n="3"/>
delivered a very entertaining monologue entitled "Is Teatro" (From the Theatre);

the Biruta chorus sang two numbers: "Ko Liudi Putineli?" (Why Are You Sad Little

Tree?), by Petrauskas, and "Ant Kalno Karklai Siubava" (The Willows On The Hill

Were Undulating), by Naujalis.</p>
      <p>After the first part of the program, dinner was served during which Mr. J. Ilgaudas 
made the following toast:</p>
      <p>"Honorable Sir: I consider it a great honor that I, as chairman of the Biruta

Society, have the privilege of expressing, in the name of the Society and the

guest of the evening, our joyful welcome to you.</p>
      <p>"More than a year has already passed by since you left Chicago. After organizing

the Biruta Society, and teaching it to get along without your aid, you abandoned

it as if to test its strength. During that time, aided by the abundant force of

inspiration, encouragement and energy which we received from you, we tried to

march forward and work for the benefit of our Fatherland; our forces are young

and weak, but we tried not to disappoint you.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0769.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>"It is true that throughout that period, more than one menacing wave struck our

weak, little ship called "Biruta," and at times threatened to swallow us and end

our life. However, we managed to stay afloat, because we were at all times guided 
by a star which led us safely through all the storms--we have named that star

the star of hope. We believed that a Society which was so honorably born could

not end its existence in a shameful manner. Death was inconceivable to us; we

were filled with hope for a bright and lofty future. We had faith in you Mr.

Petrauskas, and believed that you would return and again be our leader. For that

reason the storms of life not only failed to affect us, but on the contrary, they

have encouraged and strengthened us. And now that you have returned to us and

made our hearts flutter with joy, we the Biruta Society, can boast of the fact

that we are still alive and that we intend to live and march forward.</p>
      <p>"We know that the duties, which we have imposed upon ourselves, are not easy, and

require our whole hearted devotion and assiduity to fulfill. However, our idealism, 
our love for the Fatherland, and the sacred nature of our work, will increase 
by a hundredfold the energy of all those who are devoted to this work.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0770.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>"We believe that now, as before, you will not decline to lead us onward to glorify 

the name or our oppressed but reawakened fatherland, Lithuania. Therefore, as

a symbol of our complete surrender to your leadership, and wishing that all your

labors will be very fruitful, and that all your hopes and aspirations will be fulfilled, 
we drink to your health!"</p>
      <p>After a short talk by Mr. Petrauskas, everybody drank a glass of wine to the

health of their beloved leader, and then to the health of the members of the Biruta chorus, 
the guests, and Rev. Ambrozaitis, who is a strong supporter of Mr. Petrauskas 
and the Biruta Society; shouts of hurrah were made with each toast.</p>
      <p>After the dinner, Rev. Misius, of Pittsburgh, Pa., delivered a short address. He

received much applause for his wonderful speech. It may be said, unmistakably,

that Rev. Misius is a good orator.</p>
      <p>The second part of the program followed the dinner. A. Pocius played a number on

the piano; this musical artist is still a young man, but shows unusual ability as


<pb n="6"/>
<gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
<pb facs="4223970_4_0771.jpg" n="7"/>
evening filled him with vigor and vitality.</p>
      <p>The guests were composed of Lithuanians of many different political and religious 
affiliations. Nevertheless, because of a common love for the Daina

Lithuanian folk songs, they all felt as though they were children of one

mother--Lithuania. The so-called atheists, the religious, the Socialists, and

the Nationalists, all momentarily forgot their differences. Therefore, we can

proudly say, as J. Sutkus said in his essay on the merits of the Daina: "Long

live the Daina and those who popularize them; they are the greatest unifying

force of our nation!"</p>
      <p>Now that Mr. Petrauskas is back, there will be a sharp increase in all kinds of

activities among the Lithuanians of Chicago. During the coming winter season,

much work will be done for the benefit of Lithuanian art, and for the glorification 
of our nationality.</p>
      <p>Therefore, all Lithuanians should stop wasting valuable time and energy with

petty quarrels and foolish jealousies, and strive to do productive work.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0772.jpg" n="8"/>
      <p>All young Lithuanians who are musically inclined are urged to join the Biruta

chorus at once; by doing so you will help yourselves and assist in uplifting

our nationality.

</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
