<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV. No. 43, <date when="1906-10-26">Oct. 26, 1906.</date><title level="a">Appeal</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0652</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0652.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV. No. 43, <date when="1906-10-26">Oct. 26, 1906.</date><title level="a">APPEAL</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>No one will deny that our most essential task at present is to help the
revolution in Russia. Always in the of great struggle something comes
up that we cannot overlook or pass by. Every nation has its various
undertakings which are beneficial to the nation's progress. We cannot
neglect those who are in dire need of help, even though our minds are
set on the revolutionary cause. Let the people contribute to the
national needs if it helps the progressive movement; the more we help
progress, the better it is for us.</p>
      <p>We have a new necessity, just as urgent as the revolution. We would like
the people to understand that this need will not interfere with the aid
we owe to the revolutionary cause.</p>
      <p>A Lithuanian writer whose writings have done much to help Lithuanian
progress is asking the Americans for help. He is sick and in a very bad
<pb facs="4223970_4_0653.jpg" n="2"/>
condition. The doctors told him to go to a foreign hospital, but he
has no money. He is asking for 100 rubles; this will help him get to
the hospital. Will the Lithuanians see this necessity? That is the
question. This man did not participate in actual open activity in the

revolution in Lithuania and Russia, but he wrote much for the cause

of the revolution. Our readers read many of his articles in Lietuva.

When Dr. V. Kurdirka begged us for help, we neglected him and paid no

attention. Now that Dr. V. Kudirka is dead we are organizing societies

in his name. If we had helped Dr. V. Kudirka he would be alive today.

By our neglect we have lost a great Lithuanian writer, poet and composer.

Another man has appealed to us for help, though he is not such a great

writer as was Kudirka. If we will not help him we will allow the malady

to send him to the graveyard.</p>
      <p>We will not publish his name because it will endanger him.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
