<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918.</date><title level="a">Our Societies </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0449</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0449.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>II D 1</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918.</date><title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>There are many Lithuanian societies in America. Just exactly how many there
are nobody knows, for no one has collected the data on this matter, even 
though it would be very interesting information to have on hand. However,
if we said that the Lithuanians have about two thousand societies in America, 
this estimate would most likely be too small rather than too large.</p>
      <p>Why were these societies organized and why are they still being organized?
Today, almost everybody understands the reason. These societies were organized 
so that the Lithuanians would be better able to help each other when the
need arose; so that the Lithuanians could perform such tasks as would be difficult, 
or even impossible for individuals to perform.</p>
      <p>The people realized the power of united and common action, and began to
<pb facs="4223970_4_0450.jpg" n="2"/>
organize into groups and societies. Until they realized the importance
of organization, they did not have any societies.</p>
      <p>Our societies have brought, and continue to bring great benefits to our people
by concerning themselves with matters which individuals ignore; by offering 
a helping hand to the widow and the orphan--often when they are forsaken
by everybody, and are enduring the darkest hours of their lives.</p>
      <p>The work accomplished by our societies is a noble one. It attests to the
humanness of the Lithuanian people and to their talent for organized public
work. It testifies to the fact, that when the occasion arises, our people
do not feel themselves powerless and in need of foreign aid. on the contrary, 
they know how to take care of themselves when the need is felt.</p>
      <p>A truly great need makes itself felt today. It is a greater matter than the
Lithuanians have ever before been confronted with. Lithuania today is the
<pb facs="4223970_4_0451.jpg" n="3"/>
widow who needs the help of all of her children--all the Lithuanians.
She wants to free herself from an ancient bondage; she wants to rise and
take her place among the group of free nations of the world, today.</p>
      <p>No individual can give her all the help that is necessary. We have no single
society nor organization which by itself can lead Lithuania out of her misfortune; 
it is too great a problem.</p>
      <p>But all of our societies together--several thousands of them--can save our 
Widow, Lithuania, from her great misfortune and her distress. Combined, our 
societies can save her as easily as an individual society can aid the widow
of one of its deceased members. This is our most important task at this time.</p>
      <p>We receive news from all sides which proves that many of our organizations

understand their great duty, and are doing, what they can by donating hundreds

of dollars to the cause of their native land's independence.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0452.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>We must see to it that all the societies realize their obligation.

They must thoroughly understand that they must come to Lithuania's aid with

all their means; not only with "crumbs from the table", but with as much

money as they can spare.</p>
      <p>Then a heroic task will be accomplished; a task of which we and our children 
will be proud; a task which will be recorded in history in letters of gold;

a task which will be met by Lithuania with tears of joy.</p>
      <p>She will rejoice because she has sons who are worthy of her pride, because

they removed the chains of bondage from her wrists.</p>
      <p>Has the society of which you are a member done its duty?</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
