<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 51, <date when="1905-12-22">Dec. 22, 1905.</date><title level="a">The Second Protocol of the Revolutionary Committee of Chicago</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0679</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 51, <date when="1905-12-22">Dec. 22, 1905.</date><title level="a">THE SECOND PROTOCOL OF THE REVOLUTIONARY COMMITTEE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>A decision was made at the mass meeting which was held in the district of
Town of Lake, that such meetings ought to be held elsewhere. Therefore,
on December 10, 1905, a public meeting was held to help the revolution
and the orphans of the revolution. The meeting was held at St. George's
parish hall in Bridgeport. It was called to order by J. Varkala, and after
his short and energetic speech he gave the right of the floor to the
speaker of the evening, Mr. A. Bijanakis. The speaker told about the
necessity of helping our brothers and sisters who are fighting for freedom
in Lithuania and in Russia. The next speaker was the committee's treasurer,
Mr. St. Marcinkevicia. The Dr. Kudirka Singers Society sang the "Marseillaise." 
The 8-year-old girl, A. Kabasinskiute, delivered a declamation.
After her spoke Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, Zimontas, Bagdziunas, and Kuzma. The
speakers urged the Lithuanians to donate for the revolutionary cause.
They collected $33.56.</p>
      <p>Our compatriot J. Bagdziunas has had pictures printed which he has for
sale for the benefit of the revolutionary cause. These pictures show

<pb facs="4223970_4_0680.jpg" n="2"/>
how the Cossacks in St. Petersburg were slaughtering the innocent people.

The size of the pictures is 9 x 15, price 25 cents. To every picture sold

15 cents will be donactad to the revolutionary fund. The public accepted

Mr. Bagdziuna's offer with acclamation. Lithuanians who want to buy

these pictures should write or call Mr. J. Bagdziunas, 3314 Mospratt

St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
      <p>The treasurer, Mr. St. Marcinkevicia, has on hand the following amount

of money contributed for the revolutionary cause: At the mass meeting on

Town of Lake, $19.25; St. Stanislaw Society, at its theatrical performance 
of "America in the Bath House," collected $5.17; at the public

meeting at the St. George Parish hall, $33.56; Mr. J. Bagdziunas, for

pictures sold, $2.05. Total $60.03.</p>
      <p>In Bridgeport the following collectors were elected to go from house to

house to collect money for the revolutionary cause: J. Bagdziunas, 3314

Mospratt St.; F. Eismontas, 924 33rd St.; J. Slikas, 439 State St.;

B. Gineika, 924 33rd St.; J. P. Jovaisa, 3222 Auburn Avenue; Iz. Papauckis,

883 33rd St.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0681.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>Then Mr. Al. Bijanskis delivered a speech which roused the people. The

chairman, Mr. A. Varkala, closed the meeting.</p>
      <p>Dr. A. L. Graiciunas</p>
      <p>Secretary of the Central Revolutionary

Committee of Chicago.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
