<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI. No. 32, <date when="1898-08-12">Aug. 12, 1898</date><title level="a">The Soldier's Letter from Cuba</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0139</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.D"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III D</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI. No. 32, <date when="1898-08-12">Aug. 12, 1898</date><title level="a">THE SOLDIER'S LETTER FROM CUBA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>When you read this letter cross yourself and pray for the everlasting 
rest of the soul of the soldier who was (lying when he gave me
this paper. His name is James Furnance, a French Catholic. He left me
all his wealth, but that wealth I did not keep for myself. I gave it
to the poor and suffering Cubans. I just kept this piece of paper on
which I am writing this letter.</p>
      <p>I was wounded in the arm; the wound is not dangerous because the
bullet just pierced the flesh and did not hit the bone. The soldiers
who had been badly injured were taken to the United States. The doctor
told me that in two or three months I will be all right and ready to
join the fighting ranks again. For this reason they left me in Cuba.</p>
      <p>At the front I met the Russian and the Polish officers. I recognized 
them by their uniforms, that they were from Russia. I want to
them, shook hands, and talked with them in Russian. My officer thought
that they were my relatives.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0140.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>On June 22, the Cubans defeated the Spanish army at Morro Castle.
The next day we landed on the shore and loaded our ammunition. On June
26, we came close to the city of Santiago. On July 1, we climbed the

mountains to look over the city of Santiago in the valley. On July 14,

we made an attack on the city; we had a hard fight, the rattling of the

guns was so great that even the voice of the commanding officer was

inaudible, so the officer gave us the orders by the shots of his revolver.</p>
      <p>Then we were ordered to make the charge against the enemy. The fight

was hard and severe. It would be hard to describe it. If I come back, I

will tell more about this fight.</p>
      <p>Sincerely,</p>
      <p>Kaz. Biczus.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
