<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1916-04-14">Apr. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of Our Youth in Brighton Park</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Agotos Sunus (Son of Agatha)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0195</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0195.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1916-04-14">Apr. 14, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF OUR YOUTH IN BRIGHTON PARK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Agotos Sunus (Son of Agatha)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The cold winter with its long, monotonous evenings has passed, and refreshing
spring; is now approaching. But let us look back and see what we have accomplished 
during the winter months. Although it is not pleasant to admit, we
must say that we have accomplished nothing. Most of our youth of this district
spend their time in sweet, pleasant sleep. Only those who belong to the local
Keistutis Chorus and to the dramatic circles were active. For example, the
Chorus has about thirty members. It is true that they are as active as they
possibly can be. But in this district there are not thirty, but about two
hundred young men who are capable of engaging in some kind of useful activity.
Where are they? Why don't we see them anywhere? The answer is: Some spend
their spare moments idling; their time away on street corners; others are engaged 
in various pastimes; some spend their time in saloons; and the rest are
engaged in gambling. That, then, is how our young people waste their valuable
time. It is true that the time will come when our young people will regret
<pb facs="4223970_4_0196.jpg" n="2"/>
that they have so foolishly wasted their valuable time, but, as a Lithuanian
proverb says, "there is no time after it is too late". When money is gambled

away or spent on drinks, it will never return.</p>
      <p>It is a shame that our young people can distinguish themselves only in the foregoing 
manner. Our young people in other districts are more active; they are

constantly improving themselves from day to day, and their activities enhance

our public life. But here in Brighton Park everything is the opposite!</p>
      <p>However, the fault can still be remedied. In the course of time, our young

people should realize that they deserve the support and sympathy of the public

only when they get rid of their present bad habits. And that can be done very

easily. In this district, there is an organization in which our young people

can find plenty of opportunities for good, productive, and beneficial activities.

The name of the organization is the Keistutis Club. Let us join the Club, which

now has a small but very energetic membership. Let us all work together in unity.

Let us improve ourselves, educate ourselves, and then help our backward brothers.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0197.jpg" n="3"/>
This is a great, lofty, and highly promising work. Let us wake up, brothers and sisters!</p>
      <p>The next program of the Keistutis Club will be a lecture on the subject, "Our
Partisan Groups," which will be delivered by J. Naujalis on Saturday, April 15,
at St. Eidentas Hall, 3834 South Kedzie Avenue. The lecture will begin at 7:30
P.M. Admission is free to all. It is desirable that as many people as possible
attend, since this lecture promises to be very interesting.</p>
      <p>The next meeting of the Keistutis Club will be held on Sunday, April 16, at
St. Eidentas Hall. The meeting will start at 1 P.M. All members are asked to attend without fail 
as there are many very important problems and questions to discuss.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
