<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. III, No. 29, <date when="1904-07-15">July 15, 1904.</date><title level="a">The Polish Revery</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0712</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0712.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. III, No. 29, <date when="1904-07-15">July 15, 1904.</date><title level="a">THE POLISH REVERY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Chicago Polish newspaper, Dziennik Narodowy, published a long
article about the Lithuanian-Polish relations. Sorry that the Polish
author knows so little about Lithuanians. In writing about Lithuanians,
he makes such foolish statements as these: that Lithuanian students
have begged the Russian government to make more severe the persecution
of the Poles. Further, the Polish writer says that it should be the
most essential effort of Lithuanians to keep the Poles in Lithuania,
for if the Poles should be taken from Lithuania, the culture of Lithuania 
would disappear. "The Poles brought culture to Lithuania," he
says. The Polish nobility and the clergy did not bring culture to
Lithuania. They brought slavery, oppression and ignorance.</p>
      <p>That the Lithuanians and the Poles ought to unite against Russia is
a good idea, but such a unity is impossible. As soon as the Lithuanians
and the Poles come closer, the Poles say that in the past the Lithuanians
<pb facs="4223970_4_0713.jpg" n="2"/>
have been enslaved, so even today the Poles must be the master and
that the Lithuanians should obey the Poles. No self-respecting people
will voluntarily accept serfdom at the hands of a low-cultured people.</p>
      <p>Not only the Lithuanians, but every nation want to rule itself. When

strangers try to stop the resurrected nation from ruling itself, then

no wonder that the reborn nation refuses to have any relation with

its former oppressors.</p>
      <p>In our struggle with Russia the Poles never helped us, but denounced

our struggle against the oppressor. The Lithuanians do not want to

have in their country the Russian nor the Polish masters. Neither

do the Poles want to have the Russian masters over them.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
