<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936.</date><title level="a">Gratitude</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0391</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1936-12-25">Dec. 25, 1936.</date><title level="a">GRATITUDE</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>....In 1918, the new Republic of Lithuania was faced with the very
difficult job of rebuilding the war - ruined nation. Since Lithuania served as a
battlefield, both for Russian and German armies, the country was totally ruined. Men,
women and children were killed, their homesteads demolished, stock confiscated. To
make things worse, Bolsheviks, Germans and Poles began attacking this helpless new
republic. This was the country's darkest hour, with no army, no ammunition, and no
money to buy the needed equipment. The outlook for its future existence was very
dark.</p>
      <p>In the greatest hour of need, Lithuania turned to the half million Lithuanians living
in the United States of America, who very graciously responded to the call of their
fatherland. Millions of dollars were raised for supplying the defenders of Lithuania.
with ammunition, food and clothing. Thanks to this assistance rendered at the most
critical time, today Lithuania is free and is well on its way to economic independence.</p>
      <p>In appreciation of the assistance rendered, Lithuania is forever thinking up new ways
of showing their gratitude to the American brothers.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0392.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The most commendable idea to date is the awarding of five scholarships to young

American-Lithuanians. Three American-Lithuanian students were awarded scholarship

at the University of Kaunas. Five persons will be given an opportunity of a college

education at the Vytantas Didysis (Vytantas the Great) at Kaunas. Later the number

of scholarships may be increased and some day we may see dozens of young Lithuanians

going across to Lithuania for free education in the land of their fathers. The awarding

of these scholarships is a most praiseworthy action of the Lithuanian Government.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
