<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909.</date><title level="a"/></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0356</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.F"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0356.jpg" n="2"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>III F</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909.</date><title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unknown" reason="missing"/></title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>on Guadeloupe Island. Three years later this colony moved to New York
and tamed a colony on the shores of the Hudson River; the colony was named
Ausra (Aurora). Some historians claim that the first Lithuanian colony in
America was established long before 1688 on Tobago Island by Prince Ketleris.</p>
      <p>Every nationality honors and commemorates the important historical events
of their nation. The Lithuanian immigrants should also celebrate the important 
events in our life; we should celebrate the anniversary of Lithuanian
mass immigration to America at least once every twenty years. We should
commemorate the occasion at least by holding a mass meeting with speeches.</p>
      <p>During these mass meetings our speakers can explain the following: How
Lithuanian immigration to America increased from year to year; when and
where the Lithuanian immigrants settled in America; how they managed to
make a living; how much progress the Lithuanian immigrants in America have
made during the past forty years, especially in education, journalism,
organizations, and educational institutions; an explanation of the various 
factors which hindered our accelerated progress; effect of Lithuanian
<pb facs="4223970_4_0357.jpg" n="3"/>
emigration upon the economic life of Lithuania; and the effect of American
life upon Lithuanian immigrants. An explanation of these questions should

be intensely interesting to our people. Many of our immigration pioneers are

still alive; it would be very interesting to hear their impressions and

stories at the mass meetings.</p>
      <p>We should also make a systematic statistical study of Lithuanian-Americans

every ten years. Then we would have at least some accurate information about

the exact number of Lithuanians in the United States. Some Lithuanian

newspapers claim that there are about 200,000 families, or a total of 700,000 
Lithuanians living in the United States; they also claim that the city

of Chicago alone has about 50,000 Lithuanians.</p>
      <p>Exactly ten years ago I made a very careful statistical survey of Lithuanians

in the United states. I actually counted about 75,000 Lithuanians. To

that figure must be added about 25,000 that I missed and was unable to reach.

My final result, therefore, showed 100,000 Lithuanians. I am certain,

<pb facs="4223970_4_0358.jpg" n="4"/>

beyond a doubt, that there were no more than 125,010 Lithuanians in the United

States ten years ago. Therefore, can it be possible that the number of

Lithuanians in the United States has increased to 700,000 during the past

ten years? It would be very interesting to learn whether or not that is true.</p>
      <p>By Rev. John Zilinskis</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
