<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-05-23">May 23, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">We Must Have Better Harmony Among Our Various Clubs</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0172</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0172.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-05-23">May 23, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">WE MUST HAVE BETTER HARMONY AMONG OUR VARIOUS CLUBS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>.....In previous issues we have been hinting about a get-to-gether
for young folks of the various clubs they belong to.</p>
      <p>As a result of our announcement, several persons have asked us what value ther
could be in bringing together individuals and club members of different views.
Each club has its own distinct requirements and ideas and would not care to ally
itself with any other group.</p>
      <p>True. And we do not aim to invite any clubs. On the contrary, we are interested
in seeing each club develop as rapidly as possible. But, we are interested in
promoting a deeper feeling of friendliness toward and between the clubs of American
youths of Lithuanian descent.</p>
      <p>Each club may have different plans and its own different methods of carrying out
these plans, but after all, there in just one fundamental purpose behind all our
<pb facs="4223970_4_0173.jpg" n="2"/>
clubs, to keep together groups of young people of Lithuanian descent.

It does not matter what the specific difficulties may be, all clubs have the same

big problem, - how to attract, interest and hold desirable persons as members.

If we had a get-to-gether whereby, first, the numerous clubs could become a little

better acquainted with each other, and then, a general meeting for studying the

several situations existing in our clubs, it is very probable that some of our

most puzzling questions would be answered and great results secured. It is only

through mutual thought and united effort that worthwhile solutions will be made,

which will be of inestimable value to all clubs, individually, as well as a whole.</p>
      <p>But, before we can proceed with our plans for this get-to-gether, we would like to

hear from a few more individuals and clubs interested in our enterprise. We shall

welcome any comments or suggestions.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
