<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 337, <date when="1898-09-16">Sept. 16. 1898</date>.
<title level="a">How To Improve the Situation of Our Parish</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0047</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.5"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0047.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>I A 2 a</item>
          <item>I A 2 b</item>
          <item>II D 3</item>
          <item>II D 4</item>
          <item>II D 5</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 337, <date when="1898-09-16">Sept. 16. 1898</date>.
<title level="a">HOW TO IMPROVE THE SITUATION OF OUR PARISH</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>In the past few numbers of Lietuva you have seen the situation of the
Chicago Lithuanian parish. You have seen the Rev. Krawczunas' public
statement of income since the inception of the parish from 1892 to
1896 inclusive, as follows:</p>
      <table>
        <row>
          <cell>In the statement of 1895</cell>
          <cell>$28,787.78</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>In the statement of 1896</cell>
          <cell>34,952.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Loan from the bank</cell>
          <cell>15,000.00</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p>From the time of establishment of this parish up to 1896, income
the parish treasury was $78,739.78. Rev. Krawzounas says nothing
about how much money he collected from the people in 1897 and 1898. He gave
<pb facs="4223970_4_0048.jpg" n="2"/>
no account of it to his parishioners. The priest's statement of 1896
shows that during one and one half years he collected over $34,000
from his parishioners, which means more than $20,000 per year. Now, if
during the slack years he has collected over $20,000 per year, then 
during the better times in these last two years, if he were unable
to collect $20,000, at least he was able to collect $15,000 a year,
then, for the last two years it would be as follows:</p>
      <p>Since the establishment of the parish up to 1896 as Rev. Krawczunas

stated in his own statement, the income into the parish treasure was

$78,739.78. For the last two years, let us say just $30,000.00. From

the inception of the parish up to the present time the income to the

parish treasury was $108,739.78.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0049.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>Here we use the income. The priest is the treasurer of the parish. Now

let us glimpse at the spending: could the priest have spent all of that

hundred and eight thousand dollars?</p>
      <p>The priest even made a mortgage on the church; then how much money was

left to the priest?</p>
      <p>The priest appointed his own committee in order to show the expenses

of the parish. but the committee showed only $41,758 expenses. This is

too low. The priest had more expenses than the committee stated. We

will not go according to the committee's statement, but on the priest's

own statement or 1895 and 1896. We will take a very honest account of

the expenses:</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0050.jpg" n="4"/>
      <table>
        <row>
          <cell>Fire Insurance</cell>
          <cell>$455.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Paid off deposits</cell>
          <cell>8,265.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Rents before the rectory was built</cell>
          <cell>104.40</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The three year salaries as the priest himself stated</cell>
          <cell>4,824.64</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>And for the last two years let us make the same amount of salaries</cell>
          <cell>3,217.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Rev. Kolesinski's salary for 22 months at $70 per month</cell>
          <cell>1,540.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>14 lots (for the church)</cell>
          <cell>11,200.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Rectory</cell>
          <cell>9,700.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Church</cell>
          <cell>18,169.73</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The church furniture</cell>
          <cell>4,701.04</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The bells</cell>
          <cell>729.94</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The bell tower and steeple</cell>
          <cell>1,275.00</cell>
        </row>
        <pb facs="4223970_4_0051.jpg" n="5"/>
        <row>
          <cell>The street pavements</cell>
          <cell>$736.10</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The school house - we can say at</cell>
          <cell>2,000.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Fence, improvement of the churchyard</cell>
          <cell>1,000.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>To Rev. Kolosinski's organist at $30 per month</cell>
          <cell>660.00</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>All the expenses were</cell>
          <cell>$68,577.91</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p>New let us compare income and expenses:</p>
      <table>
        <row>
          <cell>Income</cell>
          <cell>$108.739.78</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>
Expenses</cell>
          <cell>$68,577.91</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>
Then, what has the treasurer (priest) done with the balance of</cell>
          <cell>$40,161.87?</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>
</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p>Let the priest explain to us in one way or the other; from the pulpit,

<pb facs="4223970_4_0052.jpg" n="6"/>

at the meeting, or in writing, whichever he thinks is better for him,

what became of the balance of $40,151.87.</p>
      <p>We estimated all the expenses that the priest had in the parish affairs.

We estimated the land, the buildings, the fence, everything that was

bought for the church, and the wages to the servants since the establishment 
of the church up to the present time. We estimated not of our own

knowledge, but according to the priest's public statements of 1895 and

1896. Even though the expenses were very high, still $40,000 was left

of parishioners' money.</p>
      <p>If we had taken honest account of that money, and if we ourselves had

hired the contractor to build the church, what a church we could have
<pb facs="4223970_4_0053.jpg" n="7"/>

built for $12,000, and not for $18,169.75, as our priest contracted!</p>
      <p>The owner offered those two lots at Auburn Avenue to the parish for

$2,500.00, but our priest, for the good of his parishioners, paid

$3,600 for them. Maybe all the other expenses were estimated by the

priest with the same honesty.</p>
      <p>Now, where is the truth?</p>
      <p>The treasurer (Rev. Krawczunas), by the way, calls himself honest,

but when we look into his treasury we find no justice, because the

treasurer refuses to show the parish budget books. He hides the books.

No one is required to hide the truth. only the wrongdoer is the one

who hides the truth.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0054.jpg" n="8"/>
      <p>$40,000 of the parishioners’ money was lost by the treasurer, and

on top of it, there was a $20,000 debt made on the church. Where is

Justice? Where is the morality of such a treasurer as our Rev. Krawczunas? 
Let even one moral parishioner ask himself, is our priest

doing right by such a conduct of his parishioners' budget? Shall we

leave our priest as treasurer in the future to collect money from

the people and to increase the debt on the church?</p>
      <p>As long as we keep the priest as parish treasurer, the debt on the

church will not decrease. but will grow up, as the Polish church debt

grew from $10,000 up to $100,000. No matter how many thousands of

dollars we deposit, the priest's pockets are very deep, they can

contain millions of dollars, and yet, the debts on the church will

grow.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0055.jpg" n="9"/>
      <p>If we want to improve the standing of our parish. if we want to pay

off the church debt, and to have our church free of debts, we should

not deposit our money in the priest's pocket but deposit it in the

bank. In the bank our money will be safe, and any time the parish needs

the money it can take it. But when the money is deposited in the

priest's pocket, from there you cannot take it. Once the priest puts

the money in his own pocket, than the parish will not get it. no

matter for what purpose the parish needs money. If the money is needed

for some improvement of the parish, the priest will never use the

parish money; he will borrow the money as he has done in the past.

The Polish priest has been doing the same.</p>
      <p>From this day we ought to elect the parish administration; the president,

vice-president. secretary, treasurer and collectors.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0056.jpg" n="10"/>
      <p>We must have the parish ledger. The collectors must deliver the money

to the cashier, and the cashier must deposit the money in the bank, and

then the bank book must be given to the president. All the administration

must be under bond for responsibility for the parish money. The parish

officers elected once a year must examine the ledger and the budget.

Pay salary to the priest, and leave him the profits of baptism, masses,

nuptial services and the funerals, as to the other affairs, the priest

should have no rights. The price of baptisms, nuptial services and

funerals must be set, and the priest should pay taxes for it. Then we

will have order in our parish, the priest will be good to us, and we

good to the priest. All the misunderstandings among us will disappear,

because there will be nothing to fight for.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0057.jpg" n="11"/>
      <p>From the last statement of the priest, we see that there are 3,000

parishioners. By paying to the parish treasury $5 by each person each

year, in one year $15,000 would be in the bank; in two years would be

$30,000, in three years, $45,000, and in ten years we would have

$150,000. For $30,000 we would finish our unfinished church; for

$50,000 we would establish a hospital; another $50,000 would build

an asylum for our old people, orphans and invalids, and the balance

of $20,000, we would have in the bank for reserve. We could have a good

school, so that some of our Lithuanians could be able to obtain higher

education.</p>
      <p>We would have all that, if our money would not go to the priest's pockets.

In that manner we could show ourselves that we are good Catholics, love

God and our fellow man.</p>
      <p>

Today we are depositing everything in the priest’s
<pb facs="4223970_4_0058.jpg" n="12"/>

pocket. Although in our prayers we say: "I love God with all my might

and my fellow man as myself," by saying that we are deceiving God

Himself. Let us prove where our love of God and our fellow man is.

Instead of loving God, we are only loving the priest, we are sticking

everything into his pocket, and we pay no attention to the fact that

our priest pawned the house of God to the bank.</p>
      <p>
Then where is our love for our fellow man? Today, if our fellow Lithuanian 
is injured on the railroad, or in the factory, loses his legs or

arms, where do we put him? We are taking him to the Presbyterian or

Protestant hospital. Our old people, who have lost their health, cannot

support themselves any more, they find shelter with Protestants, with

non-Catholics while we are Catholics. We show our Catholicism only with

lips and tongues, but our manners and actions are worse than those of

<pb facs="4223970_4_0059.jpg" n="13"/>

wild people. We are feeding one priest like a fatling, but the invalids,

the orphans and the old people, we do not see. If those not Catholic would

give no shelter to our poor Lithuanian Catholics, they would starve to

death!</p>
      <p>

We and our children are sinking into the abyss. We have no place to get

enlightenment and education because all of our donations are going into

the priest's pocket. Such is our love for our fellow man. Are we not

defrauding God by lying in our prayers that "We love our fellow man

like ourselves?" For the amount of money that we are wasting on the

priest, we could help hundreds of our unfortunate brothers. Then we

could show that we love our fellow man, and for that we could obtain

God's blessing. Instead of helping our brothers, we are increasing the

capital in the bank for the priest. Are we helping Catholicism? No!</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0060.jpg" n="14"/>
      <p>
We are increasing the enemies of the priest, and we are humiliating

the priest himself. It is time for us, brothers, to wake up; we must

not provoke the animosity of our God anymore.</p>
      <p>

We should not make the world laugh at us for our improper conduct. It

is time to know that God is our God, but not the priest; and to do what

God told us, but not what the priest says. As long as we will not make

God understand that we are people and behave like people, until then we

will not be able to raise ourselves from our unsuitable living condition.

So long as we will have in our mind only the priest and the saloon, the

people will take us for savages as they are holding us today.</p>
      <p>
Brothers, it is time to wake up.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
