<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-30">Dec. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanian to Hold Gigantic Protest Meeting</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0411</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0411.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-30">Dec. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIAN TO HOLD GIGANTIC PROTEST MEETING</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Terrible news comes from Lithuania! Vilna is caught between two fires! From
one side, hordes of Bolsheviks are approaching the city; from the other side,
the Poles are sending their army to occupy Vilna under the pretext or protecting 
it from the Bolsheviks. News has reached us that the Lithuanian government, 
lacking the means of defending itself and Lithuania from these enemies,
has been forced to flee the capital.</p>
      <p>What should be done? What action should be taken? Can the Lithuaniana look
on calmly while their enemies are preparing to thrust a knife into the very
heart of Lithuania? The Lithuanians of Chicago will not remain silent. For
this reason, the Lithuanians of Chicago are preparing for a gigantic mass meeting 
on New Year's Day. This protest meeting will be held in the Seventh
Regiment Armory Hall, 3401 Wentworth Avenue, where the Lithuanians held a
mass meeting last spring during the Liberty Loan campaign.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0412.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The decision [to stage this demonstration] was made by a group of Lithuanian
leaders who met at Birute Hall, 3249 South Morgan Street, yesterday afternoon.
Various committees were elected from among this group to make all the necessary 
arrangements. The program committee announces that the best speakers
from among the Lithuanians, Americans, Jews, and Ukrainians are being invited. 
The protest meeting will begin at 3 P.M.</p>
      <p>Every Lithuanian should come to this meeting. Let Chicago know, let America 
know, let the world know, what the Lithuanians think about the seizure of

Vilna and other Lithuanian territory!</p>
      <p>Therefore, do not forget! Be at the Seventh Regiment Armory, at 34th Street 

and Wentworth Avenue, on New Year's Day, Wednesday, January 1, at 3 P.M. The

hall seats about ten thousand people, but the committee is afraid that it

will be too small. Therefore, do not be late! When you come, bring
<pb facs="4223970_4_0413.jpg" n="3"/>

Lithuanian and American flags with you. Everybody, all Lithuanians, stand

up for Vilna and for Lithuania!</p>
      <p>Tonight, at 8 P.M., a preliminary meeting will be held in St. George Parish

Hall, in Bridgeport. Whoever can attend is invited to do so. There will

be a discussion of the situation.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
