<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1937-01-10">Jan. 10, 1937.</date><title level="a">Our Source of Inspiration</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0378</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>II B 2 a</item>
          <item>II B 1 e</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1937-01-10">Jan. 10, 1937.</date><title level="a">OUR SOURCE OF INSPIRATION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>One great source of patriotic inspiration for our American born Lithuanians
has yet to be tapped. This source is Lithuanian literature, and by
this we mean the scores of romantic and historical novels, biographies,
histories, technical books and collections of essays and poetry being
published every year in Lithuania. When we remember that the renaissance
of Lithuanianism fifty years ago was largely, almost exclusively, brought 
<pb facs="4223970_4_0379.jpg" n="2"/>
about by what has now become our Classical Lithuanian literature, we
cannot conceive of the preservation of that Lithuanianism among our
people in this country without a closer contact with contemporary
Lithuanian literature.</p>
      <p>A nation without its literature is doomed. The same fate awaits that
part of a nation which is denied easy access to its own literature.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0380.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>In publishing house store-rooms, in Lithuania, thousands of books are
mildewing because there is no market for them. And yet one
of the greatest potential markets for these books - America - has been allowed
to go undeveloped.</p>
      <p>However, it will not be an easy task to correct this condition and make

us Lithuanian book conscious. It will take more than a few advertisements

to budge the great body of American Lithuanian youth out of its indifference 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0381.jpg" n="4"/>

to everything that is Lithuanian, particularly Lithuanian literature. It

will necessitate a concerted campaign of advertising, publicity, and a

wide spread distribution of books to begin to accomplish this. We must

begin sometime, and the sooner the better.

We read with a great deal of interest of the arrangement recently made

between various Lithuanian publishers and Marianopolis College, in Lithuania,

to make this American Lithuanian institution a distributing center for
<pb facs="4223970_4_0382.jpg" n="5"/>

Lithuanian books. This is a step in the right direction, and we heartily

commend the authorities of Marianopolis for it. And yet such an arrangement

in itself is by no means the solution of our problem. It will do little

good if there is no attendant publicity. We cannot expect our people to

discover for themselves that there are Lithuanian books for sale, and

then flock to buy them. A mere occasional listing of the books received

will not help much either.</p>
      <p>Parenthetically, we would like to express our strong disapproval of the

selfish attitude displayed by most of our Lithuanian newspapers in this 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0383.jpg" n="6"/>
regard. For years Lithuanian publishers have been sending scores of new

books every year to our newspapers. They have been doing this at great

expense in the hope that, in return for these free books, they will be

read and reviewed and given some publicity in American Lithuanian newspaper

columns. Yet we can count, on the fingers of one hand, the reviews of

Lithuanian books that we have seen in our half dozen or so newspapers in

the past five years.</p>
      <p>The best form of publicity for books is reviewing. Nothing can arouse so

<pb facs="4223970_4_0384.jpg" n="7"/>

much interest in a book as a critical opinion of it.</p>
      <p>Reviews of Lithuanian books are particularly needed in America to dispel

the wrong impression most of us have about Lithuanian literature. Most

of us associate the literature of our nation exclusively with the sugary

"mother and child" stories and the cut and dried "they lived happily ever

after" types, and goody-good characters. These all have their uses and

their spheres of influence, but too much of anything can become boresome.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0385.jpg" n="8"/>
      <p>A balanced reading diet is what we all need. Reviews can bring out the

fact that Lithuanian literature follows the general trend of literature

the world over.</p>
      <p>Merely as an illustration, not as a commendation, we have even observed that

several Lithuanian romances, published in recent years, have been almost

too realistic for American appetites.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0386.jpg" n="9"/>
      <p>But, before we can create an American market for Lithuanian books, even

before we can arouse any interest in them, we must make them so easily

obtainable that even those with only a slight interest in and a limited

knowledge of Lithuanian, will perforce become acquainted with them.</p>
      <p>Thus, it would seem that one of our first requirements is the establishment

of reading centers or small libraries in the most important Lithuanian

colonies in this country, where our young people could borrow and read the
<pb facs="4223970_4_0387.jpg" n="10"/>

latest Lithuanian books free of charge. These libraries would not necessarily

have to be separate establishments, but could be contained in club rooms,

newspaper offices, schools, etc.</p>
      <p>Who would supply the books for these libraries? It is almost out of the

question to suppose that we could possibly bestir ourselves out of the

lethargy into which we have fallen, and buy the books ourselves, each

colony supplying its own. There are any number of possible solutions few

of which, however, are very probable.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0388.jpg" n="11"/>
      <p>We personally would look hopefully across the sea, to the Lithuanian

government, for our solution. The Lithuanian government has recently

demonstrated (by its granting of scholarships) how friendly it is to

American Lithuanian youth, and how deeply concerned it is with our future

as Lithuanians. If it was willing to grant scholarships, at great expense, 
to a select few, it would not be too presumptuous of us to hope

that reading centers might be subsidized by the Lithuanian government.

Thus, Lithuanian influence would reach, not a select few, but hundreds

and thousands of American Lithuanian?</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0389.jpg" n="12"/>
      <p>The cost to the Lithuanian government, of such a subsidy, would be

negligible, an investment that would be returned an hundredfold, both in

strengthened marketable interest in the Fatherland and in a timer and

more widespread Lithuanianism in our daily lives.</p>
      <p>We believe this idea has enormous possibilities, and we urge our young

American Lithuanians to consider it and to act upon it, collectively and

<pb facs="4223970_4_0390.jpg" n="13"/>

individually, by presenting their petitions to the Lithuanian government

either directly or through the Lithuanian consulates.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we hope that the editors of Jaunimas will find it possible,

in the near future, to begin presenting reviews of recent Lithuanian books

in these columns.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
