<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913.</date><title level="a">Contribution to the Lithuanian Science Building of Vilnius [Vilna]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0620</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913.</date><title level="a">CONTRIBUTION TO THE LITHUANIAN SCIENCE BUILDING OF VILNIUS [VILNA]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Mr. K. Jurzelionis, of Chicago, wrote to several Lithuanian newspapers of
America, urging the Lithuanians to become permanent supporters of the
Lithuanian Science Building of Vilnius [Vilna]. In tns words of Mr.
Jurgelionis, "to make an honorary pledge, that a certain amount of money
will be donated every year, as long as we live, to the Lithuanian Science
Building of Vilnius." He made a pledge that he would pay five dollars every
year, as long as he lives, to the fund of the Lithuanian Science Society of
Vilnius. Several other people have made similar pledges.</p>
      <p>The proposition is noble and should unquestionably be supported. There are
many Lithuanians who are willing to support it and to become life members of
the Lithuanian Science Society. But the material standing of some of us does
not permit us to support this honorable cause, no matter how willing we may be.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0621.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>It would be absolutely impossible for some of the young American Lithuanians
to donate one hundred dollars. The suggestion of contributing five dollars
yearly is a good one. One can make an effort to pay several dollars yearly,
no matter what one's material standing is.......Whoever cannot donate more,

can contribute one or two dollars yearly. He will not feel hurt by giving 

"the widow's mite", because by adding pennies in one place, they will become 

a large pile of money. For others, it may be inconvenient to become life

contributors; others are willing to become "benefactor members". He may not

be able to afford that today, but, he can promise to contribute one hundred

dollars by paying yearly according to his ability, until the sum is paid in

full. Many people, whose names will be published in the near future, have

promised to do this.</p>
      <p>We believe that every conscientious Lithuanian will follow the example of the

former contributors, and will promise to donate his share. The Lithuanian

Science Building in Vilnius, we, the American-Lithuanians, can erect with

our own efforts. Let us be willing! And after a few years, thousands of

<pb facs="4223970_4_0622.jpg" n="3"/>

American-Lithuanian names will be inscribed in the honor roll on the walls of

the Lithuanian Science Hall in Vilnius, Lithuania.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
