<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI. No. 32, <date when="1898-08-12">Aug. 12, 1898</date><title level="a">The Parish Affair</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0096</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0096.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>I B 4</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI. No. 32, <date when="1898-08-12">Aug. 12, 1898</date><title level="a">THE PARISH AFFAIR</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>In the last week's issue of Lietuva, we demanded a clearer explanation
from the parish committee of Rev. Krawczunas' financial statement of the
church. What became of the money, and why does not the priest disclose
the new mortgage he made on the church, and what did he do with that mortgage 
money.</p>
      <p>Now the societies are demanding from Rev. Krawczunas more specific
explanations, but the priest simply ignored the members.</p>
      <p>At last Sunday's meeting, the Rev. Krawczunas paid no attention to
the parishioners, so the parishioners left the hall. Only a few old
women and a few old singers remained on the meeting. Then Rev. Krawczunas
held the parish meeting with those few people. The priest stated that the
parishioners have no right to interfere with the finances of his church;
that at the present time even the bishop will give no consideration to
the parishioners' complaint, because the parishioners - during the last
<pb facs="4223970_4_0097.jpg" n="2"/>
three years - did not make any complaint to the bishop against the priest.
When three years passed without complaint against the priest, then the

parishioners lost all their rights to the church financial affairs; that

the priest does not need to have any parish committee, does not need to

make any explanation about the finances, the mortgages, and the debts of

the church. The parishioners have nothing to do but pay money to the priest

and demand no explanation.</p>
      <p>Some of the societies are holding their meetings on the question of

what to do with the Krawczunas' case. The two oldest societies, the Province 
of God and the Saint Casimir - which established the parish, also

will hold their meetings.</p>
      <p>We are asking all Lithuanian societies which participated in organizing 
this parish and building the church, to hold their meetings for

the protection of their rights as parishioners.</p>
      <p>The priest is denouncing us and says that we have no right to interfere
in his private church affairs.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0098.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>We have nothing to do with the priest's private affairs, but we are

concerned with the Lithuanian public affair. We, as the guardians of justice,
have waited too long, not telling the people to watch their parish

financial affairs. This church has been built by the people, therefore,

the people have full right to protect their property. The church was built

with the people’s hard-earned money and not with the priest's money. Furthermore, 
Rev. Krawczunas says that we are going against the people's religion.
We have nothing to do with their religion. We are protectors of public
rights because the church and its affair is not the private affair of the

priest, but of the public - the people who gave their money and devoted

their time for the establishment of the church.</p>
      <p>The priest is telling the people not to read our newspaper. Our answer

is this: God forgive him, because he does not know what he is doing! When

God wants to punish someone, He takes away his reason!</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
