<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. 1. No. 1: <date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date><title level="a">Aid or Exploitation</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0315</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.7"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0315.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>II D 7</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. 1. No. 1: <date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date><title level="a">AID OR EXPLOITATION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>A young man, George Kuzmickas, had a very sad experience while
traveling from Lithuania to America. George Kuzmickas was going
to his sister and brother-in-law, who lived at 1732 N. Lincoln
St., Chicago, Ill. He arrived in New York on the 29th of August
last year.</p>
      <p>This young man lost his sister's address and for that reason was
detained on Ellis Island for three weeks. He had no way of notifying 
his relatives of his detention on Ellis Island. Finally he was
taken in by the Slavonic Immigrant Society, which found him employment 
on a farm. There he worked one month and received as compensation 
for his services about $5 worth of clothing, and a ticket
to Pottsville, N. Y.</p>
      <p>From Pottsvile, N. Y., he was sent, by an agent named George J.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0316.jpg" n="2"/>
Keek, to farmer C. D. Craudall, South Hamilton, Madison Co., N. Y.,
where young Kuzmickas worked two months with no pay at all. Kuzmickas' 
relatives made every effort to have him come to Chicago
when they found out where he was, but there were some complications,
and the relatives could not get him to Chicago, for it required a
lot of money to release him from the party with whom he was staying.
Threats were even made to return him to Lithuania where he came from.
His relatives were very much excited and did not know what to do nor

where to go for help. The situation appeared quite difficult to his

relatives, who tried hard to have Kuzmickas come to Chicago. His

sister, especially, was grieved over her brother's detention, for

she had expected him in Chicago for a long time. Finally, George

Kuzmickas was released from the party with whom he was staying and

working for nothing like a white slave. His sister sent him twenty-three 
dollars for his transportation. This enabled him to reach

Chicago on February 2, 1914, after spending four months slaving

among strange people in the strange land to which he had come to

<pb facs="4223970_4_0317.jpg" n="3"/>

make his home permanently. His desire was to become a citizen of
this great nation, called the land of freedom and democracy.</p>
      <p>The question is now whether this young man, Kuzmickas, was given

aid or whether he was exploited like a white slave. If he was

exploited than he must receive compensation for his work during the

period he was there, and the guilty one should be punished by the
law of this great land.</p>
      <p>Mr. G. Kuzmickas' case must not be forgotten. We must appeal to the

proper authorities and request them to investigate this case immediately.

In order to protect our future immigrants from such experiences, we

request those who know of similar occurrences inform the Naujienos

Immigrants' Department. Our duty is to help those immigrants who are

illegally exploited by strangers.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
