<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-19">Sept. 19, 1913.</date><title level="a">Appeal
Let Us Make November 22 Lithuanian Revival Day</title> by P. J. Mulevicius
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0602</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-19">Sept. 19, 1913.</date><title level="a">APPEAL
Let Us Make November 22 Lithuanian Revival Day</title> by P. J. Mulevicius</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>November 22 is the birthday of the honorable Dr. Jonas Basanavicius, one
of our patriots who seek to awaken Lithuania. On this day there was born
a tireless worker for Lithuanian nationalism. At present, he is one of the
living Lithuanians who has devoted his energy, wealth and honor for the
rebirth of Lithuania. Now, when he is in America, to which he has come to
collect money for the National Museum, we, as Lithuanians, should meet him
not only with large donations, but we ought to express honor and respect to
him for his tireless work in the cultural field.</p>
      <p>In my opinion, the greatest expression of our gratitude towards him would be
to recognize his birthday as Lithuanian Revival Day. In memory of this day,
we should donate one day's wages for the Lithuanian National Museum in Vilnus.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0603.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>If we, the American Lithuanians, would donate one day's wages, we could
accumulate a very large sum of money. With such a sum of money, if we could
not build the entire building, we could at least give it a good start.</p>
      <p>I think it is obvious to everyone who has not yet lost his sense of nationalism, 
or has fallen so low that he would dare to reject his own mother, that

his duty is to support this project. Therefore, on November 22, let us all

donate our day's wages for the National Museum of Vilnus. By such an action

we will bring life to our exhausted nation, and at the same time, we will

express our gratitude and thankfulness to the promoter, Dr. Basanavicius. Let

us accept his birthday as Lithuanian Revival Day.</p>
      <p>Such a collection should be taken up by the Lithuanian national and the national

Catholic societies, the Lithuanian Alliance and the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance 
branches, committees and the editors of the Lithuanian newspapers. Besides

the day's wages, on the same evening, there could be arranged lectures, theatrical

performances, and other performances, and the profit should go to the National

<pb facs="4223970_4_0604.jpg" n="3"/>
Museum.</p>
      <p>If all of us, regardless of our views, would agree that our wages for one 

day, November 22, should be donated, there is no doubt but that we American 

Lithuanians alone, in two years could build the National Museum in Vilnus.

By this we could prove that the foolish attacks by certain newspapers on the 

honorable delegates were futile. This is very easy for us to accomplish. We 

need willingness and hard work, in which our intelligentsia should join and 
should help us.</p>
      <p>We wish that our hard-boiled nationalists would reply and express their views

regarding this proposal.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
