<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-26">Nov. 26, 1918.</date><title level="a">South Chicago Grows More Active</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0498</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-26">Nov. 26, 1918.</date><title level="a">SOUTH CHICAGO GROWS MORE ACTIVE</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>On November 15, at a meeting of the representatives of the Third and Fourth
Liberty Loan campaigns, it was decided that the Lithuanians ought to unite
the Lithuanian Assistance Fund and the National Fund. For this purpose it
was decided to call mass meetings in all Lithuanian colonies.</p>
      <p>Therefore, a mass meeting was held at two o'clock last Sunday under the auspices 
of the two Funds.</p>
      <p>The meeting was a success. "The speakers were Stanley Kodis and John Dymsa. 
About twenty dollars was collected for Lithuania's cause. But that was not 
sufficient.</p>
      <p>Also, a committee was selected to go from house to house to collect donations
for the cause of winning Lithuania's independence. The following were elected
to the committee: Michael Garmus, Peter Simaitis, Simon Juskevicia,
<pb facs="4223970_4_0499.jpg" n="2"/>
John Benevicius, Joseph Trijonis, Peter Briedis, Alexander Sveila, Mrs. Mary
Poska and George Snekutis.</p>
      <p>The committee will be divided into sections, which will cover the whole city
better. The most responsible men and women are included on this committee.
They have our complete confidence. The donations collected by this committee
will be turned over to a treasurer who will publicize the donations in Lietuva.

The donors will see their donations announced publicly.</p>
      <p>The following donations were collected at the mass meeting:</p>
      <p>Two dollars each: Stanley Kodis and P. Simaitis.</p>
      <p>One dollar each: A. Maniokas, A. Sucila, F. Indeikis, V. Martinavicia, M. Miuzis,

V. Maniokas, B. Tuberas, L. Skrabutenas, J. Kvietkus, J. Dymsa and J. Trijonis.</p>
      <p>A total of $5.30 was collected in small donations. Ihe total collected was

$20.30.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
