<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914.</date><title level="a">Truly, it Is a Disgrace to America </title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0318</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0318.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914.</date><title level="a">TRULY, IT IS A DISGRACE TO AMERICA
</title><title level="a">
(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>At present, when proposals to curb the rights of immigrants are being discussed
everywhere; when various societies in America, even workers' organizations are
breaking their heads trying to figure out how to block the path of immigration
into the United States; when one bill after another against immigrants is being
introduced in Congress with the support of even the president's cabinet; when,
it can be said, a hunt has been inaugurated against the immigrants--it is with
joy that we hear at least one good voice raised in support of the immigrants.</p>
      <p>Former President William H. Taft is supporting the immigrants again at this
time. If we do not yet have an anti-immigration bill, passed by Congress,
it is thanks to ex-President Taft who, supporting the immigrants, vetoed that
bill several years ago.</p>
      <p>He now raises his voice again--on another matter--in support of the immigrants.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0319.jpg" n="2"/>
He wrote a long article for the English weekly, The Independent, in which he
turns the attention of the citizens and the government to the fact that,
because of the improper administration of the laws of this country, the
immigrants are being wronged in a barbaric manner.</p>
      <p>Ex-President Taft speaks about the murdering of immigrants and the fact that

such murderers are practically never suitably punished. This especially

happens more often in the Western and Southern States where prejudice against

immigrants is very strong.</p>
      <p>Lithuanians have also had an opportunity to become acquainted with such

manifestations. Only a few weeks ago our correspondents informed us that

the third consecutive killing of a Lithuanian by an American happened in

Dorrisville, Illinois. However, in all similar cases, not only were the

murderers left unpunished but the local government did not even bother to

hold them for trial. The so-called "coroner's jury" dismissed the cases.

Therefore, this voice of ex-President Taft is now especially interesting

and noteworthy to Lithuanians also.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
