<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918.</date><title level="a">Resolutions [Favoring Lithuanian Independence] Sent to Washington</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0540</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0540.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>III B 1</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918.</date><title level="a">RESOLUTIONS [FAVORING LITHUANIAN INDEPENDENCE] SENT TO WASHINGTON</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>On this page we are publishing examples of resolutions which were sent to
Washington, favoring and demanding independence for Lithuania.</p>
      <p>The following resolution, signed by Dr. A. Zimontas, was sent in the name
of the Lovers of the Fatherland Society:</p>
      <p>"At a meeting of the supreme Board of the Association of Lithuanian Patriots
of America, representing 140 lodges, the following resolution was adopted:</p>
      <p>"Whereas The United States has always been an upholder of liberty and true
democracy and a staunch defender of oppressed nationalities, and</p>
      <p>Whereas The United States entered this World War for the defense and preservation
of these very same principles, and
<pb facs="4223970_4_0541.jpg" n="2"/>
"Whereas, The Lithuanians have been and are now shedding their blood in
profusion on the battlefields of Europe for these same principles, with
many more ready to do the same in the armies of this country, and</p>
      <p>"Whereas, The Lithuanian people, being conscious of their right to political
and economic independence, will, in the future as in the past, strive unceasingly 
for their liberty and national integrity, and</p>
      <p>"Whereas, The boundaries between Germany and Russia cannot be settled properly
and permanently without liberating Lithuania from the German and Russian
yokes and establishing a free and independent Lithuania, and</p>
      <p>"Whereas, A diplomatic settlement of European problems without a just recognition 
of an independent Lithuania would leave a feeling of unrest in that
part of Europe, which would be a menace to the peace and an unredressed wrong,
and</p>
      <p>"Whereas, The President of the United States in his message of January 8,

<pb facs="4223970_4_0542.jpg" n="3"/>
1918 A. D. announcing the war aims of the United states did not refer

to the emancipation and independence of Lithuania; therefore, be it

"Resolved, That the Lithuanians have absolute and unshaken confidence in our

government and President Wilson who proclaimed the principle of justice to

all peoples and nationalities and their rights to live on equal terms of

liberty and safety with one another, whether they be strong or weak'; and

be it further</p>
      <p>"Resolved, That the above principle cannot be fully attained unless it is

anplied also to the Lithuanian nationality and results in granting complete

freedom and independence to Lithuania; and be it further</p>
      <p>"Resolved, That President Woodrow Wilson and the Congress of the United

States be respectfully requested to take such action as will lead to the

safeguarding of the rights and aspirations of the Lithuanian people and

<pb facs="4223970_4_0543.jpg" n="4"/>

recognition of a free and independent Lithuania; and be it further</p>
      <p>"Resolved, That these resolutions be published and presented to the proper

authorities of the United States as well as th diplomatic representatives

of other countries."</p>
      <p>The second resolution, sent in the name of the Illinois lodges of the

Lithuanian Alliance of America, reads as follows:</p>
      <p>"At a meeting of the delegates representing the Illinois lodges of the

Lithuanian Alliance of America, held January 22, 1918, at Milda's Hall,

Chicago, Illinois, the following resolution was unanimously adopted:

Whereas, The United States entered this war to defend the liberty and democracy
not only of its citizens but also of all subjected and oppressed

nationalities, as expressed in the messages of the President of the United

States, and</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0544.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>Whereas, The President of the United States, in his last message setting

forth the aims of war, named the nationalities whose lands have been covered

with the blood of the struggling armies; but Lithuania, which has suffered

indescribable agony, and over whose territory the armies of the opposing

combatants have passed time and again leaving it in total destruction, was,

for some unknown reason, omitted in said message, and</p>
      <p>"Whereas, We, as loyal Americans of Lithuanian extraction, whose fathers and

brothers still remain in Lithuania, daily hear the voices coming from over

the seas from seven million Lithuanian people demanding the independence of

Lithuania; therefore, be it</p>
      <p>"Resolved, That in behalf of the seven million people comprising the Lithuanian

nation, we ask the President of the United States and the United States

Congress to demand the liberty and independence of Lithuania, and that such

demand be made specifically with reference to Lithuania, as well as with

<pb facs="4223970_4_0545.jpg" n="6"/>
reference to the other nationalities already named in the message of the

President of the United States stating the aims of the war; and be it

further</p>
      <p>"Resolved, That the chairman of this assembly telegram a copy of this

resolution to the President of the United States, and mail a copy to each

member of the United States Congress."</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
