<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 38, <date when="1898-09-23">Sept. 23. 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Conduct of Our Priest</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0036</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>I B 1</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 38, <date when="1898-09-23">Sept. 23. 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONDUCT OF OUR PRIEST</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Last Sunday delegates from two church societies went to Rev. Krawozunas
to get his permission to hold a meeting in the church hall for investigation 
of our parish budget.</p>
      <p>The priest not only refused to give the hall, but he scolded the delegates,
telling than that as to the parish books only the priest has the right to
take care of them. When the parishioners persisted, the priest chased
them out from the rectory. Our rector's conduct towards the parishioners
is the same as the tsar's conduct towards Lithuanians. How long will we
bear such a despotism of our priest, who is only our hireling and not the
master and ruler? It is just the same hireling as you are in the factories.</p>
      <p>The misunderstanding was born of the parish budget. The misunderstanding
in our parish cannot disappear because our priest does not only want to do
<pb facs="4223970_4_0037.jpg" n="2"/>
away with misunderstandings but is instigating and upholding the trouble
purposely with his untactful and misunderstanding way.</p>
      <p>Last Sunday some of the devoted parishioners made a complaint that our

rector is making debts on the church, asking how to save the parish

from the infidels, how to clean up the debts, how to restore order on

the parish budget, and how to take away the budget from this untrustworthy 
treasurer, the priest; and to deliver the parish treasure to

those who do not believe in debts. This appeal was distributed among

the people when they were leaving church. There was also in the leaflet

a cartoon of Rev. Krawczunas. It looks to us that there is some mistake

in that picture because when our Rev. Krawczunas saw the bag with

$36,000 parish money, he lifted up his skirts and ran fast with the

parish debts. It seems to us that the priest can forget the debts much

sooner than the collected money, because there is more money collected

in the bag than the debts. It looks to us that a mistake was made.</p>
      <p>On Bartholomew Day our rector Krawczunas went to Waukegan, Illinois, to
<pb facs="4223970_4_0038.jpg" n="3"/>

perform the divine service and to preach the sermon. Because the Waukegan

Lithuanians have a society under the name of Saint Bartholomew, they were

having a celebration in memory of that saint, during which Rev. Krawczunas 
denounced, in his sermon. the newspaper Lietuva by saying: "Who

will read that newspaper shall commit a deadly sin, and at the confusion

shall get no absolution."

After the denunciation of our newspaper thirteen subscriptions came in.

The people say that if the priest denounces this newspaper, then there

must be some interestings articles in it that they would like to read.

For this we are thanking Rev. Krawczunas. We are asking his to advertise

our newspaper everywhere as he did in Waukegan, and the readers of Lietuva

will increase immensely. We believe that Rev. Kraczunas will give good

advertising for our paper in his newspaper, which he is planning to publish
 
in Chicago. It is a well known fact that our rector has a very good heart

and that he upholds Christian science.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
