<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-03-11">March 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Regal Lithuanian Club</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0220</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0220.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
          <item>II E 3</item>
          <item>I B 3 b</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-03-11">March 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">REGAL LITHUANIAN CLUB</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Lithuanian youth in Chicago organizd a new club which is known as
Regal Lithuanian club. This club has forty members at the present time.
The members of this club are mostly young follows from Chicago who became
very interested in having their own place for physical training.</p>
      <p>Last week this club held its first regular meeting at which the members
discussed the affairs of the club and its great value to Lithuanian
youth.</p>
      <p>At this meeting the members decided to organise their club on lines
similar to those of Bohemian sokols. They appointed Frank Morkus,
who has come from Riga, Latvia, as their instructor in gymnastics and
wrestling. Some of the members disagreed on the name of the club, for
it looked to them too aristocratic and inappropriate. Finally the members
<pb facs="4223970_4_0221.jpg" n="2"/>
agreed to change the name of the club, and the committee requested them
to submit a new name at the next meeting. Other nationalities have
similar clubs in Chicago, so why can't we have some athletic club for
our young people to spend their leisure hours? Moreover, there are two

great advantages in having some sort of athletic club for young people:

the first advantage is to develop them physically and mentally, the

second to keep them off the streets and stop them from associating with

a bad crowd. All young men like athletic sports which develop them

physically, and we cannot deny to them the privileges of participating

in various field of sports. We should encourage them more and help them

to organize various sports in order to keep their minds occupied. It is

a well known fact that no mother or father would like to see his or her

children running around the streets and associating with bad company.

The only way to protect the young people from frequenting bad company is

<pb facs="4223970_4_0222.jpg" n="3"/>

is to keep then busy during their leisure hours. Parents must take an

interest in their children and their various activities, whether sports

or social functions. Then you will arouse their interests and ambitions

and at the same time your children will admire you more and will become

more obedient to you. Young people always like to be noticed and commented

upon by their parents for their activities in all the fields of sports

and social circles. The parents should always give credit to their children

and praise than for their good work. Encourage them to play clean in

sports and to play a clean game in life. In order to please your children

you yourself must take interest in their various games. If all the parents

took more interest in their children and helped them in their various

activities, the children would be much better and the parents would be

proud of then in the future. The children cannot mold their own character

without the inspiration and the help of their parents. The child's environment 
molds his character, and that environment must be made by the parents.

In order to inspire children, parents must make for them first a good

environment at home, because a home is the proper place for molding

<pb facs="4223970_4_0223.jpg" n="4"/>

children's characters. All parents should encourage their young men to join

the new club and help to organize larger and more active clubs for Lithuanian 
young people, and the parents will receive their reward for their efforts in the nature.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
