<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-10">Dec. 10, 1918.</date><title level="a">News from the 18Th Street Colony</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0445</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0445.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
          <item>III E</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-10">Dec. 10, 1918.</date><title level="a">NEWS FROM THE 18TH STREET COLONY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Simanas Daukantas Young People's Theatrical Club held a meeting at the
Providence of God Parish Hall on December 7.</p>
      <p>Having finished with the regular business of the organization, the secretary 
read a letter which had been sent to the Club by the Lithuanian National 
Fund. The letter asked for donations for the cause of Lithuanian liberty.
After the letter was read, the members unanimously agreed to donate to the
cause. One member suggested that the Club donate fifty dollars, but others
thought that sum was too small, and insisted that the Club donate at least
one hundred dollars. A motion was made and carried that the Club donate one
hundred dollars. The vote was unanimous.</p>
      <p>Though the donation is small, in comparison to the donations of some other
<pb facs="4223970_4_0446.jpg" n="2"/>
societies, still it is large for this Club. The Club has no money because
it suffered a heavy financial loss last year when the bank in which it deposited 
its funds went bankrupt. Therefore, the members of the Club should
be honored for making this donation, and for their love of and devotion to
their native land. May this donation help to win freedom for Lithuania, and
may the rays of that freedom brighten our lives forever.</p>
      <p>While the officers of the Club were conversing after the meeting, the president, 
A. Brozis, who is a good patriot, said: "Men, we should feel ashamed
to put the wages we receive as officers of the Club into our pockets, when
Lithuania's pockets are emptier than ours. Therefore, wouldn't it be a good
idea to donate this year's salary to the Fatherland?"</p>
      <p>That is an exemplary suggestion which should be remembered at the next meeting

when the officers will be paid their annual salaries. I believe that Mr. Brozis

<pb facs="4223970_4_0447.jpg" n="3"/>

will keep his word like a true and  honorable patriot.</p>
      <p>It was decided that the one-hundred dollar donation should be sent to the

Executive Committee of the Lithuanian Councils in Washington, D. C.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
