<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, <date when="1937-06-13">June 13, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0142</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
          <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>II B 2 f</item>
          <item>II B 2 g</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, <date when="1937-06-13">June 13, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0142.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The major weakness of the L.D.S. - M.Y.S in its work was not the
fact that the M. Y. was lax in its work, but rather that its work
had been subjected to non-constructive criticism and that the Midwest
Youth Committee did not receive the cooperation of the entire L.D.S
membership. While the report of the Midwest Youth Comittee could
record excellent activity in the way of branch socials and sports,
it indicated laxity in dramatics and the failure to develop girls'
sports.</p>
      <p>Methods of popularizing the L. D. S. were emphasized and the merit
system, popularity contests and branch "sweaters" were cited as
splendid mediums for advertising the L. D. S. youth branches. To
better popularize the L. D. S. youth organizations in the Midwest
<pb facs="4223970_4_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
enlargement of the Vilnis English section it was suggested to increase
it to eight pages.</p>
      <p>Report of Sports Activity.</p>
      <p>A review of the branch and inter-branch sports was presented in the report
of Tex Zebraitis, M. Y. C. sports director.</p>
      <p>The chief obstacle in organizing a better sports movement in the

Midwest L. D. S. branches, the report showed, was lack of proper

sports leadership, the poor response on the part of many members to

participate in sports and the difficulty of getting each branch to

participate in inter-branch sports. As a means of remedying this

fault, it was suggested that L. D. S. branches get over their apathy

<pb facs="4223970_4_0144.jpg" n="4"/>

toward sports members and make possible for youths to come into the

L. D. S. as sports members. Eventually these sports members could

be signed as insurance members.</p>
      <p>While recognizing these shortcomings, the report also registered

several accomplishments.</p>
      <p>The outstanding sport success of the year was the carrying through

of the basketball league which was not only a financial and moral

success, but was effective in attracting many outside youth to the

L. D. S. Excellent response to swimming and hiking was reported, and

this phase of activity should be encouraged.</p>
      <p>To broaden the sports activities, the establishment of a sports center


<pb facs="4223970_4_0145.jpg" n="5"/>

was proposed. Such a sports center would enable members to get together

in their idle moments and participate in ping-pong, boxing and wrestling

and would attract numerous youths to the L. D. S.</p>
      <p>Branch Reports.</p>
      <p>Much interest was manifested by the delegates in the reports of the .

branches, primarily because those reports brought out clearly the

mistakes of the branches and valuable proposals for improving and

building the E. D. S. in the Midwest.</p>
      <p>The report of the delegate from the Sparks reflected that the reason 

the Sparks conducted short and orderly meetings was because the order

of business was worked out before the meeting, by the executive committee. 
This executive committee often meets three times a month to

<pb facs="4223970_4_0146.jpg" n="6"/>

straighten out problems which face the branch. This method of arranging

the branch meetings has resulted in improving the activity of the

branch and has allowed time for the development of new activity.</p>
      <p>In the field of new activity the Sparks are taking the first step, as

the organization of a dramatic group indicates. The branch has already

conducted a Mock Trial and has selected 14 plays from which will be

chosen a play to be presented by the branch at a later date.</p>
      <p>This dramatic group is opening up new opportunities for enlistment

of members and has improved the attendance at meetings.

In reporting on the progress of the drive, the Sparks' delegate cited

the signing of eleven new members and listed many prospects.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0147.jpg" n="7"/>
      <p>Redwings' Report.</p>
      <p>The Redwings' report given by Nancy Gordon listed a total of 12 new

members signed during the present drive. This is one of the most

active branches in Chicago and its many varied activities include

sports, socials, hikes and bowling. Two of the main weaknesses of

the branch are the lowered level of educational activities and the

failure of the girls to participate in sports due to lack of time.

To interest the girls in sports a bicycle club has been suggested.</p>
      <p>Monarchs' Report.</p>
      <p>The Marquette Park Monarchs, who at one time were the monarchs of

the Chicago L. D. S. branches, reported laxity of sports activity

and lack of interest of membership in sports. To iron out these

<pb facs="4223970_4_0148.jpg" n="8"/>

shortcomings the Monarchs are signing sports members to stimulate

interest in sports.</p>
      <p>

Report of Roseland L. D. S. activities by Wally Unaris, showed lack

of interest by the membership to undertake new projects, but despite

this the branch has enlarged its membership by five.</p>
      <p>

The Kenosha delegate stated that the leadership in Kenosha considered

the formation of a L. D. S. youth branch separate from the adult branch

branch too lightly. There are splendid possibilities in Kenosha, but

more seriousness is necessary on the part of L. D. S. youth leaders

to build a youth branch.</p>
      <p>
English Section Report. The editor of the Vilnis' English Section

pointed out that the V. E. S. is an excellent means through which the

L. D. S. can grow. He emphasized that in order to fulfill the function
<pb facs="4223970_4_0149.jpg" n="9"/>

of bringing more youths into our branches it must be utilized to the

fullest extent. Branch correspondents were encouraged to contribute

regularly and encourage other youth to write stories, poetry and

articles pertaining to young people. Besides this, the columns of

the V. E. S. can be used to excellent advantage to conduct discussion

of certain phases of L. D. S. activity.</p>
      <p>
Educational Report. Jessie Shaiko reported that educational projects

at meetings have been neglected because of lengthy business meetings.

This can readily be overcome as soon as the branches learn to conduct

shorter business meetings.</p>
      <p>

As a means of making the educational part of the meeting more interesting,

debates were suggested.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0150.jpg" n="10"/>
      <p>To better equip our membership with the knowledge of the L. D. S. and
to develop youth leaders an L. D. S. training school was suggested.
The L. D. S. school to hold classes in the evening to enable better 
attendance.</p>
      <p>
After these remarks had been concluded a new form of L. D. S - M. Y. C.
was suggested and discussed. The new committee, as was agreed on by the 
conference, will be composed of five regularly elected members 
and three alternates and three members from the executive committees
of each branch. It is expected that this work of the Midwest Youth 
Committee will provide better leaders in and guidance to the information
of committees which will facilitate the work of individual branches.</p>
      <p>
From this summary can be gathered many valuable suggestions for the 
improvement of our L. D. S. youth branches.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0151.jpg" n="11"/>
      <p>There have been many problems raised and many suggestions offered.
This growth of our L. D. S. in the Midwest depends upon the extent to
which we apply the proposals of this conference.</p>
      <p>
Wally Unaris.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
