<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913.</date></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0616</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0616.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913.</date></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Last Saturday the Chicago Lithuanian Societies Association have a farewell
banquet to Dr. J. Rasanavicius, representative of the Lithuanian Scientific
Society of Vilnius [Vilna], and to Mr. Ycas, representative in the
Russian Duma, who are leaving Chicago on their lecture tour through other
Lithuanian colonies. The banquet was held at the Sherman Hotel.</p>
      <p>Eighty people were present at the banquet. Among them were representatives
of Chicago Lithuanian newspapers, of various societies and businesses, etc.
Among the guests were Mr. Palandech, representing a Serbian newspaper, and
Mr. A. Bowers of the Young Men's Christian Association.</p>
      <p>Before the banquet began, the photographer, Mr. Stankunas, took a picture
of the guests. After the banquet had begun, various speeches were made.
Mr. J. J. Elias opened the banquet and introduced the Right Reverend
<pb facs="4223970_4_0617.jpg" n="3"/>
utmost to join in cultural activity, the Lithuanians of America with
their brothers in the fatherland. In the latter part of his speech, Mr.
Ycas highly praised the Chicago Lithuanian women and girls, who were the

first to collect $125, which they presented to Mr. Basanavicius at this

banquet. The people heartily applauded such a large donation from the

Chicago Lithuanian women.</p>
      <p>Besides Dr. Basanavicius and M. Ycas, there were many other speakers, but

it is impossible to enumerate every speech. The best speech was delivered

by the Reverend Seratinas of Roseland. His speech was impressive and

dignified; he stated what the obligations should be between the Lithuanian-Americans 
and their brothers in the fatherland. Other speakers were: Mr. A.

Olszewskis, publisher of Lietuva; Mr. J. Hertmanavicius, editor of Lietuva;

Mr. B. N. Balutis, manager of Katalikas; Mr. S. Tananevicius, Dr. [A. L.]

Graiciunas, and Dr. A. K. Rutkauskas.</p>
      <p>A grand impression was made when Mr. Palandech, in the name of the Chicago

<pb facs="4223970_4_0618.jpg" n="4"/>
Serbians, delivered a speech of welcome in the Serbian language...

He closed his speech in the English language, extending best wishes to Dr.

Basanavicius and M. Ycas. He wished them success in their cultural

activity, and he hoped that the Chicago Lithuanians would go forward on

the path of progress.</p>
      <p>Mr. Bowers' speech was blunt; he wanted to bite the Lithuanians because

they are too selfish, etc. Dr. A. Rutkauskas then spoke. His speech was

too enthusiastic; he went too far when he demanded that everyone present

raise their hands and swear that they would contribute a certain amount

of money to the Lithuanian Scientific Society of Vilnius [Vilna]. When

he asked the guests to raise their hands, half of them did so, and Dr.

Rutkauskas proceeded to denounce as scoundrels those who did not raise

their hands..... Such a speech by the honorable Dr. Rutkauskas had a very

bad effect on the guests.....</p>
      <p>The program of the evening was enriched by the wall-known artists, Mr. A. 

Pocius and Mrs. Janusauskiene.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0619.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>The farewell banquet lasted until 1: A. M.</p>
      <p>Last Wednesday morning, our honorable guests, accompanied by Chicago Lithuanians,

left Chicago for Grand Rapids, Michigan.</p>
      <p>[Translator's note: Dr. J. Basanavicius and M. Ycas, during their lecture

tour among the Lithuanian-Americans, collected sixteen thousand dollars for

the erection of the Lithuanian Science Building in Vilnius [Vilna]. When

they returned to Lithuania, they deposited the money in the Russian Land

Bank of Vilnius [Vilna]. At the beginning of the European war, in 1914, the

Russian government moved the bank and all the money to the interior of Russia.

Up to the present time, this matter is still disputed with the Russian government.]</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
