<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 13, <date when="1901-05-03">May 3, 1901.</date><title level="a">We Should Form Daumantas Branches</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0725</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 13, <date when="1901-05-03">May 3, 1901.</date><title level="a">WE SHOULD FORM DAUMANTAS BRANCHES</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>(Translator's note: The writer in his article does not state who Daumantas 
was. In the Russian Chronicles there is a story written about
Daumantas, that he was a duke of the branch of Lithuanians. In the
12th century, Daumantas defended the Merkine Castle, in the province
of Vilna, and he successfully defeated the Russians, as the Russian
story goes.</p>
      <p>One of the most important problems of the Lithuanian public is to help
the poor Lithuanian young students, because every nation must have its
own national leaders in various branches of science. The Daumantas
Society exists in Europe to help the poor Lithuanian students. The
majority of the Lithuanians in America do not know about this society,
nor do they know where to send the money donated for that cause. For
this reason donations are coming slowly for the help of the students in
their higher education.</p>
      <p>The American Lithuanians should organize a Daumantas branch to collect
<pb facs="4223970_4_0726.jpg" n="2"/>

the money, in order to help our students in Europe, where they are

seeking higher education.</p>
      <p>I don't want to believe that there are in America such Lithuanians as

would refuse to donate for the poor students who are striving to gain

education. I am promising to donate a few cents every month to the poor

students fund. I believe that many of our compatriots will support

this great cause and donate as much as they can for this noble work.

By the way, in America there is a clerical society, Motinele (The Little

Mother), the aim of which is to help the students. But unfortunately,

we cannot come to any agreement with the clergy as to the helping of

the students. The clergy do not take into the Motinele Society those

who can do their own thinking; they only accept blind fanatics, and they

support clerical students only. From such clerical students the nation

will have no benefit. The clergy want to support their students in order

to have more exponents of their own class, because the clergy hate and

despise the civil intelligentsia.</p>
      <p>Sabonis.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
