<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916.</date><title level="a">B. Vargsas Buried Yesterday</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0751</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916.</date><title level="a">B. VARGSAS BURIED YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>It was proved by the unusually large attendance of Chicago Lithuanians at
the funeral of Bruno Vargsas-Laucevicius yesterday that the Lithuanians have
lost, in the person of Mr. Laucevicius, one of their most active and honored
writers and dramatists. No less than six hundred people came to pay him
their last respects yesterday. A large crowd filled Wallace Street, and
waited for the sorrowful procession to begin. At 2 P.M., about thirty
automobiles, accompanied by the crowd on foot, began a procession to
Halsted and 33rd Streets, down 33rd Street to Morgan, down Morgan to 35th
Street, and from there to the Lithuanian National Cemetery.</p>
      <p>The unusually large participation in the procession, the sea of flowers
from various organizations and individuals, and, above all, the magic name
of Vargsas, who was well known to almost all Bridgeporters, attracted the
attention of a large crowd. Beginning at 33rd Street and ending at 55th
and Morgan, a large, swaying mass of people lined both sides of the streets.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0752.jpg" n="2"/>

I am not exaggerating when I say that this was the largest funeral the

Bridgeporters had ever seen.</p>
      <p>An unexpectedly large number of people arrived at the Cemetery for the

burial, some coming in automobiles, others by street car. Short addresses

were delivered at the grave by the following friends of the deceased:

K. P. Gugis, A. Petratis, B. Sidiskis, Stasys Strazdas, and P. Grigaitis,

editor of the Naujienos. About one hundred and fifty dollars was collected 

then and there for the widow and her two children.</p>
      <p>Yes, once we had Vargsas among us, once we worked together with him, and

now--we have him no more. There remain only his works, which will speak to

us for a long, long time. We, the living, must make it our duty to draw

from them new energy to continue the work which was being carried on by our

friend, Bruno Vargsas-Laucevicius, up to the last hour.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
