<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-07-27">July 27, 1917.</date><title level="a">Results of Reverend Zilinskas' Mass Meetings in Chicago</title> by Reverend J. Zilinskas
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0559</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-07-27">July 27, 1917.</date><title level="a">RESULTS OF REVEREND ZILINSKAS' MASS MEETINGS IN CHICAGO</title> by Reverend J. Zilinskas</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>In saying goodbye to Chicago, I thank all Chicago Lithuanians for their generosity 
and their gracious hospitality. At my mass meetings, I collected a total
of $130.25 in the Chicago district for Lithuanian war relief purposes. This
amount was raised in the following places: Cicero, $46.34; Roseland, $23.16;
Oglesby, $12.75; Spring Valley, $24; Racine, $24.</p>
      <p>The greatest and most important purpose of my visit was to acquaint Lithuanian-Americans 
with the political aspirations of Lithuania. I urge all Lithuanians
to assist in the movement to regain the political liberty of Lithuania at the
conclusion of the present war. If we ourselves do not work and organize, if
we do not interest ourselves in this cause, then liberty for our fatherland
will be meaningless.</p>
      <p>I also urge Lithuanian-Americans of the Chicago district to subscribe for shares
<pb facs="4223970_4_0560.jpg" n="2"/>
of the Bank of Lithuania. In this district sixty-eight Lithuanians have subscribed 
$7,100 for shares of the Bank; they have already made a cash payment
of $2,782, and will pay the balance in instalments. In addition, one Lithuanian
subscribed to some shares and paid two hundred rubles in cash. Subscriptions
for shares were received in the following amounts from the following localities
in the Chicago district: West Side (Chicago), $600; Cicero, $450; Bridgeport

(Chicago), $400; Town of Lake (Chicago), $1350; North Side (Chicago), $1,200;

West Pullman, $700; Spring Valley, Illinois, $1,000; Racine, Wisconsin, $150;

Sheboygan, Wisconsin, $750.</p>
      <p>I thank all Lithuanians who have joined in the support of this honorable institution. 
This help will be of great benefit to our fatherland and of great

service to the mined farms of Lithuania. It will save more than one Lithuanian

from the claws of the Jews and other non-Lithuanians. Those who have subscribed

to the shares will also benefit.</p>
      <p>We Lithuanians must have faith in the future of Lithuania and her institutions.


<pb facs="4223970_4_0561.jpg" n="3"/>

If we do not have faith in our own forces, in our own leaders, then why should

we seek liberty and independence? We cannot achieve these aims if we ourselves

do not work and strive to achieve them; no one else will do this work for us.

If we depend on foreigners to unite us, than even if we do receive some measure 

of liberty, we will still be ruled by foreigners who will keep us in financial 
and industrial slavery. It is the duty of every Lithuanian to be a

member of some organization that is striving to organize and rebuild Lithuania.</p>
      <p>The many Lithuanians of the Chicago district who have joined the Bank of

Lithuania are the pioneers of the Lithuanian independence movement: Many

others have promised to join in the near future. All those who desire to join 

the Bank can do so by applying to the Universal State Bank, 3252 South Halsted 

Street, Chicago, Illinois. The shares are fifty dollars each. Those who have

already subscribed to shares can pay the balance at this bank. When the payments 

are completed, the Bank of Lithuania will issue receipts or provisional

stock certificates. Those who desire further information on the Bank of Lithuania


<pb facs="4223970_4_0562.jpg" n="4"/>

are requested to write to Reverend John Zilinskas, 50 West Sixth Street, South

Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
      <p>(Translator's note: Reverend John Zilinskas came to America from Lithuania

to collect funds for Lithuanian war relief and to assist in promoting the 

Lithuanian movement for independence.)</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
