<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-03-21">March 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Ruta (Rue) Gay Girls</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0176</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-03-21">March 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">RUTA (RUE) GAY GIRLS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>p.2. Before I tell you about our first hike, which by the way was a real success, I
must acquaint you with our club.</p>
      <p>The Ruta Gay Girls Club was formed recently mainly with outdoor activities in mind,
but we hope to do many other things, too. For instance, we plan to stage a little
play in the near future; there will also be opportunities for musically inclined girls
to take part in musical programs; and, we are going to learn some new dances and
perfect the ones we already know. And many things more, to be sure. Though the March
wind howled, we met as planned shortly after nine, Sunday morning and after leaving
the Western Avenue Car headed for Beverly Hills. Aldona tried her hand or rather her
back, at carrying the knap-sack, which was filled almost to over flowing - and her
back held. She enjoyed carrying it so much that she refused to part with it until we
selected a camping place.</p>
      <p>Soon we had a fire going and all day we roasted and toasted weenies, apples, marshmallows,
yes and bananas! Albina seems to be our best apple roaster - she peels
them so beautifully.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0177.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>We spent most of our time playing "peggie." Here again Albina took the prize. She

hit home runs, one after another. But we were all fairly good at "peggie" at times.</p>
      <p>It was four o'clock before we finally made a real effort to go home. May and Freda

appointed themselves clean-up committee and we left our camping grounds in good

condition. Nolie carried the knap-sack which was fairly empty at this time on the

return trip. Taking her size into consideration, we gave Little Nelie no hard jobs -

but just wait till she grows up! We missed Anna, but we hope that she will be able

to come the next time.</p>
      <p>This, I think, is not the last news item about the Ruta Gay Girls Club.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
