<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Hold Benefit Affair for Relief of War Victims</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0575</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>I B 1</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">HOLD BENEFIT AFFAIR FOR RELIEF OF WAR VICTIMS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Englewood Lithuanian Committee, which is composed of representatives
of the Lithuanian organizations of Englewood and was formed for the
purpose of raising funds for the relief of war victims in Lithuania, sponsored
a benefit affair for the above mentioned purpose on February 7.</p>
      <p>The program had many features and consisted of speeches, recitations, songs,
and a theatrical presentation.</p>
      <p>The program was started with tne singing of "Lietuva Tevyne Musu" (Lithuania
Our Fatherland), the Lithuanian national anthem. The entire audience joined
in the singing of the anthem; Mr. R. Bigelis assisted with a violin, Miss
V. Bigelis played the piano.</p>
      <p>The main speaker on the program was Mr. J. A. Chmieliauskas, a member of the
editorial staff of the Lietuva, (Lithuania). He spoke about assisting war
victims and refugees in Lithuania and about the many different relief funds 
<pb facs="4223970_4_0576.jpg" n="2"/>
that have been created among Lithuanian-Americans. He denounced
the Lithuanian factions who, while agitating for their own funds,
attempt to hinder the success of tne funds of other factions.</p>
      <p>After the speech, a comedy entitled "Apsiriko" (Disappointed) was staged. The

following were members of the cast of players:</p>
      <p>"Siupinis" by Mr. V. Janulis; "Siupiniene,"  Mrs. Marozas; "Veronika,"

religious fanatic, Miss K. Siuris; "Bogumila," Miss M. Orentis; "Juozas,"

Mr. Krasauskas; "Levike," Miss B. Daminaitis; "Vargonininkas," Mr. St. Kriukas.</p>
      <p>Generally speaking, the performance was very good. Mr. V. Janulis was

especially good. He appears to possess the required talent for a great actor.

Miss Orentis, who played the role of a priest's housekeeper, also did her

part well.</p>
      <p>The best recitation was made by Miss J. Urbis, who recited "Ne Tas Yra Didis", 

(Not That Person Is Great), a poem by Vincus Kudirka.



<pb facs="4223970_4_0577.jpg" n="3"/>
Miss M. Radzevis entertained the audience with songs at the

conclusion of the program.</p>
      <p>In respect for our brothers and sisters who are suffering in

Lithuania on account of the war, dancing was not permitted at the affair.

Intoxicating drinks were not sold.</p>
      <p>About two hundred people attended. They all behaved very nicely. It is believed 
that there will be a large profit from the affair for the relief of

Lithuanian War Victims and refugees. A collection for that purpose was made

at the affair. The collection netted a total of $13.20.</p>
      <p>The Lithuanians in Englewood are very active in efforts to raise funds for

the relief of war victims in Lithuania. It is being; reported that the

Committee has already raised a total of $229.26 for that purpose. In addition

to that, the local St. Augustine the Bishop Society donated fifteen dollars

directly to the Lithuanian Relief and Autonomy Fund.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0578.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>Englewood Lithuanians do not intend to cease their activities

in behalf of the Lithuanian war victims. They will endeavor

to raise still more funds for the relief of Lithuanians who are

suffering from hunger, misery and cold in Lithuania.</p>
      <p>The Englewood Lodge (182nd) of the Lithuanian alliance of America will hold

an affair on February 28 for the benefit of Lithuanian war victims. The

program will consist of speeches, recitations, and a theatrical presentation.</p>
      <p>The Lithuanians in Englewood deserve much praise for their patriotic and

humanitarian deeds.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
