<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914.</date><title level="a">New Lithuanian Girls Club</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0214</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0214.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>I B 3 a</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914.</date><title level="a">NEW LITHUANIAN GIRLS CLUB</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>This new club me quite recently organized by the Bridgeport Lithuanian
girls. The purpose of this club is for getting acquainted with the young
man and holding courteous social gatherings at least once a month.</p>
      <p>Last Wednesday the girls had the first courtesy dance at the Mark White
Square Park Hall, 30th and Halsted. We believe that these courteous
social gatherings will lead further and the result will be marriages
among these young people. This club will be the place where Cupid will
concentrate his barrage of fire and there will be many casualties, no
deaths but severe wounds in many hearts. The attack by Cupid is imminent,
and we expect about ten young people on the casualty net. From the estimate
of the situation, we can easily see that ten young hearts will be pierced
by Cupid’s arrows and their single life will end either at the altar or
at a minister's home. We wish those young people the best luck in the
world. Some widows, grass widows, and the old bachelors became joyful when
<pb facs="4223970_4_0215.jpg" n="2"/>
they heard of this new girls' club. their emotions were around and they

are thinking of marriage now. Those who had not been married yet and those

who had been married are all planning to get married. It is interesting

to see the widowers thinking of getting married again. The girls' club,

we believe, gave than an inspiration to get married. But they cannot

marry any girl from the girls' club became those girls are too young for

them. Widowers and bachelors will have to look for partners of their own

age. Old bachelors and widowers will have to establish their own matrimonial 
bureau, because they are too old to mix with the young crowd.</p>
      <p>The girls’ club is very successful so far, and is getting more new members

at every meeting. We wish you much luck, girls!</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
