<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I. No. 1, <date when="1892-12-12">Dec. 12, 1892</date><title level="a">Remarks.</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0372</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
          <item>III A</item>
          <item>I M</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I. No. 1, <date when="1892-12-12">Dec. 12, 1892</date><title level="a">REMARKS.</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>November 30 we read in English paper "Chicago Daily News" a very important
news. That the Senatorial Committee of the United States introduced a bill to
stop European immigrants to America for the coming year; from March 1, 1893 to
March 1, 1894. The causes for stopping the immigration is cholera. Americans
are afraid that next year cholera will arise again in Europe, there is a fear
that immigrants will infect America with cholera. This introduced bill would
be very beneficial to the workers of this land. Americans despise those immigrants 
who cannot write nor read. Their opinion is such: unenlightened person, 
uneducated, is living like an animal. Man needs material and spiritual
nourishment. He who does not eat cannot live, if you will not nourish your
spirit by reading books and newspapers, which gives nourishment to your soul,
then such a man is not fair to himself, weakens and impoverishes his own soul,
and soul without spiritual work is lost. For this reason Americans build schools,
print books, publish large quantities of newspapers, which enlighten the man
and the enlightened man morally reared will not become criminal.</p>
      <p>The United States statistics show that the great majority of robbers, thieves
and all kinds of criminals are from the uneducated class of people.</p>
      <p>Therefore. for this reason the United States is thinking to issue a new

statute against such immigrants of Europe. The new statutes are as follows:</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0373.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>If a person between 12 to 55 years of age cannot write or read the native 

language, if married and head of a family, and not having $100.00 will not be

allowed to enter United States land, besides this, must have an affidavit from

the ambassador of the United States.</p>
      <p>Brothers Lithuanians! We have been speaking to you many times, we did ask

and beg you to take out citizen papers, which is of great value to you. Here is

what the government can do to those who have no citizen papers: it can send

them to such a place where there are very few inhabitants, or unhealthy climate,

or if you disobey to such government's attempt, you will be send back to the

old country like a prisoner.</p>
      <p>By seeing that the immigration statutes of the United States are changing

every year, brothers Lithuanians, we must take in consideration for ourselves

that by lack of knowledge of laws, we may get very easily into trouble. Now is

the time to bring over our relatives and friends. If you are thinking to remain

in America, take out citizen papers without any delay.</p>
      <p>We will help our countryman with courtesy and devotion. Come to our printing

shop "Lietuva," at 567 W. 18th St., and we will help you in whatever you need.

Do not think, countrymen, that we are doing wrong to you, we are doing this for

your sake and Lithuanianism.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
