<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918.</date><title level="a">"Let's Save Lithuania and Ourselves," Shout the Poles </title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0510</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0510.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 4</item>
          <item>III B 1</item>
          <item>I G</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
          <item>III B 2 (Polish)</item>
          <item>III H (Polish)</item>
          <item>I C (Polish)</item>
          <item>I G (Polish)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-05-24">May 24, 1918.</date><title level="a">"LET'S SAVE LITHUANIA AND OURSELVES," SHOUT THE POLES
</title><title level="a">
(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>From time to time we bring to the Lithuanian' attention what
the Poles are doing, what they desire, and what they would like to do when
the question of Lithuania is raised. The Lithuanians ought to know these
things in order to know their "brothers" better and to be better prepared
to defend themselves from Polish greed.</p>
      <p>The fact that the Poles' greed is growing greater and greater is attested
to by the voices in their press, which recently has been overstepping all
bounds of patience.</p>
      <p>Formerly our "brother Polacks" soaped the eyes of the Lithuanians [Translator's 
note: English equivalent to this would be "pulled the wool over the
<pb n="2"/>
<gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
<pb facs="4223970_4_0511.jpg" n="3"/>
to mix in foreign affairs, the fate of Lithuania rests in the hands of the
German Government, as far as Europe is concerned, and in the hands of the
Kaiser's agents, as far as America is concerned. Pro-German leaders (This
refers to the Lithuanian Nationalist leaders.--Editor.), both here and
abroad, have surrendered blindly to Berlin's influence. (Just listen to
this next sentence!--Lietuva Translator). The people of Lithuania, receiving 
no help from our side, are following these leaders, not realizing that

they are thus preparing a Prussian noose for themselves.</p>
      <p>It Seems That the Lithuanian General Convention Favored the Poles</p>
      <p>"Because of this indifference on our part, things came to pass so that, at

the Lithuanian Convention held in New York during March, the Lithuanian

leaders, who are led on a Prussian leash [And a man's tongue doesn't dry up

after such expressions!--Lietuva translator.] could not collect too much

saliva with which to spit on the Poles and Poland. Thanks only to the unusual 
efforts of the mentally balanced Lithuanians at the convention,

passages which dripped with poison against Poland were deleted from the

resolutions which were passed at the Convention and later presented (by a



<pb facs="4223970_4_0512.jpg" n="4"/>

special committee), to President Wilson in Washington. Deleted also was a

passage which announced that Lithuania did not want to have anything in

common with Poland and preferred Prussian rule to a union with Poland.

(Those poor little Polacks; they heard something ring, but don't know where

or what. So they feed their public with such rottenness and with halucinations. 
--Lietuva translator.)</p>
      <p>"Having arrived in Washington, however, the Lithuanian delegation falsified

the New York resolution. Though it could not add all the scandalous items

against Poland which were deleted by the New York convention, it did, nevertheless, 
add that 'Lithuania shivers at the very thought of the return of

the former personal union with Poland, to which it would prefer even Prussian
rule.'"</p>
      <p>(Editor's note: The falsifier in this case was not the Lithuanian delegation,

but the editor of the Dziennik Zwiazkowy. We want to nail this liar-falsifier to the 
"pillar of shame" right here and now, so we publish here, word

for word, the message delivered by the Lithuanian delegation to President 


<pb facs="4223970_4_0513.jpg" n="5"/>

Wilson, as it is attested to by an official United States Government bulletin, 
and than we shall print also, what that Pole made out of it.</p>
      <p>What the Lithuanian Delegation Said</p>
      <p>According to the Official Bulletin, May 7, 1918: [Translator's note: The

following quotation appears in English] "She has been abandoned by Russia,

with whom she would not, if she could, renew her former coercive connections. 
She revolts at the idea of resumption of the old personal union

with Poland and feels that obliteration would be preferable to Prussian

domination."</p>
      <p>How the Poles Translated This</p>
      <p>According to an editorial in the Dziennik Zwiazkowy, May 16, 1918:</p>
      <p>The Lithuanian translation of this Polish sentence is given above. When 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0514.jpg" n="6"/>

this same Polish newspaper later published the full, supposedly true, translation 
of the Lithuanian delegate's speech in Washington, this same newspaper interpreted 
the above-mentioned English sentence in this manner also:</p>
      <p>[Translator's note: Here is given the text of the translation as it appeared

in Polish:]</p>
      <p>The final falsified sentence means the following in Lithuanian: "She revolted

from the thought of union with Poland on former conditions and, in this instance, 
would prefer to remain under Prussian rule."</p>
      <p>From these quotations it should be clear with what kind of black-handed

Polish swindlers and falsifiers we must contend. Persons who falsify official

documents in order to fool their ignorant people, in order to pull the wool

over the eyes of the Polanized Lithuanians, ought not have places in editors'

chairs--a more suitable place for them would be a jail where they could split

rocks.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0515.jpg" n="7"/>
      <p>Here follows the continuation of the above-mentioned Polish article:)</p>
      <p>
Say Lithuanians Falsify</p>
      <p>
"To prove that the falsification was made," continues the Dziennik Zwiazkowy,

"and that the majority of the delegates at the Lithuanian convention were

scandalized by the brutal attack on Poland and ordered passages offensive

to Poland deleted from the resolutions, we have the reports of the convention 
sessions. One of them was published in the April issue of one of the

most serious publications in America, Current History Magazine published

by the New York Times. Then we also have the word for word text of the

convention resolutions which were presented to President Wilson and published 
by the United State's Government organ the Official Bulletin, of

May 7, 1918."</p>
      <p>
(Editor's note: This is another brazen lie.
</p>
      <p>
Neither Current History nor the Official Bulletin published all of the 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0516.jpg" n="8"/>

resolutions passed by the convention. The Lithuanian convention, as can be

seen in the official protocol, expressed itself thus in the resolution regarding 
attitudes toward neighboring nations:
</p>
      <p>
"This Convention, taking cognizance of frequent reports in the press regarding 
unsupported and, to the Lithuanians, undesirable attempts of the Poles

to unite Lithuania and Poland in one political body, or to obtain a path to

the Baltic Sea through Lithuania, protests against all of the above-mentioned

efforts of the Poles."</p>
      <p>

In other words, who are the falsifiers and who is engaging in political

fraud?)
</p>
      <p>
This misleading newspaper then nukes the following lament:
</p>
      <p>
"The very publication of these resolutions in an official organ of Washington

reveals how earnestly President Wilson regards the question of Lithuania. We

<pb n="9"/>

<gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
<pb facs="4223970_4_0517.jpg" n="10"/>

Lithuania, who are the salt of that country." (That's right! "Salt"--

which has made the soup too salty and will have to be diluted!--Lietuva

translator.) "We act as though we are relinquishing our rights in

Lithuania--rights blessed by tradition, by history, by culture, and by

the fact of ownership.
</p>
      <p>
"We remain silent. (And you had better continue to do so; it's healthier.

--Lietuva translator.) The Lithuanian minority (?) has a voice in Lithuania,

while the Poles, who are in the majority, have no voice or, if they have one,

it is entirely worthless. (It has a worth, but it is negative. Lietuva

translator.)</p>
      <p>

"Why shouldn't the greedy Prussian refuse us our rights to this land if we

ourselves, because of our stagnation, do not claim our rights? What will

happen if President Wilson, who is the champion of small nations, hears

the pleas and demands of the Lithuanians while we remain silent? Will he 

not grant our rights to the Lithuanians?"
</p>
      <p>
Here the newspaper gives the falsified translation of the message delivered

<pb facs="4223970_4_0518.jpg" n="11"/>

to President Wilson by the Lithuanian delegation. Then it continues thus:
</p>
      <p>
"Gewalt!"
</p>
      <p>
"All of those Lithuanian lies, contained in the appeal of the Lithuanians

of America to the President of the United States, plus their unfounded pretensions, 
upon which the President is to make a decision, have not met with

any opposition from our side.
</p>
      <p>
"We are sleeping a sweet sleep, as though we are unconcerned, as though these

were matters which concern not us but some Zulus and Hottentots. They threaten

our national future, block our path to the sea, right against us and seek to

seize the wages of our centuries of labor, and we remain silent, as though

nothing were happening.
</p>
      <p>
"Who should act for us Poles hero in America? Who should defend Polish rights

in Lithuania for us at Washington? Who should correct the falsifications and

<pb facs="4223970_4_0519.jpg" n="12"/>

enlighten the United States Government on the true state of affairs? Perhaps 
we must depend on the European Poles, who not only know nothing of

what is going on here, but can take no step forward because of the German

fist which lies heavily upon them.
</p>
      <p>
"The difficult duty of defending not only our Polish brothers in Lithuania,

but also Lithuania itself from the reach of the greedy Germans, rests upon

us, and only us. We alone can present the true state of affairs in Lithuania

to Washington. we alone can prevent the President, who is deceived by the

lies of Lithuanian radicals, from taking the step which would, by allowing

the Lithuanians self-rule in Lithuania, permit them to hang a German-Lithuanian yoke on two million Poles.
</p>
      <p>
"Because of this situation, much praise is due to the Unija Lubelska (Lublin

Union) Society, Chapter 578 of the Polish National Alliance, which has called

a Lithuanian-Polish mass meeting for May 28. Not only all the mixed Lithuanian-Polish 
societies and branches, but also the national societies are invited 
to this meeting. (Let the Poles stop trying to deceive people. No 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0520.jpg" n="13"/>

Lithuanian society, chapter or organization, plans to participate in a

Judas-like activity. --Editor. )
</p>
      <p>
"When our leaders remain silent, others must take the initiative and with

a strong voice awaken those who slumber. Let us save Lithuania and Polanism

in Lithuania: Perhaps this mass meeting will be the turning point in our

political activity and will induce those who should be doing so to get to

work. Lithuania, as well as Polanism in Lithuania, must be saved, and this

salvation lies in the hands of the Poles in America only."
</p>
      <p>
That is what the Polish daily writes.
</p>
      <p>
It is good that the Poles are inciting their people and even some misled

Lithuanians by calling this mass meeting. It is good that they are planning

to raise this question publicly. The Lithuanians will have an excellent

opportunity to reveal the Poles to the world, to reveal their politics,

their falsified documents and their stealing of Lithuanian donations to

<pb facs="4223970_4_0521.jpg" n="14"/>

war sufferers. Very good! The Poles have decided to start a political

dance, so "Haj Ze Kaska Du Tanca!" (Come and dance, little girl!) The

Lithuanians will reveal the dirty hem of your skirt to all the public!

</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
