<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 40, <date when="1898-09-07">Sept. 7, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to the Rytas (The Morning).</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0066</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0066.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I B 1</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 40, <date when="1898-09-07">Sept. 7, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THE RYTAS (THE MORNING).</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>In No. 39 of Rytas Mr. Parishioner is scolding Lietuva for telling that
at the parish fair in Chicago they sold liquor. Mr. Parishioner names
us as liars and says that according to the decision of bishops at the
Baltimore convention, to sell liquor at the parish fairs is prohibited.
Do they prohibit according to the bishop's request to sell the liquor
at the fairs in Waterbury. We do not know. but in Chicago, as we have
stated, the liquor at the parish fair was sold freely. At the fair in
Chicago they sold beer, and beer is a liquor, and most of the Lithuanians 
became drunk by drinking that beer.</p>
      <p>If the bishops at the Baltimore convention decided to forbid to sell beer
at the parish fairs, then the Chicago rector himself is breaking and
trampling the decision of the bishops, and according to the Rytas instruction 
to us, the Chicago rector is making new laws to suit him in
order to gain more benefit for himself by disregarding the bishops'
orders.</p>
      <p>That the rector is making better decisions for himself, we have many
<pb facs="4223970_4_0067.jpg" n="2"/>

facts. Let us take the last event. Last week died one Lithuanian, Nowagrodski. 
He was a member of the church society, the King David, and of

the nationalist society of Sons of Lithuania. At the funeral the

rector forbade the national society to go into the church to participate

at the funeral service, because the society members wore the national

colors. The priest said that if anyone should come wearing the national

colors to the church, he would chase them out from the church.</p>
      <p>We beg the Rytas to explain to us, do the bishops make order or decision

to prohibit wearing national colors? Did Rev. Krawczunas make such a

decision because he hates Lithuanians and the national colors? We have

seen many times the Irish wearing national colors at their funerals. We

never heard that anybody ever tried to forbid them to wear their national

colors at their funerals.</p>
      <p>Did the American bishops prohibit the wearing of the Lithuanian national

colors? This in a very important question, we are begging the Rytas to

explain. The rector brought nuns who do not know Lithuanian, to teach

Lithuanian children. He has forbidden Lithuanians to read books and

newspapers; he has wasted $40,000 of the parish money. Has this been
<pb facs="4223970_4_0068.jpg" n="3"/>
done according to the bishops' order and their decision?</p>
      <p>(T. N. - The weekly newspaper Rytas was a clerical paper, published

at that time in Waterbury, Conn.)</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
