<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. 52, No. 52, <date when="1900-12-28">Dec. 28, 1900.</date><title level="a">Lithuanian Misfortune</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0727</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0727.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. 52, No. 52, <date when="1900-12-28">Dec. 28, 1900.</date><title level="a">LITHUANIAN MISFORTUNE</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>We have seen in the Lithuanian papers that during the last year there
were extinguished in the Lithuanian field several bright lamps; that
in one year the Lithuanians have lost several well known leaders. First
we have heard about the death of Dr. Kudirka, later Dr. S. Matulaitis,
Judge A. Krawczunas, and Dr. A. Linge. They spread enlightenment among
the Lithuanians; explained the lack of understanding; that only through
education and knowledge the Lithuanians can free themselves from the
slavery of tsar and clergy. They urged that the Lithuanians should
achieve culture. Then even the Lithuanians' enemies would not despise
them. They told us that we, as the children of one mother nation, should
work together, love each other, and by doing that, we will accomplish
great deeds for our lost nationalism. They have told us to be honest
in our work, because with honesty we can go further.</p>
      <p>Let us see how many of us take into consideration the good advice of
our dead leaders. Among us there are many who call themselves followers


<pb facs="4223970_4_0728.jpg" n="2"/>
of Christ, but let us look at them. Do they act as the apostles of Christ?

(We say nothing bad against the good priests; but how many of the priests

are good is another question). As long as the Lithuanians live without

the priest, they live in peace; but no sooner the priest comes than the

fight starts among them; no sooner they build a church and invite the

priest than the spiritual leader turns the day into night. Then the

ignorant people sees nothing good in the priest, but greed, exploitation,

immorality and drunkenness. What, then, is the future of Lithuanians

who are following such spiritual leaders? Instead of giving the money

to the clergy, it would be better that even part of it be donated to

the martyrs who are exiled in Siberia, for the cause of Lithuanianism.

Instead of giving money to the priests, give it for a good cause.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
