<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-12-31">Dec. 31, 1909.</date><title level="a">Can We Be Proud of Lithuanian Emigration?</title> by J. Laukis
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0337</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>I D 2 c</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>III A</item>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I H</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I M</item>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>I C (Polish)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1909-12-31">Dec. 31, 1909.</date><title level="a">CAN WE BE PROUD OF LITHUANIAN EMIGRATION?</title> by J. Laukis</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Lithuanian immigrants in the United States' are now commemorating
the fortieth anniversary of Lithuanian mass emigration to America.
I will not say that this move is entirely a bad thing, especially
since the proceeds from these commemorative affairs, which are being held in all
principal Lithuanian-American colonies, go towards a fund for the publication of
instruction books for our schools; that is a very worthy cause. However, it is
very unbecoming to conduct such affairs for the purpose of boasting of our
emigration. It is unbecoming, because after we abandoned our homes in the Fatherland, 
where we could have continued to live in peace, we came to America and did
not find a better life. When we came to America, we found that the only way we
could make a living was by accepting the hardest and filthiest jobs, which are
fraught with all kinds of dangers to our health and lives. Of what value are
the larger earnings if the jobs sap the vitality from our bodies too early, rob
<pb facs="4223970_4_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
us of our health, embitter our lives, and send us to an untimely
grave?</p>
      <p>Mr. Joseph Gabrys (world-famous Lithuanian leader and patriot)

recently stated in the Lietuva (Lithuania) that it would not be
possible to definitely ascertain whether or not Lithuanian emigration 
to America has been beneficial until after a statistical

survey of the Lithuanians in America has been made. However, the miserable plight

of our people, and the harmful effects of emigration to America are so clearly

visible that no statistical survey is necessary in order to see them.</p>
      <p>First: Emigration to America is detrimental to us--the immigrants. The high wages,
of which we boast so much, do not last long; after a period of good times, years
of depression come, and we are forced to spend everything we earned during the
good times. We boast of American luxuries, but such products as Swift's artificially 
cured ham and the best American beer adversely affect our health; we
have no reason to boast about them. Second: The wealth which we possess, both
personal and real, such as the churches we built, do not belong to us. It could
<pb facs="4223970_4_0339.jpg" n="3"/>
have been acquired without coming to America, if we would have
exerted as much labor and energy in Lithuania as we do here in
America. Third: We have also failed to rise in the intellectual
field above our brothers in the Fatherland. Morally, we appear to

be lower than our people in Lithuania.</p>
      <p>Therefore, after taking everything into consideration, we find that

we did not gain anything by coming to America. Not only did we fail to gain anything 
here, but our emigration has harmed our Fatherland; our emigration has

decreased the number of workers, without which no country can rise culturally.

America boasts of her industrial greatness, but that greatness is entirely due to

the large and incessant flow of emigrants from foreign lands. The social and

economic status of Americans in the Southern states, where practically no immigrants 
settle, is just as miserable as that of our people in Lithuania.</p>
      <p>Our Fatherland does not enjoy any immigration. On the contrary, our countrymen

in Lithuania are abandoning everything, and fleeing to foreign lands; some are

<pb facs="4223970_4_0340.jpg" n="4"/>
forced to go, but the greater majority leave on their own accord.

The result is, as should be expected, an intensification of the

miserable conditions which exist in our Fatherland. The social,

economic, and cultural uplift of any country depends upon the

inhabitants. A country which has a shortage of inhabitants cannot

expect to enjoy any appreciable degree of prosperity. Our countrymen 
evidently, are not aware of this important fact. As a result,

they are trying to find a more abundant life by fleeing to the wastes of Siberia,

or to some other land. The greater majority are coming to America, where they

expect to find mountains of gold. They are showing no concern over the fact that

when they leave their Fatherland they increase the hardships of their countrymen

which they leave behind. And, as if to laugh at our brothers who remain in the

Fatherland, we are celebrating an anniversary of our emigration with the apparent

conviction that it is something of which we ought to be proud. That is our great

sin, although we my not realize it.</p>
      <p>However, not all Lithuanians are blind to the folly of celebrating our emigration

anniversary; there are souls who see it very clearly, and consequently look upon

<pb facs="4223970_4_0341.jpg" n="5"/>

it with discouragement. The other day I happened to hear the

reading of a letter from a prisoner, who is serving a four year

sentence in Russia for his activities in behalf of the Fatherland

(Lithuania). The letter, which consists of eight pages in minute

handwriting, was sent to a friend in America. It is filled with

convincing arguments about the dire consequences of Lithuanian

emigration. "Go, speak, and open the eyes of Lithuanian newspapermen 
to this evil; let them explain to the people how detrimental emigration

is to our Fatherland," pleads a distressing voice from behind the walls of a

Russian prison to us Lithuanian-Americans, who are quietly suffering in the land

of liberty.</p>
      <p>Perhaps we will wake up some day and recognize the evil consequences of emigration 
from our Fatherland. But while we sleep, others are preparing to take

advantage of our indifferent attitude in regard to this matter. The large Polish

landowners in Lithuania are no longer able to reap a profit from their lands because 
of the growing shortage of cheap labor. As a result, they are being forced

to abandon their land. But they have decided to take advantage of this bad
<pb facs="4223970_4_0342.jpg" n="6"/>

situation by performing a patriotic deed for their nationality.

They are dividing their large land holdings into small parcels,

and are inviting Poles to emigrate to Lithuania and purchase

these parcels of land at bargain prices. Since the land is very

fertile, it affords an excellent opportunity for a comfortable

livelihood.</p>
      <p>It is not strange that foreigners are able to find opportunities for making a

comfortable living in the very same land from which we are fleeing for fear of

a famine? Therefore, we cannot blame conditions in our Fatherland if we were

unable to make a living there. Instead, we should blame ourselves for not knowing 
how to live. There cannot be any doubt that foreigners will live and become 
prosperous on the land which we have abandoned, unless we hurry and reclaim

it. The foreigners will work hard, develop trading possibilities, raise their

standards of culture, and all that will be left for us to do will be to envy them.

The marvelous deeds which the foreigners will perform in our Fatherland will not

serve to warm our hearts. The cultural and commercial progress they make will be

foreign to our people; and, eventually, they will turn our native land into a
<pb facs="4223970_4_0343.jpg" n="7"/>

foreign land; we will become foreigners in our own Fatherland.

The full significance of all this is known to everyone who has

gone to a foreign country to look for bread. It is possible to

find wealth and happiness in a foreign country, but neither

wealth nor happiness in a foreign country can obliterate the

fond memories of our native land, the ties of consanguinity, and

the congenial social atmosphere--these precious memories will

remain with us as long as we live. That is the direction in which we are headed

--the loss of our Fatherland to foreigners.</p>
      <p>Mr. Dumbre, a popular Lithuanian writer and patriot, recently wrote an article

on the above subject. The article is entitled "Under the Pretext of Brotherly

Love," and appeared in the Viltis (Hope), which is being published in the city

of Vilna (Lithuania). In his article,  Dumbre severely censures the Polish

land barons in Lithuania for their plan to invite Polish immigrants to take over

our land; he appears to be very angry at this ungrateful action of the Polish

barons. He probably has a right to expect gratitude from the Polish landowners

in Lithuania, but what right have we to get angry when others try to make use
 
 
<pb facs="4223970_4_0344.jpg" n="8"/>
of something which we have voluntarily discarded? It is foolish

to do so.</p>
      <p>No, we must not get angry, but go into action. We must do something 
to prevent all this work from going to naught. We must

put forth every effort to revive our nationality. But what can

we do? The answer is very short: Let us return to our Fatherland 
and live there. I am not saying that we should return without money, and

thereby increase the number of the poor in our Fatherland. We should return

with money, purchase the land that is for sale, establish modern farms, and

take commerce and industry into our own hands. There is plenty of land, and

there is no shortage of necessary commodities in the Fatherland; all that is

needed is people with sufficient means to get established. But the greatest

obstacle is a lack of money with which to become established. How can we obtain

money for this purpose?</p>
      <p>Ways and means for raising the necessary funds can be found if we care to do so.

We, undoubtedly, still possess a loyal feeling towards our Fatherland. We always

<pb facs="4223970_4_0345.jpg" n="9"/>

support every good cause for the benefit of our nationality.

If we have made many sacrifices in the past, then how can we

fail to assist in assuring the very life and existence of our

Fatherland in the future? In the long run, that would not be

a sacrifice, but a deed for our own benefit. Those of us who

are here know very well that life in America is not as sweet

as it is being pictured. Those who will return to the Fatherland 
will only escape all kinds of dangers to their lives and health, many

hardships due to unemployment and strikes, the feeling of insecurity, and the

ghastly fear of the future.</p>
      <p>Therefore, while employment lasts, all those who are sympathetic to this movement 
can group themselves together, and contribute a certain amount of money

every month to a common fund for the purpose of buying land in the Fatherland.

The plan should be operated in a manner that will be satisfactory to all members

of the group; no one should be deceived, nor overburdened. The contributors to

the fund will be made up of two groups: The first group will consist of those

who will take over and live on the purchased land; the second group will aid

<pb facs="4223970_4_0346.jpg" n="10"/>

the first group. Therefore, not all members of the group can

expect a large financial return for their money, but they will

have the satisfaction of having aided a worthy cause, which is

worth more than money. It is not necessary for all members to

invest an equal sum of money, but only as much as they are able.

Investors in this project cannot expect large dividends, but

their money will be safe; and they will have the satisfaction of

knowing that their money will be aiding the Fatherland.</p>
      <p>If the above plan is employed, in would not be difficult to raise the necessary

funds for this important cause; all that is needed is the will to do so.</p>
      <p>I have explained these matters in detail to the Lithuanian public, because I
 
hold them to be of great importance. however, if there are people who disagree

with my views, than I would be very glad to hear from them.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
