<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Record Book of Loru of the Lithuanian Youth Society and its Lithuanian Day.</title><date when="1937-02">Feb. 1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian Youth Society, Chicago, Ill.
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0154</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
          <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Record Book of Loru of the Lithuanian Youth Society and its
Lithuanian Day.</title><date when="1937-02">Feb. 1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Lithuanian
Youth Society, Chicago, Ill.</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Fun and color characterized the Lithuanian Day festival sponsored by the Lithuanian
Society on the evening of Saturday, January 9, at LaFollette Park, Hirsch and
Laramie Streets.</p>
      <p>National dances, ballroom dancing, barn dances, a two-hour swim and a supper of
Lithuanian nutriments comprised the entertainments of the colorful evening - a wide
range of activities that afforded those who attended plenty of lively enjoyment.</p>
      <p>Among the guests were members of the Chicago Outings and Hiker Club, who, with their
leader, John Sheridan, came for a few hours of relaxation among the Lithuanian youth.
Ernest Story, barn dance instructor for the Chicago Park District, also came to give
a helping hand in adding fun to the evening. Great enthusiasm was shown by all
participants, who eagerly tried to learn the barn dances. The two-hour swim in the
"pool" of sky blue waters' was very refreshing. After the swim it was just the
proper procedure for the merry-makers to satisfy their ravenous hunger with a good and
wholesome Lithuanian luncheon.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0155.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>Now a few words about the society: The organization has been most active in the

preservation of the national dances of Lithuania. Its costumed national dance group

is widely known through its many appearances. With a group of seventy-six dances, it

participated in the first Chicagoland Folk Dance Festival at Soldier's Field on Labor

Day. Besides its numerous local performances, the group left the city almost every week

during the fall and early winter for appearances in widely scattered cities throughout

the adjoining states, Indiana, Wisconsin and Michigan.</p>
      <p>The Society has for its purposes, the fostering of an interest in the culture of the

native country among the descendants of Lithuania in America and the dissemination of

information concerning the little-known Lithuanians among the descendants of other

nationalities. In keeping with those purposes, the group has been active in the

exhibiting of Lithuanian art, in providing Lithuanian-American youth with an outlet for

literary expression through its publication, the Farrow, and in conducting an English

page in the Lithuanian Daily News, Naujienos.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0156.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>The officers of the organization are: V. Beliajus, president; A. Azukas, vice-president; 
Birute Kromialis, secretary; N. Munarin, treasurer; J. Munarin, 
sergeant-at-arms; Helen Dambas-Yushka, officer pro-tem.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
