<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1908-07-31">July 31, 1908.</date><title level="a">Mikas Petrauskas Leaves Chicago for Lithuania</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0773</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II B 1 a</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1908-07-31">July 31, 1908.</date><title level="a">MIKAS PETRAUSKAS LEAVES CHICAGO FOR LITHUANIA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>On Thursday, July 23, the Lithuanians of Chicago said adieu to Mikas Petrauskas
famous Lithuanian singer and composer, who has left Chicago for Lithuania. A
large number of friends, former pupils, and admirers were at the railroad station
to bid him farewell.</p>
      <p>Mr. Petrauskas will be missed a great deal by the Lithuanians of Chicago, especially
by the non-Catholic element. His greatest achievement here has been the organization 
and development of the Birute Singing and Dramatic Society, which will
always remain as a monument to his memory. Under his able and energetic direction,
the Lithuanians of Chicago were entertained with a long string of musical programs
and theatrical presentations. During his stay in Chicago, he instructed and
trained many young Lithuanian men and women in the art of music. He has successfully 
laid the foundations for a permanent practice of the art of music, and its
culture among the Lithuanians of Chicago. The work which he has started is certain 
to grow and flourish.</p>
      <p>Mr. Petrauskas was responsible for the first participation of Chicago-Lithuanians
<pb facs="4223970_4_0774.jpg" n="2"/>
in an inter-racial program. That historical event took place in Ogden Park
on June 20, when the Birute Singing and Dramatic Society, under the direction
of Mr. Petrauskas, successfully performed before a crowd of ten thousand people,

which consisted of Americans of all nationalities. The affair was sponsored

by the Chicago Playground Society. Besides Lithuanians, representative artists

of the Czechs, Jews, Norwegians, Dutch. Irish, and Swedes, also participated

in the program.</p>
      <p>We are very sorry to see Mr. Petrauskas leave. It will be unpleasant for quite

some time to carry on our musical and theatrical activities without his presence.

We wish him all the success in the world in his activities among our sisters and

brothers in far-off Lithuania. We hope that in the near future he will return

to Chicago.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
