<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-10-10">Oct. 10, 1930.</date></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0271</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.F"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III F</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-10-10">Oct. 10, 1930.</date></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0271.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>historian, who wrote the first book published on the history of Lithuania.</p>
      <p>The year 1938 will mark the 250th anniversary of the first Lithuanian
colony in America. Chicago Lithuanians should soon start preparing
for an appropriate celebration of the anniversary of that important
event.</p>
      <p>The first Lithuanian colony in America did not stay on Guadeloupe
Island. The Lithuanians were dispersed by repeated attempts of
the British to wrest control of the island from the French. The Lithuanian
colony then moved to New Amsterdam, later renamed New York, which was, at that
time, only a small town.</p>
      <p>There is some evidence indicating that Lithuanians emigrated to the new world
long before 1688. However, the writer does not have enough information on
<pb facs="4223970_4_0272.jpg" n="3"/>
hand to dwell on the matter. Ever since America was discovered by
Christopher Columbus in 1492, Europeans have crowded into it. The
Spaniards were the first to form permanent settlements in the new
world. The first permanent English colony was at Jamestown, Virginia, 
in 1607. The pilgrims of the Mayflower came in 1620. The

Lithuanian pilgrims arrived in America in 1688.</p>
      <p>Therefore, Lithuanians were among the early settlers of the new

world. They contributed their bit in developing and making the

United States the most Democratic and the most prosperous country

in the world. Besides Tad Koscinsko, the great Lithuanian hero of the American

Revolution, many Lithuanians from New York fought side by side with the brave

soldiers of George Washington in the struggle for liberty against the tyrannical 
rule of the British King. Since the Lithuanians are one of the most liberty

loving people in the world, there can be no doubt that the Lithuanian soldiers

of George Washington's army distinguished themselves in battle against the

<pb facs="4223970_4_0273.jpg" n="4"/>

British Redcoats.</p>
      <p>Lithuanian emigration to America has continued uninterrupted. Famine 
years in Lithuania, persecution by the Polish tyrannic landlords, 
and slavery under the feudalistic Polish rule, helped to

accelerate Lithuanian emigration to America.</p>
      <p>When serfdom held sway and Polish feudal landlords overran Lithuania 
and held the peasants in cruel slavery, many Lithuanians

were forced to leave their native land and seek justice and freedom 
in the new world. Many robust and able-bodied young Lithuanian men left

their homeland to escape Polish feudal landlords and emigrated to the United

States.</p>
      <p>There are now over one million Lithuanian-Americans living in the United

States. The largest Lithuanian colony is in Chicago, Illinois, where there 

are about 150,000 Americans of Lithuanian descent.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0274.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>Although colonial United States was populated chiefly by the British, 
today no single nationality constitutes a majority. The

population is now a conglomeration of all the nationalities under

the sun. All American citizens, irrespective of national origin,

are guaranteed equal rights and opportunities by the Constitution.

Despite a flood of un-American propaganda from the British who

seek to give the United States an "English character," a new and

distinct nationality is slowly but surely being formed by means

of the great American melting pot--the new American nationality.</p>
      <p>A large group of Lithuanian-Americans assembled at Shenandoah, Pa., in 1888,

to celebrate the 200th anniversary of the founding of the first Lithuanian

colony in America. Now that the 242nd anniversary of that important and most

interesting event has arrived, it should be an occasion for celebration by

all Lithuanians in all Lithuanian-American colonies.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
