<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-03">Dec. 3, 1918.</date><title level="a">They Reap but Do Not Sow or Plow</title> by A. M.
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0467</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0467.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>II D 1</item>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-03">Dec. 3, 1918.</date><title level="a">THEY REAP BUT DO NOT SOW OR PLOW</title> by A. M.</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Lodge 36 or the Lithuanian Alliance of America held a meeting last Sunday
at the Milda Hall in Bridgeport. It was the last meeting of the year, at
which officers for the coming year are usually elected. Such meetings are
usually noisy and this meeting was no exception.</p>
      <p>This Lodge has about three hundred members, but less than fifty attended the
meeting. Those who came were our Leftists, the socialist members of this
Lodge. They do not make up a tenth of the membership, but they always attend
in a group, and often create much confusion. They always interrupt and try
to ruin discussions on nationalist matters. They followed their usual
tactics at this meeting.</p>
      <p>A letter from the executive committee was read, urging all lodges to contribute
<pb facs="4223970_4_0468.jpg" n="2"/>
to the cause of Lithuanian independence. After this appeal was read,
Attorney F. P. Bradchulis moved that three hundred dollars be donated
from the treasury of the Lodge to the cause. The Lodge had about five
hundred dollars in its treasury.</p>
      <p>Here our "Red Guard" awoke. They were against making any donation. How,
they asked, can one donate to a cause which wants to impose a king upon the

Lithuanian people?</p>
      <p>Finally the captain at the "Red Guard," K. Jurgelionis arose and offered a

compromise--that the aforesaid sum be divided, one half for the Lithuanian

Independence Fund, the other half for the Socialist fund, which they call,

most ironically, the Lithuanian Liberty Fund.</p>
      <p>There were long and heated arguments. It was pointed out that the Socialist

fund did not even have a charter, that it does not concern itself at all

with Lithuanian independence, and that it visualizes a Lithuania which will

be free only when it is dominated by a socialist order.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0469.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>It was pointed out further, that the money was not paid into the

treasury by the Socialists because there aren't even thirty of them

in the Society, out of a membership of about three hundred.</p>
      <p>But that did not matter! However, because there were twenty-seven Socialists

and only twenty-two non-Socialists at this meeting, the vote went their way.

That is, a half, one hundred and fifty dollars must go to the Socialist fund 

which has not contributed as much for the liberty of Lithuania as a strained 

egg is worth. In truth, it [this fund] is not concerned with the liberty

of Lithuania. It is concerned only with the "class struggle" and revolutions.</p>
      <p>The result was, in the words of the proverb, "They reap, but neither sow

nor plow." The "Red Guard" walked off with one hundred and fifty dollars of

the people's money.</p>
      <p>There is a valuable lesson in this. The people must be careful and must

attend meetings, because "when the cat is away, the mice run the household

[according] to their [own] liking".</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0470.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>The election of officers for the coming year was also held. The

officers elected were the same, with the exception of the president

and vice-president. J. Juknis was elected president and A. Micevicius, vice-president. The "Red Guard" members wanted to elect their own treasurer.

However, since it is necessary for the treasurer to put up a bond and our

"proletarians" are not able to do so, the old treasurer, attorney F. P.

Bradchulis, was re-elected.</p>
      <p>The Lodge also formed a committee to collect donations for the cause of

Lithuanian independence. The following were included on the committee:

Alexander Micevicius, S. Valancauskas, S. Stankauskas, and M. J. Damijonaitis.</p>
      <p>Thirty dollars was collected from among the members at this meeting. These

donations were turned over to the office of Lietuva for publication in the

"Christmas Tree" section. (The thirty dollars has been received--Editor.)</p>
      <p>The Lodge also decided to change its meeting place after the New Year. Up

until now meetings were held in the Milda Hall. In the future they will be

<pb facs="4223970_4_0471.jpg" n="5"/>
held in the new headquarters of the Birute Society at 3249 South

Morgan Street.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
