<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-08-03">Aug. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian-American Soldiers to Demand Freedom for Lithuania</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0557</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.D"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0557.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III D</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-08-03">Aug. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN-AMERICAN SOLDIERS TO DEMAND FREEDOM FOR LITHUANIA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Lithuanians in Roseland and South Chicago who are being drafted into the United
States Army have decided to take a step that will probably have a very favorable 
effect upon the future of Lithuania. The soldiers have made the following
decision: All those who are about to be drafted. will hold a meeting where they
will formulate a resolution which will be signed by all the men and then sent
to President Wilson in Washington.</p>
      <p>The proposed resolution will be drawn up along the following lines: Whereas
Lithuanians who reside in this country will become a part of the United States
Army and will probably spill their blood in defense of this country, those
Lithuanians who are already in the Army, or who will subsequently become members
of the Army, hope and pray that the United States and her President will not
forget to intercede for the freedom of Lithuania when the peace congress will
convene after the war.</p>
      <p>In our opinion this step taken by the Roseland Lithuanians is unusually important
<pb facs="4223970_4_0558.jpg" n="2"/>
and deserves to be emulated by all Lithuanians who enlist or who are drafted
into the army. Such a step will be of still greater importance if a proposed

law requiring everyone to take out first papers is enacted.</p>
      <p>Such a memorial [the resolution], when presented to President Wilson, would be 

one of the greatest victories in the struggle for the independence of Lithuania.

There are reports that Lithuanians in other sections of Chicago are planning to 

emulate the Roseland Lithuanian.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
