<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-05-06">May 6, 1914.</date><title level="a">New Lithuanian Attorney</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0757</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>II A 1</item>
          <item>I E</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-05-06">May 6, 1914.</date><title level="a">NEW LITHUANIAN ATTORNEY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>On the first day of this month Kazys Gugis was admitted to the federal court
to practice law. The Chicago Lithuanian ought to be proud to have one more
Lithuanian as attorney-at-law. We feel that all Lithuanians, not only from
Chicago but from all over the United States, will congratulate our young attorney 
and wish him the best of luck in his new profession. In addition, attorney
K. Gugis is very popular among the various Lithuanian organizations, and he is
known as the most active individual in Chicago. He became well known among
Lithuanian people while a student in the law school. He is a ceaseless worker
and an organizer among our people in Chicago. For many years, as a member of
the Socialist Party he supported the Socialist movement among Lithuanian
people and helped to organize them.</p>
      <p>He has been a very active member of the Socialist League in this country
<pb facs="4223970_4_0758.jpg" n="2"/>
for a good many years. As a member of the Lithuanian Alliance of America,
the Lovers of Fatherland Society, and the Students Aid Society Aurora,
he worked very hard to make them larger and stronger.</p>
      <p>Recently he took an active part in the Chicago Lithuanian Society League,
which consists of thirty different societies, and finally he became the

president of this league. Moreover, he is a founder of Naujienos' corporation 
and has been elected president thereof. Attorney K. Gugis,

with other Socialist leaders, realized the necessity of having Socialist

newspapers in Chicago, which is the city with the largest Lithuanian

colony in America. He recruited people for the Naujienos in his personal

conversations, at various meetings, and by making personal contacts. He

even went canvassing from house to house asking the people to subscribe

to the Naujienos and to support the organization. He worked very hard

until he accomplished his purpose. Of all Lithuanian public workers in

Chicago, it is Attorney K. Gugis, who has helped most to establish the

<pb facs="4223970_4_0759.jpg" n="3"/>
Naujienos' corporation.</p>
      <p>It is a remarkable thing that all this work was none by Attorney K. Gugis

while he was a student in the law school. At the same time he was working

his way through school.</p>
      <p>This young attorney deserves all the credit that is given to him for taking

active part among Lithuanian people in various Lithuanian organizations and

attending the school of law at the same time. He showed unusual ambition

for education and a strong desire for participating in various social circles.</p>
      <p>It is not enough that he took an active part in various Lithuanian organizations, 
but he attended the Armour Institute of Technology, where he received a B.S. 
degree in mechanical engineering and then took up the study

of law, graduating from Kent Law School this year and receiving his

<pb facs="4223970_4_0760.jpg" n="4"/>
degree. He set a very good example for the future Lithuanian students. 
He showed that if a man wants to accomplish something worthwhile

in his life, he can do it with ease and become a professional in any field

of education.</p>
      <p>The working people should be proud to have such a man, bright and energetic,

who comes from the working class and who is their leader and is fighting

for their interests. When he came here from Lithuania he was very young

and worked hard in the mines and steel mills, just like any other worker. He

labored with others shoulder to shoulder and he did not feel that he was

better than they. His attitude toward the working men has not changed. He

still remains in their ranks as their leader. He has not forgotten his

brother workers, even though he graduated from two colleges and has two degrees. 
Although a professional, he still feels that he is one of the people,

struggling for existence.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0761.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>Some people who attain degrees in higher education forget their brother

workers, but attorney K. Gugis will never leave the ranks of the workers,

and will never forget them, because he is one of them and will remain as

a true member and their loyal leader. Friend K. Gugis, who is a brilliant

speaker and an able man, will open his office and will start to practice

law soon. We believe that he won't forget us when he starts to work in

his new profession. He will support the ideas for which he fought while

he was a student in college. We hope that he will remain an active member

in our organization, a leader of the Socialist party among our people.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
