<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-07-17">July 17, 1914.</date><title level="a">About the National Buildings</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0593</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0593.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 4</item>
          <item>II B 1 d</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-07-17">July 17, 1914.</date><title level="a">ABOUT THE NATIONAL BUILDINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">
(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>How to obtain sooner its own independent national buildings was discussed
at this year's convention of the Lithuanian Educational Society (in Lithuania).
The Society now has 49,916 rubles, besides a large piece of land, for this
purpose. Readers will recall that when the messengers returned from America
it was planned to buy the buildings near the Zalioji Bridge. Now it becomes
evident that nothing has come of that bargaining. A special committee--five
persons from the Educational Society and five from the Lithuanian Art Society
--has been appointed to take care of this matter in the future. These ten
persons will also compose a permanent committee in charge of the construction
of the buildings. This committee is also entrusted with the task of founding
the National Fund, with the cooperation of the Americans. The purpose of this
fund is to aid, among other things, the Educational and Art societies.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0594.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The appointment of a special committee to concern itself with the construction 
of the buildings is a practical step forward--especially if more energetic 
people will be included in the committee.</p>
      <p>It would be very regrettable if this vital project finally goes into the
wastebasket. That would be an unhappy incident, especially for the Americans
who have donated generously for this purpose and who desire to see the results 

of their donations as soon as possible.</p>
      <p>If the committee will begin to work energetically and will undertake the construction 
of the buildings, it can be expected that the Americans will not

refuse to support this matter in the future. It is true that the Americans

are already sick of donations--especially during these hard times of unemployment.
But before they get everything organized over there, we can expect 
better times to return here. Then the Americans will not forget the

work which has been started.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
