<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date><title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians Greet New Government of Russia</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0565</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>I G</item>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date><title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS GREET NEW GOVERNMENT OF RUSSIA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>During the week of March 23, cablegrams were sent by two Chicago Lithuanian
organizations to Petrograd, capital of Russia, to greet the new Government
and the newly won liberty of Russia.</p>
      <p>One of the cablegrams was sent by the Lithuania Club to Rodzianko, president 
of the Russian Duma. The cablegram reads as follows:</p>
      <p>"Together with seventy-five thousand Chicago Lithuanians we are happy over the
newly won liberty of Russia. Long live free and democratic Russia!"</p>
      <p>The second cablegram was sent by Dr. Anthony J. Zimontas, president of the
Lovers of the Fatherland Society [Translator's note: This society is also
known in English as the Association of Lithuanian Patriots of America], in care
of Prince Lvoff. The contents of the cablegram are as follows:</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0566.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>"On the morn of the birth of Russia's freedom the Association of Lithuanian
Patriots of America begs Your Excellency to accept this expression or our
profound joy and sympathy. Long live great Russia!"</p>
      <p>The following message was received in answer to the above cablegram:</p>
      <p>"Petrograd,</p>
      <p>"April 1, 1917.</p>
      <p>"President of the Association of Lithuanian Patriots, Chicago:</p>
      <p>"Deeply touched by your telegram. I am convinced that the freedom of Lithuania
will be established now that the freedom of all nations is an absolute and inalienable 
principle. Free Russia will do her duty for her Lithuanian brother.</p>
      <p>"Prince Lvoff."</p>
      <p>Prince Lvoff's telegram indicates that the Lithuanians who opposed the old Russian
Government, but maintained friendly relations with the democratic people of

Russia, did not make a mistake and will not be disappointed. As soon as the

<pb facs="4223970_4_0567.jpg" n="3"/>
democratic Russian people took over the Russian Government, their first

step was to do away with the former government's persecution of other

nationalities. Instead of persecuting and defrauding the oppressed nationalities,

the new Government immediately declared that "the freedom of all nations is an

absolute and inalienable principle," and for that reason, "the freedom of

Lithuania will now be restored".</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
