<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. V, No. 11, <date when="1897-03-13">March 13, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A Protest of the Chicago Lithuanians</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0105</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0105.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I B 4</item>
          <item>I B 1</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. V, No. 11, <date when="1897-03-13">March 13, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">A PROTEST OF THE CHICAGO LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Last Sunday, twenty-five hundred Chicago Lithuanians held a mass meeting
in the St. George's church hall in Bridgeport, where they adopted the
following resolution:</p>
      <p>That the Lithuanians from the ancient times were and at present are the
confessors and sons of our mother, the holy Roman-Catholic Church, always
acknowledging with obedience as the head of our church His Holiness the
Pope and the bishops.</p>
      <p>That in these days, among the Lithuanians, Satan with the help of the
Russian hirelings, brought forth the seed of heresy and error by
establishing the heretical church, otherwise called the Independent
Church, whose leaders are the excommunicated Catholic priests, or such
persons who never had been Catholic priests.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0106.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>That the servants of Satan, the Poles, under the cover of some kind of
of Independent Church, began to mislead our Lithuanians, by taking away
the faith of our ancestors, that is, from the teaching of Jesus Christ.</p>
      <p>We know that Lithuanians have suffered a martyrdom, they have shed their
blood for the cause of faith, and they are still shedding their blood,

as they did at Kraziai.</p>
      <p>Therefore, we, the twenty-five hundred Lithuanians in this meeting, are

openly condemning the church of those heretics as the product of the

Satanic and the Russian Hell, and those Lithuanians who belong to that

church, or take a friendly attitude toward it, we are holding them up

as the Russian spies and as the sellers of God and the Fatherland.</p>
      <p>We are deciding that every Lithuanian who belongs or helps such a church.

can not be accepted by any church society, or if he belongs, he ought

<pb facs="4223970_4_0107.jpg" n="3"/>

to be expelled from such society at once; and that every good Lithuanian

must have nothing to do with them, and protect himself as from a poisonous

plague or a mad malady.</p>
      <p>By such an attitude you will show the immorality of that damnable church.</p>
      <p>We are appealing to every faithful Lithuanian, we are begging of him to

pray to the Lord, that he will convert them back to the right road, that

He will return them back to the old Roman-Catholic church.</p>
      <p>Joseph Garinskas, President</p>
      <p>Julius Astrauskas, Secretary of the Parish Meeting.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0108.jpg" n="5"/>
Vincent Berzinski's church of St. Stanislaus, at Noble and Division St.</p>
      <p>When some members of the church got sick, they called for a priest

instead of a doctor. Most of the parishioners got sick at night from

over eating and drunkenness. So the sick people called the priest to

their houses for confession. As Anthony Kozlowski was a vicar, so his

rector, Vincent Barzinski, sends the Vicar Kozlowski to the sick people

to confess them.</p>
      <p>Every time Vicar Kozlowski went to confess the sick women, he used to

take to them a bottle of wine belonging to his rector, Barzinski. When

later Barzinski found out that his wine was almost gone, he asked

Vicar Kozlowski what had become of that wine. Vicar Kozlowski admitted

that he took the wine to the sick women. So Rector Barzinski expelled

his vicar, Kozlowski, from his church. Then the priest, Kozlowski, went

to a priest, Joseph Barzinski, a brother of the priest Vincent Barzinski. who had St. Jadwiga's church at Noble and Lubaok Avenue. Later</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0109.jpg" n="6"/>
      <p>on Kozlowski was expelled by Rector Joseph Barzinski for the same reason,

taking his wine to the sick women.</p>
      <p>Now Vicar Kozlowski had no place and no priest wanted to accept him because

Vicar Kozlowski stole wine from his superiors and gave it to the women.</p>
      <p>A. L. Graiciunas, Alex Szidlauskas, and Anthony Steponavice, spoke Polish

language fluently, saw their chance to organize an Independent Catholic

Church. They explained to the priest, Lozlowski, their plan and the

priest accepted.</p>
      <p>A saloon keeper, Mr. Dzilwer, at Hoyne and Luback Avenue, had a hall

above his saloon. The saloon keeper permitted them, of course, for

business reasons, to make a temporary church in his hall. The altar, etc.

was installed. With leaflets this new church was advertised far and wide.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0110.jpg" n="7"/>

On the first Sunday the large hall was crowded with the people, mostly
women, to whom the priest Kozlowski previously used to deliver the wine.

The collection was large, over $500</p>
      <p>
The Polish Roman-Catholic priests were greatly alarmed because this new

priest Kozlowski had no fixed price for confession, mass, etc. The people

could pay as much as they wanted. If they had no money, the priest confessed 
them, gave absolution, held mass free of charge to the poor people,

because this Independent Church was not for exploitation, but for service

to the people.</p>
      <p>
This new Independent Catholic church was such a great success that the

parish built a large hospital at Hoyne and Luback Avenue.</p>
      <p>
Then the Roman-Catholic priests started to blackmail the Independent

Church. They succeeded in making disturbances and fights in the Independent 
Catholic church. Many times the Roman-Catholic Poles, with the

help of police who were also Roman-Catholics, attacked the parishioners

<pb facs="4223970_4_0111.jpg" n="8"/>

of the Independent Catholic church in their church, during the mass.
</p>
      <p>
The women used to beat off with red peppers the attack of police and

others.</p>
      <p>

About those great fights in 1897 between the Polish Roman-Catholics and

the Independent Catholics, you can find information in the Chicago Daily

Tribune and the Dziennik Chicagoski, a Polish newspaper.
</p>
      <p>
Also an Independent Catholic church was organized at 18th and Ashland

Avenue, and the other at 32d and Auburn (Lituanica) Avenue.
</p>
      <p>
For this reason the Lithuanian Roman-Catholics held that mass meeting as

a protest and denunciation of the Independent Catholic church movement.

The protest mass meeting was held, not at the instance of the Lithuanian

people, but under the leadership of the Priest Krawczunas.

</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
