<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1910-07-01">July 1, 1910.</date><title level="a">How Do We Love the Motherland?</title> by A. Raizis
        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0642</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0642.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1910-07-01">July 1, 1910.</date><title level="a">HOW DO WE LOVE THE MOTHERLAND?</title> by A. Raizis</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>You take a newspaper which is published in Lithuania and you cannot be
happy enough on seeing how our brothers over there, having the press returned 
to them, are working, scattering the dark clouds that lay over the
people for several centuries. But it is not enough merely to rejoice in
the efforts of our brothers in the motherland; we must at least help with
our pennies if we cannot do so in any other way. Let us donate money for
the enlightenment of Lithuania! Let us be true lovers of our people and
our motherland!</p>
      <p>Recently an appeal was heard from the Lithuanian Education Society and the
Lithuanian Art Society begging for donations for the building of an independent 
home in which the two could assemble. But a building in the
Lithuanian capital [Translator's note: This refers to Vilna] is necessary
not only to provide a place of assembly for the aforementioned Societies. 
A building is also needed by the Lithuanians for the presentation of
<pb facs="4223970_4_0643.jpg" n="2"/>
theatrical performances, concerts, educational lectures, which, properly

systemized, could be changed into a permanent "People's University."

In it all the intellectual power of the Lithuanians would be concentrated.</p>
      <p>But are the donations for such a building coming in as they should? Very

few donations have been collected up to now for that purpose. We boast

of our love for the motherland with words, but when we should prove that

love with donations, then many of the Lithuanian Americans say: "I will

not go there to eat potatoes!" You see, they do not understand these things.

To a Lithuanian, a Lithuanian potato should be more delicious than an

American egg. We have some wealthy merchants here in America who could

donate one hundred and more dollars for his nation's needs and would

thus urge others to donate, but they ignore this. Before they became

wealthy they appealed to fellow nationals for support; now when donations

are needed for nationalistic matters, they do not acknowledge their

nationality.</p>
      <p>It is the same with the societies. Very few were found which did not

<pb facs="4223970_4_0644.jpg" n="3"/>

ignore the invitation for donations, for instance, the Lithuanian Alliance

of America. How long will we love our motherland with empty words? It

is necessary to show this love in other ways, especially in these times

when all of the civilized nations are competing to promote enlightenment

and culture as much as they can. Let us follow the paths indicated by

these nations and become, like them, true lovers of the motherland.

Let us donate our earnings made on the day of the anniversary of the

Battle of Gruenwald for the elevation of Lithuania and the enlightenment

of its people. We will not become poor because of this, but will do much

good to our nation. At present, our brothers in the motherland, having

just begun to live, need everything. They need national, agricultural

and industrial schools; they need a national building, commercial institutions,
art schools; a national bank for the protection of the farms so

that they will not be forced out of the hands of Lithuanians by foreigners

who are taking every opportunity to exploit us. We also need a national

Lithuanian university in our capital, Vilna, so that the Lithuanians who

feel the urge for education will not have to wander through the various

institutions of the whole world, in [the course of] which [wandering] 

<pb facs="4223970_4_0645.jpg" n="5"/>
elements; only because of the Lithuanians' lack of enlightenment and understanding. 
The time will come, it is known, when with the promotion of

enlightenment and the obtaining of more liberty, Lithuania will recuperate

and the people will have not only enough potatoes but even more nourishing

food for the mind and body. We will not be ashamed then, when on returning

we will take advantage of the liberty in Lithuania, knowing that we have

co-operated in its rise. Therefore, let us co-operate now while there is

something to help, while it is not too late. Let us not be deaf to the

cries of our brothers, who give all for the good of the motherland, who

do not begrudge their strength, not even their lives; who dedicate all for

the promotion of enlightenment among all of the Motherland’s people!</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
