<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 11, <date when="1902-03-14">March 14, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">You Must Act Without Delay</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0364</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0364.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>III B 1</item>
          <item>II D 10</item>
          <item>III H</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. X, No. 11, <date when="1902-03-14">March 14, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">YOU MUST ACT WITHOUT DELAY</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>We can call emigration a bad or good thing, but we cannot deny one
thing: The Lithuanian emigration up to the present time has brought
benefit to the nation. The fatherland has lost its sons and their
labor, but what of it, when they have no chance to work in Lithuania.
Looking from the other viewpoint, the emigrants in America have
raised Lithuanianism very high; they could not have done the same
in Lithuania. Further, emigration gives perpetual material help to
Lithuania; just count how many thousands of American dollars are sent
to Lithuania yearly.</p>
      <p>If the rights of the immigrants in the United States would be suppressed,
as the heavy paw of Russia suppresses on the other side, then the
Lithuanians would be pressed inside of four walls, and our brothers
would be lost.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0365.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>Our duty is to put all our energy against the suppression of immigration. 
We must take into consideration that when the suppression
of immigration becomes a law, no force will be able to get rid of it.</p>
      <p>Our individual or group protests at the meetings will not bring the

desired results. Therefore, we are making the last and the easiest

plan which can be used by Lithuanians of good will. Do it yourself

and urge others to do likewise. The time is short but the danger is

near. This plan is not made by the editor, but impelled by the 

American organization, The Immigration Protective League whose duty

is to protect the immigrants.</p>
      <p>Every Lithuanian in this country without delay should sign his name

and write a short protest and mail it to his congressman and senator.

<pb facs="4223970_4_0366.jpg" n="3"/>
If you cannot formulate the wording of such writing, write as follows:</p>
      <p>(State name of your congressman or senator)</p>
      <p>U. S. Senate</p>
      <p>Washington, D. C.</p>
      <p>Dear Sir: I Hereby respectfully request you to cast your vote

against any proposition to restrict the immigration of healthy and honest

persons.</p>
      <p>Respectfully yours,

(Sign your name and address).</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
