<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-03-04">March 4, 1914.</date><title level="a">Proposal to Restrict Immigration</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0295</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III G</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
          <item>I A 1 c</item>
          <item>I F 3</item>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, <date when="1914-03-04">March 4, 1914.</date><title level="a">PROPOSAL TO RESTRICT IMMIGRATION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Congress of the United States is considering the bill to restrict
immigration into the United States. The House of Representatives passed
the bill almost unanimously. Now it is ready to go to the Senate for
approval. After the signature of the president is affixed, the bill
one a law.</p>
      <p>A similar bill, a little more liberal, was passed by the House during
Taft's administration, when Republicans were in the majority, but
President Taft vetoed this bill, and finally it was rejected.</p>
      <p>The bill against immigration which was passed by the House recently,
we believe, will meet with the same fate as the bill which president
Taft vetoed. While the Senate will very likely approve the bill,
President Wilson has indicated a desire to study it thoroughly before
signing it.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0296.jpg" n="2"/>
It appears to us that President Wilson is not very much interested in
Burnette's bill against immigration. It is a strange thing that

Mr. Wilson did not take immediate steps to approve Burnette's bill,

especially when President Wilson, himself, was a strong advocate of

restricted immigration. His attitude is now different toward such

restriction. It is obvious that President Wilson has no desire to

make Burnette's bill a law now, when he has a chance to fulfill his

wishes and carry out his policies advocated for so many years. If

Mr. Wilson is not planning to kill this bill, it is clear to us that

he will delay it for the time being.</p>
      <p>The majority of the American people are for restricted immigration.

Their strength is proved by the fact that the majority of the Republican

mmigra/
and Democratic congressmen are in favor of restricted imigration

only for political reasons, but they are not against immigration in

principle.</p>
      <p>The immigration bill was rejected before, and it may be rejected again for
<pb facs="4223970_4_0297.jpg" n="3"/>

some particular reason, but not on account of general immigration

principles. The general opinion now is to stop immigration to the

United States for the following reasons:</p>
      <p>That the people who live in America are a better physically built

human species than those human beings that come from other countries;

that the American people are more enlightened than the average immigrants; 
and that we have a better cultural condition and better living

standard than those countries from where the immigrants come.</p>
      <p>We must protect our race, our standards of living, and our cultural
life.</p>
      <p>The argument is how to restrict immigration, and what methods or means

it would be necessary to use in order to accomplish this purpose.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0298.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>Those advocating the restricted immigration bill are puzzled trying to

find a good reason for demanding such restriction. They even bring into

the argument the difference between certain human species, of which

some have achieved a better physical development than others who are

physically weaker.</p>
      <p>The theory about improving the human species is strongly emphasized in the

discussion of restricted immigration. This theory is wrong in the first

place, because there is no definite boundary line set among races, especially

white races. Such proposed theories have no logical bases on which to support

their argument consuming the immigration question. The very same human

species will change physically under different climatic, social, and

economic conditions; but the species, as such, will remain the name. It was

observed long ago that man; white immigrants who came here the third

generation had acquired the same physical characteristics as the old

settlers who had been living here for centuries. In addition, they assimilated 
rapidly and and made one large nation which is known today as America.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0299.jpg" n="5"/>
      <p>Therefore there is no danger to America from that standpoint. So far this

argument has not proved why they want to restrict immigration and what

are the real reasons. We believe that those who want to restrict immigration 
object to the illiterate and unskilled laborer who comes here

from Europe where the standard of living is low as compared with the

standard of living in America. The foregoing arguments are weak and

have no value. Politicians are using this argument as a political issue

and are gathering material for their future campaign. It is obvious that

American education will not be decreased by adding two million more

illiterate to three million whites who are also illiterate in the United

States. Of course, a great number of illiterates is a bad thing, but

this situation can be remedied by using rational means, that is, by

giving the people the opportunity to educate themselves, instead of closing

the door of immigration to them. The educational opportunities in the

United States are much better and the schools are more accessible to the

working class than in any other country in the world.</p>
      <p>It is not true that educating these people would overburden the United States
<pb facs="4223970_4_0300.jpg" n="6"/>

and the tax-payers of this country. Those who say so forget the fact that

the foreign people are the heaviest tax-payers in this country. They work

hardest and under the worst conditions, and at the same time are exploited

more by the politicians than any other group of people in this country,

because they are foreigners. However, they pay all the taxes to the government 
with a smile and take all the insults from dirty local politicians

and the police force. This is the reward for their loyalty to the government. 
Why are these deplorable conditions existing in the foreign colonies?

The answer is just because they are foreigners. Who has the greatest number

of property owners and home builders? Who are the hardest-working people?

Who slaves for a small salary, saves his money to build a home for his

family and pays his taxes? Almost every family has its own home and pays

taxes to support the government and political parasites who do not pay

taxes to the government. Every city in America is built mostly by foreign

people, but not by political parasites who get their pay for doing nothing

from tax-payers' funds. The foreign people have done much more by helping
<pb facs="4223970_4_0301.jpg" n="7"/>

to build this country, by paying all taxes to support the government and

by giving life and energy. In return for their great sacrifice they

received very little as compared to what is given Americans. For their

sacrifice they receive a small percentage for education and enlightenment, 
which is considered by the politicians as a great reward for helping 
to build this great nation. But let us analyze the situation, then

we will have a better picture of foreign labor in this country, especially

in Chicago. If any body wants to have real facts about the exploitation

of foreigners, we recommend them to read the book entitled The Jungles,

by Upton Sinclair, who describes conditions in Chicago stockyards, where

foreign people work under the worst conditions in the world. A real

American is too proud to work under such conditions. He would feel hurt

to be a slave and work long hours for a small salary but foreigners have

to work under such conditions and keep quiet and be satisfied with that

they got for their work. Yet they accumulate a little money to buy property

and pay taxes to the government, as does any other citizen of the community.</p>
      <p>This propaganda is spread against foreign labor in order to restrict immigration 
to this country. The argument is brought forward that foreigners

<pb facs="4223970_4_0302.jpg" n="8"/>
lower the standard of living and the wages Americans (should receive). Any

intelligent American will understand that foreigners do not lower the

standard of American labor. In the first place foreigners do not take jobs

away from Americans. Besides, the American people do not like these jobs

because these jobs are too hard and too dirty. Most of the Americans are

tradesmen and specialists, while foreigners are unskilled laborers. For

that reason they cannot take the place of American tradesmen. They do

not compete with American skilled labor. Most of the foreigners have no

education or technical training. They have no trades of any kind. From the

foregoing statement we know that foreigners cannot lower the American labor

standards. The only thing that lowers the standard or living in industrial

progress, technical development, the machine age, the efficiency of newly

invented machines which take the place of skilled labor and specialists

in various industries throughout the nation.</p>
      <p>We may discuss immigration problems from another angle by asking ourselves

the question: Who discovered America? What type of people were they who

<pb facs="4223970_4_0303.jpg" n="9"/>

made the United States of America? We know this as a fact that this

country was made by plain people, the pioneers of America, who were

foreigners from other countries. Those who first came here were not

scholars or educators, or scientists. They were ordinary people with no

special training who came here to make their new home in this country.

They were not selected people from t special species of the human race;

they were of different nationalities of white races of Europe.</p>
      <p>There os no difference between immigrants who come now and those who

came before. There is no difference between the two groups, those who

came earlier and those who came later. The American people have not changed

as a race and their build and general appearance are the same as those of

any European people. It is obvious that European people cannot spoil the

American race, because they are the very same human species as the American

people. So far we cannot see the reason for restricting immigration, and

there is no real motive for closing the door of immigration to white race.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0304.jpg" n="10"/>
      <p>Maybe some politicians know the secret motives, but we cannot see their

side and they don't come out openly and tell why they want to restrict

immigration. We are still in the dark on that subject. We would like to

have a little more light on it.</p>
      <p>The real motives for restricted immigration is concealed in the bill

proposed by Burnette to the Congress. This bill contains a clause which

forbids all revolutionists to come to this country, i. e., those who are

the most energetic and most able people. This proves that the restricted

immigration is for political reasons only and not cultural.</p>
      <p>
American capital has outlived its days, has reached its age of maturity

and its downfall in the future is inevitable. In politics the time for

downfall has already started.</p>
      <p>
American capitalists are making every effort to destroy all the new

measures which are introduced into the houses of Congress; they are strongly

<pb facs="4223970_4_0305.jpg" n="11"/>

opposing progressive movements, especially the labor movement at the present

time. They only defend those measures which are to their advantage and

which enable them to exploit labor and thwart its progressive movement in

the United States.</p>
      <p>

The labor movement in recent years instilled a great fear in all ruling

classes and put them in a peculiar predicament. Now they are wondering

what to do with this situation.</p>
      <p>

Immigration restriction appears to the capitalists as one of the best

means of fighting the labor movement. Socialism and the revolution are 

in their opinion, strange ideas to Americans, because socialism and

revolution are brought from some other country and have not originated

in the United States. Some people who belong to the working class and

are paid better than others are also supporting the bill to restrict

immigration, proposed by Burnette.

<pb facs="4223970_4_0306.jpg" n="12"/>
Those people are ignorant of the situation and don't understand it at

all. They are making conditions worse for themselves by supporting this

Burnette's bill in Congress. Among the political organizations there

are some that oppose the restriction of immigration. The most important

role is played by class-conscious workers of this country and also by

workers who have not been Americanized, yet are supporting the labor

movement and opposing the restriction of immigration. Some organizations

forced President Wilson to doubt the theory of Professor Wilson. They

forced President Wilson to appeal to various public leaders and ask

them for advice on the immigration problems. Among various public

leaders there will be one representative from the Socialist Party, by

name, Charles Edward Russell, who will help President Wilson to solve

the immigration problem, which has become so complicated at the present

time.</p>
      <p>

Scientific arguments cannot decide a political question, only the power

<pb facs="4223970_4_0307.jpg" n="13"/>

of public opinion can do that.
</p>
      <p>

In order to reject this backward, uncultural and undemocratic bill

proposed by Burnette against immigration, we must vote against this bill

unanimously.

</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
