<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-10-25">Oct. 25, 1918</date><title level="a">Association of Friends of the University of Vilna</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0500</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-10-25">Oct. 25, 1918</date><title level="a">ASSOCIATION OF FRIENDS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VILNA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>A meeting was held in New York, on September 22, 1918, the purpose of which
was to found an organization which would undertake the financing of a Lithuanian 
university in Vilna. The organization was begun by the Eastern Lithuanians 
and completed by the Chicago Lithuanians.</p>
      <p>On September 29, a group of intellectuals met at Milda Hall in Chicago. They
selected the directorate, and framed the aims, and bylaws of the organization.</p>
      <p>The meeting was opened by Dr. Sliupas, who later was elected president. Mr. V.
Giraitis was made secretary.</p>
      <p>The following registered as members: J. Sliupas, K. Sliupas, P. Sinusas,
F. P. Bradchulis, J. Stankus, Dr. M. Drangelis, A. Petraitis, J. Sileika,
<pb facs="4223970_4_0501.jpg" n="2"/>
Justin Kulis, J. Bartkus, M. E. Zaldokas, Joseph P. Olekas, Attorney K. P.
Gugis, Dr. J. Kulis, Dr. A. Zimontas, Stasys Simkus, F. .J. Juozapaitis, S. Kodis
and B. K. Balutis.</p>
      <p>The following registered as visitors: S. Kvietkauskas, J. J. Giraitis, I.
Pupauskas, M. Silinskas, J. J. Baciunas, A. Milvidas, Miss J. Zemaitis,
M. Janulevicius, A. Kaulakis, K. Garmus, K. J. Kiras, William Kazlauskas,
K. A. Cineitis, and K. Rutkus.</p>
      <p>Without much discussion, the meeting agreed that such an organization was necessary; 
therefore the minutes of the meeting held in New York were approved.</p>
      <p>A committee of four, Dr. K. Drangelis, Mr. Zaldokas,  A. Petraitis and K. Sliupas,
was appointed to name the organization. The name decided on was "Association of
Friends of the University of Vilna". The meeting, however, gave the directors



<pb facs="4223970_4_0502.jpg" n="3"/>
the authority to change the name if they find it necessary to do so.</p>
      <p>The location of the headquarters of the organization was also left to the discretion 
of the directors.</p>
      <p>On the matter of dues, it was decided that active members will pay twenty-five

dollars a year; co-workers, fifteen dollars a year; and boosters, five dollars a year. 
Those who pay a thousand dollars will be members for life.</p>
      <p>The annual meetings of the organization wil1 be held in September of every

year, at a place designated by the directors.</p>
      <p>The proposed bylaws were read, discussed, and passed.</p>
      <p>The following were elected directors: K. P. Gugis, Dr. K. Drangelis, Attorney

<pb facs="4223970_4_0503.jpg" n="4"/>

F. P. Bradchulis,  S. Simkus and A. Petraitis in the West; J. Sliupas, J. S.

Lopatto, K. Cesnulis, M. Petrauskas, Dr. A. Bacevicius, M. W. Bush, and R. Karuza

in the East.</p>
      <p>The directors appointed officers from among these.</p>
      <p>A long, friendly discussion followed the close of the meeting.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
