<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-10-23">Oct. 23, 1914.</date><title level="a">A Jubilee Affair</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0205</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 1 a</item>
          <item>II B 2 g</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1914-10-23">Oct. 23, 1914.</date><title level="a">A JUBILEE AFFAIR</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Last Sunday the National Club of Young Lithuanians in America held a gay
Jubilee celebration at Liberty Hall, 30th Street and Union Avenue. The
affair was arranged to commemorate three things: the fifth anniversary of
the existence or the Club; the tenth anniversary of the regaining of the
freedom or the press in Lithuania; and the presentation of a Lithuanian
flag to the club.</p>
      <p>The arrangers of the program, headed by Mr. Juodis, prepared a varied program 
consisting of speeches, songs, and music.</p>
      <p>Dr. K. Drangelis spoke on the Lithuanian press. B. K. Balutis, editor of
the Lietuva, spoke on the meaning of the Lithuanian flag. J. Jankauskas,
president, P. Motiejunas, secretary, M. K. Juodis, president of the Club's
choral and dramatic unit, and Miss J. Lukosevicius also spoke.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0206.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>Especially noticeable was the zeal of the Club's officers and
leaders and the members themselves. Though the organization is
young, it surpasses many of our societies not only in membership but in
other matters. Several hundred youths now belong to the Club. It has its
own band, a large and excellent chorus, and a unit of amateur actors which

has presented many theatrical plays. It has purchased a beautiful flag for

about eighty-five dollars. It laid the foundation for a public library,

etc. It is not often that a club or society can boast of so many accomplishments, 
especially, as we have pointed out, in such a comparatively short

time.</p>
      <p>At this affair the Club's Chorus, under the direction of Mr. Grinius, entertained 
the audience with several Lithuanian songs. The Club's band is also

large, perhaps too large for a medium-sized hall.</p>
      <p>A large crowd attended. It was mostly composed of young people. While

acknowledging that the Club had arranged a beautiful affair, we would like 
<pb facs="4223970_4_0207.jpg" n="3"/>

to make one friendly suggestion which could make such gatherings

even more successful: it would be a good thing if the Club members

would see to it that there be no talking in the audience during the program,

that is, during songs, recitations, and speeches.</p>
      <p>After the program there was dancing until late hours. We have heard that

the affair was likewise a financial success. One member said that about

one hundred and thirty dollars was made at this affair.</p>
      <p>The meetings of the Club are held on the first Sunday of every month at

the T. Radavicius Hall, 936 West 53rd Street, at one o'clock.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
