<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-29">Nov. 29, 1918.</date><title level="a">The Fair Sex Is Active</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0484</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II B 1 a</item>
          <item>II D 1</item>
          <item>I K</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-29">Nov. 29, 1918.</date><title level="a">THE FAIR SEX IS ACTIVE</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>On Wednesday, November 27, the Women's Lodge 208 of the Lithuanian Alliance
of America held a rally at Milda Hall for the purpose of collecting donations
for Lithuania's independence. Although the attendance was not very large, the
meeting was very successful, thanks to the efforts of the president and her
helpers. After Mrs. M. Damijonaitis, the president, explained the purpose of
the meeting, everybody present made a donation.</p>
      <p>After a heated speech by Dr. A. Zimontas, the guests were anxious to make
donations. Among other things Dr. Zimontas said that he would be the first to
announce in the Lithuanian papers the names of all those "slackers" who had
lived in America many years and had done a good business with the Lithuanians
without ever donating one cent for a Lithuanian cause. Those words wounded
many a heart. Dr. Zimontas also thought up a good scheme regarding the young
men. He told them that they must buy the flowers which the girls were selling
in the hall. He instructed the girls not to dance with those men who did not
<pb facs="4223970_4_0485.jpg" n="2"/>
have flowers in their lapels.</p>
      <p>One very original idea was that of Mrs. Valasevicius' ten-year-old daughter,

who auctioned off a wreath for the benefit of Lithuanian freedom. Therefore,

as a result of these good suggestions money poured in from all sides.</p>
      <p>The program was varied by music. Miss Marion Rakauskas sang. Only those who

have heard the warbling voice of Miss Rakauskas know how pleasant it is.</p>
      <p>She sang "The Star-Spangled Banner", "Lithuania, Our Fatherland", and "The

Marseillaise". She was accompanied by Miss Salome Staniulis, another great

music lover who has done much in the field of music among Chicago Lithuanians.

An orchestra under the direction of Mr. J. Jakaitis played. Mr. Jakaitis is

known to Chicagoans as a good violinist.</p>
      <p>The program was excellently rendered. Chicagoans undoubtedly will wait anxiously 
for similar rallies.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0486.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>The following donations were collected: From the sale of the wreath of

little Petronella Valasevicius, $35.87. From flowers, $26.13. The total

was $62. The money will be turned over to the Christmas Tree Fund of Lietuva.</p>
      <p>[Translators note: On Christmas Lietuva conducted a drive for donations to

the fight for Lithuania's independence. This fund was called "The Christmas

Tree". The thought behind it was that every donation was an ornament for the

Tree, which represented Lithuania's independence.

Of those who sold flowers, Miss Helen Volteris and Miss Antoinette Zemaitis

collected the most money. The following bought flowers: [Editor's note:

There follows a list of those who bought flowers to the sum of $11.]...</p>
      <p>Miss M. Rakauskas and Miss S. Staniulis worked free of charge.</p>
      <p>The money received from the bar and from the sale of tickets will be held by

the Lodge. Some of it will pay for the orchestra, hall, printing, and other

expenses. The remainder will be added to the profit of the next rally.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
