<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IV, No. 30, <date when="1906-07-27">July 27, 1906.</date><title level="a">Appeal to the Chicago Lithuanians Societies and Individuals</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0654</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IV, No. 30, <date when="1906-07-27">July 27, 1906.</date><title level="a">
APPEAL TO THE CHICAGO LITHUANIANS SOCIETIES AND INDIVIDUALS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>There is no necessity of giving a long explanation about the revolution
in Russia. Our fatherland is submerged in tears and blood. But we hope
that our countrymen will get rid of the foreign yoke which has kept
them in oppression for many years. We, as the children of our fatherland,
must help our country in her struggle for freedom. Therefore, we are
appealing to all the Chicago societies and individuals to unite in
action in order to help our brothers in Lithuania in their struggle for
freedom. It is impossible for us to participate in the actual fight, to
lay down our lives for the cause of liberty; but we can help them
materially and spiritually by donating as little as one cent per day.</p>
      <p>In Chicago, on June 10, there was organized a committee of the united
societies, endeavoring to help our brothers in Lithuania in their
struggle for freedom. The following societies have joined this united
<pb facs="4223970_4_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
committee: The liberty society, the Simonas Daukantas Society, the Young
Lithuanians Friendship Club, the Lovers of Truth Society, the 36th
Branch of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, St. George Society, St.
Rokas Society, the King David Society, the Society of the Grand Duke

Algirdas of Lithuania. All societies that do not belong to this unity

of societies yet, should elect three delegates and send them to the

meeting which will be held on August 18, at 7 P. M. at Rugis Hall,

53rd and Morgan streets.</p>
      <p>COMMITTEE OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES</p>
      <p>A. Rudauskas, President</p>
      <p>A. J. Zimontas, Secretary</p>
      <p>John Vaitkevicias, Treasurer.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
