<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-01-10">Jan. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Clubs Among Lithuanians</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0181</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0181.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
          <item>III A</item>
          <item>III E (Bohemian)</item>
          <item>III E (German)</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Sandara</title>, <date when="1930-01-10">Jan. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CLUBS AMONG LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>P.5.....There have been and there still are numerous Lithuanian Young
People's  but in comparison to the organizations of other nationalities, they
have been sadly lacking. The Bohemians with their Sokol, the Germans with their
Turners, the most outstanding of such groups, are noted the world over for their
strength in organization. Their numerous halls, gymnasiums, and athletic fields are
fit reminders of what concentrated effort can accomplish. It has long been a puzzle
to me just why we Lithuanian young people have not been capable of such great deeds.
Too long have we been setting back, while others were doing what we are also able
to do. The main reason for our inactivity is our gradual Americanization. With
no Lithuanian organization great enough to warrant our interests, we have been joining
those American Clubs which offer us greater advantages. So great has been this
tendency to Americanize that many of us have even forgotten the beautiful language
of our mothers and fathers. Whenever it has come to a choice between an American or
a Lithuanian organization, the American club has won out principally because it had
more to offer.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0182.jpg" n="2"/>

Sectarianiam A Drawback: Another thing which has tended to discourage young people

from joining Lithuanian clubs is the inclination of most of these clubs to be

exclusive. There are Catholic, Student, Socialistic and other sectarian organizations,

- all built on faith, or some singular following. Before one can become a member of

such an organization one must subscribe wholly to the principles of that faith. This

hampering of ones' self-expression has discouraged many.</p>
      <p>There is nothing of the present in such prominent organizations like the Y.M.C.A.,

the Sokol or the Turners. The tendency of the older people to manage the affairs of

the clubs which have been organized has also had its influence. Young people like to

manage their own affairs. In many cases interference in matters of policy has caused

internal disruption. Any group of young folks will always have radical ideas as to how

things should be done with the result that the old-fashioned elders will disapprove,

and who can gainsay their superior wisdom and experience in affairs, musty though it
be.</p>
      <p>Right Spirit Essential: The surest way to eradicate any or all of these evils would

be to form a club which would admit all Lithuanians, regardless of creed or policy
<pb facs="4223970_4_0183.jpg" n="3"/>

but limiting the membership to young people. Of course the start would have to be

small but with the right kind of spirit, an organization could be built which would

have enough to offer the prospective members to wedge him or her away from the large

American organizations.</p>
      <p>The policy or platform of the club could follow that of the American type in which

democracy and unity are the basic features. However, there must be incorporated

somehow, athletics. Too much, the Lithuanian organizations have been run only on an

intellectual basis. This feature is not bad; in fact, it would have to be present.

But with nothing but hot air circulating through the club-rooms, with differences

arising, it is very easy to disrupt unity. Athletics can go a long way in forming a

compact body of younger people.</p>
      <p>With teams organized, battling to win against other teams; with everybody doing everything 
possible to help the team to win; compactness will be the outcome.</p>
      <p>Of course nobody will expect a club just newly organized to have a big club-house

with dance-halls, smoking rooms, and a gymnasium. It may take a few years to attain


<pb facs="4223970_4_0184.jpg" n="4"/>

this, but Rome was not built in a day. No matter how small the start, if a club has

the right spirit, any one will be able to see that it has a great future and that it

will develop. Therefore, the platform of this organization must be outlined free

from sectarian policies and it must contain other forms of amusement besides

continuous discussions and musical programs.</p>
      <p>Sincere Co-operation Necessary: There is one little fault among young people which so

often ruins a whole organization. When a certain person distinguishes himself or

herself as a good leader, the tendency is to let that person "do it all." And then,

after leaving everything to such conscientious worker to arrange certain persons will

grow jealous and attempt to undermine all the good work done simply from the motive

of mere envy.</p>
      <p>Another thing; whether nobody else noticed it or not the tendency has been for young

women to become the leaders. Is this a reflection against us, men? Whether anything

comes of this little article, remains to be seen. I hope somebody becomes inspired

enough to start something.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
