<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 49, <date when="1905-12-08">Dec. 8, 1905.</date><title level="a">Helping the Revolution and the Orphans in Lithuania</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0682</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0682.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>IV</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 49, <date when="1905-12-08">Dec. 8, 1905.</date><title level="a">HELPING THE REVOLUTION AND THE ORPHANS IN LITHUANIA</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>A Lithuanian public mass meeting was held at the M. Ruzgis Hall, 45th 
and Marshfield Avenue, at 5 P. M., on November 26, 1905, to organize
a committee to collect money for the revolutionary movement in Russia.</p>
      <p>The meeting was opened by Mr. P. J. Varkala, who explained its purpose,
asking the public to elect a chairman. Mr. Varkala was nominated and
elected. In his speech, Mr. Varkala described the horrors of the Russian
tsarist regime, against which the people of Russia and Lithuania have
revolted.</p>
      <p>The Russian revolution is going on; both the ignorant and the enlightened
people have revolted against the tyranny of tsardom. The speaker appealed
to the people to help the revolutionary movement in Russia Mr. J. Jancevskis 
and Mr. A. Algminavicia were the next speakers.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0683.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The Doctor Kudirka Singers’ Society sang the Marseillaise. Then an 8-year-old 
girl, A. Kabasinskiute, recited the poem, "Liberty." The public was
moved by this little girl's declamation. Then Dr. A. L. Graiciunas spoke,
urging the people to contribute to the cause of the revolution. Some of
the people started to leave the hall in order to avoid the donation. Then
the doctor said, "Do not be degenerates. Do not blame us if when you go

back to Lithuania the people will close the door against your face for

refusing to help your brothers in their fight for freedom."</p>
      <p>Other speakers were S. Marcinkevice, Golubickis, Bijanskis and Eismontas.</p>
      <p>After the necessity of helping the revolution in Russia was discussed,

there was elected a central committee to act for the revolutionary cause.

Joseph Varkala, 4605 S. Ashland Avenue, was elected president; Stasys

Marcinkevicia, 4605 S. Ashland Avenue, treasurer; Dr. A. L. Graiciunas,

3202 S. Halsted, secretary.</p>
      <p>Authority was given to this central revolutionary committee to arrange


<pb facs="4223970_4_0684.jpg" n="3"/>

meetings all over Chicago to collect money and spread propaganda in

behalf of the revolutionary movement in Russia, as well as to elect

collectors with authority to go from house to house and get contributions 
for the revolutionary cause and for the orphans that were made

during the revolution.</p>
      <p>The following collectors were elected for the district of Town of Lake:

Franciskus Poska, 4559 S. Hermitage Avenue; John Jankauskas, 4559 S.

Hermitage Avenue; Mrs. Mary Damijonaitiene, 3108 S. Halsted St.; Peter

Sliesoraitis, 4618 S. Paulina St.</p>
      <p>The election of additional collectors was left to the central revolutionary committee.</p>
      <p>At the massmeeting $19.25 was collected. This money was given to the

treasurer, Mr. Stasys Marcinkevicia.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0685.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>The chairman thanked the public for the collection for the fatherland's

cause, and the meeting adjourned with cries of Long live the Revolution!

Long Live Liberty and Fairness to Humanity!</p>
      <p>Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, Secretary</p>
      <p>Central Revolutionary Committee of Chicago.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
