<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1930-01-25">Jan. 25, 1930.</date><title level="a">Chicago Net Star Finds Lithuania a Wonderful Place to Live</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0400</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.3"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>, <date when="1930-01-25">Jan. 25, 1930.</date><title level="a">CHICAGO NET STAR FINDS LITHUANIA A WONDERFUL PLACE TO LIVE</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The editor of our Vilnius, one of Kaunas' well known magazines recently
interviewed Joseph Lukas, the Chicago net star who is now in Lithuania,
and is a sports instructor in the physical culture department in Kaunas.
He was asked how well the American Lithuanian youth is informed on
Lithuania.</p>
      <p>Mr. Zukas said, "None of the American born Lithuanians even imagine how
wonderful it is to live in Lithuania, the land of songs. I, from my own
experience, know that life in Lithuania was a pleasant surprise. But,
you can't blame the Lithuanian-American youth because their parents, who 
have not seen their fatherland for thirty or forty years, don't know
their own country's standing at present. Their parents picture Lithuania
<pb facs="4223970_4_0401.jpg" n="2"/>
as a country of misery, where everyone is persecuted, where the Lithuanian
peasants with calloused hands labor for daily bread. They ran away to the
new world and left Lithuania in the hands of their former oppressors. It

is really marvelous to see how Lithuania in such a short time built itself

up from the ruins of war and maintained its economic independence.</p>
      <p>"What should be done in order to bring the American Lithuanian youth

closer to the land of their parents?"</p>
      <p>Mr. Zukas states: "In my opinion, the best was is through sports. One

must remember, nothing will interest an American more than physical culture.

I am convinced that relationship in sports would appeal to the Lithuanian

youth of both countries."</p>
      <p>Does Zukas believe that the Lithuanian athletes can give a good account 
<pb facs="4223970_4_0402.jpg" n="3"/>

of themselves during their forthcoming visit to the United States? "Yes,

of course sports are young in Lithuania and they have still a long ways

to go, but they have some marvelous prospects.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
