<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 31, <date when="1898-08-05">Aug. 5, 1898</date><title level="a">How the Chicago Lithuanian Parish Treasury Stands</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial. Summary</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0099</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III C</item>
          <item>I B 4</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II B 2 d 1</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 31, <date when="1898-08-05">Aug. 5, 1898</date><title level="a">HOW THE CHICAGO LITHUANIAN PARISH TREASURY STANDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial. Summary</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Light, more light! The light of truth is not afraid of accusation,
only injustice is afraid of the truth.</p>
      <p>A Chicagoan writing in No. 30 of the newspaper Vienybe Lietuvrinku
(the Union of Lithuanians), says that we said nothing, nor did we criticized
the accounting given by Rev. Krawczunas of the St. George's church treasury.
We said nothing for a while because when we said before about the incompetence 
of Polish nuns to teach the Lithuanian children, Rev. Krawczunas
denounced us that we are trying to destroy the Lithuanian church. We said
nothing because the church committee undersigned the statement. We think
that the committee was elected by the parish not to take care of the pigs,
but to watch the parish treasury. For this reason we paid no attention
for a while to the statement of the treasury, even though the statement
was fraudulent from the beginning to the end.</p>
      <p><pb facs="4223970_4_0100.jpg" n="2"/>
The two final statements of the final account from January 1, 1894
to June 30, 1895, and from July 1, 1895 to December 31, 1896 (I omit the
details), shows that the statements are fraudulent.</p>
      <p>For instance. One item states that Rev. Krawczunas had paid to his

vicar $100.22 for saying the masses, but the rector Krawczunas does not

state how much money he got for saying the masses during those three

years. The priest shows the amount paid for the improvement of the church,

but does not state what the improvements were. The report also shows a

$1,500 new mortgage made on the church property. But Rev. Krawzcunas never

asked the parishioners to make this mortgage. and does not say what he had

done with that $1,500</p>
      <p>Even the taxes for his residence are fraudulently stated; one item

states $14.00 and the other $736.10. We know that such high taxes for the

residence is impossible.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0101.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>We are asking the parishioners and all the Lithuanian societies who

donated money for the church that they ask Rev. Krawczunas to give a final

and honest accounting of what he had done with the money donated for the

church, and especially what the priest had done with that $1,500 mortgage

money he had made on the church. The parishioners, with their hard-earned

money, are upkeeping the church, they must call the parish meeting, and

ask the priest for the final and honest accounting.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
