<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-29">Nov. 29, 1918.</date><title level="a">Be Poles </title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0481</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0481.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I C</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-11-29">Nov. 29, 1918.</date><title level="a">BE POLES
</title><title level="a">
(Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Germany never had many good friends. Her haughtiness and arrogance caused
her neighbors to stay aloof. True, there were many who bowed to Germany's
will, but they did so because of fear and not because of love. Finally,
by her greed and arrogance Germany aroused the whole world against herself--
then she fell to pieces under the blows of an angered world. That is a
good example of the fact that the politics of greed is bad politics, both
in an individual's private life and in the life of a nation. However, it
is apparent that not everybody is able to profit by the lesson taught by
that example.</p>
      <p>Take, for instance, the Poles. We who have known the Poles for ages know
that their greed practically has no equal. Today other clear-sighted observers 
are also beginning to notice this. Even the American press is
<pb facs="4223970_4_0482.jpg" n="2"/>
beginning to pay far more attention to the aristocratic and imperialistic
tendencies of the Poles.</p>
      <p>If those who exalt the Poles to the heavens would become better informed

by examining the Polish question more closely, they would see that the

Poles do not have one friend among their closest neighbors. The Czechs,

the White Russians, the Lithuanians, the Ukrainians--none or these can live

in harmony with the Poles, whose greed holds them all aloof. Still bound

by their own misfortune, the Poles today are already stretching their claws

to seize the lands or other nations. They speak loudly of "democracy",

while at home they kneel before the most corrupt aristocracy of Europe.

With the slogan "equals with equals", they attempt to persuade other nations

to join them, while at home they arrange pogroms for the Jews whom they cannot denationalize.</p>
      <p>Nowhere among their neighbors do the Poles have a good reputation. They are



<pb facs="4223970_4_0483.jpg" n="3"/>

beginning to lose their reputation among other nations also, as those nations

become better acquainted with them.</p>
      <p>The Poles have pulled the wool over the eyes of certain statesmen in France

and England who are in accord with Polish ambition to create a "Greater

Poland" by annexing the small neighboring nations.</p>
      <p>Today we dare to prophesy that the result of such a plan will be the creation

of another greedy country whose appetite will be equal to that of former

Germany. "Greater Poland" means a great cancer in the very heart of Europe.

Tho sponsors of the plan for a Greater Poland believe--and believe with a

clear conscience--that they would thus guarantee peace in Europe. They believe 
so because they do not really know the Poles. If they did know them,

they would realize that by creating a "Greater Poland" they are digging a

grave for the future peace of Europe.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
