<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, no. 34, <date when="1900-08-24">Aug. 24, 1900.</date><title level="a">Appeal</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0729</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VIII, no. 34, <date when="1900-08-24">Aug. 24, 1900.</date><title level="a">APPEAL</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>We, the Chicago Lithuanians living between 46th Street and 5th Avenue,
held a meeting on August 11th, where we decided to collect money for
the building of the new church at Szwekszna, County of Raseiniai,
in the province of Kaunas, Lithuania. The collectors are N. Urbonas
and D. Zebelis. They will come to all the Lithuanians who are from
the parish of Szwekszna. We are inviting the Lithuanians of other
cities to donate for this cause. The money should be sent to the
committee, N. Urbonas, 239 W. 46th St., Chicago, or in the rector's
name, the Rev. Julius Macijawskis, Szwekszna, Kaunas.</p>
      <p>The Committee.</p>
      <p>Editor's note: no one has the right to condemn when one donates his
own money for a charitable purpose, even to strangers, but when he
donates and neglects his own, no one will praise such a person or
persons. The American Lithuanians have their own essential affairs.
<pb facs="4223970_4_0730.jpg" n="2"/>
In Chicago, the national work is neglected entirely, and even their
spiritual affairs are neglected. If we collect donations for strangers

we will lose our effort and energy to take care of our own affairs.

The Lithuanians are even collecting money for the starving Hindus

who are under England's rule. What benefit will the Lithuanians get

from Hindus? None. England is much richer, and it is England's duty

to help the starving Hindus. This is not the affair of Lithuanians.

There are in Chicago many Lithuanians who are living in misery. Why

do the Lithuanians not consider helping their own nationalists? If

we will collect money for Chinese, Hindus and for the liberation of

Africans, then where will be the end of supporting strangers and

neglecting our own people? It is time to take into consideration our

own affairs. By neglecting our own duty we are going into disaster.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
