<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 52, <date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899.</date><title level="a">The Termination of the Year (Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0736</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>II B 1 e</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VII, No. 52, <date when="1899-12-29">Dec. 29, 1899.</date><title level="a">THE TERMINATION OF THE YEAR (Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The terminating year brought very little benefit to us. Our brothers
in our fatherland are still suffering the oppression and the persecution 
of the Russian tsar and his servants. Many of our brothers
were exiled just because they were trying to enlighten their ignorant
brothers.</p>
      <p>For better government of our fatherland, in order to overthrow the
tsar's regime, we must unite among ourselves, work together, in order
to help our oppressed brothers to free themselves from the Russian
yoke.</p>
      <p>The most important accomplishment among the American Lithuanians is
the support of the Lithuanian exhibit at the Paris exhibition. This
shows that the national conception of our Lithuanians is not dead
<pb facs="4223970_4_0737.jpg" n="2"/>
yet. Even though newspapers like Saule (The Sun), and Katalikas (The
Catholic) in their correspondences denounced and scolded the Lithuanian 
publications for the exhibit at Paris, the good Lithuanian
people paid no attention to these newspapers’ slander, and donated
$1,000 for this great Lithuanian cause. We like to ask why the
Lithuanian clergy are against national progress, why the clergy

refuses to support culture.</p>
      <p>Last year a new newspaper, Katalikas, was started in Chicago. The

appearance of any new newspaper is worth our congratulations. Everyone 
has the right to spread his views and defend them, but the

newspapers should not be published for someone's personal gain or

egoism. This newspaper is full of denunciations, lying and slander.

With such writings the newspaper degrades itself.</p>
      <p>In the last year died one of the best Lithuanian writers, Dr. Vincas



<pb facs="4223970_4_0738.jpg" n="3"/>

Kudirka. He is known by his literary name as Vincas Kapsas. His

death is a great loss to the Lithuanian nation. He was 41 years

of age.</p>
      <p>(Translator's note: Vincas Kudirka was the son of a well-to-do farmer,

religious people, Roman-Catholics. At that time the people in Lithuania 
did not care to educate their sons to be engineers, doctors,

etc.; their aim was that their sons be priests. So the parents of

Vincas decided that their son, Vincas, must be a priest. When Vincas

was graduated at the Mariampole (county seat) four-year course in

the Gymnasium High School, he refused to study for the priesthood.

Then his parents denounced him, and told him that he did not belong

any more to their family, and refused to give help for his further

studies. Than Vincas went to Warsaw, Poland, to study medicine. As

he got no help from his parents, he gave private lessons to Polish


<pb facs="4223970_4_0739.jpg" n="4"/>
students and to the rich people's children. He played the violin,

gave lessons in violin, so in this way he continued the course in

medicine. Lack of money, unable to get good food and good rest,

tuberculosis got him. After graduation in medicine, he wrote many

articles on Lithuanianism, against the Russian government's oppression; 
for that he was persecuted, thrown in jail. As he was sick

from tuberculosis he died young. The village where Vincas was born

is Paezeriai (by the lakes), county of Vilaviskis. Dr. Vincas

Kudirka died at the county seat of Naumiestis, about eight miles

from his home. His friends put a monument on his grave. The Russian

gendarmes cut the inscribed letters of his name off the monument).</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
