<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 50, <date when="1904-12-09">Dec. 9, 1904.</date><title level="a">Our Strength (Editorial)</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0709</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>I G</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 50, <date when="1904-12-09">Dec. 9, 1904.</date><title level="a">OUR STRENGTH (Editorial)</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>It is understood by us that in order to accomplish any important
purpose we must have sufficient strength.</p>
      <p>We want a Lithuanian republic. In order to obtain this we must use
all our strength. If all the Lithuanian classes would unite we could
gain the independence of Lithuania. We must take into consideration
the Japanese. They are a small nation, but united they are defeating
Russia, a country many times larger, with which she is now at war
in Manchuria.</p>
      <p>Formerly the Russians used to laugh at us and especially at the
Poles. After every revolution in Poland the Russians took the
official places in Poland, while the Poles were exiled to Siberia.
The revolt of the Poles against the Russian regime lowered the Poles
in the estimation of the Russians.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0710.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>If all the nations oppressed by the Russian government could come
to an understanding among themselves and take united action against
the Russian tyranny, the revolt would be effective. The Lithuanians,

Poles, Latvians, Estonians, Finns, Poles, White Russians, the

Caucasian and the Siberian nationalities at present have the best

chance of success in rising against Russian despotism. The Russian

oligarchy is beaten at the front in Manchuria. All those small

nations mentioned have strength, but they have no unity. The sons

of these nations are sent to the Russo-Japanese war in Manchuria

to be slaughtered while the real Russians are kept at home. Russian

soldiers are sent to all these countries to watch for revolt. If 

any single nation should revolt, it would be crushed with great

massacre. If all these nations could understand their strength

they would unite and revolt at the same time. No power could then

stop them. The yoke of the Russian tyranny would be overthrown.</p>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0711.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>If these nations would revolt even the Russians themselves in Russia

would join the uprising for the people of Russia hate the tsar's

despotic regime. Now the time is ripe to take up arms and to overthrow 
the Russian yoke.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
