<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date><title level="a">Samanas Daukantas Society Resolves to "Beat Them All"</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>4223970_4_0453</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2013-01-26">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="4223970_4_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III H</item>
          <item>II D 1</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, <date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date><title level="a">SAMANAS DAUKANTAS SOCIETY RESOLVES TO "BEAT THEM ALL"</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Simanas Daukantas Society, one of the largest and most important [Lithuanian]
societies in Chicago at the present time, does not intend to lag behind the
other organizations now that they have all become active in the campaign to
free Lithuania.</p>
      <p>At its last meeting, the Society discussed ways and means by which the Simanas
Daukantas Society can help in the drive to win liberty for Lithuania. The
president of the Society, Mr. M. Tamulevicius, brought up the subject and all
the members agreed that the campaign must be supported in such a manner that
Simanas Daukantas, the Lithuanian historian after whom the Society is named,
would not be ashamed of the society.</p>
      <p>After a discussion, it was decided that each member of the Simanas Daukantas
<pb facs="4223970_4_0454.jpg" n="2"/>
Society must donate at least one dollar to the cause of Lithuanian independence. 
The Society has more than three hundred members. In addition to this,
the Society has sixty-five dollars, the profit from its last affair, which
will go to the same fund.</p>
      <p>Therefore, the least that we can expect from the Simanas Daukantas Society
for the cause of Lithuanian liberty is five hundred dollars. If the members 
make an extra effort, they can easily go over this quota.</p>
      <p>The following were elected officers for the next term: M. J. Tamulevicius,

president; P. Jonaitis, vice-president; P. Kenutis, recording secretary;

Anthony Jonikas, financial secretary; S. Martinkus, treasurer; A. Kaulakis,

S. Stankus and A. Karpavicius, trustees; Thomas Janulis and V. Stankus,

librarians; and Mr. Kilevicius, sergeant at arms.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
