<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXV, No. 69, <date when="1926-04-09">April 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Communists Are Bribing Workers' Press</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0082</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.D.2.c"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0082.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>I D 2 c</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXV, No. 69, <date when="1926-04-09">April 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTS ARE BRIBING WORKERS' PRESS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Communists are trying hard to bring themselves close to the working
class and we must give them credit for being very unscrupulous every
time they want to pull a lie. We heard the confidential news that
Communists organized a new press bureau, whose aim is to propagate,
print, and distribute articles, with the keynote as to how the working
class in Russia enjoys heavenly privileges. In fact we and the majority
of the world know that these stories and propaganda are ridiculous, full
of lies, but still Communists are steadily pounding the same motive.</p>
      <p>As an example of this ridiculous propaganda we will ask the readers‘
attention to a recently published article which was trying to employ
statistics as a convincing fact of the workers’ heavenly life in Russia.</p>
      <p>Among other things painting workers’ life we found that Communists
proudly state that in Russia there are over 7,000,000 registered Communists. We must admit our skepticism concerning Communists‘ rights
<pb facs="5425406_0083.jpg" n="2"/>
to rule and regulate the life of 165,000,000 Russians. We believe that
this country, with 120,000,000 population, will be a bit worried of
having communistic rule or even influence, if we have 7,000,000 Communists here.</p>
      <p>Now comes the employment situation. This situation, no matter how much
colorful paint be spent by the govermnent-guided press, doesn't look
so brilliant. Of course, very obliging Communist writers did not overlook the question of workers wages, which looks so big on paper but
do not mean very much in everyday life, if we just compare existing
prices. With all will to believe that communistic workers‘ heaven
really exists, we hardly find trace of it, despite such bribes as
the Communist Press Bureau.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
