<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXX VII, No. 227, <date when="1928-11-27">Nov. 27, 1928</date>.

        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0168</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.D.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.B.2"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II D 1</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXX VII, No. 227, <date when="1928-11-27">Nov. 27, 1928</date>.
</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>It had long been the desire of our people in Chicago that all small organizations, 
the existence of which, it seems, always have been endangered by
lack of members and financial conditions, to be united in one strong
society. It took a long time to come to actual amalgamation, but at last
it was accomplished to the satisfaction of all.</p>
      <p>We, Slovenians in Chicago, had over fifteen small benevolent lodges. Upkeep
of such number of lodges with members of same nationality, with similar
rules and regulations, looks just foolish. People wasted money on so many
rents, secretaries, etc., and if we are to take into consideration personal
jealousy among officials of those small lodges, here we have a clear picture
of the handicap which holds the activities down.</p>
      <p>No wonder that a great number of members of various lodges started protesting 
against such doings, and after quite a fierce fight, they succeeded
in bringing unification and amalgamation.</p>
      <pb facs="5425406_0169.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>The new society was named United Lodges of Chicago K. S. K. Jednote. The
general idea of this new united organization is as follows: To keep the
organization's expenses down as much as possible; to increase sick benefit
for outstanding members; strong representation on national conventions;
promotion of good will among former members of small lodges; stronger support 
of our church St. Stjefan, etc.</p>
      <p>We all must admit the great importance of such unity and are sincerely
congratulating the individuals on the hard work which brought this excellent 
idea to life.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
