<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vo1. 13. No. 1076, <date when="1928-04-26">April 26, 1928</date>.<title level="a">Educational Department of Jugoslav Socialist Federation</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0043</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.A.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.f"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.g"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>I A 3</item>
          <item>II B 2 f</item>
          <item>II B 2 g</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vo1. 13. No. 1076, <date when="1928-04-26">April 26, 1928</date>.<title level="a">
EDUCATIONAL DEPARTMENT OF JUGOSLAV SOCIALIST FEDERATION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The purpose and activities of the Educational Division of the Jugoslav Socialist
Federation have been outlined a number of times before. Still there is that
clamoring for more information from many of our friends. We have decided,
therefore, to give a brief and accurate account below, paying particular attention to the necessity of education to all the workers. and especially to the’
Jugoslavs.</p>
      <p>Education is the prime factor of all progress. If you go back into the dark
ages, you will find that those races that adopted newer, more practical methods
as a result of many experiments, held the controling power of the earth. The
early centuries produced the forward looking elements of Greek and Roman philosophers who lifted their races above those of the barbarians. But leave what
is gone, behind. Education today is a necessity. It is necessary that you
study and learn daily because you may have work today, but tomorrow you might
be obliged to look for it elsewhere. You must know what you are doing because,
after all, you are selling for a small salary your ability, which in turn de-
pends upon your knowledge - that is your answer. Education is your means of
<pb facs="5425406_0044.jpg" n="2"/>
securing food and shelter so that your body may live. It is just as essential
as food and clothing.</p>
      <p>Not only should you know and learn more about your daily earning power; you must
also know and learn about the wonderful human mechanism, your system. What to
do and what not to do when sickness overtakes you; what is good and what is bad
for it.</p>
      <p>To keep in constant touch with the world, you must read and study periodicals,
books, eto., just as most of you must follow the procedures of your fraternal
societies to know what it is doing or what it contemplates to do.</p>
      <p>There are countless numbers of features about which we know very little. You
must know art to love it - song to admire it; but more attention to it together
with your incessant desire to know, to learn, will bring art closer to your eyes
and song closer to your ears.</p>
      <p>It has been conceded so often that centralization of all groups and organization 
enables and permits them to function better, and that all such centralized work
is less expensive. One group can do little, but one hundred groups united can
<pb facs="5425406_0045.jpg" n="3"/>
do much; because separate groups operating alone would gain less exerting the

same amount of energy than a centralized union of many such groups.</p>
      <p>The Jugoslav Socialist Federation under date of November of }921, organized this

Central Educational Division for the purpose of:</p>
      <p>First: (a) Supply such literature which would eventually persuade its readers to

look toward the future, even though we perish without securing that for which we

crave.</p>
      <p>(b) Literature which will describe the vast natural resources and the

powers that now exploit it, with the tendency and argument that this world with

all its beauty, power, and raw material, rightfully belongs to you, who work from

day to day to make it bigger and better, as much as it does to those who have

done nothing, but still claim it.</p>
      <p>Second: (a) By elevating our social lives to greater heights; teaching and encouraging plays of meaning and benefit, as well as plays of amusement. For 

after all, a worker needs to laugh to keep fit, much more than a non-producer.</p>
      <p>(b) Supporting those musically inclined to satisfy their hearts’ great<pb facs="5425406_0046.jpg" n="4"/>est desire to keep on singing merrily in spite of‘ our many hardships. Life with-

out music - would there be any?</p>
      <p>Third: (a) To arrange and prepare lectures.</p>
      <p>(b) Discussions.</p>
      <p>(c) Debates.</p>
      <p>People of our race will much more readily comprehend our views when a fluent

speaker addresses them with knowledge and gesture - one who has a sincere desire

to help people understand, giving everyone an equal opportunity to express his

viewpoints on questions of vital importance.</p>
      <p>Fourth: To inspire, teach, and uphold the truth above everything else in spite

of all our handicaps.</p>
      <p>The Educational Division of the Jugoslav Socialist Federation has supplied literature which is fit to read and has helped in the uplift of our social, dramatic,

and musical lives. It has prepared lectures, discussions, and debates for the

past seven years. and its membership grows each year; for as the work expands,

it speaks for itself. It is self-evident that from the growth of about forty

<pb facs="5425406_0047.jpg" n="5"/>

organizations, contributing the first year to one hundred and six organizations

for 1927, ours is a worthy cause deserving all the support you and your branch

can give it.</p>
      <p>While it is true that much of this material may be obtained at school, it is

also true that our Jugoslav race has had but an inkling of it. You are one of

us; it is your duty to yourself and to your friends to work in behalf of this

eduoational division. It is not too late to enroll for 1928. Address all correspondence 
to Mr. Charles Pogarelec, 3639 W. 26th St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
