<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXV, No. 32, <date when="1926-02-17">Feb. 17, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">People‘S Sentiment against Prohibition</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0049</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.B.2"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0049.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>I B 2</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXV, No. 32, <date when="1926-02-17">Feb. 17, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLE‘S SENTIMENT AGAINST PROHIBITION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>For the past seven years the American people have been feeling the taste
of prohibition. This law was enacted during the war and its enforcement
is getting tougher. Prohibition is commonly known. as the Volsted Act;
it acquired this name from Senator Volsted, who was the father of the
Act.</p>
      <p>It is a known fact that this Act was not accepted so cheerfully by
the drinking public, and Volsted has been cursed by this class of people,
but still Volsted eagerly defended his Act. He sincerely believed that
by enforcement of this Act, the country would greatly benefit by eliminating 
lots of evils. He also believed that his Act would cut down
heavy drinking, but he overlooked the fact that prohibition developed
such enormous corruptions that government and people really got to 
thinking which was better: corruption or free drinking.</p>
      <p>Seven years of prohibition experience shows us that despite strong
<pb facs="5425406_0050.jpg" n="2"/>
enforcement of the Volsted Act, we in America have as many drunkards
as it was registered before prohibition era. On another side it is
already a proven fact that thousands of innoceent people paid with
their lives enjoying bootleg liquors of various kinds.</p>
      <p>During the prohibition era a great many enormous and small fortunes
are made. "Beer flats" and "big shots" of lawbreaking organizations
developed the system of bribing police, and without any interference
were selling openly "poison drinks" for the prices from 25 to 75 cents.</p>
      <p>No wonder that a great many millionaires with an army of hoodlums were
reaping profits.</p>
      <p>The Catholic Church teaches people to be humble. It preaches to its
followers that being humble is the greatest asset in character. Over-
<pb facs="5425406_0051.jpg" n="3"/>
drinking can be considered as a debit in good character; it is a sin
against religion.</p>
      <p>Our church leaders openly opposed prohibition, which become cow for
numberless politicians, officials and boot-leggers. Prohibition in a
form as it exists nowadays, is nothing more than a sort of fanaticism
and as such will not bear wholesome fruits. The people in their majority,
especially people of Slav extraction, are against prohibition.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
