<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. 1. No. 8, <date when="1906-08">August, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">To All Slovene and Crdatian Leaders of the Socialist Federation</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0156</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.E"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0156.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>I E</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. 1. No. 8, <date when="1906-08">August, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL SLOVENE AND CRDATIAN LEADERS OF THE SOCIALIST FEDERATION</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Executive Branch of the Socialist Party in Cook County, Illinois decided
to publish a resolution, as follows:</p>
      <p>Slovenian Comrades, Attention!</p>
      <p>Whereas, it has been made known to the County Central Committee of Cook County,
Ill., on complaint of the Slovenian comrades composing the South Slovenian
Branch No. 11, that the Glas Svobode, owned by one, M. V. Konda, and published
in this city (Chicago), is preaching openly against socialism in its columns,
and</p>
      <p>Whereas. this paper was at one time used by the Slovenian comrades as their official 
organ, and on account of its open attacks on socialism, it has ceased to
be such, and</p>
      <p>Whereas. the said M. V. Konda has been, but is not now, a member of the Socialist 
party, and</p>
      <pb facs="5425406_0157.jpg" n="2"/>
      <p>Whereas, the Slovenian comrades have now a paper named Proletarec, owned collectively 
by them, published in the city of Chicago, and printed in the Slovenian
and Croatian languages; be it therefore</p>
      <p>Resolved, that we condemn the action of M. V. Konda and consider as unfair and
unjust his attacks against the Socialist movement and its noble aim in behalf of
oppressed and down-trodden humanity; and we, therefore, call upon all Slovenian
comrades to give to Proletarec their loyal and financial support; be it further</p>
      <p>Resolved, that a copy of these resolutions be printed in the Chicago Socialist,
a copy transmitted to the national office. and also that we ask the socialist
press of America to publish same with a view to giving these resolutions as wide
publicity as possible.</p>
      <p>Published by order of Cook County Central Committee.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
