<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1. <date when="1906-01">Jan. 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Editor's Notice.</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0158</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.E"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>I E</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. 1, No. 1. <date when="1906-01">Jan. 1906</date>.
<title level="a">EDITOR'S NOTICE.</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>With this first issue of the Proletarec, Slovenes of the working class came into
the intellectual world with their own publication. This step toward mass organization 
can be considered a real accomplishment of the working class, which never
has the opportunity to express its socialistic opinion.</p>
      <p>Until today Slovene workers did not own or publish their own newspaper; therefore
it was impossible to openly state their opinion. All existing Slovene newspapers
were owned and published by people who were against the workers' interests. With
the aid of the Proletarec we hope that workers will understand that this publication 
is the only powerful and sincere means of gaining knowledge of our social,
economic, and religious statute, as well as to learn the whole truth that the
capitalists are the most dangerous enemies of the working class.</p>
      <p>Proletarec pages will always be wide open to workers for criticism. Workers need
not be afraid that their correspondence or articles will be thrown into the waste-
basket, because their contents are not favorable to the capitalistically inclined
<pb facs="5425406_0159.jpg" n="2"/>
newspaper owners.</p>
      <p>Proletarec will offer select and rich reading material, which will consist of:
extracts from American newspapers, magazines, etc.; humorous stories; economic
and social references; and the strict policy of defending working class interests.
It will keep workers posted and well informed about international and local happenings 
and will depict our socialistic fight for workers’ rights.</p>
      <p>For the time being the Proletarec will be issued only once a month and will be
printed on eight pages. Subscriptions will be only fifty cents for one year,
remittance to be sent to the address of our comrade, Anton Peshern, 678 W. 17th Street,
Chicago, Ill.</p>
      <p>Articles and all correspondence should be addressed to 483 Loomis Street, Chicago,</p>
      <p>Signed:</p>
      <p>Andrey Popravne, President.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
