<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, <date when="1932-04-28">Apr. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Otis M. Walter</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0230</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-IV"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.A.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>IV</item>
          <item>II A 1</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, <date when="1932-04-28">Apr. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">DR. OTIS M. WALTER</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Dr. Otis M. Walter, one of the most prominent Slovenian physicians
and surgeons on the West Side of Chicago, will celebrate a rare
accomplishment. It was exactly twenty years ago May 1, that the
doctor established his office on Twenty-sixth Street and Crawford
Avenue.</p>
      <p>At that time, the vicinity was not developed to the extent that it
is today. One little room comprised his whole office. As the years
rolled on, the doctor annexed larger quarters and installed modern
medical equipment. All types and nationalities of people trekked to
him, and his fame as a surgeon spread rapidly, as one after another
of the many patients successfully overcame the most serious complications 
and illnesses, and his ability as a surgeon became known.</p>
      <p><pb facs="5425406_0231.jpg" n="2"/>
From that same location, the doctor has been serving the people of this
community continuously during these twenty years. No worker, unable
to pay for treatment or surgery work, has ever been turned away.</p>
      <p>The doctor has been an instructor in schools and colleges prior to the
beginning of his present professional career, and even after entry
into private business, he has been experimenting and developing new
and modern methods of surgical and medical procedures. For the past
thirteen years he has been a member of the surgical staff of the Francis
Willard Hospital, and for the past ten years a member of the surgical
staff of the North Chicago Hospital. Dr. O. M. Walter is well-known
among the Jugo-Slavs of this city. When asked to what he attributes
his success, he is firm in saying "to the Slavic people."</p>
      <p>It is indeed a coincidence that the doctor should have reason, to celebrate 
on the day of all days, May 1, and it is our hope that he may live 
many more years, and assist the workers as he has heretofore.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
