<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, <date when="1919-03-27">Mar. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Socialism and Schools</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>5425406_0086</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.A.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="5425406_0086.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>I E</item>
          <item>I A 1 a</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, <date when="1919-03-27">Mar. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISM AND SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>Socialism is the main ideal which is to break down the great difference
existing between the capitalists and the working class. It must fight
for the equal education of the workers‘ children also.</p>
      <p>Capitalists are doing their best to provide the best education for their
children, but the workers‘ children are obtaining education mostly from
public schools.</p>
      <p>Capitalistic schools are teaching their pupils Science and distributing
practical knowledge, but the workers‘ children are "fed" with fairy stories
from the Old Testament.</p>
      <p>A long time ago, People's schools became ineffective so far as their program
<pb facs="5425406_0087.jpg" n="2"/>
was concerned, and more and more adapted their program to serve the purpose 
of the capitalists‘, because, as the old proverb says: "It is easier 
to rule the masses when they are ignorant."</p>
      <p>Socialism did not see children as future slaves of the capitalist regime,
but as full-fledged and equal members of society. Socialism is against
capitalistic culture, which is depriving the workers’ class of its rights to
live intelligently and comfortably.</p>
      <p>Schools in capitalistic countries are grooming reaction and military culture.</p>
      <p>Socialism, on the contrary, is striving to put the schools in the service of liberty
democracy, and strives to make them free in all grades from grammar school
to college.</p>
      <p>Socialism strives to make the present day schools Socialistic.
<pb facs="5425406_0088.jpg" n="3"/>
Feudal masters in the Middle Ages kept the schools with the main idea of
developing good citizens of the feudal regime. Capitalistic governments of
today have united their efforts with the church influence, and are doing
everything possible to educate the masses to be obedient church followers,
tireless workers, and soft material for exploitation. For this last reason,
capitalistic schools are in open war with the working class.</p>
      <p>The pious element should be entirely removed from the school program, because
the general purpose of the school is to teach Science, which will help us
to improve our lives right here in this world, but not to prepare us for
an imaginary life in the sky.</p>
      <p>The purpose of the school is to give the people practical knowledge, but
the schools of today are dominated with the idea of distributing theoretical
and practically worthless information.</p>
      <pb facs="5425406_0089.jpg" n="4"/>
      <p>Professional education is what the workers need badly. This type of

education will give us an opportunity to develop skill and gain knowledge

in several lines, and make it easier for us to find jobs. In the situation

as it exists now-a-days, a minority of skilled laborers and experts monopolize

the jobs. Socialist schools must develop in the pupils a sense of self-

respect and initiative, and open to them a new horizon for ambition, not

helpless slaves for capitalistic regime. Against the foolish theory of the

six days‘ creation of the world, we must place the Darwin theory. The modern

school, supported by scientists of reputation is exactly what we want.</p>
      <p>Capitalists should not rule the schools and make the system conform to their

selfish desire to promote intellectual ignorance.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
