<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Manifestation for Peace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1467</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1467.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT MANIFESTATION FOR PEACE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the horrors of war affect anybody to a greater degree than most of us, it is the woman who has not only to bear the burden of unusual cares, but frequently is deprived of all that forms the foundation of her life. It is therefore quite natural that women would raise their voices in these war-like times and demand that their protest against the cruel paradox of the enlightened twentieth century--war--be heard. Never before has humanity been plunged into the abyss of war for more trifling reasons than now and, therefore, it is still more imperative to voice a protest.</p>
   <p>A protest against the present war will be voiced today, at the meeting called by the Klub Ceskych Obcanek (Bohemian Women Citizens' Club) in the hall of Sokol Chicago at 2 P. M. The organizers hope that all those who wish to protest against this war and manifest their desire for peace will be present at this meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1468.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A number of prominent speakers will address the meeting, among them, Mayor Harrison, Judge Watson, Professor V. Zmrhal, secretary of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), Mr. A. G. Melichar, Mrs. Klara Klaus, etc. The admission is free in spite of the fact that musical selections will fill in the program. A very large attendance is therefore expected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
