<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-23">July 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[The Fight for Freedom]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-23">July 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[THE FIGHT FOR FREEDOM]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Liberty is best appreciated by a nation to which it was denied for centuries--a nation kept in abject slavery. We Czechs and Slovaks have had a particularly harsh experience in this respect; and that is why our people in the old homeland rose in vigorous protest, and why our Czechoslovak Army is performing acts of outstanding bravery. We know that our people could not have done otherwise, for they were led by the dictates of their hearts and by their conviction. Our people perceive very accurately that the hour of redemption from century-old thralldom is here, and that in this critical time the moment of just retribution has come.</p>
   <p>This is why our proverbial dove-like nature has turned into one of steel and rock. Our people in the motherland revolt openly, in the face of Austrian <pb facs="5418478_2_0497.jpg" n="2"/>spears, and our Czechoslovak Army is accomplishing "historic wonders" of bravery. It is only natural that these feats win sympathy for us everywhere.</p>
   <p>The world has always cheered an enthusiastic and sacrificing people. But when all the details of our incomparable fight for Czechoslovak independence shall have come to light--when people know the real horror of our sufferings--when they have comprehended the immense amount of work accomplished with comparatively small means--then their admiration for Czechoslovak valor will be complemented by a no less well-merited esteem. This moment is swiftly drawing near.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
