<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">For Liberty Bond Sales</title><title level="a" type="sub">Big Meeting of the Czech Campaign Division</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FOR LIBERTY BOND SALES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Big Meeting of the Czech Campaign Division</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All members of the Czech division of the campaign for the sale of Liberty bonds met in the clubrooms at Mr. Joseph Placek's hall, 2347 South Kedzie Avenue, last night. Ways and means by which propaganda for the sale of war bonds could be intensified were discussed. The bonds are the third issue of Liberty war bonds, the public sale of which will open in the near future.</p>
   <p>As you already know, a large organization has been formed in Chicago which will support the United States Government in its efforts to provide the financial means with which to carry on the program which has been forced upon it by the war. This organization works in a field divided into districts and sections according to nationalities distributed over the city.</p>
   <p>The Czech division is by no means the smallest. It is headed by our fellow countryman, Anton J. Čermák, chief bailiff of the Municipal Court. He has sent <pb facs="5418478_2_0621.jpg" n="2"/>out invitations to all those who were active in the campaigns for the first two bond issues, and also to representatives of the press, asking their co-operation. This work is the best proof of the loyalty of the Czechs, who have always upheld the administration of our great President Wilson. Men and women from all walks of life came to this meeting to become better acquainted with each other, so as to bring forth the best results at the very time when their work will have to grow most intensive and when it will be needed most.</p>
   <p>At a dinner given by Mr. Čermák, who was the first to speak at the meeting that followed, he expressed the hope that the enthusiastic response which the Czechs made to the first two issues they will equal, or even surpass, in the case of the Third Liberty Loan. The chairman asked the audience to make suggestions on ways in which the work might be begun to secure the highest possible efficiency. The consensus of opinion during the ensuing discussion climaxed with the resolve that the Czechs must not lag behind other groups under any conditions, and that they must be ready for sacrifices to the limit of their <pb facs="5418478_2_0622.jpg" n="3"/>abilities in order to demonstrate their genuine American patriotism.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting was one of the most enthusiastic ever held among us. Its keynote was intense patriotism, which gave assurance in various forms that when the time comes and the Czechs begin to work, the action will be crowned with brilliant success. Every one of the suggestions made was well taken and contained valuable points on how we could best work together.</p>
   <p>Mr. Strickland was the first non-Czech speaker. As director of the office of the bond campaign among the immigrants of the seventh Federal Reserve Bank district, to which Illinois belongs, he is acquainted with the work accomplished by Czechs and Slovaks. He gave testimony to it which may well fill us with pride. He declared that our community showed the best results among twenty-four nationalities of Cook County when the campaign for the negotiations of the second war bond issue closed.</p>
   <p>The second non-Czech speaker was Mr. Henry Chandler, secretary of the organization known as "Four Minute Men". He was followed by Mr. John Palandech, a <pb facs="5418478_2_0623.jpg" n="4"/>leader among the Serbian immigrants, who spoke of the aims common to Czechs and Serbians.</p>
   <p>Mr. Čermák, chairman, expressed regret over the fact that the Czech section has lost Mr. William Pflaum, one of its ablest speakers, who will follow a call from the American speakers' headquarters. Mr. Pflaum was present and assured the gathering of his confidence in the willingness of the Czechs to make this third campaign an unqualified success.</p>
   <p>Mr. Čermák then read the names of all the subcommittees which had been active during the first and second campaigns. He also acknowledged with appreciation the valuable services performed by the Czech press. At the same time he announced that the number of existing subcommittees will be increased by two: One for Cicero and Berwyn and one for all Chicago, headed by officers of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
