<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-07">Dec. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[Citizenship Papers]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0735</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0735.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-07">Dec. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[CITIZENSHIP PAPERS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The declaration of war has caused great discomfort to a large number of former Austrian subjects who, for one reason or an other, have omitted to take steps to become citizens. We have repeatedly emphasized the importance of the naturalization papers. The entire Czech-American press has always been pointing out to its readers that it is the sacred duty of every Czech here in this country to become an American citizen. When the war broke out, we redoubled our efforts to induce our fellow countrymen to renounce Austria, and there should not be a single person who has failed to take out the papers if he is entitled to them.</p>
   <p>In general, our appeal did not remain unheeded. Those who refused to lend an ear to it will probably, in due time, have to take the consequences of their negligence or lack of foresight.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0736.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every noncitizen born in Austria will be classified as an enemy alien and will become subject to the same regulations that govern the sojourn of German-born noncitizens. He will have to register. He will be barred from certain places where he might obstruct the war activities of the United States, or otherwise damage the cause.</p>
   <p>Although it is likely that certain war measures enforced against alien enemies may be applied against Slav noncitizens in a somewhat moderated form, a determined intervention and a direct appeal to the President to remedy the predicament of those concerned will probably be necessary. The American press has given some hints in this respect, and Senator J. H. Lewis is doing his best in this direction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
