<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-02">Feb. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Editcr Assails Hcarding of Foodstuffs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-02">Feb. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">EDITCR ASSAILS HCARDING OF FOODSTUFFS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.4--Even he who does not feel the high cost of living is interested in the agitation carried on in various quarters and in the methods used by the agitators, as well as in the investigations promoted by various authorities. An overwhelming majority of the population is hit by the high cost of foodstuffs, and people are seeking to find the causes of it and to provide means for the stabilization of prices.</p>
   <p>Cold-storage warehouses are now being accused as the main contributors to rising costs. These investigations are directed by a Chicago alderman has contributed his bit by an ordinance to prohibit the storage of foodstuffs for more than sixty days, after which period they must be destroyed.</p>
   <p>In order to understand the opposition to storage warehouses, let us consider their real purpose and examine the actual practices of the owners of these <pb facs="5418478_2_1596.jpg" n="2"/>establishments.</p>
   <p>In one respect cold-storage warehouses have a beneficial effect, for they preserve the surplus food produced in times of abundance; they are legal commercial establishments and necessary elements in our present economic structure. Capitalists, however, eager to utilize them for gain, are abusing to the utmost the opportunity offered by the storage of food. The owners of the warehouses are accused of keeping foodstuffs from the market in order to boost their prices. That such charges are perfectly well justified is obvious from statistics based upon detailed information, according to which fourteen million pieces of beef, six million pieces of veal, twenty-five million pieces of mutton, and fifty million pieces of pork are being hoarded, so that every inhabitant of the United States has one piece of meat which is being kept in storage for him, and besides this an extra pieces of meat is in storage for every family.</p>
   <p>But other foodstuffs also are stored in incredible quantities. For example, twenty-five million fishes are kept in storage for a full year before they reach the market. Add to this 1800 million eggs, 130 million pounds of <pb facs="5418478_2_1597.jpg" n="3"/>poultry, and fruit valued at fifty million dollars. Finally, there are immense quantities of potatoes, onions, preserves, butter, and cheese; the value of these latter foodstuffs is estimated at a hundred million dollars. There are in the U. S. about 558 large storage warehouses, containing, according to surveys, foodstuffs worth three billion dollars.</p>
   <p>If this quantity of food were in the hands of the people or of a people's government, or if there were any laws for the protection of the interests of the people, cold storage would be of great benefit to the community in times of scarcity; but the manner in which it is now being abused is nothing less than a crime against the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
