<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-30">Dec. 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[The New Year]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-30">Dec. 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[THE NEW YEAR]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The New Year of 1915 is being anticipated by us with greater hopes than any of its predecessors. In the first place we hope that it will bring the European war to an end; that it will liberate the European nations from militarism, which, like a vampire, has been sucking their life's blood and finally driven them into a horrible spree of murder and destruction without equal in the history of the world. We trust that it will fulfill the ardent hopes of our nation and of our brothers, the Poles, both of whom desire to enter the company of free nations, able to decide and work for their own future. We trust that the Serbian nation will be fully compensated for all it had to suffer at the hand of the Germans and Hungarians, all it had to sacrifice in order to achieve and keep its liberty, by uniting all its national groups in one strong state whose national and economic life will continue developing under the most favorable <pb facs="5418478_2_1417.jpg" n="2"/>conditions. In other words, we are hoping that the coming year will bring about a complete regeneration of Europe, a regeneration based on a firm foundation, on justice to all nations, and particularly to all Slavic nations.</p>
   <p>For ourselves, for the United States, we hope that the New Year will bring jobs to millions of industrial workingmen and women; that it will bring real prosperity; that it will make it possible for our President Wilson to maintain peace for our Republic in spite of the traps and intrigues by which foreign diplomats and some of our local people try to lure the United States into a general war. If the New Year will fulfill all these hopes, it will assure for itself a foremost place of honor in the annals of history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
