<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Twelfth Ward in the Red Cross and Savings Stamp Drive</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE TWELFTH WARD IN THE RED CROSS AND SAVINGS STAMP DRIVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of workers for the Red Cross and War Savings Stamps drive was held last afternoon in Mr. Anton J. Cermak's office and presided over by Mr. Cermak, chief bailiff of the municipal court and chairman of the Czech section of the American Red Cross. All precincts of the Twelfth Ward were represented. Mr. Cermak explained the purpose of the meeting in the following remarkable speech:</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen: I have called you for a discussion of the best ways and means to be employed in the Red Cross and War Savings Stamps drive. First come the Stamps; when we finish, the Red Cross campaign will be joined by us. There is no one among you, I am sure, who does not comprehend the necessity for this work. There is no one among you who would not show his love for the homeland by doing all that is in his power. First, I should like to read to you some of the letters from our boys on the fighting front. They demonstrate <pb facs="5418478_2_0536.jpg" n="2"/>clearly that our soldiers are very well aware of what we are doing here in their behalf and of the joy with which we are following their activities."</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermak read the letters, from the contents of which it is evident that our soldiers are closely informed concerning what is being done, and also that they feel proud of being thought of so much. There is a grave undertone in some of these messages, particularly when the hardships of war are mentioned. All of them, however, reflect confidence in ultimate victory for the just cause. In them all grateful mention is made of the Red Cross which gives our soldiers motherly care. Some of the letters breathe humor, such as one describing the pleasure which the soldiers derived of phonographs while they were still in training camps. The letter continues:</p>
   <p>"Now, however, we have different music. Bullets whistle past our ears, and shrapnel plays merrily around us. By golly! It's beautiful music when a fellow gets used to it."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0537.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After reading [the letters], Mr. Cermak proceeded:</p>
   <p>"This week is left for the Stamps. Well, go from house to house, from one family to another, and try to obtain a signed pledge [from each person] that he or she will buy stamps regularly for the rest of the year. Next week we shall begin to work for the biggest and noblest institution in the world, the Red Cross. We wish to point out to you that the main object will be not to acquire members but to obtain contributions from good-hearted, well-meaning people. We are sure to receive abundant contributions. Indeed, every one knows today what the Red Cross means. It is the second mother of our soldiers, the mother that follows them everywhere they go. It cares for them in the camps over here; it cares for them on the voyage across the ocean; it cares for them on the battlefield; it nurses them in hospitals; and it watches over them when they become prisoners. The Red Cross aids many soldiers' families and seeks to alleviate their sufferings. No one can fathom how badly the Red Cross is needed, or how important it is for us to support it. In Russia the soldiers are tightly bound before operations, since there are no <pb facs="5418478_2_0538.jpg" n="4"/>anaesthetics. In German camps, again, prisoners are so badly starved that if one of them spills some soup, the rest of them rush to lick it from the floor. The Red Cross steps in in cases like this.</p>
   <p>"If you bring these conditions before the eyes of our people, they will not skimp. Chicago needs six millions this time. Let's see to it that our people contribute the lion's share."</p>
   <p>Judge Harry Fisher, Alderman James Bowler, and both the aldermen of the Twelfth Ward, Messrs. Joseph I. Novak and Otto Kerner, also addressed our delegates. There will be two more meetings, and a big parade will be held this week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
