<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-04">Apr. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Women in the Foreground</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-04">Apr. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH WOMEN IN THE FOREGROUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our women are in the front ranks in every department of work that tends to help toward ultimate victory over the Teutonic enemy. They work in this way in behalf of the campaign for the promotion of the Third Liberty Loan sales. They will, with good reason, be proud of the work they accomplish and will do honor to our entire nation.</p>
   <p>Leaders among our women met in Placek's hall, Kedzie Avenue near 24th Street, yesterday to discuss plans for an organized campaign. The meeting was well attended, and all the ladies declared themselves willing and ready to accept any assignment, no matter how difficult or wearisome it may be.</p>
   <p>Two women were elected to preside at the meetings, so that two of the largest Czech women's organizations could share the honor. Mrs. Marie Smrcek, president of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Czech Ladies' Unity), and Mrs. Marie Liska, president of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Sisterhood Unity), were <pb facs="5418478_2_0610.jpg" n="2"/>elected; Mrs. Anna Zenisek was chosen secretary. A press committee and a speakers' committee were formed. The members of the latter will visit meetings of our women's organizations and appeal for aid and co-operation in the drive.</p>
   <p>After this necessary item of organizing had been disposed of, Messrs. Anton J. Cermak and A. J. Salat, representing the Czech section of the campaign, were introduced. The former, the chairman of the Czech committee, has done preliminary work to make the results of the third campaign still better than those of the first two campaigns. Both speakers made ardent appeals which were wholeheartedly applauded.</p>
   <p>In accord with plans followed hitherto, the ladies will work independently while forming a part of the Czech section. The agitation for the Third Liberty Loan will officially open next Saturday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
