<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-27">Mar. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[Activities of Czech Alderman]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proper Taxation of Large Corporations and of Rich People in General is Recommended by Alderman Anton J. Cermak in order to Bring Our City Out of Financial Distress.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-27">Mar. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[ACTIVITIES OF CZECH ALDERMAN]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proper Taxation of Large Corporations and of Rich People in General is Recommended by Alderman Anton J. Cermak In order to Bring Our City Out of Financial Distress.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Judicial Committee of the City Council held its meeting yesterday, and Chairman Anton J. Cermak grasped the opportunity to express his opinions on where and how our city could open a source of income in order to get out of its bad financial situation. He said, "Our present method of taxation is faulty. When the Board of Assessors adjusts the taxes of a utility corporation on the basis of an assessed valuation which is less than one-half of the assessed valuation made by another public taxing body for the purpose of determining the tax rate, then it is about time to stop. Also, many owners of downtown real estate and rich residents are permitted to avoid paying their just share of taxes. This is being practiced by the Board of Assessors and by the Board of Review. I do not assert that any of them is <pb facs="5418478_2_0234.jpg" n="2"/>knowingly helping the rich people to avoid paying their just share, but somewhere in the system there is a leak which must be stopped." The alderman further added that in a few days he would submit to the Judicial Committee a new plan, which will be properly elaborated upon before the county assessing bodies begin to work in the spring.</p>
   <p>Great aversion is being manifested by the aldermen over the manner in which the Finance Committee is raising the wages of city employees. Alderman John Toman, who in a past meeting introduced a motion to appropriate the sum of four million dollars, to be used to raise wages, announced the following: "My intention, and I suppose the intention of every alderman who voted for this motion, was to raise the wages sufficiently of the lowest paid people and to use the balance only to raise the wages of the higher paid men. Instead of this, it now appears that the Finance Committee is taking care of the big men first, and only what is left will be divided among the little ones."....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
