<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemians in Serbia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter to the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIANS IN SERBIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter to the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Skoplja, Serbia, Dec. 16, 1914.</p>
   <p>"Dear Friends of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau): There is not a day when I am not busy from morning to night. There is a great deal to do in the hospital of which I am the head. We are taking care of thousands of wounded, and since the wounds are frequently of a most terrible and dangerous character and we are having very good results, I am greatly pleased and so are all those official Serbian bodies which are familiar with our work.</p>
   <p>"Also, the military authorities have only praise for us. We are all satisfied and contented, and the discipline in our group is excellent. We also treat our brothers from Bohemia, that is, Bohemian prisoners of war of whom <pb facs="5418478_2_1408.jpg" n="2"/>there are thousands here in Skoplja. Indeed, there are entire regiments of them here who have deserted or refused to fight, because as Slavs they would not help the Austrians in a war against their own brother Slavs. Whatever you read about the bravery of Bohemian soldiers fighting in the Austrian army is false.</p>
   <p>"The prisoners of war are comparatively well off here. Every artisan, every student of medicine and of other sciences has plenty of opportunities to prove himself useful. Many prisoners of war work in the country and have fairly good food and lodgings, although there is a need for many things, particularly now during the cold winter months. One must not forget that we are in a small country that is now going through its third war and consequently is rather exhausted.</p>
   <p>"The Serbs are fighting with enthusiasm, and the mocking Serbian peasant keeps on winning his battles while the mendacious Vienna press deludes its readers with stories about the atrocities allegedly perpetrated by the Serbian Army.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1409.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I have taken the trouble to find out for myself about these matters and visited with a good friend of mine, a higher army officer in Nis, and what I learned was just the opposite. It is the Hungarians who behave like demented demons whenever they enter a Serbian house. They have been raping Serbian women and girls, cutting off their breasts, torturing old men, and mutilating the wounded. Such are the members of the chivalrous, noble Austrian Army.</p>
   <p>"Can you, then, be surprised that it is they whom the Serbians are particularly after? I have a number of them here in the hospital, and, just the same, they are treated with exemplary courtesy. Thousands of renegades of Cheb [German Eger] and other 'German' children of Bohemian mothers here maintain that they are Bohemians. The word 'Bohemian', and particularly 'Sokol', has a mighty good sound here.</p>
   <p>"Concerning other matters, I shall let you learn them from the enclosed letter <pb facs="5418478_2_1410.jpg" n="4"/>written by a Bohemian who is now a ranking officer in the Serbian Army and is fighting in the front lines. I am sure the letter will be of good service to both our and the American press.</p>
   <p>'In the trenches, Dec. 13, 1914.</p>
   <p>'My dear friend: I learn from the papers that a Bohemian-American medical expedition has arrived under your direction in order to help the thousands of our brave men who are wounded in battles against our worst enemy.</p>
   <p>'They are fighting like lions, helping the Serbs to defend their dear, beloved country. I know you will be most keenly interested in hearing about the behavior of Austrian Slavs, especially our Bohemians.</p>
   <p>'I was in the battle at Cer. This was the first great battle after the enemy had crossed the rivers of Sava and Drina and had invaded Serbia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1411.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>There were Serbian [composed of Austrian Serbs], Bohemian, German, and Hungarian regiments. The Austrian government, knowing well the "enthusiasm" of her Slavs, had put the Serbs and Bohemians into the first lines, behind them the Hungarians, and behind these the Germans with machine guns. And now, forward! If the Serb or the Bohemian tried to back up, he was shot from the rear by his own "comrades", and still he would not go ahead against his own brothers. But he had to; he was forced to go--but was shooting over our heads, and when the first chance came, he surrendered. And thus the Bohemian regiments were surrendering, the same as the 75th Infantry Regiment from Jindrichuv Hradec, the 88th Infantry Regiment from Beroun, the 28th Infantry Regiment from Prague, the 11th from Pisek, the 36th from Boleslav, and the 6th and 22nd "Huntsmen" Regiments from Bohemia surrendered in the most recent battles. The boys came over with a merry song on their lips, happy that they had gotten rid of Austrian tyranny and were in free Serbia, which received them with open arms.</p>
   <p>'I shall write you more later on; the shooting is starting again....Best <pb facs="5418478_2_1412.jpg" n="6"/>regards, and the heartiest welcome to your men.</p>
   <p>Yours, N. N., Lieutenant.'</p>
   <p>"This letter will remove some of the doubts concerning the behavior of the Bohemian soldiers in the war against the Slavs.</p>
   <p>"After the great victories of the Serbian Army, there were many wounded and many dead. At times I work late into the night, and during the day again. Ours is a brave group. There are thousands of wounded men here, and the majority of them are Bohemian. They are getting along well and are being treated even better than that. Indeed, they have nothing to complain about. Some of them, however, and mostly members of the 'educated' classes cannot seem to understand how it was possible that Austria got a 'licking' from the small Serbia and how her men are 'kicking and squawking to beat the band, even as prisoners of war.</p>
   <p>"Much more could be done here if you fellows at home would get busy and start <pb facs="5418478_2_1413.jpg" n="7"/>collecting medical material, such as cotton, gauze, bandages, and other such goods for the wounded Serbians.</p>
   <p>"We do not need any money, but medical material is completely lacking; the country is one huge hospital, full of graves, full of orphans. But they do not get disheartened. There was much joy everywhere yesterday because the Serbs have retaken Belehrad (Belgrade).</p>
   <p>"A Japanese medical group is also here, and we are expecting another trained nurse from New York who should arrive one of these days. What medical material we brought over from Chicago and New York is all gone by now. Get busy, therefore, and start collecting right after the receipt of this letter. Get in touch with the Serbs and other Slavs in Chicago, and work together to help our brothers in their need. You can order the stuff by wire in New York, and from there it can be sent to Athens, in care of the Serbian minister, and for the American-Bohemian United Red Cross. The minister will see to it <pb facs="5418478_2_1414.jpg" n="8"/>that the material is forwarded to Skoplje, to the barracks of the engineers, where we have our hospital. Our hospital flies a Bohemian, an American, and a Red Cross flag. I am running this hospital myself, and I have the rank of a major. Believe me, at times I do not know what to start doing first.</p>
   <p>"Greetings to all,</p>
   <p>"Dr. J. Rudis-Jicinsky"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
