<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-23">June 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Czech Warriors</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-23">June 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CZECH WARRIORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Literary Digest, one of the most widely read of English language weeklies, printed in the latest issue a group photograph of our Czech volunteers in the 223rd Canadian battalion. The picture and necessary information had been supplied by the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance. The editor of the Literary Digest wrote under the picture:</p>
   <p>"In spite of oppression by Austria, the Czechs have proclaimed their allegiance to the very principles for which we too are fighting. It is reported by newspapers that extremely violent rebellions are occurring in the Austrian army. The commanding officers dare not send Czech soldiers against the Russians, because the soldiers would instantly go over to the Russians and join with them in brotherly unity."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0890.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The London New Europe announces: "The Czechs have joined the Allies....The Czechs of America are not restrained from proclaiming their ideals openly, and they aid the Allies wherever an opportunity offers itself.</p>
   <p>The New Europe also mentions the Czech National Alliance and the Bohemian Review, whose editor, Dr. Jaroslav Smetanka, has supplied the Literary Digest with information. The recent proclamation of loyalty to the United States, a formal manifestation of the sentiments of the Czech National Alliance representing the Czechs, is also given prominence in that American periodical.</p>
   <p>The page devoted to us by the Literary Digest will prove an excellent medium for disseminating information on our aims and efforts to America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
