<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-06">Feb. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Send Your Soldier Boy to the Theater--"Smileage" Will Make it Possible</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-06">Feb. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SEND YOUR SOLDIER BOY TO THE THEATER--"SMILEAGE" WILL MAKE IT POSSIBLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Here is an opportunity to show your goodheartedness. Here is the way to make your brother, cousin, or good friend feel that he is not as far away from you as he thinks he is. You can prove that to help defend one's country does not mean relinquishing all the pleasant things in life.</p>
   <p>"Smileage" means entertainment, recreation--it means a visit to the theater. Large theaters have been installed in each of the sixteen camps of the United States Army and National Guard. Each of them is full of first-class attractions. There are not only lectures, music, solo performances, and humorous programs, but also vaudeville and moving pictures. Actors, directors, and producers are giving their services for mere daily wages, at the smallest possible expense to the Government.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0656.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Your boy can enjoy a one-dollar or two-dollar performance for only five, ten, fifteen, or twenty-five cents.....If you want him to go to the theater, a "Smileage Book" will get him in. A "Smileage Book" with twenty coupons costs one dollar; one with one hundred coupons costs five dollars.</p>
   <p>Buy one today and send it to your soldier! The certainty that you think of him will heighten his enjoyment. As soon as you think that he might need another book, send him one!</p>
   <p>Just think how pleasant it is for you to be able to do something like this. Show the boys in khaki that their friends at home cannot forget them. Coupons are better than letters; your soldier boy is waiting. Coupon books are obtainable at the local branch offices of the "Smileage" Committee.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: One full page of advertising space has been donated in a series of issues by Denni Hlasatel Printing &amp; Publishing Company, 1545 West 18th Street, Chicago.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
