<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-26">Sept. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our War Loan Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-26">Sept. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR WAR LOAN COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovak committee for the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign held a meeting in its office at 3342 West 26th Street, near Homan Avenue, last night. Mr. Anton J. Cermak is chairman, and Mr. Joseph J. Salat, secretary. We take pleasure in stating that a large crowd attended. This consisted of bankers, businessmen, tradesmen, delegates from our associations, ward organizations, communities from churches, and a great many individuals. Everyone was fully aware of the high significance of the occasion, and the business was conducted accordingly. There was no idle talk or purposeless debating. Every word had a significance, and every motion was thoroughly considered before it was presented.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermak opened the meeting with a statement of its objective, and closed with these three weighty words: On to work! Without going into detail of the various motions, we may confidently declare that preparations for the campaign were so thoroughly worked out that success is bound to result.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0449.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One point was emphasized as being of prime importance, i.e., that every bond bought by us must be credited to our nationality. We must show to America that Czechoslovaks in addition to being first at the front are also first in the fight here. For this reason, our people should be instructed to buy bonds only from people who will give us credit for them.</p>
   <p>Before buying bonds, convince yourself that the purchase is credited to us. Many cases from the Third Liberty Loan campaign have come to our attention, where our people bought bonds in large numbers, which were credited to corporations and other employers. This should be changed in the present campaign; we shall then surely be among the first in this duty.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Jos. A. Brabec and J. J. Novak, representing aid societies and brotherhoods, reported that activity in their organizations is in full swing. A new system of buying bonds will be introduced: The individual brotherhoods are to make a survey of members who intend to buy bonds. The management of the lodge will then purchase the corresponding number of bonds and sell them to <pb facs="5418478_2_0450.jpg" n="3"/>the individual members. The members will be allowed to pay for them in installments. Some brotherhoods have already begun to subscribe in amounts from $200 to $500.</p>
   <p>Czechoslovaks of the Twenty-seventh Ward are going to meet in the Zdrubek School, 4624 North Crawford Avenue, at 8 P. M. today. Mr. Jos. Ringl is chairman of that campaign group.</p>
   <p>Heads of ward campaign organizations are requesting all who volunteer to work in the campaign to notify them immediately, and thus help to insure its success. Information can be had from the Czechoslovak Bureau, 3342 West 26th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
