<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-25">Nov. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">We Are Just Pretending</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-25">Nov. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WE ARE JUST PRETENDING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is unnecessary to try denying that the neutrality of the United States in this war is merely formal, a seeming one. It is limited to the Government only, which is obliged to act in accordance with international law and does, but that is as far as our neutrality goes. The American public is not neutral and it cannot be neutral any more than a spectator of a gigantic world struggle can who has not water instead of blood in his veins. For America, the decisive factor is not only her sense of justice, which was aroused when Germany violated the neutrality of Belgium, when she sank the Lusitania, when she sinks other ships with hundreds of poor emigrants, women and children, when she shot Cavelle, and committed a long series of other actrocities. Of course, emotions, compassions, play a great role here, but we believe that the deciding factor with Americans who are in <pb facs="5418478_2_1202.jpg" n="2"/>power is principally the interest of our nation and the fear of things that may come in the future. If Germany should win, it would go badly with the United States. But not because we shipped ammunition to the Allies, or because we failed to worship the Kaiser as a god. Retaliation and revenge play no part in politics. There the main thing is self-interest and individual advantage. The United States would be attacked by Germany because we have an enormous trade which Germany would like to take away from us, because we have huge markets in South America, because we sell a great deal to China--in short, because we have a lot of things Germany could make good use of. Somebody may suggest that we are threatened with a similar danger by the Allies, by Great Britain. But that is absolutely not the case. True enough, Great Britain has a big navy, but she would not use it for an attack on a great and powerful country. The British are highly acquisitive, grabbing; they do not mind wars with weak nations, but for a war with the United States they would need a still greater army than they need now. Nobody in America is afraid that there would be a war with Great <pb facs="5418478_2_1203.jpg" n="3"/>Britain. Likewise a war with Russia, or with France, may be safely designated as impossible. The only nation that could attack us is Germany and that would certainly happen if she should conquer Europe and begin to feel cramped within that continent's bounds. There might also be a slight possibility in the case of Japan.</p>
   <p>So, it is not necessary to claim that America is neutral. America's sincere desire is to see Germany thoroughly thrashed, and we are hoping that her desire will be fulfilled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
