<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-08">May 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Straz Osvojenych Calls on Chicago Mayor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-08">May 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRAZ OSVOJENYCH CALLS ON CHICAGO MAYOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A delegation from the Straz Osvojenych (Sentinel of the Liberated), consisting of Dr. F. Iska, Mrs. Marie Blazek, and Mr. Vaclav Janda, presented a letter to Mayor Thompson yesterday containing a recently adopted resolution by the Straz Osvojenych which reads:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The City Hall and its offices have been closed on St. Patrick's day during the past few years, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, By this act special consideration has been given to the holiday of one of the religious sects (sic) or the holiday of one nationality, whereby the citizens of Chicago have been put to disadvantage if they were not members of either the sect or the nationality, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, By the same token, other religious creeds, and ethical or cultural societies, as well as other nationalities residing in Chicago would have the <pb facs="5418478_2_0100.jpg" n="2"/>right to claim the same privilege for their holidays and national celebrations, which would lead to the cessation of work at the City Hall in a great many cases; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved,That we protest against such an unseemly custom and express the hope that Your Honor will resume the viewpoint that all citizens of our city, without regard to their creed or nationality, are equal; that no creed or nationality shall enjoy special privileges, and that no other holidays shall be observed at the City Hall except national holidays, and such other memorable days as have the same significance to all of us, without regard to creed or nationality. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That should our justifiable demand not be given consideration, and should Your Honor disagree with the aforesaid point of view and be disinclined to discontinue the evil custom of closing the City Hall and its offices on St. Patrick's day, a formal request shall be filed with Your Honor to keep the City Hall and its offices closed (in the same way that they <pb facs="5418478_2_0101.jpg" n="3"/>are closed on St. Patrick's day) on July 6, the quincentenary anniversary of the death of the Bohemian martyr and noted fighter for truth and liberty, John Huss.</p>
   <p>"While we, as Bohemians, would very much appreciate such recognition of a great Bohemian figure by our city, as Americans we would retract our request in the event that Your Honor agrees with our contention that no religious sect should enjoy any special privileges, or be given special advantages by the city administration, and that, therefore, the City Hall will not be closed on St. Patrick's day in our city, which is not inhabited by Irish and Catholics alone."</p>
   <p>Mayor Thompson listened to the reading of this resolution with evident interest. When St. Patrick's day was mentioned, he remarked that in view of the fact that St. Patrick's day does not come until March, it would be better to take up this matter at a later date. When he heard the second part of the <pb facs="5418478_2_0102.jpg" n="4"/>resolution, however, referring to July 6, he assured the delegation that their resolution will be given proper consideration, and,in all probability, will be submitted to the City Council. Today's English-language press deals with this matter at considerable length; thus its instigators cannot be denied the credit, if for nothing else then at least for calling public attention to the approaching quincentenary anniversary of the death of John Huss, and to his Bohemian nationality. All Protestants honor this man as one of the greatest reformers, and all educated people without distinction of religion or nationality, remember him as a great martyr who preferred death at the stake to life at the cost of repudiating his truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
