<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-04-04">Apr. 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Election Comment.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-04-04">Apr. 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION COMMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tuesday's election brought many surprises and much enlightenment. Especially among us Bohemians, there was plenty of both. The election of Joe Sindelar as alderman surprised many Democratic politicians, but it did not surprise those who went among the people and observed their attitude. Another surprise was the insignificant number of votes cast for the Social Democratic candidates for the offices of alderman. Only the Bohemian aldermanic candidates carried on honorably, although they did not receive the number of votes that were expected from among their friends. In the tenth ward the socialists made wagers that their candidate would receive over 500 votes. The failure of the candidacies of Mr. Novak and Shabeck was a surprise to many.</p>
   <p>It seems to us that the interest of Bohemians in political matters is dwindling. Formerly there were so many movements, so much debating and such great interest, but this year nothing could be seen or heard.</p>
   <p>Politicians, especially those who make the decisions should takenotice and strive to regain the favor of our people by caring for their wishes and requirements. If they continue to think only of themselves and never about the voters, they will live to see even greater surprises.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
