<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-22">May 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">No Danger in Taxation of Profits</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-22">May 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NO DANGER IN TAXATION OF PROFITS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English language press, which has been strongly advocating the introduction of compulsory service, is getting scared now because of the prospect of high expenditures concomitant with the upkeep of an army of millions. It especially loathes to see the main burden of War taxes imposed by the new law resting upon the shoulders of the wealthy classes, such as manufacturers and merchants. The press equally dislikes the Government control of railroads, the wholesale trade in foodstuffs, etc. All these War measures appear too radical to those newspapers, too radical to be safe.</p>
   <p>The Sunday Chicago Tribune fears that Congress and the administration will introduce regulations which will make the burdens of the War weigh heavier than necessary upon us, and thus retard the advent of victory.....</p>
   <p>The Tribune's apprehensions are groundless. The industrialists and the merchants will not be exposed to any danger if all that they have to do is to let <pb facs="5418478_2_0933.jpg" n="2"/>the Government have a share in their profits. He,who has an income of $40,000 per year, can easily pay ten per cent, and the one with one million per annum can give up seventy per cent without being hurt. The workingman, who is taxed on everything, has the heaviest load to carry.....</p>
   <p>The workingmen and the farmers will have to pay for the War with their blood. If those people who represent an overwhelming majority of the population can part with almost everything they possess, even with their lives, why could not the rich man sacrifice one part of or, indeed, his entire superfluity?....</p>
   <p>No measures for the prosecution of the War, however radical, will endanger the welfare of the rich. The War is an occurrence of a revolutionary character, and consequently, demands extraordinary, revolutionary regulations.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
