<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The First Czech Assistant State's Attorney</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST CZECH ASSISTANT STATE'S ATTORNEY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czech influence in the realm of politics has been felt for a great number of years. Many Czech-Americans have held important offices in the government of this city, county, and state. Mr. Joseph C. Pisa, well-known lawyer, became the first Czech assistant state's attorney of Cook County. He held the position for four years and is active as an attorney-at-law again.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pisa was born in Chicago forty years ago. He comes from one of the oldest Chicago families. His father, Matthew, operated a saloon many years ago on De Koven Street between Jefferson and Desplaines Streets. At that time this neighborhood was densely populated by Czechs, many of whom used to gather in the tavern. Mr. Pisa's grandfather, Blazej, came to Chicago before the Civil War, and together with the Chicago Czech banker, W. Kaspar, founded the first Czech aid society. This society became a great boon to the <pb facs="5418478_2_0247.jpg" n="2"/>early Czechs in Chicago, for many of them were rescued from impending financial disaster by timely support. Mr. Joseph C. Pisa's uncle, a policeman known to almost every Chicago Czech, was one of the leaders in the first gymnastic tournament of the American Sokol societies held in New York City in 1879. Mr. Matthew Pisa and his wife, Ann, were good Czech patriots who believed in sending Czech children to Czech schools; so they made their children attend the Czech St. Venceslas school on De Koven Street, where Mr. Jan Geringer, now a banker, was a teacher. After two years Mr. Pisa had learned Czech grammar and changed to a public school, and then he went to West Division High School on Ogden Avenue and Harrison Street. He was counted among the most gifted and zealous pupils and was graduated with excellent marks. At Northwestern University Mr. Pisa completed his legal training. He was graduated in 1896, although not quite twenty-one years of age.</p>
   <p>After several years of practice at the bar, he went into partnership with Jos. Z. Uhlir, now associate judge of the Municipal Court of Chicago. This connection lasted from 1904 to 1908, when Mr. Uhlir was elected judge. Mr. Pisa married Miss Emily Mares who is known as a gifted painter.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Pisa is a member of numerous Czech societies and is a Knight of Pythias. He is an expert in the real-estate business and special attorney for many of our aid societies. He lives at 3401 West 26th Street. His office is located in Room 1900, City Hall Square Building, 139 North Clark Street, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
