<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-30">June 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">What American Citizenship Means to the Czech Man</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance, Chicago.) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-30">June 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT AMERICAN CITIZENSHIP MEANS TO THE CZECH MAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance, Chicago.) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Mr. Karel [Charles] Pergler, director of the Slovanská Tisková Kancelář [The Slavonic Press Bureau], journalist by profession, devotes his spare time to correspondence in behalf of the Czech National Alliance, of which he is a representative. The Slavonic Press Bureau is maintained jointly by the Czech National Alliance and the Slovak League. Mr. Pergler delivered an address in the English language before a native American audience in New York recently. We present the translation from the English into the Czech.)</p>
   <p>"What does American citizenship mean to the Czech? Surely it does not imply the complete severance of all spiritual ties that bind him to the <pb facs="5418478_2_0883.jpg" n="2"/>nation of which he is a son. I am reminded of the address delivered by President Wilson on the occasion of his presence in Chicago on October 19 last year. 'A man or a woman who becomes a citizen of the United States is neither asked nor expected to give up his love for the old country--to cease to be proud of the nation from which he came. Since the American people represent all nations of Europe, there is no branch of them here who could not boast of a glorious history and tradition.'</p>
   <p>"The Czechs have remained in close communion with the land of their forebears. I am firmly convinced that just for this reason they have brought with them cultural qualities of unquestionable value, just as immigrants of other nationalities can retrace their cultural characteristics to their motherlands. Nevertheless, I am certain that Czechs who became American citizens feel as such not in the legal sense only; they feel American in the very meaning of the word.</p>
   <p>"For, what is nationality? The definition of nationality is, like all <pb facs="5418478_2_0884.jpg" n="3"/>definitions of concepts, unstable and rather hazy. One judgment is as valid as another, and it may be said that Mr. Toynble's definition is just as admissible as others. He defines nationality as 'the will to co-operate'. The Czechs in this country never lacked this quality. I submit a few examples to support my contention; they refer to events of only a few days ago.</p>
   <p>"The instant that war broke out in this country, the Czech National Alliance sent out a call to all Czechs and Slovaks to become citizens and fulfill their obligations toward America. At the same time the Alliance urged the Czechs to throw off the shame of being called subjects of Austria-Hungary, whose history is nothing but a continual assault against her own Slavonic nations. When German violence became unbearable and this country entered the war to preserve democracy for the world, the Czechs answered the call of their adopted country instantly and without hesitation. I hope this statement will not be interpreted as a vain <pb facs="5418478_2_0885.jpg" n="4"/>boast, for it is merely a restatement of a fact. In Chicago for instance, one-half of the volunteers were Czechs and Poles. While visiting in the State of Texas, I learned from official sources that in the town of East Bernard there were twenty-two Czechs among twenty-seven volunteers. I found a similar ratio in numerous other cities of that state. Austin, Texas, I was told, 'must surely be a Czech city, because its streets are swarming with soldiers who speak Czech'.....Thus, the Czechs have won for themselves the prerogative to be called Americans in the most sublime significance of the term.</p>
   <p>"Americanism bears no relation to the land of birth. Those who have grasped the spirit of American institutions are good Americans. They are always ready to sacrifice their lives for the preservation and perpetuation of these institutions and for their development in the broadest sense of the term 'democracy'. In other words, Americanism is primarily a mental relation. We are happy to live in a time when this fact has been expressed <pb facs="5418478_2_0886.jpg" n="5"/>in both words and deeds in a more powerful manner than ever before. Some individuals contend that America is permeated with the philosophy of materialism and is impelled by base motives. Yet, America entered this war for the salavation, so to speak, of spiritual and idealistic values only. America cannot gain much by this war, but it may lose a great deal. Yet, at the same time America is well aware of the peril that lies in a German victory--a victory which would bring about a 'peace of the grave-yard' and would mean the annihilation of the small nations. These small nations may well justify their right to exist by their cultural contributions to the intellectual world. America is aware of the fact that a victorious Germany would mean the abolition of the rights of all nations and individuals to free thinking and self-determination.....For the first time a great nation is engaged in a war not for material gain, but for idealistic possessions. That is the mainspring of American pride today.</p>
   <p>"Democracy in a nation means equal opportunity for all individuals. International democracy spells equal opportunity for all nations, big or small.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0887.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>World democracy cannot stand firmly established as long as discrepancies in equality continue to exist; as long as there are privileged nations. A representative of the Germans of Austria called the Slavonic nations 'inferior nations'. The Magyars who rule Hungary deny the Rumanians, Serbians, Croats, and Slovaks the most fundamental rights; the Magyars entered the war in order to get a firmer governmental grip upon the non-Magyar element of the population under Hungarian rule; in fact, they want to create conditions which would enable them to rule the country as they please.</p>
   <p>"Czech and American ideals are identical. This is the correct attitude for a small nation to take when it openly proclaims its independence; a nation which, after the reformation of John Hus, defended spiritual liberty against all of Europe.</p>
   <p>"You will now understand the significance of citizenship for us, and also <pb facs="5418478_2_0888.jpg" n="7"/>the reasons why there are so few Czech non-citizens."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
