<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-28">Mar. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Woman Suffrage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-28">Mar. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WOMAN SUFFRAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is reported that "General" Rosalie Jones, who led the suffragettes' march to Washington, will soon be starred on a New York vaudeville stage. The ways to such artistic fame are inscrutable; at one time they feature a bully who won a bloody prize fight; at another they star the heroine of a sensational divorce suit; and sometimes they feature a crazy female with efficient walking tools.</p>
   <p>What the suffragettes are now doing will soon be intolerable. News of their exploits is reaching us daily from London, and it sounds like news from a battlefield. They burn public buildings, attack private and government property, obstruct the mails, smash windows, and show a most remarkable ingenuity in inventing new methods of warfare. Now the suffragettes have worked out a plan according to all laws of strategy to <pb facs="5418478_2_1661.jpg" n="2"/>capture a general of the enemy army, Premier Asquith, because he does not show a great deal of willingness to yield to their wishes and dictates. The London police are in a state of permanent mobilization in order to better counteract the warlike activities of these women. They spurn no means by which to stress their demands. At times their means are drastic and brutal enough to remind one of the poet Friedrich Schiller's description of women fighting in a revolution:</p>
   <p>"....then women hyenas became,</p>
   <p>For whom engendering terror is just a pleasant game."</p>
   <p>It is a regular women's war which no doubt surpasses in its vehemence the well-known "war of maidens" in Bohemia after the death of King Premysl, when Vlasta and Sarka became as prominent as Mrs. Pankhurst and Mrs. Drumond are now.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1662.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There has not been much news from the theater of war in the Balkans lately, and now it is most fortunate that the Fort of Drinopol has fallen. Otherwise the readers of newspapers would have lost all their interest in the Slavic-Turkish struggle and would have centered their interest exclusively in the struggle of the suffragettes, which, in its fury, approaches a regular war. Small wonder, therefore, that recently the suggestion has been offered in England to treat all arrested suffragettes as prisoners of war.</p>
   <p>Cecil Rhodes proposes to deport suffragettes arrested for acts of violence to some distant island where they could give vent to their fury at their pleasure. It is said that police and government authorities are helpless in the face of the suffragettes' riots--some less gallant newspapers call it "a maniacal raving". Putting the women in jail is of no avail, because they go on a hunger strike and finally have to be released. They then leave the jail with a martyr's halo around their heads. They would rather starve than surrender to the enemy. According to Cecil Rhodes, the only <pb facs="5418478_2_1663.jpg" n="4"/>solution is deportation--the same as in Napoleon's case....although in any other way we should refuse to compare Mrs. Pankhurst with the great general who, as far as we know, never gave a thought to woman suffrage.....</p>
   <p>Both the British and our own suffragettes claim all the rights of men, but principally an equality in political rights--suffrage. Apparently they believe that once they are admitted to the polls, England or America, as the case may be, will become a paradise.....They claim that so far, women have been men's slaves; that they have been excluded from all public activities, and therefore unable to show their talents and abilities. As soon as they are liberated and get full equality with men, they will prove that they are as good as men or even better.</p>
   <p>But we know that many branches of human endeavor have been accessible to women since antiquity, and it does not seem that they have made a great success of them. For instance, the field of music has always been open <pb facs="5418478_2_1664.jpg" n="5"/>to women everywhere, but we have yet to hear of a Mozart, Beethoven, or Dvorak in skirts! The same principle applies in literature; and according to some statistics, twenty per cent of European women are active in literary work, or at least claim to be. The fact is that writing is an obsession with many of them, but we are sorry to say that they do not produce anything that would move the world.</p>
   <p>We fear that it would be the same with women sitting in parliaments. Woman's nature is not fitted for crude and rough public life, especially life in the political arena. This is entirely a man's privilege, a privilege which women should be happy to have escaped so far. Women of all times and nations have always excelled in the culinary arts, in which we men will seldom become their dangerous rivals. Perhaps it would be far better if they agreed to go on preparing good dishes rather than poor laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
