<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-11">Apr. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Women Keep Faith</title><title level="a" type="sub">Throng Pilsen Park at Meeting for Sale of Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-11">Apr. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH WOMEN KEEP FAITH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Throng Pilsen Park at Meeting for Sale of Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The impressive mass meeting of Czech women, held in behalf of the Liberty bond campaign, was telling proof of their willingness to sacrifice, for which there is a great need in this time of war. The meeting took place in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Park. Women assembled there yesterday under the leadership of two well-known and active patriotic workers: Mrs. Marie Smrcek and Mrs. Marie Liska, who head the Czech ladies' group of the foreign language division of the bond campaign. The meeting demonstrated that our women stand firmly behind President Wilson and his administration. They stand up for the country, not by mere words, but with tireless activity as well. Our women appeared in overwhelming numbers such as we have never seen before in our meetings. The spacious pavilion was literally packed to capacity.</p>
   <p>Shortly after 2 P. M., the hour at which the meeting was scheduled to open, our women, single and married, filed in. They came from all walks of life, <pb facs="5418478_2_0589.jpg" n="2"/>which proves that our people are thoroughly permeated with patriotic sentiment.</p>
   <p>The opening of the meeting was delayed more than one full hour, because the Marine Band from the Great Lakes Naval Training Station did not arrive in time. But when it appeared, finally, it was greeted with frenzied applause which did not subside until the men had taken their places and struck up the first chords of the American anthem. The multitude chimed in with spontaneous enthusiasm. Three more pieces--dashing, peppy marches--were then played by the band, which was to appear at another place later. At 4 P. M. the band played "The Star-Spangled Banner" once more and departed. This finished the orchestral part of the program. A collection was made for the musicians, Mrs. Antonia Cervenka, wife of Mr. John A. Cervenka, president of the Pilsen Brewery, and accredited patriotic worker, giving the initiative to the move. It yielded forty dollars, which was sent in the form of a check to the captain of the Great Lakes section to be used for the musicians' fund, as the men themselves are not allowed to accept private remuneration of any kind.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0590.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Cervenka introduced the first speaker, Mrs. Marie Smrcek, who represents the ladies' Czech campaign division for the City of Chicago proper. Greeting the assembly most cordially, she appealed for the wholehearted co-operation of Czech women. She also apologized for a mistake, as a result of which the name of Mrs. Clara Klaus, a noted worker who was to address the meeting, had been omitted from the program. After an introduction, Mrs. Klaus explained in her own charming manner that it is not only incumbent upon the men, but also upon the women to give testimony of Czech patriotism and good will. She made an ardent appeal to the women to support our Government and be true to this new homeland that has become our second mother. She closed amidst turbulent acclaim.</p>
   <p>Little Miss Sikla then recited a poem appropriate to the Red Cross campaign, for whose benefit she made a collection which netted a handsome amount.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Frank Jedlicka spoke in flaming words which left an indelible impression on all those who were present. He reminded them of the tragedy in which our Czech soldiers were involved on the Russian battlefields. He <pb facs="5418478_2_0591.jpg" n="4"/>invoked the aid of all those who may consider themselves happy, because they are in a position materially to help our Government that demands no more than adaptation to present conditions and liberal subscriptions for the Third Liberty Loan. He declared that by buying bonds, Czech men and women insure the victorious return of our soldier boys, and also the liberty of the soil where our cradle once stood. If our people do their duty here at home, then no one of them, after the victorious homecoming of our soldiers, will have to be ashamed because he could not contribute in the same measure as our boys did, and because he could not perform as great a sacrifice as our warriors to the great work which insures liberty for us and posterity.</p>
   <p>Two songs in the English language were sung by Miss Jenie Fail.</p>
   <p>Genuine regret was expressed by the gathering after Mrs. Cervenka had taken upon herself the task of explaining that Sarah Bernhardt, world famous French actress who had promised to speak on this occasion, was unable to appear because of sudden illness. A delegation had called on the artiste in the <pb facs="5418478_2_0592.jpg" n="5"/>Congress Hotel the morning of the meeting. They were informed that she felt fatigued after the long journey to Chicago and had caught a serious cold, so that her physician forbade her to leave her apartment for at least one week. The actress assured the delegates that, although she was prevented from being among the Czech people in person, her heart would be with them. She asked that her sincere greetings be conveyed to the Czech people, together with her conviction that ultimate victory will also be a victory for the Czechs.</p>
   <p>After this information, which visibly impressed the gathering but did not alleviate its disappointment, Mr. Anton J. Cermak, introduced by Mrs. Cervenka, took the floor. Mr. Cermak, chief bailiff of the Municipal Court, is one of the foremost workers in the Liberty bond campaigns. His address was short and contained terse information on how and where subscriptions may be applied for and secured. He laid particular stress on the opinion which authorities in Washington will form of this meeting and of all the future work still to be performed by the American Czechs. The effects of the efforts exerted by the Czechs here in support of the United States and the Allies will be felt <pb facs="5418478_2_0593.jpg" n="6"/>at the final peace negotiations, when those presiding will feel morally obligated not to forget the Czechs and to act for the establishment of independence for the old Czech homeland.</p>
   <p>This speech was followed by a song recited by Mrs. Matus, after which Mr. John A. Cervenka gave a broad view of the war and the bond campaign, and explained why it is our sacred duty to support President Wilson. The speaker presented, by way of analogy, a vivid illustration of what this war really means to us. He compared our soldiers in the field with miners who work in a pit, stricken by a catastrophic explosion, which clogs and chokes the shaft. Those above the ground must volunteer to rescue the buried ones and pull up the salvage. They must drag at the rope together, as if they were one single man. We are those volunteers who are holding up the rope upon which the fate of our country hangs--the rope is our army.</p>
   <p>Recitations by little Miss A. Sramek and Mmes. Stoces and Cervenka closed the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0594.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The absence of Sarah Bernhardt is easily understood when one considers her age, her grave malady, and the fatigue which follows long and strenuous travel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
