<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-06">Aug. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">No Elevated for Blue Island Avenue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-06">Aug. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NO ELEVATED FOR BLUE ISLAND AVENUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Feeling was running high among our people when, some time ago, it became known that an elevated line was to be built from Harrison and Halsted Streets on Blue Island Avenue up to 22nd Street. The structure would have disfigured the appearance, and destroyed the business, of our best street, aside from the certainty that it would have completely ruined real-estate values. It would have made another Lake Street out of our main thoroughfare.</p>
   <p>The plan originated with the Traction Commission, which was to submit the solution of the transportation problem to the committee which, in turn, was to report to the City Council. The matter was to be voted on at the next election. The business associations of the neighborhood appeared before the transportation committee a number of times, always lodging the most vigorous protest against the plan. After several months of hard work, their objections finally produced results.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0165.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Frank J. Bílek informs us that the part of the proposed ordinance concerning Blue Island Avenue is to be stricken out. Aldermen Klaus, McNichols, Bowler, Powers, and Cullerton, have accomplished this, aided by protests from citizens. The committee acknowledged that the particular branch was necessary for the development of the elevated system, true enough, but recommended that it be built either east or west of Blue Island Avenue. In those locations, however, too much private property would have to be expropriated.</p>
   <p>The proposed ordinance in its amended form has been placed before the City Council, which body, of course, cannot make it a law until the voters have passed on it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
