<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Liberty Loan Campaign</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LIBERTY LOAN CAMPAIGN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first day of the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign met with full success in the City of Chicago, and particularly in the wards peopled with Czechoslovaks. The Tenth Ward, for example, sent in a report to the main Czechoslovak campaign office at 3342 West 26th Street, headed by Mr. Anton J. Cermak, stating that at least $200,000 worth of bonds were sold in the Tenth Ward on the first day. The reports are, however, incomplete, according to Mr. J. A. Brabec, head of the campaign in the Tenth Ward. Similar encouraging news is arriving from other Czechoslovak districts, indicating our people will not only be the first to fill the quote, but will over-subscribe, and so do better than residents of wards much richer than ours.</p>
   <p>Subscriptions in the main office exceed those of all others. This is only natural. The office is located in the Twelfth Ward, which is the largest Czechoslovak settlement in Chicago. Many of our fellow countrymen from outlying districts went there <pb facs="5418478_2_0454.jpg" n="2"/>to buy their bonds. Some of our smaller communities have no Czechoslovak campaign office. Czechoslovaks came from Pullman, Kensington, Grand Crossing, the Thirty-fourth Ward, and other sections, for the explicit purpose of purchasing their bonds from the Czechoslovak central office, to ensure that their subscriptions will be credited to the Czechoslovaks. These considerations contributed to the fact that, in our main campaign office alone, over $75,000 was subscribed in one single day, Saturday. According to advance reports, more than $250,000 was subscribed in the Twelfth Ward. This figure is expected to be considerably augmented after complete accounts of the activities of workers in places of business, theatres, etc., arrive. Businessmen on 23th Street alone have sold over $40,000 worth.</p>
   <p>Our aid societies and brotherhoods are also acquitting themselves in a very satisfactory manner. The Homan Brotherhood, for instance, announces its subscription figure at $2,000.</p>
   <p>Mr. O. Kostner, head of the campaign committee of the Thirty-fourth Ward, reports <pb facs="5418478_2_0455.jpg" n="3"/>a minimum subscription figure of $240,000 for his section. This figure will, in all probability, prove to be a low estimate, but Mr. Kostner does not wish to be too optimistic.</p>
   <p>Czech women have declared that they will work as hard as possible to make the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign a pronounced success. As the first step to that end, they called a meeting at Vojta Naprstek school, on Homan Avenue. Representatives of our women's clubs and other associations appeared in large numbers, Mrs. Marie Smrcek, presiding, explained the purpose of the meeting. Mrs. Klara Klaus and other members spoke. They decided to take subscription sheets and bonds and start their selling campaign immediately.</p>
   <p>Campaign propaganda in the Eleventh Ward is being conducted by Mr. Ferdinand Svoboda, at 1808 South Ashland Avenue. All true Czechslovaks there are expected <pb facs="5418478_2_0456.jpg" n="4"/>to respond spontaneously. Mr. Svoboda is invoking the national consciousness of his fellow countrymen, and expects them to help in the campaign work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
