<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Outstanding Czech-American Lawyer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN OUTSTANDING CZECH-AMERICAN LAWYER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some of our fellow-countrymen still labor under the impression that their interests in case of need will be best served when they seek help from other nationalities, whom they seem to be convinced are superior in conscienciousness or ability to the people of our own blood.</p>
   <p>This holds true particularly concerning affairs transacted in the legal profession. Yet it is a well-known fact that there are lawyers among our people who are excellently qualified in every respect. One of the foremost of these is Mr. Anton Zeman, who enjoys a reputation as attorney in both civil suits and criminal cases. His name has appeared in the Czech and the English language papers innumerable times, and frequently in cases of unusual public interest. A large number of persons, in critical moments of their lives, have obtained most efficient aid from Mr. Zeman; naturally he can boast of a multitude of grateful friends.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1749.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the remarkable cases in Mr. Zeman's practice was the one of Jan Siska, who was accused of an abominable attack on Mary Daley, 1147 N. Franklin Avenue. The overwhelming evidence against the defendant resulted in his conviction by a jury before Judge Kersten of the Criminal Court. The well-known Czech club Prazaci (The Boys from Prague) hired Mr. Zeman, who started one of the most ardent and pertinacious defenses in the history of the Criminal Court. The defendant was granted a new trial which, after a brilliant plea by Mr. Zeman, resulted in acquittal by a jury before Judge McKinley. At the banquet given by the club Prazaci in honor of Mr. Zeman the exonerated man thanked his counsel with tears in his eyes; the club presented the attorney with a diploma.</p>
   <p>Another signal success crowned Mr. Zeman's exertions; it was the case of Michael Bradshaw, 2002 W. Hastings Avenue, who was charged with the murder of Policeman McTighe; Mr. Zeman won an acquittal, thus retrieving the young defendant's good name, and restoring him to his mother.</p>
   <p>During the labor trouble of the year 1915, when garment workers figured <pb facs="5418478_2_1750.jpg" n="3"/>prominently, six of these persons were accused of having slugged and killed a strikebreaker. Mr. Zeman, together with Clarence Darrow, won the case over the strenuous efforts of the State's Attorney to bring about a conviction. In the case against the Czech-American Josef Hurtak, who was arrested by the police as the murderer of another Czech, Jaroslav Dvorak, Attorney Zeman succeeded in establishing the fact of selfdefense, so that the Coroner's jury did not turn Hurtak over to the Grand Jury; and his release followed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zeman has made a name for himself in many more cases, involving a great variety of charges, such as arson, incest, rape. Equally, in the realm of civil law Mr. Zeman has handled many cases with success. A large percentage of the divorce cases in our Czech-American community are entrusted to him. He lives with his wife Emma at 2612 S. Springfield Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
