<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-17">March 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Politics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-17">March 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN POLITICS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We believe that every citizen, who in recent years, took the slightest interest in local politics, will agree with us, if we say, that Bohemian politics have thus far failed to achieve the success to which it is entitled by reason of its strength. It cannot be denied that the Poles, who thus far can not boast of such strength or influence, have managed to gain greater benefits than we have attained.</p>
   <p>Let us consider, for example, last year's County elections. Local Democrats, who were trustingly supported by the Bohemians, ignored their assistance completely in the convention, and only after long entreaty was citizen Stajner graciously accepted on the party ticket.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now they are again guilty of such a mistake. Although, the Poles are represented on both township tickets, the Bohemians were not given even the smallest office, yes, not even a clerk-ship, which in the past has always been reserved for them. There were plenty of candidates in the field, and we believe that all those who sought a place on the ticket were as capable as any of those who received the nominations. The convention did not even hesitate when it came to the request of the Bohemians, and worked out the nominations as smoothly as if there were no Bohemian element in the Party.</p>
   <p>The nomination for alderman in the 8th Ward can also be considered as an intentional snub for the Bohemian Democratic group. Even though a Bohemian was nominated, and, as we belive he is a capable citizen so that Bohemian citizens could be fully satisfied, nevertheless, the defeat of Sindelar was a defeat of Democracy in the 8th Ward, because that ward wanted him nominated, and it did not recommend anyone else.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us examine the achievements of the Irish. They have their own political leaders, whom they trust fully. The words of their leaders are law. They are well organized soldiers, who support the side that offers them certain gains.</p>
   <p>It is possible to expect a like organization on our part. No doubt we could find enough capable leaders among us, who could, before each election, examine the field and know in which direction we should proceed, but the question remains as to whether or not these leaders would be supported as are the leaders of other nationalities?</p>
   <p>Bohemian Democrats are strong enough today to take an important part in the party. It depends on their being able to utilize this strength.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
