<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-03">Apr. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[A Czech's Duty in the War]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-03">Apr. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[A CZECH'S DUTY IN THE WAR]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If you want bo be good Americans, true citizens of the country which you have chosen for your second homeland, you must not forget the nation from which you came and the country in which you were born. The Czech nation is now in the most critical situation of its existence. It may gain everything, but it also may lose what little has been left to it. For this reason, all those who belong to it should exert their efforts to the utmost to help our nation win what we long for and for what thousands of its true sons have already sacrificed their lives. We in America shall do our duty by contributing liberally to the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics of America. We are anticipating one of the greatest enterprises in Chicago Czech history: The Bazaar which will be held in May. Every one of our organizations and every <pb facs="5418478_2_0612.jpg" n="2"/>individual must give it his enthusiastic support.</p>
   <p>Should this Bazaar not turn out as we expect, it would mean undying disgrace for us before the forum of all our fellow countrymen in America, but particularly before our people in the old country who are not frightened even by the worst persecution and gladly offer their lives for the cause. We are asked only for our surplus--for what we can possibly spare. If we do not want to part with this, we shall not be worthy of looking into the faces of decent Czechs. Are we going to let things go that far?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
