<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-31">Dec. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Two Czech Leaders Enthusiastically Welcomed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-31">Dec. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TWO CZECH LEADERS ENTHUSIASTICALLY WELCOMED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Captain Zdenĕk Firlinger of the staff of the Czechoslovak Army, and Jan Janček, Slovak writer and news editor, came to Chicago last week. They are delegates of the Russian branch of the Czechoslovak National Council. They will confer with our leaders on the extension and further organization of the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday they were welcomed by a multitude of Czechs and Slovaks at a meeting held at the Sokol Chicago Hall. Although the week-end is not a favorable time for demonstrations of this kind, the hall was packed. We have to acknowledge that our brothers, the Slovaks, were in the majority.</p>
   <p>Mr. F. J. Kubec opened the meeting. Then Mr. Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary of the Czech National Alliance, expressed the gratitude of the Czechoslovaks <pb facs="5418478_2_0699.jpg" n="2"/>to the sister republic of France for the great political advantages that accrue to us from the creation of the Czechoslovak Army, which France permits to fight alongside her own forces in France. This Czechoslovak Army will guarantee us independent political standing, and at the peace conference of the Allies and the United States it will strengthen our claim to self-determination as a Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>The speaker stressed the duty of the Czechoslovaks in America to see to it that the size of that Army be ever increased. He expressed his confidence that the presence of the two distinguished visitors will materially help enlistment.</p>
   <p>Captain Firlinger, who is a young man, then took the floor. On the uniform of his army he wore the cross conferred upon him for bravery in action. His striking personality evoked great applause. Greetings from our brothers in Russia and expressions of joy because so many American Czechoslovaks are doing their duty formed the introduction of his message. The spirit of the <pb facs="5418478_2_0700.jpg" n="3"/>American Czechoslovaks, he continued, is especially refreshing now, when Russia, of which so much has been expected, is undergoing a crucial political and economic test. The American Czechoslovaks, the speaker declared, deserve wholehearted thanks from the fighters in Russia. The latter have suffered unexpected reverses, true enough, but they firmly believe in the ultimate success of their arms and in an overwhelming victory of the Slavs.</p>
   <p>When the war broke out, Mr. Firlinger said, the Czechs felt instinctively that they could not fight their Russian brothers.....</p>
   <p>When Firlinger left, the Czechoslovak Army had about thirty thousand men in eight regiments. It had its own artillery and all necessary technical equipment. By creating this Army, the speaker pointed out, we have given distinct proof that we are against Austria, and that we want to live. Serbians and Rumanians joined this Army. The Czechs and Slovaks are, however, to be credited with having conceived the original idea of its creation. The Army is supported by the "national head tax", which is self-imposed by the <pb facs="5418478_2_0701.jpg" n="4"/>Czechoslovaks. This tax is gladly paid even by the Czechoslovak soldier himself, who is thus made conscious of doing his duty, and is convinced that his sacrifice is not in vain......</p>
   <p>Captain Firlinger's address was enthusiastic, and the audience responded with frenzied applause. We regret, however, that he did not go into detail about the courageous deeds of our Czechoslovak volunteers in the battles of Zborov and Tarnopol, because these deeds belong to the most brilliant chapters in the history of the entire international struggle. Also, had Captain Firlinger given us a truer picture of the actual conditions in Russia, he doubtless would have far better ingratiated himself with his audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jan Jancek, the next speaker, was received with equal ardor. He represents the type of intelligent Slovak who speaks with a pinch of humor even when relating his sad experiences as a prisoner of war. He has been through all phases of the war so far.....He described conditions in Austria-Hungary before the beginning of the World War......After the mobilization, the Slovaks felt <pb facs="5418478_2_0702.jpg" n="5"/>as the Czechs had, that they would not shoot the Russians.....</p>
   <p>The audience, by its applause, expressed complete accord with the speakers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rubringer's band played patriotic airs, and the enthusiasm reached a high pitch when Mr. Tvrzický read a resolution that expressed sympathy and loyalty to the sister republic of France. The resolution is to be sent to Washington and from there to the French government. It reads:</p>
   <p>"Czechs and Slovaks of Chicago, at a meeting called by the Czechoslovak Committee on Military Affairs, unanimously passed the following resolution, which we beg you to present to the Government of the Republic of France:</p>
   <p>" 'Czechs and Slovaks in the United States joyfully perform their duty in expressing to the sister republic of France our deep and loyal gratitude for so generously permitting us to shoulder arms with the most glorious army of all times and on a soil most sacred to mankind.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0703.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>" 'In the great battle of democracy, at the head of which stands France, in the struggle of light against the world of darkness, we cannot remain in slavish obscurity. The flaming torch that France threw into Teutonic serfdom illuminates the heart of Europe, our Czechoslovak lands. Its glare travels over the ocean and augurs a better future for the oppressed nations.</p>
   <p>" 'Czechs and Slovaks have participated in the great struggle actively from the very beginning of the war, and if France will make it possible for them joyfully to demonstrate their loyalty to the cause of democracy, they promise eagerly to do their duty on the front, and here across the ocean as well.</p>
   <p>" 'By recognizing the Czechoslovak Army France has demonstrated to the world her historic adherence to right and justice, and her indomitable loyalty to democracy.</p>
   <p>" 'France will mean a second homeland to our fighters, and the soil drenched with their blood will forever be sacred to our nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0704.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>" 'We love democratic France. We love France, the protector of the rights of small nations, the great mother of the oppressed.</p>
   <p>" 'Glory to France, who led the nations, clearing the road for the freedom of citizens, and who today is blazing the path to liberty for the nations! Undying fame to her valiant army and to the entirety of the Franch people! Liberty for Alsace-Lorraine, liberty to the Czechoslovak nation, liberty to all the nations groaning under the Teutonic-Magyar yoke!' "</p>
   <p>This manifesto is signed by Dr. Ludwig J. Fisher, president of the Czech National Alliance; F. J. Kubec, chairman of the Czechoslovak Committee for Military Affairs; Captain Firlinger, representing the Czechoslovak Army; Jan Jancek, representing the Czechoslovaks in Russia; and Andrew Schustek, president of the Chicago branch of the Slovak League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
