<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-02">Sept. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Mass Meeting of Bohemian Men and Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-02">Sept. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT MASS MEETING OF BOHEMIAN MEN AND WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Českĕ-Slovanský Červený Kříž (Bohemian-Slavonic Red Cross) is calling a mass meeting of Bohemian men and women at the hall of the Sokol Pilsen, at 18th Street and Ashland Avenue, for Thursday, September 3.</p>
   <p>The sad news which has slowly been reaching us from our dear old country brings more heart-rending pictures of the conditions into which our old country has been thrown by the outbreak of the European war.</p>
   <p>It must be said, and it may be said with full justification, that the situation of the Bohemian nation is the most tragic: While thousands of Serbs, Germans, Frenchmen, Russians, or Belgians are sacrificing their lives today, they at least have a reason for doing so--they are helping their country. Our brothers, however, are being armed by force, and by force they are driven to slaughter against their own beloved Slavic brothers. Any one of our countrymen who dares to express his feelings toward this terrible situation is murdered without mercy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1515.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this reason, the disaster in our country is much greater, much more horrible than elsewhere, and our duty to save our country from complete distruction is a greater one than that of any other nation. Our goal is: One Million Dollars for the Salvation of Our Country and for the Relief of Her Sons' and Daughters' Suffering! If every one of us will do his duty, our beautiful plan will be realized. We have the sympathy of all intelligent, educated Americans. Some of the most prominent among them are offering us their active help. People like Miss Addams and Professor Henderson will speak to us at the meeting we are calling. Let no one fail to attend, so that our manifestation against the war may be a true and dignified expression of the feelings of the Bohemian people. Let deeds prove our love for our Bohemian motherland.</p>
   <p>Signed: The meeting committee of the</p>
   <p>Českĕ-Slovanský Červený Kříž.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
