<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-08">Oct. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Prepare for Celebration Masaryk to Appear in Official Capacity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-08">Oct. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARE FOR CELEBRATION MASARYK TO APPEAR IN OFFICIAL CAPACITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many crowned heads from various European countries have been visiting here, and have been received as guests by the United States Government, representing the people of this land. We remember that the American press gave attention to these visits, although not more, indeed, than to everyday events. Our big English language newspapers reported, but did not give the foreign guests much space in their news columns, and still less in editorials. An example of this fact is given by the recent visit of the Danish crown prince, who came to our city a few days ago. Our local papers recorded his arrival, true enough, but did no more. In general, they passed over the event with a few flimsy notes.</p>
   <p>In view of this we feel overjoyed, for American newspapers have been assuming an entirely different attitude in regard to the arrival, today, of T. G. Masaryk. He comes from plain people, true enough, but he represents a people whose liberty and independence were lost once, but were reborn in this great World War.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0417.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>News items have been appearing for days stating that the undaunted leader of the movement for Czechoslovak independence--Professor Thomas G. Masaryk, president of the Czechoslovak National Council [recognized as the provisional government of the future independent Czechoslovak State], and commander-in-chief of the Czechoslovak Army in Russia, France, and Italy--will appear as diplomatic representative of the Czechoslovak nation, to open the celebration of the one hundredth anniversary of the induction of the State of Illinois into the United States of North America.</p>
   <p>The local English language press welcomes him with enthusiasm, not only in the news columns but in editorials as well, and in such a manner that they implicitly refer to all Czechoslovaks also, and that is why we are so proud of being thus mentioned. It is, therefore, a duty for Czechoslovaks to extend a most ardent greeting to the man who had to endure many a grievous moment, who suffered from many painful memories, and lived through anxious suspense, before he was able to gain recognition by the highest authorities for the nation from which he came. This was due to his astonishing energy and admirable courage and, mainly,to his <pb facs="5418478_2_0418.jpg" n="3"/>flaming love for his people. This recognition by the most influential authorities constitutes a firm guarantee for the future liberty and independence of Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <p>We are certain that Czechoslovaks will fulfill their duty to Professor Masaryk today, and show their determination and readiness for future sacrifices which the liberation movement will demand of them. Masaryk has been placed at the head of this movement by the people of our old homeland.</p>
   <p>The determination of our people to sacrifice should be of the same sterling quality which radiates from the picture by the Czech-American artist, K. Sarka, bearing the legend "The Rebirth of a Nation," and symbolizing the Czechoslovak nation proclaiming its independence. The picture is reproduced at the head of this column by permission of Leslie's, a weekly magazine, where it was first printed upon the cover of September 28 issue of this year.</p>
   <p>Professor Masaryk is expected to arrive from Washington, D.C., at the Baltimore <pb facs="5418478_2_0419.jpg" n="4"/>and Ohio railroad station, Harrison and Wells Streets, shortly before 9 A.M. A delegation of thirty will extend the official welcome to him. It consists of representatives of the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, the Slovak League, the press, and the arrangements committee, whose members are Mr. James F. Stepina, the Reverend Vaclav (Wenceslaus) Vanek, and Professor Jaroslav J. Zmrhal. Our distinguished guest will, after a short welcoming ceremony, be accompanied to his suite in the Blackstone hotel, from which the Czechoslovak flag will wave during his sojourn. With due regard to the fact that Professor Masaryk will feel fatigued after his long journey, the entire day will be reserved for his comfort till evening, when he is scheduled to address the mass meeting in the Auditorium Theater at the opening of the Illinois State anniversary celebration, which will last one week, and in which this evening is reserved as "Czechoslovak Day."</p>
   <p>Our evening has been arranged by the Czech National Alliance, sponsored by the State Council of Defense and the American Security League. Admission is free. It is expected that the Auditorium will be filled to the last seat, and that an overwhelming majority of the attendance will be composed of Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0420.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Places upon the platform and boxes are reserved. The latter have been bought up mostly by native Americans; the money thus collected will help pay expenses of the celebration. One half of the 300 seats upon the platform are reserved for representatives of Czechoslovaks and Jugoslavs, the other half for prominent Americans. Invitations were sent to all members of the City Council, the State Legislature, and prominent Czechoslovaks.....</p>
   <p>Miss Olga Masaryk, daughter of Professor Masaryk, is expected to come to Chicago. In case she arrives tomorrow, she and her father will be guests of the Union League Club, at a banquet given by members in their honor tomorrow night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
