<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-12">June 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[A Message] to the Czech People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Executive Committee of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-12">June 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[A MESSAGE] TO THE CZECH PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Executive Committee of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the rupture of diplomatic relations between Austria-Hungary and the United States, our hopes for the liberation of the old homeland have risen considerably. President Wilson in his note to Russia declared himself unconditionally for the rights of the small nations and for the removal of Prussian militarism. Guided by these principles our great republic is battling for the same ideals which serve as slogans for our own efforts and endeavors.</p>
   <p>Czechs and Americans of Czech descent are surely fulfilling their duty. It is necessary to lend the republic and the Allies effective financial support.</p>
   <p>We have all gladly joined the Red Cross; now we must do everything in our power to boost the sale of bonds.</p>
   <!-- 5418478_2_0908 omitted, duplicate of 5418478_2_0909 -->
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0909.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Almost every one of our fellow countrymen is in a position to buy a fifty-dollar bond; others can buy a one-hundred, or one-thousand-dollar bond.</p>
   <p>The success of the Liberty bond drive conditions the success of our arms, without which our hopes for victory would dwindle.</p>
   <p>Every Czech businessman, doctor, lawyer, tradesman, or workingman, as well as every farmer, is under a patriotic obligation to buy bonds, to support the government, and so to help democracy emerge victorious.</p>
   <p>The fate of mankind depends upon this victory, and so does the future of our own Czech nation across the ocean.</p>
   <p>All fellow countrymen are urged to buy their Liberty bonds in Czech banks or other Czech places so that our willingness to help the Government will become more conspicuous.</p>
   <p>Signed: Dr.L. J. Fisher, president; J. Tvrzicky, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
