<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-10">Dec. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For America and a Free Czechoslovakia</title><title level="a" type="sub">For the Liberation of the Oppressed Nations under Austria-Hungary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-10">Dec. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR AMERICA AND A FREE CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">For the Liberation of the Oppressed Nations Under Austria-Hungary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow must become a day of paramount importance in the history of the Czechoslovaks in America. All Czechs and Slovaks are expected to take part in the mass meeting which will be held in the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion. They will give testimony to their hopes and efforts and openly proclaim their sentiment as foes of Austria-Hungary, its dynasty, and the German-Magyar clique that rules there. The Czechoslovaks will declare themselves a nation which could not be beaten into submission, even after three years of persecution. They will swear that they are determined to win their liberty and independence at the point of the sword!</p>
   <p>We shall meet again as we did in June, 1914, when we received the information about the ultimatum prepared by Austria and directed against Serbia. On that occasion we protested against the attack on our small brother nation. Tomorrow we shall hail the great republic of America, aligned with the foes of Austria.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0722.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They will--there can be no doubt about that--destroy Austria, remap Central Europe into free and independent states, and remove the dynasties of the Hohenzollerns and the Hapsburgs.</p>
   <p>We could not answer either before the tribunal of history or before our own consciences if we failed to proclaim loudly our intention to fight Austria until a victory is won for rights and justice over century-old oppression and injustice. We owe this to ourselves. Let us not think that what America now knows about us is sufficient, or that we have given America enough information about our efforts.</p>
   <p>Influential political and financial circles in America have learned of our efforts, true enough. This is due to the activity of the Czech National Alliance. We must, however, try to widen our acquaintances and deepen the information about us by perpetual propaganda. This should be done at the earliest possible date.</p>
   <p>Some people are of the opinion that the President omitted to mention the Czechs in his proclamation. Diplomats often decline to reveal the ultimate aims of <pb facs="5418478_2_0723.jpg" n="3"/>their actions. Too much disclosed information might and the enemy and obstruct the prosecution of the war. The President used judgment and prudence in his proclamation in not making special mention of our cause. However, he will not object if we voice our sentiment and advance our claims in a mighty demonstration in which we take a stand against Austria, demanding its dissolution and complete independence for our old homeland, in accordance with the program of our people in Czechoslovak lands.</p>
   <p>The time has arrived when we are in a position openly to take a stand against Austria and its dynasty, and to attack the German-Magyar clique in the most relentless manner.</p>
   <p>The demonstration is due to our nation as well as America. Only by united action can we attract the attention of America and put up an effective claim for our demands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
