<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-03-20">March 20, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-03-20">March 20, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Leading Bohemian citizens, working men, and business men recently signed a proclamation, in which they express their recognition of the work in the City Council of the 10th Ward Alderman, Ed. J. Novak, and at the same time, request him to again seek re-election.</p>
   <p>There were many names on the list and we saw names of persons whose one word is worth more than the long speeches of speakers, who really do not know why they are exciting themselves. On this list are to be found the names of people of solid character and convictions, who certainly are not deserving of being abused and distrusted by political antagonists, as is now happening in various places. Every citizen who signed the proclamation, for Mr. Novak, is convinced that there could not be a more capable candidate than Ed. J. Novak in the coming election, of the 10th Ward, and all will work ardently in order that Ed. J. Novak may be re-elected.</p>
   <p>The Irish of the 10th Ward want to profit by the disagreements amongst the Bohemians, and therefore they will actively support their independent candidate, Gary, who is also a candidate for the long term. This, however, <pb facs="5418478_2_0299.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemian citizens must resist with a harmonious union of their votes for Ed. J. Novak, who has proven himself to be their capable representative. If the Bohemian vote were divided, it might possibly happen that the most Bohemian ward in Chicago would be represented in the City Council by two Irishmen. Certainly our countrymen of the 10th Ward will not allow this to happen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
