<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-17">Feb. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Artists' Club Meets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-17">Feb. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ARTISTS' CLUB MEETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A resolution was passed in the meeting held February 13, 1918, by the Czechoslovak Artists' Club of Chicago. It reads:</p>
   <p>"At the meeting on February 11 of the conference of the Czech National Alliance it was contended that the Artists' Club does not take any interest in the movement for the liberation of Czechoslvak lands, and that it seems to pay no attention to the Czech National Alliance at all. In view of this we declare:</p>
   <p>"l. The person who made these charges either does not know much about the liberation movement, or he suffers from a defective memory. The Artists' Club was the first among Czech associations in America to turn its coffers upside-down and place their contents at the disposal of the Czech National Alliance. This occurred on November 25, 1914, during an early phase of the <pb facs="5418478_2_1729.jpg" n="2"/>movement when money and good examples were needed most.</p>
   <p>"2. This Artists' Club gave evidence of its attitude when it was the first Czech-American body to make Professor Masaryk an honorary member. This was at a time when others would not have dared to take action, since they were afraid to displease certain parties.</p>
   <p>"3. The Artists' Club helped wherever an opportunity presented itself. Among recent examples we point to the Allied Bazaar in the Coliseum, the Bazaar of the Czech National Alliance in Pilsen Brewery Park, and the exposition in connection with Bohemian Day at the University of Chicago. The members of the Artists' Club devoted many weeks to preparations for these events. Besides this, the members gave their services innumerable times to further liberation.</p>
   <p>"Witness the work done by our members in creative arts! Our artists drew and painted what was needed by the Czech National Alliance. They donated or loaned their creations for the Bazaar. The Club's music section was always <pb facs="5418478_2_1730.jpg" n="3"/>ready to furnish Czech music for other nationalities and the general public, especially at the Bazaar of the Czech National Alliance. Our literary members eagerly placed their pens at the disposal of the movement for the independence of Czechoslovakia from its very inception.</p>
   <p>"The Artists' Club protests against the charges of laxity, and at the same time refuses to accept the subvention of five hundred dollars awarded to the Club without its consent. Whenever it needs any money to support the action for independence, it will obtain it from its members. The members do not ask for any subvention granted without their anticipation or knowledge. They are, as they have been on countless occasions, ready for sacrifices in behalf of the cause so dear to all of us.</p>
   <p>"Those who spoke disparagingly of the Artists' Club should publicly state where they were when the Club arranged a Shakespeare festival in the Pilsen Sokol hall for the benefit of starving artists in Bohemia. This event ended with a deficit, in spite of the splendid program, just because of the <pb facs="5418478_2_1731.jpg" n="4"/>pitifully small attendance.</p>
   <p>"For the Artists' Club: V. E. Dibelka, president; Fr. Horlivý, secretary; Václav Jiskra, treasurer."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
