<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-16">Apr. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Recruits in Farewell to Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-16">Apr. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITS IN FAREWELL TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Loučení...." (Parting causes grief), the translation of the old folk song did not come to the surface when the first Czech and Slovak volunteers said good-bye to their friends and relatives in the halls of Sokol Havlíček-Tyrš yesterday afternoon. They prepared for their trip to the training camp in Jefferson Barracks, Mo. The enthusiasm made it clear that they were following the voice of their conscience and full of hope to contribute to the upkeep of the ideals of mankind. Their spirit bolsters up the conviction of others, thus promoting enlistment. It is expected that more young men will join the recruits before they leave tomorrow, so that the number will be raised to at least one hundred and fifty.</p>
   <p>The big court hall began to be filled with throngs of men and women as early as 3 P. M., the time set for the beginning of the friendly gathering <pb facs="5418478_2_1038.jpg" n="2"/>arranged for the parting defenders of the country. The latter were, of course, the center of attention. They were those who had enlisted on or before last Saturday to form the nucleus of the Czecho-Slovak regiment of volunteers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Doležal, vice-president of the Czech Sokol Community, welcomed the gathering. Mr. R. J. Pšenka, editor of the Denní Hlasatel, pointed to the duty of all citizens to stand up for the country which is threatened with war, and has been maliciously offended by infringement upon the rights of the entire nation. Mr. Smiřický spoke in the same trend. He was followed by Sergeant Vosátka, United States Army, who invited lively participation in the process of bringing the Czecho-Slovak regiment up to its war strength.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Havlíček-Tyrš (gymnastic association) distinguished itself by <pb facs="5418478_2_1039.jpg" n="3"/>presenting the volunteers of the Czecho-Slovak regiment with their own gorgeous banner which will be carried in today's parade, and then taken to Jefferson Barracks. In case the regiment sees action on the European battlefields, the banner will be there to inflame the fighters to deeds of bravery with which the history of the Czech people is replete.</p>
   <p>During the ensuing informal entertainment, more men signed up for enlistment. The result of the evening as to new enlistments must be called gratifying, and will no doubt serve as an inspiration for further enlistments, which in turn will call the attention of the authorities to our action. This has been demonstrated already by the honorable mention received by the Czechs from Captain Kenney, United States Army, chief recruiting officer for the Chicago district.</p>
   <p>During the entertainment which closed at 12:30 A. M., another patriotic <pb facs="5418478_2_1040.jpg" n="4"/>enterprise was initiated, which proves that the sense of duty is being fully grasped also by our girls and married women. The idea of creating a women's auxiliary unit leaped from the ranks of the Sokol Havlíček-Tyrš. This auxiliary will care for the immediate needs of the recruits, and see to it that they will be remembered with gifts of love which shall be presented as tokens of gratitude for the volunteers' patriotism and readiness for sacrifice. The auxiliary unit will meet in the next faw days. It will be composed not only of female members of Sokol organizations, but all women willing to lend their helping hands for the best of the cause, may join.</p>
   <p>(Follows list of names of recruits who signed up last night.)</p>
   <p>Those who enlist in the Pilsen district station not later than 3 P. M. today will be sent along with the first contingent of Czech recruits to Jefferson Barracks, Mo. They will have to be fitted out with the necessities while at camp.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1041.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The march will start from the home of the Sokol Havlíček-Tyrš, on Lawndale Avenue at 6 P. M., sharp. Mr. Husa's band will head the procession which will take its way through 26th Street, Blue Island Avenue to State and Harrison Streets, and then to the railway depot where a military train will be waiting.</p>
   <p>It is interesting to read the news reports about the recruiting activities of the Czechs and Slovaks. The Chicago Herald writes in a semi-humorous and yet earnest tone: "The United States Army Recruiting Station, 526 South State Street was stormed and taken by seventy members of the Czech Sokol Havlíček-Tyrš, the largest Czech gymnastic organization in Chicago. The recruiting officers offered no resistance, but instead welcomed the invaders as the most grateful and fertile material for the Army. Captain Kenney declared that these members of a Sokol organization are only the <pb facs="5418478_2_1042.jpg" n="6"/>forerunners of several thousands of Czechs. He said: "Their response to my appeal to their patriotic sense of duty is highly gratifying." No better commendation could be given the Czechs.</p>
   <p>Similar ardor, according to assurances given us by the authorities, has swayed other Czech settlements in America. The office of the Bohemian National Alliance, where the Czech Military Committee conducts its business, is receiving inquiries from a great number of Czech communities outside of Chicago. Information is sought about the necessary steps for the acceptance of applications for service in the Czecho-Slovak regiment. When these inquiries were conveyed to Captain Kenney, he declared he had sent three telegrams to Washington for special instructions. No answer has arrived at his offices as yet, presumably on account of congested business in the capital. In view of the convincing proofs that the Czechs are ready to fight for their new homeland, Captain Kenney was prompted to do all in his power to bring about a permit from Washington <pb facs="5418478_2_1043.jpg" n="7"/>to make specific enlistment for service in the Czecho-Slovak regiment an easy affair. If accepted, the Czech volunteer will simply have to state his desire for service in that particular regiment, where-upon he will be sent to Jefferson Barracks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
