<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-01">Apr. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Societies in War Time</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-01">Apr. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES IN WAR TIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If War with Germany should break out, there is no doubt that a great number of our young fellow-countrymen, members of our societies, will join the ranks of the army as volunteers. Some have, perhaps, joined the militia or the regular Army already. It is not known to us how many of them belong to aid societies; the latter will probably furnish a large contingent within a short time. For the time being the interest of members of aid societies does not seem to be so important as it was in the Spanish-American War. The interest will surely grow once War is really on. Many of the aid societies, if not all, have a by-law in their statutes to the effect that a member joining the Army will loose the benefits until the time of his return, then he may become a member again. This condition was already discussed when there were preparations made for a military expedition into Mexico. Some of the aid societies announced that said by-law would be abolished. This patriotic decision was favorably commented upon. We do <pb facs="5418478_2_1097.jpg" n="2"/>not know whether this proclamation is still held as valid by the societies. A new announcement by the societies is expected when War will become a fact. It is evident that if many members joined the Army, the reaction upon the financial foundation of the various societies could not be underestimated. But no society would hesitate to make sacrifices which in this case would have a patriotic character. No society would take away the benefits from the brethren who joined the Army when the United States issues the call to the arms.</p>
   <p>The state legislature will probably pass no law detrimental to the financial standing of the aid societies. There is only the danger that it may curtail their right to arrange dances and other entertainments according to their traditional custom. A proposed law forbids the sale of alcoholic beverages where four or more persons gather to dance, and where admission is paid in any form, be it even for the wardrobe only.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1098.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The bill is devised with the utmost cunning and subtlety that it would destroy the very spirit in which our entertainments are given and stultify the good purpose of the affair. The prohibitionist's proposal is known as the Barbour bill. The United Societies took energetic steps toward its defeat, and so the danger for our entertainments seems removed, for this year, at least.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
