<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-15">Mar. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Farewell to Our Volunteers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-15">Mar. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FAREWELL TO OUR VOLUNTEERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another contingent of our volunteers left Chicago last Tuesday night to go to France, there to join the Czechoslovak Army. The farewell given for them by our community was exceedingly cordial, and hundreds of men and women did everything to make their last hours here as pleasant as possible.</p>
   <p>Mr. Urban, a saloonkeeper, invited the soldiers to his place, Springfield Avenue and 26th Street, for refreshments, where genuine hospitality had been extended to volunteers prior to this occasion.</p>
   <p>The glee club Kosy hired a band of union musicians which played at Urban's saloon and also accompanied the soldiers on their march along 26th Street to Kedzie Avenue. Mr. F. J. Krbec, president of the Czechoslovak military committee, and Mr. J. Tvrzicky, secretary of the Czech National Alliance, spoke at Mr. Urban's tavern.</p>
   <p>The ladies of the Slovak singing club Lipa (Linden Tree) brought smoking <pb facs="5418478_2_0619.jpg" n="2"/>supplies. There were scenes of both deep emotion and exuberant joy.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ludwig Fisher, president of the Czech National Alliance, and Vojta Beneš, its organizer, with other officials of that organization, joined the parade before it came to a halt at Kedzie Avenue and 26th Street. The soldiers then stepped into automobiles and were taken to the railroad station. The vehicles had been kindly furnished by Messrs. Zeman, Kotka, Jos. Kaiser, and the Pilsen Brewing Company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
