<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-03">June 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Reason for Apprehension</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-03">June 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">REASON FOR APPREHENSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is one matter that gives us reason for considerable apprehension. We believe that the war, which has revealed such wide differences of opinion among various immigrant races in the United States, cannot fail to have a serious effect on the future. It is perfectly true that all immigrants except the Germans (not even all the Germans), the Hungarians, and a certain small fraction of various national groups of uneducated people from parts of Austria are in the same camp in which sensible Americans are found; that is, they are absolutely against the Germans, as our President likewise has been with the entire administration, ever since the commission of the terrible crime of sinking the "Lusitania". But let us not be deceived! The American Germans are a very powerful element. They are very loud in voicing their dissatisfaction and disagreement with the President and the administration; they are working and <pb facs="5418478_2_1344.jpg" n="2"/>disseminating propaganda, and you see them everywhere displaying their extreme partisanship for their "Vaterland". They do not even shrink from committing crimes, such as dynamite attacks and the falsification of passports--anything to help Germany in her struggle to dominate the world.</p>
   <p>Do you think that all this will have no consequences in the future? Do you think that the Germans will bear the brunt of it? We are afraid that such will not be the case. All immigrants will bear the brunt of German crimes. When the war is over, the fight against immigration will begin again, and we may be very certain that everything that happened in the war will be laid upon the immigrant's back. All that the Germans have done will be charged against all immigrants. The Americans who dislike immigrants will remind the public of the unreliability of foreigners and will recall their partisanship for their kinsmen in their old homes, their disloyalty to their new country, and their antagonism to ward the Government at Washington. The fact that all this applies only to the Germans will be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
