<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-28">Apr. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">More about Patriotic Fervor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-28">Apr. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT PATRIOTIC FERVOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We wrote about American patriotic enthusiasm in this space one week ago. We are reverting to that subject because the present time lends itself fittingly to an elaborate discussion. We have been deploring a certain coolness among the native American youth, which is evident enough to fill anyone from our ranks with embarrassment. It is not that which we read about or hear of the native American, but it is the very slow rate at which the American youths enlist for service which astonishes us. The recruiting office, and even the War Department itself, furnishes data which show clearly that more than two-thirds of the volunteers hail from <pb facs="5418478_2_0981.jpg" n="2"/>the strata of the immigrant populace; that these very same volunteers for the most part have been members of the Sokol (gymnastic) societies. The official reports also prove that the majority of the volunteers have been in the United States only a short time and that many have only taken out their first naturalization papers. We are sure that these numbers will not be subject to a more favorable adjustment up to the present day. It will be surprising if they should not appear in still more glaring disproportions to those of the last week.</p>
   <p>It certainly is worthwhile to think of the causes why the American youth of unmixed American blood still turns a deaf ear to the appeal of our President, of our Government, and of our country itself, in a moment <pb facs="5418478_2_0982.jpg" n="3"/>when the need of support is most pressing. We do not think that in order to find the cause we will have to turn unto a path either too long-winded or steep. It is the haste, pure and simple, the characteristic trait of American life, which finds its climax in the chase after the almighty dollar, and which leaves its mark everywhere. It can be traced primarily into family life which is not only one-sided, but very superficial also. There are very few factors which would tend to instill into the soul of a child moral conceptions of a deeper character such as should be the essence of patriotic and national enthusiasm. After a child has attained the proper age, it is sent to school where it is accorded almost the same bringing up. If any American consciousness is awakened in the child, it is purely that of the ego, and based on selfishness and lust for profit. It may also take its support from thoughtless fanaticism, which for its very thoughtlessness, becomes sterile and empty.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0983.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The roaring and whistling into which the American youngsters are wont to burst at the appearance of the flag cannot be accepted as an emanation of patriotic sentiment and national enthusiasm, because that clamor lacks any profundity and significance. Equally, the noise made at the sight of marching soldiers seems flimsy to us.....The temperament of American youth can be awakened only when personal interest is at stake.</p>
   <p>The bringing up of Czech youth in the old country moved along deeper lines. The oppression to which the Czech and other Slavonic nations were exposed created a reaction which expresses itself as a sense of self-preservation. The American people are not subjected to any similar pressure which would threaten their existence. For this reason, Americans exhibit indifference even toward questions of paramount importance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0984.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We would not object to patriotic clamor at the sight of the flag, or the pictures of Washington, Lincoln, or Wilson; we only Wish that Americans acclaiming their great men would consider the sacrifices made by them, and that they would become aware of the obligations toward the country. Americans can best demonstrate their sentiment by enlisting for service, in the United States Army.</p>
   <p>The American youth should try to be an example for the immigrants, and should not allow the contrary to pass by slackness in enlistment."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
