<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-15">Feb. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"Beware of Foreign Agitators!" Editor Warns</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-15">Feb. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"BEWARE OF FOREIGN AGITATORS!" EDITOR WARNS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Large numbers of German and Magyar agents are now roaming the country spreading false news and trying to bring about a panic in the country. These agitators are obviously disseminating rumors of an impending calamity in the form of a bankruptcy of the whole structure of our land in case of hostilities against the central powers should be started by the United States. By confusing the mind of the people, they hope that the public will take an antagonistic attitude toward a declaration of War on the part of the United States.</p>
   <p>They proclaim that Uncle Sam will confiscate money deposited in the banks, and use it for the purpose of conducting the war. This is a lie deserving to be punished, for the United States is different from Austria, <pb facs="5418478_2_1144.jpg" n="2"/>where now, in the third year of the war, the government intends to confiscate, or "requisition," fully one-third of the people's property in order to be able to carry on the War.</p>
   <p>Now, what may happen in Austria is not possible in the United States, where the property of every citizen is protected by the law. In fact, the money deposited in well conducted state and national banks is safer than anywhere else.</p>
   <p>We are dwelling with emphasis on this point, for if people should allow themselves to be misled into withdrawing their money suddenly, they might really precipitate a "run" on the banks, thus endangering their own deposits. People should, therefore, take counsel and refer the Austrian agitators to their proper places. Whenever approached by them <pb facs="5418478_2_1145.jpg" n="3"/>in the manner described, they should secure their names, and addresses and report them to authorities or to our office. We cannot warn our countrymen enough not to lend an ear to the seditious talk of the German and Magyar agitators, who want to lure them into financial transactions which will unfailingly prove harmful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
