<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">For Bohemian Prisoners of War</title><title level="a" type="sub">Article by the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FOR BOHEMIAN PRISONERS OF WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Article by the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodne-Socialni Vzdelavaci Beseda J. V. Fric (J. V. Fric National-Socialist Educational Club) of Chicago has decided to undertake the following activity. The Beseda will send once a week to begin with and twice and three times a week later on to all places in Russia and Serbia where there are Bohemian prisoners of war a large number of Bohemian-American newspapers which support the political movement for Bohemian independence. The purpose of this activity is to furnish them with news from the old country about those from whom they have not heard anything since they were taken prisoners, make them acquainted with the developments in the war in which they as prisoners of war are, undoubtedly, keenly interested, and give them general and truthful information on all major happenings having relation to the world struggle. It is to be supposed, that all information which they may have about these matters has come to them through Austro-German channels from <pb facs="5418478_2_1388.jpg" n="2"/>biased sources and is, therefore, one-sided and tendentious. The last and most important purpose is to tell them about the movement for political independence and the liberation of Bohemian lands, inaugurated by Bohemians living overseas.</p>
   <p>Through this activity, the Beseda, under the auspices of which huge demonstrations have been organized, and which has other important patriotic deeds to its credit, hopes to stir up our politically indifferent compatriots and strengthen the hopes of the politically-minded masses of our nation, who expect that the present European war will result in a turn for the better for the Bohemian cause. The news thus received will, no doubt, make particularly happy all those whose political convictions caused them to surrender.</p>
   <p>If the French government is finding it necessary publish a special newspaper of war, in which they get truthful information about the events of the war connected with it our responsibility is greater still toward our fellow countrymen who have been taken prisoners, and who, as we know from their <pb facs="5418478_2_1389.jpg" n="3"/>letters, suffer terribly because of their uncertainity and their complete isolation from the world. The American-Bohemian newspapers will be a soothing balm for their aching hearts and their martyred minds, and they will do a great deal of important propaganda work among them.</p>
   <p>This activity, which will be performed on the largest possible scale and very conscientiously, will involve some expense. The members of the Beseda have made the voluntary pledge to contribute to this expense by paying ten cents a week or more, if it should be found necessary. In fact, this movement has already been started, and newspapers have been sent to fifteen places, all that could be identified as internment points--in Russia and Serbia. Since it can be foreseen that they will be asking for all sorts of information and, no doubt, also for the forwarding of their letters to friends in the old country, we request those who favor this idea will help us with practical suggestions and small monetary contributions. From time to time we shall publish reports of our enterprise in our newspapers. Letters and <pb facs="5418478_2_1390.jpg" n="4"/>money should be addressed to Joseph J. Nosek, 2322 South Clifton Park Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
