<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-12-16">Dec. 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Skimping on Local Improvements.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-12-16">Dec. 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SKIMPING ON LOCAL IMPROVEMENTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4, Col. 2 - The streets of our Bohemian districts are neglected. That is a well known and oft repeated tale. Who is to blame for this? No one else, except the people, living on these neglected streets, whose property lies there. These people are against themselves. Various repairs require an outlay, which every one fears, as the devil fears holy-water. Nevertheless any such expense would be repaid many-fold in the course of a few years. The better the condition of a street, the more it is visited.</p>
   <p>Whether anyone is walking, or riding, or otherwise following his calling, he always picks the best streets, where he does not have to plod through mud, or jump over broken walks, streets which are properly illuminated and full of life, where one need not have any fear of being waylaid. Businessmen on such streets enjoy greater patronage; benefits are derived not only by the businessmen, but by the property owners as well, because these in turn can ask higher rentals from the businessmen who make more profit.</p>
   <p>For this reason, the businessmen and property owners should work together for the improvement of the streets in our Bohemian districts. What is needed here <pb facs="5418478_2_0133.jpg" n="2"/>is for the businessmen and property-owners to form improvement clubs, in which discussions could be held as to what kind of improvements should be undertaken to ameliorate our district.</p>
   <p>Pilsen has been remarkably neglected of late. Especially our sidewalks and street pavements have become notorious. Now, however, the walks are being improved a little, because they had become practically impassable. The pavements, however, especially on 18th Street, remain untouched. It seems as though the property owners did not insist on repair because of the considerable expense involved for them.</p>
   <p>They are making a mistake, however, because in this way they are killing the street and stifling its business. It would please us indeed, if we saw several prominent businessmen and property owners rise and begin an energetic movement for the benefit of an organization which would endeavor to secure needed improvements. The Pilsen district is destined to become a great business center for all Czechs and of the entire neighborhood, but it must not be neglected; its advantageous position and conditions which will fulfill this destiny must be enhanced so as to be fully utilized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
