<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Stand Up for Your Nation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">STAND UP FOR YOUR NATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a time when the whole world stands aghast at what the near future has in store for us; when the clamor of statesmen drowns the thunder of cannons; when new viewpoints are born; when the irrepressible influence of democracy is making itself felt: We, Czechs and Slovaks, follow in suspense the avalanche of rapidly changing events.</p>
   <p>The demands of America and Great Britain as interpreted by their representatives, and the answer expected from the Central Powers--those inveterate foes of democracy--demonstrate that democracy is firmly determined to change the face of Europe entirely. This is to be done upon utterly different principles from those upon which the servants of potentates under the leadership of Metternich, the Austrian, built the Holy Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Autocracy had at that time organized itself to subjugate the Poles, to oppress national entities.</p>
   <p>It is a long way toward peace today, true enough. But today also there is felt in the diplomatic world the unknown power of democracy. Today, when statesmen voice the will of the people (in the Allied countries at least), we, the American branch of the Czechoslovak nation, are straining our eyes and gazing toward the world tribunal--toward the future universal peace conference to which our nation has addressed itself concerning our strife and our rights.</p>
   <p>Although Lloyd George and President Wilson did not specially mention our nation, they guaranteed it the right to a free, unfettered life, even though they did not express themselves as to the form in which this should be materialized. They leave this problem,in fact, to our nation itself to defend its rights before the world's forum in a manner that will best serve its particular interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0674.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the first moments after the proclamation (George's and Wilson's), many of our good fellow citizens began to waver and seemed to have lost that fearlessness which is our heritage from our early protagonists of liberty. Many of our citizens failed to grasp the words of Cavour, eminent Italian statesman, "that the greatest danger to a nation is fear, and that a nation should not harbor any fears concerning its future".</p>
   <p>And we have no fear of this sort! There have been many occasions for fear during these past three years. Our nation at home not only did not become panic-stricken, but progressively stiffened its struggle for independence.</p>
   <p>From the time of the proclamation of Czech representatives in the Vienna parliament up to the present, the radicalism of our representatives, as well as those of other Slav nations, was on the ascendancy and remained unbroken even when Austria, together with Germany, exerted new pressure upon Italy with the result of an at least temporary conquest.</p>
   <p>Our nation has a glorious tradition and a strongly developed sense of duty <pb facs="5418478_2_0675.jpg" n="4"/>toward itself and its future generations. It is conscious of its duty toward those who have shed their blood for it and toward those who are still volunteering for service in the Czechoslovak Army in France and even in the Third Army on the Italian front. We do not fear that such a nation would commit treason against itself, that such a nation would give up its ideal which is approaching realization now, when democracy is knocking over thrones and setting up new governments of the people and by the people.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that our people will understand the proclamations made by statesmen in the past days and will understand that if these proclamations agreed to the independence of Poland, then this consent surely was unavoidable, for the Germans themselves gave the first impulse to the establishment of a Polish state in order to get ahead of the Allies.</p>
   <p>The situation in the case of our nation and of the Yugoslavs is, true enough, more complicated for us and the Allies. Not one quarter of <pb facs="5418478_2_0676.jpg" n="5"/>Yugoslav soil, or ours, is in the hands of the Allies, except a small corner of southernmost Serbia. Neither Great Britain nor America has a single soldier on German or Austrian ground.</p>
   <p>We know, therefore, that Austria will not be crushed by force from the outside, but that the final blow must come from within the monarchy. And independence also does not spring up overnight, but is the result of a great struggle and fight, in which the contestants must not let any scruples lead them to relax their efforts.</p>
   <p>The unification of Italy was achieved after several decades; the independence of Hungary was the result of fights carried on in the political arena, on the battlefields, and on barricades for fully twenty years. The same applies to the independence of Poland.</p>
   <p>Our nation, after three hundred years of oppression, and its Slovak branch, which has been subjugated for one thousand years, have learned patience and <pb facs="5418478_2_0677.jpg" n="6"/>self-denial enough to carry on the fight today when democracy is on the road to victory. We will continue in the struggle for three years, five years, ten years, and longer, if necessary.</p>
   <p>We, the living Czechoslovak branch, have had our share of blood sacrifice during the past few months, contributing to the attainment of ultimate victory in the battle against autocracy. We must stand and shall stand by our nation, by its strength, its character, and its patience, in all times of ordeal.</p>
   <p>We clung to our nation during the entire existence of the American branch of Czechoslovaks. We adhered to it in the first three years of the war. We all are going to stand up for it as long as it is not liberated. Stand up for your nation!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
