<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-17">May 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Many Bohemian Women Voters of the Tenth Ward Democratic Club Participate in Demonstration of May 2</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-17">May 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MANY BOHEMIAN WOMEN VOTERS OF THE TENTH WARD DEMOCRATIC CLUB PARTICIPATE IN DEMONSTRATION OF MAY 2</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[A half-tone, three columns--one sixth of a page, showing a group of Bohemian women voters holding American flags]</p>
   <p>It is well known that a great parade of Chicago women voters took place May 2, 1914. They demonstrated for their right of suffrage which had already been granted them by the State Legislature and Governor Dunne, but the legality of which still has to be decided by the State Supreme Court. This public demonstration was to show their strength and interest in a cause so vital to them.</p>
   <p>All women entitled to suffrage were invited to march in this parade, and a group of Bohemian women who took part is shown herewith. They are members of the Democratic Club of Bohemian Women Voters of the Tenth Ward, a club Which was especially invited by the central committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1645.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman of the central committee is Mrs. Mendel, who at the time of this demonstration was out of town, and whose duties were taken over by three very active ladies, Mrs. R. Chmelik, Mrs. A. Straka and Mrs. M. Ruzicka. They interested enough women and girls to make a very presentable showing in the parade.</p>
   <p>The above picture shows the meeting place at 18th Place and South Laflin Street. In the background is a float filled with suffragettes dressed, as were all the others, in black skirts and white waists. On their heads they wore white caps with blue bands, the white lettering on which read "Illinois". The women marchers are grouped in front of the float, and sitting on a horse to the right is the captain of the parade, Mrs. Steere.</p>
   <p>This group of Bohemian women voters of the Tenth Ward made a very noticeable part of this parade.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
