<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-04-12">Apr. 12, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Politics and Chicago Bohemians.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-04-12">Apr. 12, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS AND CHICAGO BOHEMIANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago - Pokrok Zapadv (Western Progress) reproached Chicago Bohemians, asserting that they take no part in political movements and, thereby, have absolutely no political influence or representation in office.</p>
   <p>The reproach of the above named paper, so far as it concerns the indifference of Chicago Bohemians is in large part true.</p>
   <p>What truth, or, better said untruth, was included in the second part of the accusation, we have proved before, and therefore need not prove again.</p>
   <p>Chicago Bohemians of late have acquired quite satisfactory representation, though the successes were all accidental and brought about by miscellaneous circumstances.</p>
   <p>In comparison with previous years, Chicago Bohemians can boast of fitting representation in public administrative bodies and offices; however, it is not meant thereby that this representation is such as it could be - or shouldbe.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0218.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is an undeniable fact that we could carry a remarkably decisive word in local political circles, a word that would bring us remarkable successes, if we would only hang up our blasted carelessness and indifference, and awaken to a full realization of our own strength.</p>
   <p>For many years Chicago Bohemians carried on the battle to elect a city councilman from their midst, notwithstanding, various previous efforts met with failure. Why? Because there was no strong organization among us, because we went into battle with a powerful foe equipped with money and other advantages, with only insignificant financial means and without the necessary preparation.</p>
   <p>Ordinarily we drummed up two or three meetings during a period of 14 days; about three weeks before election after lengthy pulling back and forth a candidate was nominated, several distributors of election tickets were appointed and that was about all that was done - that was our entire preparation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0219.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whoever wanted to voted; whoever didn't care to vote stayed at home.</p>
   <p>There were many, who for various reasons, mostly personal, did not want to vote for a Bohemian nominee and the result of all this was that our candidate was always defeated.</p>
   <p>It is plainly evident from this that we are not politically mature and awakened. Still more, however, by the circumstance that even at the time when our Bohemian candidate, Mr. Martin Baumruker, was actually elected, we permitted ourselves to be robbed of our victory instead of defending our rights to the furthest limits by lawful means, as it was done that same year, in like circumstances by the citizens of the 14th ward, helping their defrauded candidate Stauber to his place in the council, to which he was entitled.</p>
   <p>Chicago has about 30,000 inhabitants of Bohemian nationality. Such numerical strength could accomplish something, if it were well orgainized, well managed and directed. Now we are in a post-election period and the next very important city election, at which there will be elected the Mayor and other high city officials; we have remaining a full year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0220.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These elections should not find us unprepared, indifferent and careless, as has thus far happened.</p>
   <p>The work of organization of the various Chicago voters should already be in progress, such an organization, as would necessarily do honor, and gain as many concessions as possible for us from both political parties. It is not an impossible task. A little good will on all sides,and continuance of activity toward the purpose throughout the year, would overcome all obstacles, and before a year had passed Chicago Bohemians could appear before other nationalities and demand that which, by all right, belongs to them.</p>
   <p>We want to work for a thorough organization of Bohemian voters, and we hope that, in this work, we shall receive the earnest support of all those favorably minded. This will suffice for today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
