<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-28">July 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Public Bath for "Czech California"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-28">July 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC BATH FOR "CZECH CALIFORNIA"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, a public bath was opened in the building on 24th Street and Kedzie Avenue. This accommodation has been desired by the residents of that district, most of whom are Czechs, for a long time. Aldermen Otto Kerner and Joseph I. Novak deserve full recognition for the efforts they have made to have the building erected. A community center is connected with the bath, and special attention has been paid to supplying recreational facilities for our youth.</p>
   <p>The building has two stories. It occupies a space of 56 by 122 feet and was built from plans made by Charles W. Kallal, city architect. Modern shower baths, a large hall for public meetings, and a smaller one for gatherings, are located on the first floor. It is planned to have one room serve as a reception room, where the two aldermen will spend sometime every day to hear the wishes and complaints of their constituents. A large room on the second floor is to be given over to the Infants Welfare Department under the <pb facs="5418478_2_1691.jpg" n="2"/>supervision of the Board of Health. A waiting room, a kitchen where food for children may be had, a doctors' office, and, finally, a sort of garden or playground under the open sky, covered with canvas, will also be installed on the second floor. The baths will be divided in compartments for men and women.</p>
   <p>It is a beautiful building and will be an ornament to the neighborhood. Health Commissioner A. W. Miller, Mrs. E. T. Johnson, Anton J. Cermak, and Aldermen Kerner and Novak spoke at the opening ceremonies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
