<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-27">June 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Cermak Exonerated</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-27">June 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CERMAK EXONERATED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An assembly of twenty-one judges of the municipal court declared that the charges made by William N. Gemmill, associate judge of the court, against the office of Anton J. Cermák, chief bailiff of the court, were unfounded and that the evidence presented indicated nothing "smacking of graft" in the conduct of the chief bailiff. The vote taken by the judges on this decision was unanimous. Judge Gemmill was not present.</p>
   <p>The chief bailiff's office was not only given a "clean bill of health," but was, in addition, highly commended for the perfect manner in which it handled its agenda.</p>
   <p>Of course Judge Gemmill was not satisfied with the findings of the judges' commission, but dubbed it as "dumb and silly". The judges, he declared, <pb facs="5418478_2_0320.jpg" n="2"/>should have searched for graft instead of covering it. He particularly pointed out that the judges had neglected to swear in the deputy bailiffs called on the witness stand.</p>
   <p>The following incident may show how empty the accusations against Mr. Cermák are: Judge Wells,a member of the investigating commission, declared that Judge Gemmill had told him that the two daughters of Cermák were employed in the latter's office. In answer to this the chief bailiff proclaimed emphatically that one daughter was employed in his office up to the time of her marriage. "My other daughter, Ella, never was on the payroll. If it can be proved that she was, I am ready to retire from office."</p>
   <p>Mr. Cermák announces that he, in turn, will file serious charges against Judge Gemmill in due time and prepares to appear armed with weighty evidence.</p>
   <p>For preliminary details on this case see Denní Hlasatel, June 18, 1917.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
