<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-11-06">Nov. 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Taxpayers Refuse Role of Wall Flower.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-11-06">Nov. 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH TAXPAYERS REFUSE ROLE OF WALL FLOWER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.--The "big shots" surely profess a great love for us Czechs whenever they want us to do something for them, but when they are asked to do anything for us, even when the demand is most justified, they suddenly do not know us. We don't mean the well proven love of the Austrian Government in Vienna for the Czech nation, but we mean the manner in which we Chicago Czechs are being treated by the Republican administration of this city. All of the other nationalities are able to gain recognition sooner than we Czechs, and this refers not only to politics, but other fields as well. Let us thus take a look at the way the Republican Park Board handles our interests. In accord with former planning there are to be created three smaller parks: one in the Pilsen district between May and Fisk streets, Twentieth and Twenty-first streets, one park in the Jewish settlement, and one on the northwest side.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0184.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Logically the building of the park in the most intensively tax paying district should have the preference; that is our Pilsen district. We are informed, however, that the Park Board intends to build the park in the Jewish settlement first with the one on the northwest side to follow; what is left of the appropriation is to go for our park. The majority of the Park Commissioners think that nothing will be left. This time, however, the gentlemen of the Board have made an error in their calculation. They believe that the Jews in the Ghetto and the Poles on the northwest side would set up a vigorous protest if the creation of their parks were delayed, whereas the Czechs in their proverbial patience, which borders on indolence, would not stir. Those politicians are convinced that they can promise us anything and deliver nothing. We have to show them that we are filled up with promises and want action. Our fellow countrymen of the Pilsen district will certainly remonstrate with the Park Board and let them know the opinion of the Czechs in regard to the park issue. The tax payers of the Sixteenth Ward shall be the first to push the matter until the park stands in the midst of our district.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
