<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-12">Mar. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Volunteers Step Forth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-12">Mar. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">VOLUNTEERS STEP FORTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>People engaged in the campaign for the sale of the third issue of Liberty war bonds have become convinced that the best results can be obtained if there is one person appointed for every block to act as a salesman, agent, and agitator. Mr. C. W. Sills, chairman of the agitation committee, issued a call to that effect, inviting men and women to enlist as volunteer solicitors.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt but that there are many energetic and patriotic women among us who will join, so that the results of this campaign will be still more gratifying than those of the previous campaigns.</p>
   <p>The recruiting of these volunteers must be started briskly and carried on vigorously, for April 6 has already been set as the date when the campaign will be in full swing. All volunteers will have to be properly instructed and trained before that time. They will also be supplied with all requisites and paraphernalia necessary for the work. All those who are willing to join this patriotic movement are requested to present themselves at room 407, First <pb facs="5418478_2_0625.jpg" n="2"/>National Bank building, the office of Mr. C. N. Strotz, chairman of the ward and district organization.</p>
   <p>The work required of the solicitors will be done in the evenings, so that it will not interfere with regular occupations. They will approach people who have not bought bonds yet and will remind them of their duty. An office is going to be opened in all districts. Bonds will also be on sale in schools and banks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
