<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-09">Mar. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Bazaar of the Czech National Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-09">Mar. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BAZAAR OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sokol Day! These words speak for themselves. They contain everything that moves the soul of the nation, and also the statement that the Sokols have done their duty. They came by the hundreds; the Havlicek-Tyrs Sokols came corporatively with their banner. It was expected that the Sokols would constitute the bulk of the attendance, but no one fathomed that the crowd would exceed the numbers of last Sunday. The halls of the pavilion in the Pilsen Brewing Company were completely filled by sunset, and more than three thousand men and women had to remain outside without even getting a glimpse of the bazaar, for the police found it necessary to close the gates. No one can remember such a crowd of people - well, it simply was the day for people with sincere Czech sentiment, it was Sokol Day.</p>
   <p>This sincere sentiment became still more evident during the touching <pb facs="5418478_2_1116.jpg" n="2"/>manifestation of fraternal feelings between the Czechs and their French guest. At nine o'clock Roggenbush, the old French veteran and Alsatian, already known to us by his former visits to the bazaar, arrived accompanied by Mr. Pergler, president of the bazaar committee, Mr. Vojta Benes, Mr. Psenka, editor of the Denni Hlasatel. Peals of applause greeted him, and the orchestra burst into the strains of the "Marseillaise" joined by the multitide, which gave expression to their enthusiasm by never-ending calls of "Vive La France!" The veteran, who had bled from seventeen wounds for his country, stood at attention giving the salute, then played on the bugle the solemn prayer of the army for the comrades who had given their lives for liberty, and finally stepped forward to deliver an address in the English language in which he said: "France is fighting today not only for herself but for the future of mankind. I am proud of having been given the opportunity to shed my blood for the Republic. I feel equally happy to see the Czech nation sacrificing herself for the independence <pb facs="5418478_2_1117.jpg" n="3"/>of her country. This shall be a memory indelibly written into my life. I wish to the Czech and the French peoples a complete victory and well-assured liberty."</p>
   <p>These sublime and fiery words were rewarded by thundering calls of "Vive La France," by the throngs, among whom stood many with tear-filled eyes. This certainly was a high point in the history of our bazaar and reached its very climax when brother Sokol [proper name] kissed the French veteran in brotherly emotion.</p>
   <p>During those unforgettable moments it was impossible to develop the financial energies to their fullest measure. Nevertheless, the overcrowded condition granted the evening a pecuniary success which reached the record figure, as did the attendance.</p>
   <p>The Slovak booths, especially those of the Slovak Sokol and of the Slovak <pb facs="5418478_2_1118.jpg" n="4"/>League, seemed to be one of the main centers of attraction in the bazaar. The "Letkvar" and indigenous Slovak drink, and the "Liptovska Brindza," a cheese containing such ingredients as chives, capers, and paprika pepper, were coveted by everyone. At the same time, the election of the Queen of the bazaar was making great strides towards the ultimate results which are to be announced on the last evening of the bazaar, next Saturday.</p>
   <p>The Sokol bazaar evening was an affair of all strata of the people. This will be evident when the "Golden Book" is published.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
