<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-28">May 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Slavs Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-28">May 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE SLAVS PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) a great mass meeting took place in the Hall of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs last night. The meeting was attended by the Bohemians and other Slavs, and it had a three-fold purpose. First, it was a farewell party of Chicago to Mr. Frantisek Kopecky, the delegate of our London colony who has rendered so many valuable services to our cause overseas; then an energetic protest was to be made against the barbarous behavior of the Germans, which culminated in the recent sinking of the Lusitania; and finally, a resolution was to be adopted in which the Bohemians, as a cultural element, would most vigorously protest against feeding our youth such pedagogic wisdom as the article about the German Kaiser Wilhelm which has found its way into the readers of Chicago schools through the efforts of School Superintendent Ella Flagg-Young. The organizers of the meeting have fully achieved their aim. The attendance was enormous, and the speakers' arguments were responded to by spontaneous out-bursts of enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Kopecky was introduced by Editor Tvrzicky-Kramer, and his speech made a very favorable impression on all those present. He spoke about the causes of the present bloodshed which he does not ascribe so much to the commercial expansiveness of Germany as to Germany's desire to subjugate other, militarily weaker nations. He outlined the advantages with which Germany had started the fight: it was fully prepared, had been getting ready for war for decades, and had accumulated an enormous stock of supplies of food and other materials. All this provided Germany with a huge advantage over her opponents. But today the tables are being gradually turned. For another three or four months Germany may hope for occasional successes, but these will be rather the convulsions of a dying Titan than anything that could discourage the Allies. It may be expected that the Allies will have some two million additional soldiers in the field by fall, and another four million by Christmas. This should bring us close to the end of the war. And the end of the war will necessarily mean the fulfillment of the desire of the Bohemian nation--that is, its liberation from the Austrian yoke. All the Allied warring powers reckon with this, <pb facs="5418478_2_1359.jpg" n="3"/>and it is the duty of all Bohemians everywhere, and particularly in America, to give the Allies ample proof of loyalty, friendship, and appreciation. The world must become convinced by public demonstrations, that the Bohemian soldiers have been forced to bear arms under the black and yellow flag against their will and against their own better judgment, and that they remain under that flag, insofar as they do remain, with disgust and hatred.</p>
   <p>For three hundred years the Germans have not had a single good word for us, but now they are praising the Bohemian soldiers lavishly, admiring them greatly for their valiant fight to keep the Austro-Hungarian Empire intact. All that is, of course, rather too transparent, calculated to create the impression that the Bohemians are loyal subjects of the dual Monarchy, an impression we must counteract. This is being done in the first place by the Bohemian voluntary legions in Russia, England, and France.Our men there are happy to fight on the side of the enemies of Germany and Austria and in that way render the most valuable services to the Bohemian cause. The speaker pleaded for full confidence <pb facs="5418478_2_1360.jpg" n="4"/>in the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni. Time will show that the Sdruzeni, by its propaganda work throughout the United States, is doing a piece of good, honest, and eminently purposeful work.</p>
   <p>The storm of applause that followed Mr. Kopecky's speech lasted for several minutes.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Tvrzicky-Kramer. He designated the act of the sinking of the Lusitania as a new link in the chain of atrocities which Germany has been guilty of and will continue committing in the future before the war is over. What means the vile Central Powers are employing appears in the recent order of the old Austrian Emperor in which he says that, in the campaign against Italy, the army should employ any device that may be considered useful in achieving the purpose of revenge against the treacherous country and punishment of it. What such an order really means is easy to understand. Now it may be expected that the same kind of bestialities as the Austrian army was committing during <pb facs="5418478_2_1361.jpg" n="5"/>the invasion of Serbia, when everybody, including defenseless women and children, was being murdered, will repeat themselves in Italy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tvrzicky's comment on Mrs. Young's article about Kaiser Wilhelm, the modern Caligula, which she had smuggled into our children's readers, was equally scathing. The speaker urged all those present to give their full backing to School Board member Holpuch, who insists that all readers containing that article be confiscated and destroyed. In case Mrs. Young wants to present to our impressionable youth examples of great men, why doesn't she use men like Komensky (Johannes Amos Comenius), Hus (John Huss), Jiri z Podebrad (George Podiebrad), or George Washington, or Lincoln. These would be shining examples for our youth to emulate, not the bloodthirsty German despot whom history is certain to condemn as the vilest usurper of other peoples' rights.</p>
   <p>A speech in a similar vein was made by Mr. Biankini as the representative of the Croatians, and Editor J. Palandic for the Serbians, both of whom said a few <pb facs="5418478_2_1362.jpg" n="6"/>sentences also in their native language. Finally the following resolutions prepared by Mr. J. F. Smetanka were adopted.</p>
   <p>Resolution for the Canadian Government</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Many Bohemians living in Canada have been arrested as enemies and interned with other Austrian subjects as prisoners of war, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Bohemian people are Austrian subjects against their own will, having lost their independence three hundred years ago in a war, the whole Bohemian history being a continuous struggle against unceasing German efforts to subjugate the Bohemians and annihilate the Bohemian nation, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Bohemian people have repeatedly manifested their sympathies for the Allies, and expressed their hopes for the victory of the Allies' armies, a <pb facs="5418478_2_1363.jpg" n="7"/>proof of which is the frequent executions of Bohemian men, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Men and women of Bohemian nationality living outside of Austria have unanimously taken the side of the Allies, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Thousands of Bohemians living in England, France, and Russia have voluntarily formed Bohemian legions which fight side by side with the Allies on the Eastern and the Western fronts, where hundreds of them have given their lives for the Allies' cause, in which they hope to find a better future for their native lands, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The British, the French, and the Russian Governments have recognized the Bohemians as their friends and have excluded them officially from the treatment which is being given other Austrian subjects, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Bohemians who live in the United States are doing all they can to <pb facs="5418478_2_1364.jpg" n="8"/>give financial assistance to their brothers in Europe in their support of the Allies, and in their efforts for the liberation of the Bohemian lands, and are also conducting a campaign through which the American public is being informed of the true cause of the enormous conflict in Europe, thus creating sympathies for Great Britain and the Allies; therefore be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, the Bohemian-Americans, request the Canadian Government to realize how unjust it would be to punish the Bohemians for being formally Austrian subjects. We address, therefore, to the Canadian Government the respectful request that it instruct its officers and officials not to treat the Bohemians as enemies in case they speak the Bohemian language and express their sympathies with the side taken by Great Britain and her Dominions."</p>
   <p>This resolution was sent to the Canadian Prime Minister, Robert L. Borden.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1365.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Resolution against the Sinking of the "Lusitania" and the "Reader-Hero" Wilhelm</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The ruthless and barbarian methods Germany has been using in this war have culminated in the piratical destruction of the Lusitania, which resulted in the murder of thousands of nonbilligerents, including women and children, as well as many American citizens, and the Germans living in this country openly defend and praise this terrible crime against humanity, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Many Germans here in America who have sworn allegiance to this great Republic continue to act as subjects of the German Kaiser, and try to promote blind admiration of him in our school system by prostituting (sic) the reading of American children by articles in which the man who ordered the sinking of the Lusitania is depicted as the prototype of chivalry and knighthood, while American great men are neglected in these readers; therefore be it"Resolved, That we, the Bohemian-Americans, agree in condemning the loathsome <pb facs="5418478_2_1366.jpg" n="10"/>crimes committed by Germany in her insane self-admiration and hatefulness, and we shall enthusiastically support our President in such steps as he took when he demanded that an end should be put to such piracy and obstruction of American free trade. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we condemn as indecent and unfair the attitude of American Germans, and also that of a portion of the German-American press, who hold loyalty to the Kaiser and the Vaterland above humaneness and loyalty to this country to which they have sworn allegiance. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That a copy of this resolution be forwarded to the Chicago Board of Education with the request that it discontinue the use of the above-mentioned readers by our Bohemian and other Slavic children."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
