<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czech-Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bureau of the Czech National Alliance of Catholics)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECH-AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bureau of the Czech National Alliance of Catholics)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this critical time, when we feel compelled to draw the sword for the defense of human rights and the liberation of the oppressed peoples by autocratic governments, our duty stands out clearly before us. Our new homeland has received us with friendliness and granted us the same rights as enjoyed by the native citizens. We have found here what our poor old homeland could not give us: liberty. It is not only the sense for the fulfillment of our duty, but the impulse of gratitude which ought to urge us on to come to the defense of the country which is threatened by the enemy now. Our place is under the Star Spangled Banner, the symbol of equality and liberty. Let us not wait until compulsory service is introduced, but let us show that we have grasped the meaning of duty and <pb facs="5418478_2_1036.jpg" n="2"/>intend to hasten to the colors to increase the numbers of those willing to lay down their lives for the country.</p>
   <p>The American government does not demand the services of fathers of families or men upon whom the old folks or relatives, incapable of earning their living, are dependent. In our Czech communities there are, however, thousands of men who are under no such obligations towards their families; they are those to whom our appeal is primarily directed.</p>
   <p>We are daily receiving information about members of Sokol and other organizations who are enlisting for service in the United States Army or Navy. We feel proud of these men, and are requesting their names so that we may publish them.</p>
   <p>Czech National Alliance of Catholics,</p>
   <p>2601 St. Louis Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
