<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-09">Feb. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Boost War-Saving Stamps</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0653</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0653.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-09">Feb. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO BOOST WAR-SAVING STAMPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems that there is not sufficient interest and proper comprehension among our people in regard to the importance of war-saving stamps for the successful prosecution of the war and for the economic life of our country. It is necessary to inaugurate a very vigorous campaign to make our public acquainted with the purpose of these stamps and the advantages which they offer.</p>
   <p>There was a meeting at Troy and 22nd Streets last night, in which fifty of our foremost citizens, businessmen, and professional men took part, and where plans were laid for an effective campaign among our people to boost the purchase of these stamps. Mr. Charles Pflaum, a member of the real-estate firm Pflaum &amp; Ceska, is chairman of the Twelfth Ward branch of the committee for the sale of war-saving stamps. He presided at the meeting, while Mr. I. W. Dvorak acted as vice-chairman, and Mr. Otto Besserer as <pb facs="5418478_2_0654.jpg" n="2"/>secretary.</p>
   <p>Some of the most important subcommittees for the drive were constituted and their presiding officers named. Mr. Thomas Chval is chairman of the group that will visit associations and clubs and spread propaganda among members. Mr. Strauss will take care of propaganda among our businessmen. Mr. Charles Novak is chairman of the finance committee.</p>
   <p>The main efforts will center around the big meeting which will be held in the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion, 26th Street and Albany Avenue, next Wednesday night. Prominent speakers will deliver addresses. The band from the Great Lakes Naval Training Station will play. The meeting is destined to become a magnificent patriotic demonstration of our people's will to contribute in every possible way to ultimate victory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
