<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-05">June 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For Czech Independence</title><title level="a" type="sub">University of Chicago in Enthusiastic Accord with Professor Masaryk's Plan to Remodel Central Europe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0915</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0915.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-05">June 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR CZECH INDEPENDENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">University of Chicago in Enthusiastic Accord with Professor Masaryk's Plan to Remodel Central Europe</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently the American intelligentsia has begun to admit that if the nation is to stand in harmony behind the Administration, it is absolutely necessary that every American fully grasp the gigantic problems constituting the background of the war. We must be aware of the facts in order to put Prussian militarism in the limelight, and so to emphasize the acuteness of its menace before the United States as well as the entire civilized world. If only the American people would grasp the gravity of the situation, the work done by the Administration could be facilitated. Only then can we expect that an effective halt will be put to the mischievous activities of the German spies who are exhibiting almost incredible arrogance and daring, in spite of all our preventive measures.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0916.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The attitude of the American press toward these conditions has become firmer recently, and is known to everyone. The patriotic propaganda of our newspapers will no doubt be supported by our institutions of higher education. The first step in this direction was taken by the University of Chicago from whose faculty of four hundred members a committee was formed. This committee has set itself the task of persuading the adherents of all the foreign nationalities to be loyal to the Star-Spangled Banner, regardless of the land of their birth. An appeal is to be sent ot all nationalities except, of course, the Teutons and their Austrian allies who have been unable to cast off their ludicrous loyalty to the two bloated dynasties. Professor Harry Pratt Judson, president of the University, is the leader of the movement, together with Professor Shailer Mathews, dean of the theological faculty and a well-known friend of the Czech people.</p>
   <p>The first appeal was addressed to the Czechs. A brilliant meeting was held in one of the university buildings. The two professors represented the <pb facs="5418478_2_0917.jpg" n="3"/>University of Chicago which had issued this first appeal. The Czechs had sent several of their most prominent and mature workers in the movement for Czech independence. Among them were Mr. J. F. Stepina, Professor J. J. Zmrhal, Dr. J. F. Smetanka, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, Reverend Vaclav Kralicek, Dr. B. K. Simonek, architect Adolf Lonek, instructor Vojta Benes, Bohus Hak, Otto Pergler, and Anton Novotny. The Czech-American Press was represented by Jindrich Ort for the Denni Hlasatel and R. J. Psenka for the Svornost.</p>
   <p>The group was conducted around the campus of the University and was escorted on an inspection tour through the impressive library founded in memory of William R. Harper, the first president of the University. We were then guided into the cozy dining room where a richly decked table awaited us. A pleasant, jovial conversation soon developed which lasted several hours. During this time the professors gathered information from authorities about the point of view of the Czech-Americans and the Slavonic peoples in this country in general. This discussion greatly enhanced the mutual understanding <pb facs="5418478_2_0918.jpg" n="4"/>between the representatives of the Czecho-Slavonic element and the American intelligentsia.</p>
   <p>The true purpose of the invitation extended to the Czechs was revealed by President Judson in words that made each of us want to press his hand. "The United States entered the war," the president explained, "primarily to aid in the liberation of the small oppressed nations, particularly the Czechs and other Slavonic peoples. The best way to prevent Teutonic aggression is to isolate Germany, first of all from he ally, Austro-Hungary," he continued, and this end will best be achieved by creating several Slavonic independent states. Czechoslovakia, wedged between the two monarchies, will offer the only security for lasting peace in Central Europe. The ultimate creation of a Czechoslovak state therefore appears to be an indispensable necessity, and victory for us in this war is the condition upon which its realization hinges. Much depends upon the attitude and behavior of the people of the United States to whom a task of the highest importance has thus been assigned. The Administration depends upon the loyalty of the immigrants, who <pb facs="5418478_2_0919.jpg" n="5"/>have to be properly informed and instructed in regard to the full magnitude of the German menace. This meeting purports to enlighten the authorities of the University of Chicago on the point of view and the aims of the Czech and other Slavonic-American nationalities," the president concluded.</p>
   <p>It goes without saying that the two professors were fladly given all possible information. Mr. Stepina gave an explicit account of the activities of the Bohemian Press Bureau. This institution is making strenuous efforts to acquaint the American public with the aims and aspirations of the Czechs, although manifold difficulties present themselves; among them Mr. Stepina mentioned the lack of funds, and the resistance which the English language papers offer to our approach. "We have always testified openly to our loyalty to this country, but we were not always given a hearing when it would have been advantageous."</p>
   <p>Professor Zmrhal enthusiastically assured President Judson of the most ardent <pb facs="5418478_2_0920.jpg" n="6"/>co-operation of the Czechs, adding that they merely need some directions for making the best showing possible. "We are," he exclaimed, "loyal, honest Americans! We shall be ready whenever the occasion arises!"</p>
   <p>Mr. Ort, addressing himself to President Judson, stated that the words just spoken by the head of the University of Chicago are identified in every sense with the activities of Professor Thomas G. Masaryk; that the Czech National Alliance has accepted Masaryk's program as its own, as coming from the recognized spokesman of the entire Czech people; further, that "what we are being urged to do now we have been performing faithfully for fully three years, from the very beginning of the war in Europe. The Czech press, our powerful organizations, and the whole branch of our people here in America stand loyally behind the starry flag. They are fighting for the independence of the old homeland and merge their sentiments as Czechs with American patriotism into a most beautiful union."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0921.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Moreover, he pointed to the rapidly thinning ranks of the Czech Sokol societies whose members hastened to enlist for service at the first call for volunteers. He pointed to the organization of a Czech branch of the American Red Cross and the establishment of courses for Czech-American war nurses. "What is going on among us Czech is also being done among the rest of Slavonic nationalities in America. It is the most telling document of their sentiment for which one may ever wish!"</p>
   <p>The two professors listened to these accounts with rapt attention. To lend the information already given a more firm and broader basis, other Czech guests enlarged upon certain points and phases. Vojta Benes gave lavish accounts from his abundant experiences. Although he has been in America only a short time, he has mastered the English language sufficiently to carry on easy conversation with the professors. Dr. Smetanka was another Czech who placed himself at the disposal of the inquiring professors, and he proved himself an inexhaustible source of information. Messrs. Pergler and Psenka also took their turns in this informal but valuable talk.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0922.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The contact made with the University yesterday will be permanent. For this purpose a committee of six was formed, consisting of Dr. Smetanks, Professor Zmrhal, Mr. Vojta Benes, and Messrs. Pergler, Ort, and Psenka. It will probably initiate its activities by arranging for a great demonstration in connection with the John Hus celebration on the occasion of the festival commemorating the unification of all Sokol societies. The Fourth of July will probably be the day set for these patriotic affairs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
