<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-04">May 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Magnificent Manifestation Promoting the Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-04">May 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Magnificent Manifestation Promoting The Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czech-Americans have never forgotten their motherland, and yet they have always shown that they are good citizens of this country who can be relied on in the critical days of war as well as in times of peace. They can be relied on now when the United States needs loyal citizens more than ever. The Czech-Americans have attested to their faith on innumerable occasions, the latest being the response they gave to the call issued by the Third Liberty Loan campaign, and its foreign language committee in particular. The latter has given an opportunity to each nationality of this city to show to what extent it is interested in the welfare of its adopted country. This opportunity was hailed by the Czechs and used in full measure so that the results left no doubt as to the Czechs' sentiment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0557.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, the last day of the campaign, we are in a position to announce that our patriotic efforts have borne abundant fruit. Czech Day was held in order to stimulate our people and interpret their sentiment. The activities began early in the morning. The Czech settlement was richly decorated with American and Czech colors. We have, with much satisfaction, established the fact that in the Czech settlement almost every house was decorated in one way or another, giving the neighborhood a festive appearance, and contributing very much to the spirit of the day.</p>
   <p>The main features of Czech Day were the grandiose parade, held in the evening, and the magnificent gathering of our people in the Pilsen Brewery Park. The parade started at Crawford Avenue and 26th Street, moving along 26th Street to the park. It was composed of workers of the Third Liberty Loan campaign, soldiers in uniform, recruits in civilian clothes who left for training camps the same day, members of the recruiting commission, and sokol men, women, and children. There was, of course, plenty of music <pb facs="5418478_2_0558.jpg" n="3"/>accompanying the march. The queue of the procession was formed by countless decorated automobiles. Spectators lined the sidewalks leading to the park.</p>
   <p>A similar atmosphere pervaded the camp in Pilsen Park where numerous speakers addressed the crowd. This is the last day of the campaign, and Czechs should hurry and subscribe. They will not only show their loyalty, but will boost the campaign so that the quota can be reached; it is now deficient by about ten million dollars. This means that no one should have anything else in mind but the Liberty Loan campaign. The world is looking toward Chicago and New York. These two cities are in arrears, and it is anticipated with much anxiety that they will come up to expectations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
