<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-04">Sept. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-04">Sept. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the several meetings that are being held systematically under the auspices of the Česko-Slovanský Červený Kříž (Bohemian-Slavonic Red Cross) in Bohemian and other Slavic communities throughout Chicago these days took place in the hall of Sokol Pilsen last night.</p>
   <p>The purpose of these meetings is to protest against the vileness of the Austrian government and the German element, both of which are primarily responsible for the present terrible carnage in Europe, and to prepare the ground for mass collections which will start next Monday and will be conducted regularly thereafter. The war will have most serious consequences for all Slavic countries and will be strongly felt in our native land, and therefore it is our sacred duty to give generously to our unfortunate countrymen.</p>
   <p>The attendance at the meeting was large, but it must be admitted that it should have been larger. It was presided over by the well-known Sokol worker, Brother <pb facs="5418478_2_1508.jpg" n="2"/>Jan Siman, who first presented the reasons for the absence of two prominent American personalities, Miss Jane Addams and Professor Henderson of the University of Chicago. Miss Addams was unexpectedly called to Wisconsin, and Mr. Henderson's appearance was prevented by other duties which could not be postponed.</p>
   <p>The first speaker of the evening was Dr. Jan Rudiš-Jičínský. In his spirited talk, he properly attacked the snobbish servility of some Bohemians who, in the most critical period in the life of the Bohemian nation, have been assuring the Austrian government of their humble loyalty. He described them as men of debased, rotten character who are able to suppress all feeling, even the last vestiges of patriotism, national pride, and human charity for the expectation of some measly little order of merit. These men will be the first whom the sound core of the Bohemian nation will hold for accounting as soon as the persecuted country sees the first dawn of freedom.</p>
   <p>Mr. Palandič, the Serbian editor, made a reference to the speech of Dr. Singer <pb facs="5418478_2_1509.jpg" n="3"/>which was delivered before the Chicago Press Club. Dr. Singer was supposed to reply on behalf of the Germans to the speech Mr. Palandic delivered before the Press Club sometime ago, but in his reply, which lasted one hour and forty minutes, he did not mention the Serbs more than once, but devoted fully forty minutes of his time to deriding and slinging mud at the Bohemians. He maintained that the Austrian government is most gracious to the Bohemians, because it keeps up no less than 247 schools throughout Bohemia. The Bohemians, therefore, have no reasons for complaining, to say nothing about stirring up revolutionary movements.</p>
   <p>Mr. Palandič made the fitting remark that in spite of the large number of Germans living in Chicago, not one of them stood up to defend their ground; that had to be done by Dr. Singer, an Austrian. The graciousness of the Austrian government is very well known to many who come in contact with it--for example, the Serbs. Austria is a federation in which all nations should have equal rights and privileges, but how its government has been treating the Serbs is demonstrated by the results of the census. Of the six to seven million <pb facs="5418478_2_1510.jpg" n="4"/>Serbs living in the kingdom of Serbia, less than one thousand have migrated to the United States, while more than half of a million of the two-and-one-half million Serbs living in Austria have sought refuge in this country. How utterly without mercy the Austrian government deals with the Slavs is demonstrated by the fact that over sixty clergymen were shot in Bosnia and Herzegovina only because they had refused to serve in the army, and one clergyman was made to serve as a private. Only one government in the world is capable of such beastliness--the Hapsburgs.</p>
   <p>A very excellent speech was delivered by the noted rationalist and speaker of the independent church society (sic), Dr. John Emerson Roberts. He looks at the present war, which directly affects some nine hundred million of the sixteen hundred million people in the world, from a strictly impartial point of view. He takes it as evidence that the human race is not yet at the peak of its development. The right of the stronger over the weaker prevails, and all over the world there is a life-and-death struggle. On land, at sea, and in the air, the existence of one living organism depends on the death and destruction <pb facs="5418478_2_1511.jpg" n="5"/>of another. Not even man is an exception to this rule. Wars are declared and waged only in order that one nation may grow and expand at the expense of another. But when this present gigantic struggle is fought to its end, perhaps the dreams of those who visualize one great nation, one immense human family in which peace and amity reign, will reach fulfillment. War is a terrible evil which does not concern only those who lose their lives on the battlefield. It concerns mothers, widows, and children who wait in vain for the return of their dear ones. War is responsible for innumerable deserted, bereft homes and broken hearts which suffer for years. To them should go our deepest sympathy, our greatest help.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the Reverend Václav Vanĕk, who said that the present situation in Bohemia is most critical, and therefore it is the duty of Bohemian America to put forth every possible effort to alleviate the crisis. The first thing that is needed now is planned, systematic work. For this, the Českĕ Národní Sdružení (Bohemian National Alliance) has been formed out of three of our national institutions, the Česko-Americká Národní Rada (Bohemian- <pb facs="5418478_2_1512.jpg" n="6"/>American National Council, the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář (Bohemian American Press Bureau), and the Česko-Slovanský Výpomocný Výbor (Sic) (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee). [This third body was referred to in an earlier article as the Českĕ-Slovanský Červený Kříž (Bohemian-Slavonic Red Cross). In one of the following articles, the translator finds a remark to the effect that there was a change of name, no other reference having been made to this effect so far.]</p>
   <p>This body will be the headquarters for intensive propaganda in the interest of the Bohemian cause throughout Bohemian America, where all our efforts should be centered. A detailed plan of the work of this body and a proclamation in regard to it will be published later in the newspapers.</p>
   <p>The meeting was also addressed by the noted Slovak scholar, Mr. Štefán Osuský whose fiery speeches are vivid in the memories of participants of pro-Slavic meetings held in Chicago during the Turko-Slavic war by Mrs. Stanĕk-Bujárek, Mr. J. V. Nigrin, and the well-known Sokol worker, Mr. Bohus Hak. At the <pb facs="5418478_2_1513.jpg" n="7"/>end of the meeting, a collection was taken, which yielded $121.78. The firm of Novak and Stejskal contributed one hundred dollars to this amount.</p>
   <p>The systematic fund-collecting activities will start throughout Chicago next Monday, as was announced in the meeting. A little army of kindly, agile ladies will solicit from house to house, knock on the doors, hearts, and especially the pocketbooks of our people; and we are firmly convinced that nowhere will they knock in vain. Every one of us, from the richest to the poorest, should constantly bear in mind the fact that our people in the old country need help now more urgently than ever before, and that "he that gives quickly gives twice".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
