<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-08">Apr. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Preliminary to the Coming Czech Women's Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-08">Apr. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Preliminary to the Coming Czech Women's Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czech women and mothers! We are in the grip of a terrible war that has dragged our new homeland down into its vortex and makes it incumbent upon us to join in the celebration of the anniversary of America's entrance into the war against Germany. Although this celebration will not take place until next Saturday, we Czech women will glorify that memorable event in our own mass meeting in the Pilsen Brewery Park, Wednesday, April 10, at 2 P. M.</p>
   <p>Let us show our gratitude to our President by firmly standing up for him, shoulder to shoulder, with all that is within our power, and complying faithfully and gladly with the demands of our Government.</p>
   <p>Behold what women beyond the ocean have had to endure! They lost their supporter, their children. They are starving, they are destitute, and perhaps are afflicted <pb facs="5418478_2_0602.jpg" n="2"/>with grave diseases without the prospect of immediate relief. They are exposed to all sorts of discomfort, yet they do not grumble.</p>
   <p>We are now in this new homeland, which admitted us when fate toyed with us in a strange manner and compelled us to cross this vast ocean to begin a new life here. Let us examine ourselves and solemnly swear that we shall gladly and conscientiously perform all that we are able to accomplish. We shall thus show that woman's heart is in the right place when liberty and rights of mankind are at stake.</p>
   <p>Onward, Czech women! Let us stand in serried ranks, so that when the present time will need us, we shall do our duty unflinchingly, instantly. Let us prove that, among women, there are no shilly-shalliers or slackers--these are found among men only.</p>
   <p>We should not shirk our duty for the following reasons: First, we feel as <pb facs="5418478_2_0603.jpg" n="3"/>mothers, and, therefore, with all those mothers who have lost, or are liable to lose, their sons. Second, we feel like sincere Czechs, who experience deep down in their hearts all the misery of our old Czech homeland, and are ready to help to smash the heavy shackles, so that liberty may spread its luster over the whole world and the nation from which we hail. Third, let us attest to our gratitude to our new homeland, not only as women, but also as citizens, by keeping ready to help wherever help is demanded.</p>
   <p>What we have achieved we owe, for many reasons, to this land of the free. Let us, therefore, pay back honestly in the hour of need. We want to show that woman is not only man's fellow worker in the building up of a better existence, but also a real companion in the performance of civic duties. We want to show that she is not pampered, that she helps man to lay a solid foundation for the welfare of the family, and that she is a sincere and grateful daughter of the motherland, which is groaning under a yoke, and is in dire need of Czech woman's help.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0604.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our motherland! Lend an ear to thy daughters' answer: Beloved mother, we are here. Just command, and Czech women will readily and joyfully place their powers upon the altar of the old homeland. Onward! There shall not be one Czech woman who would shirk her sacred duty by being absent next Wednesday. We shall meet again!</p>
   <p>For the committee on resolutions,</p>
   <p>Mrs. Antonia Cervenka.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
