<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-04">Feb. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[Petitions for Political Nominations]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-04">Feb. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[PETITIONS FOR POLITICAL NOMINATIONS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>City Clerk John Siman made an excellent decision relative to the filing of petitions for aldermanic nominations, which is that the petitions received by mail will be given preference to those delivered in person.</p>
   <p>Years ago the offices of the city clerk were beseiged by politicians with petitions. Each of these men strove to get his or his friend's petitions in as soon as possible, because the rule then applied that the first petition received headed the list of names of candidates, and all the candidates wanted their names placed at the head of the list of candidates.</p>
   <p>The candidates for office try to get their names in first, which means that a man has a better chance of winning a nomination if placed at the top of the list.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many men waited all night in the corridors of the election commissioners' offices. Naturally with all those men cluttering the corridors, great disorder prevailed, a condition which should have been stopped long ago.</p>
   <p>Even this new order did not satisfy all the candidates, because certain candidates claimed the police who were left on guard arranged it so that their favored candidates received the preference.</p>
   <p>Human nature is so constituted that, even with the greatest care such complaints will appear, because certain candidates seem to think that they are wronged, no matter how equitably others try to treat their fellows. These men will claim that they are wronged if their names do not head the list of candidates.</p>
   <p>The only known remedy for this existing evil would be,if the election regulations were so changed that names of candidates be placed in alphabetical order, which would do away with the hurry now seen, and would, <pb facs="5418478_2_0336.jpg" n="3"/>we believe, change the prevailing conditions so that there would be no more complaints.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
