<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-06-22">June 22, 1892</date><title level="a">New Proof</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-06-22">June 22, 1892</date><title level="a">NEW PROOF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have said several times that the Republican Party is one which has inherited and accepted the principles of the old "Know Nothing" party and that whenever the opportunity is offered, these principles are put into effect with well recognized conscientiousness. The heart of the Republican Party contains an element which is greatly interested in hatred of everything which is not genuinely American, which maintains that only full-blooded Americans have the right to direct the fate of the community, and that the immigrant citizen only, has the right to pay and to remain silent.</p>
   <p>We do not belong among those who are under the impression that we are duty-bound to support this or the other party merely because it appoints some Bohemian inspector, or because it gives to a Bohemian some other minor office. We believe that the Bohemian nationality derives not the slightest benefit from enabling several Bohemian politicians to make a living for themselves at the city or county trough. But when a party adopts this attitude toward the Bohemian element, when we continually are received with coolness, disfavor, yes even unfriendliness, when it is clearly shown that we are not wanted, then <pb facs="5418478_2_0194.jpg" n="2"/>indeed one would have to be crazy to force themselves upon such a party. It would be much better to give up all political activity or turn to that party which knows how to value services rendered. It is not only in Chicago - but also in all other cities. Our countrymen complain rightfully, that they are not recognized by the Republican Party, and that the leaders of the party are the most determined denouncers of the immigrant element. Not only in local politics but also in higher circles has it been made quite evident that they can get along very nicely without us.</p>
   <p>Now our Republican mayor has again given us proof regarding his favor. The entire Bohemian element and the Bohemian press joined in recommending to him a capable Bohemian for the school board nomination, but the mayor threw all these requests and all petitions into the waste basket. Why didn't he satisfy the Bohemians in their desire for a previous Bohemian representative on the school board who had shown himself to be capable? Was it because he is a Democrat? He named Mr. Nettlehorst last year and he belongs to the Democratic Party!</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0195.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our candidate was a Bohemian and this was sufficient for Mr. Washburne. We are certain that this was not the work of the mayor alone - for before he named the members of the school board he surely consulted with his lieutenants. Therefore, this rejection can be accepted by us as not coming from an individual, but as coming from the Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
