<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Selling War Stamps</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SELLING WAR STAMPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign for the sale of war savings certificates is in full swing, at least in our own districts, and all indications point to success for our workers, particularly our ardent and self-sacrificing ladies. They report favorably on the reception given to them while soliciting. A number of cases, however, give reason for complaint. The workers were treated not only impolitely, but downright gruffly. Sometimes their offers were rejected in so rude a manner that disloyalty became evident. Some persons went to a point just short of attacking the workers, who had done nothing worse than offer a certificate for sale.</p>
   <p>Two cases in particular were reported to us by a lady who has been working in a certain part of the 26th Street business section. (We mention in advance that this does not mean Czech businessmen, for they act at least decently.) One of the men, a descendant of Israel, refused in an insolent <pb facs="5418478_2_0481.jpg" n="2"/>manner. The other told the worker that he is "king" in his own house, and would let her know it. The lady answered pertinently that his boorish manners will do him no good, and reminded him of the fact that the "kings" in Europe are on the way out. In both cases proper information was filed at the right place. Therefore, we remind our fellow countrymen that by buying certificates from the volunteering ladies, they do no favor to these workers but, on the contrary, they do a favor to themselves. In acquiring certificates they are investing their money in the most advantageous way. By buying the largest possible amount they will, in addition, help the efforts of the government to dispose of a certain quota of certificates within a predetermined period.</p>
   <p>The certificates sell now at $4.19, and their value will be $5 at the beginning of the year 1923. The investment is as secure as cash, that means, the safest known up to today. This investment is especially designed for the benefit of the "little fellow". It excludes big capital, for the <pb facs="5418478_2_0482.jpg" n="3"/>amount purchased by any one person is limited to $1,000. Furthermore, the certificates may, in case of need, be exchanged for ready money at any time. There is, therefore, not the slightest reason why certificates should not be bought eagerly--there should, indeed, be a scramble for them.</p>
   <p>One has not yet done his full duty when he has bought Liberty bonds. He should buy certificates, too, as many as possible, and not use flimsy excuses as is being done sometimes. It is our duty to buy Liberty bonds just as it is our duty to buy war savings stamps and war certificates. The more one buys of them the prouder he will be, after victory is won, to point to his share in the final success.</p>
   <p>This is only a small contribution compared to the sacrifices our men in the army make in health and life. Yet small services also are necessary, and <pb facs="5418478_2_0483.jpg" n="4"/>they give satisfaction in the consciousness of duty performed.</p>
   <p>Therefore, buy certificates in abundance; buy gladly, knowing that you are doing a service for yourself and for your country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
