<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-02">June 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">What Kind of Loyalty?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-02">June 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT KIND OF LOYALTY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the greatest crime of our age was committed, and the English steamer "Lusitania" was sunk at the order of an imperial moron by a German submarine, when the mass murder of innocent people took place, among whom were some hundred and fifty Americans, the whole world shuddered with horror and disgust at such a deed. Not, however, our Germans and their newspapers.</p>
   <p>Our Germans and Austrians, just as the Germans and Austrians in Europe, expressed their pleasure over this new "victory" of Germany over England. But it did not take the Germans in America long to learn that the whole world condemned--and justly condemned,--the felonious deed, and that this deed had aroused even the Government of the United States of America--which is quite proper and easy to understand.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1355.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our Germans have been hearing words of condemnation from all sides;they have had to listen to expressions of disgust and hostility uttered by those who had been friendly toward their national cause or were at least neutral. So, after the President had sent his note to Berlin, our Germans--for public consumption--changed their attitude. Their newspapers approved of the President's action and expressed themselves in agreement with the Government and with the American people--all this in public. But privately they had nothing but bitter criticism and condemnation for the President, the Government, and all Americans. Some of them went so far in their hypocrisy as to publish expressions of assurance that they were loyal Americans, and that they were even ready to go to war against Germany. How such assurances are to be understood was discussed the other day in the Polish newspaper Kuryer Polski of Milwaukee, a city where German convictions find their strongest and most definite expression. Says the Kuryer:</p>
   <p>"No sane person will believe these statements. We are convinced that every self-respecting American German secretly damns those who are capable of <pb facs="5418478_2_1356.jpg" n="3"/>publishing such assurances, [which to them seem] humiliating to any red-blooded man."</p>
   <p>This Milwaukee expert in German mentality asserts further that if there should be a war between Germany and the United States, "our Germans would refuse to fight; they would not actively help their new, adopted country, though they might show their loyalty by not betraying her to their old one".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
