<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-01">Oct. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Bond Campaign Offices</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-01">Oct. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR BOND CAMPAIGN OFFICES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There cannot be any doubt about the material aid given to the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign by the celebrations attending the raising of service flags in the Twelfth, Thirty-fourth, and Tenth Wards, last Saturday and Sunday. Speakers are being offered a splendid opportunity to raise the patriotic enthusiasm of our people. We are certain they will use it to the fullest extent.</p>
   <p>The rapid progress and the results of the starting campaign were very conspicuous in the substations of the various wards, and especially in our main campaign office, located at 3342 West 26th Street, near Homan Avenue. This office resembled a beehive from the earliest hours of the campaign. Hundreds of our people call there to subscribe. The campaign activities in other words are also directed from there. Its workers, headed by Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chairman of the Czechoslovak section in the Liberty Loan drive, are kept extremely busy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They also make the preliminary arrangements for flag raising celebrations which are held all over our settlement. Speakers are secured, and artists sent out to co-operate with all other workers to help make individual celebrations a success. All those men and women are feverishly active, and we doubt whether there is another campaign office in Chicago that could compare with ours as to vigor and variety of activity. Reports from other wards are received here, payments made, and business disposed of to the smallest detail.....</p>
   <p>An urgent appeal is being directed to our artists, musicians, singers, and various entertainers to report and offer their services for the cause. A large platform in front of the office on 26th Street is occupied every evening by artists and actors as well as speakers. The effect of this method of campaigning is always felt immediately after--it shows in the receipts of subscriptions.</p>
   <p>Heads of ward substations need not take the trouble of reporting daily results to the main office. Get in contact with Mr. Otto R. Fuerst, in charge of <pb facs="5418478_2_0434.jpg" n="3"/>publicity, and your reports will be printed in our dailies.</p>
   <p>We have already mentioned the fact that large numbers of patriotic Czechoslovaks from the outlying districts, such as Pullman, South Chicago, West Hammond, and Kensington, come to the main office on 26th Street to pay their bonds. That gives them a guarantee that their bonds will be credited to their nationality. There were many additional applications received from these people yesterday. It is gratifying to note that the Slovaks are taking an active part in the campaign.</p>
   <p>The Catholics also are making rapid progress. The Reverend Bozenek informs us that one of his workers sold $1,400 worth of bonds to the family of Dr. F. G. Hellebrandt, 2327 South Albany Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
