<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the Czech Campaign Office</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CZECH CAMPAIGN OFFICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A long list of subscriptions in the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign was submitted to the main office of the Czechoslovak section, 3342 West 22nd Street, yesterday. Truly, some of these subscriptions are highly gratifying, and prove that our people endeavor to stand in the first ranks of those who fulfill their duties to the country.</p>
   <p>Mr. F. C. Lajer, for instance, handed over subscriptions amounting to $5,000 from Czech National Alliance. Mr. Anton J. Cermak, head of the Czechoslovak campaign section, also received $1,000 worth of subscriptions from the Sokol Community, and $1,000 from the Builders' Brick Company. These two bought their bonds through the Czech National Alliance. Announcement was made at the same time that the Pilsen Butchers' Association, with a membership of 116, subscribed $17,350. These are results which should serve as an incentive to business houses, other associations, and individuals, many of whom have not yet done justice to their patriotic conscience.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0414.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To date, the Tenth Ward has subscribed $224,000, the Thirty-fourth Ward $275,000, Town of Lake $80,000, and the Twelfth Ward $486,000,--all by Czechoslovaks. This is, however, not enough, and much more will have to be subscribed. Our people have to prove that they stand behind our Government, and behind those boys of ours in France, and on various other fronts, fighting for the liberty of all nations.</p>
   <p>A grievous mission has brought Charles Matousek, a young soldier, whose parents live at 2843 South Springfield Avenue, back to Chicago. He appeared at the main Czechoslovak campaign office and told his story. He had come from the camp at Dodge, Iowa, to bring back the body of his comrade Vaclav (Wenceslaus) Lukes, formerly of 2811 South Springfield Avenue. His eyes brimming with tears, he gave an account of the last hours of his friend's life.</p>
   <p>"He was longing to see his father and mother once more, and regretful that he could not have the opportunity to take a whack at the Germans, and thus do his part in <pb facs="5418478_2_0415.jpg" n="3"/>the achievement of victory. When the news reached our camp, on October 13, that President Wilson and his Government had recognized the existence of an independent Czechoslovak state, with Professor T. G. Masaryk as its president, it was Lukes who was taken off his feet with joy. It behooves me to state that the entire camp celebrated the significant decision accordingly. The commander ordered a gorgeous parade, in which seventeen thousand soldiers stood in a formation symbolizing the Statue of Liberty. All regimental bands played patriotic tunes, and the general addressed the gathering on the import of the President's proclamation of independence for Czechoslovakia. This was a glorious day in our camp which I never shall forget. A bitter drop mingled into all this. My comrade Lukes fell sick. He died, and I have brought his remains home."</p>
   <p>Matousek depicted the sorrow the parents and friends of the departed felt. He was deeply grateful when Mr. Cermak assured him that his friend will be buried with military honors. The funeral will be held Friday and close at the Catholic cemetery. [Report omits to give location.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
