<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-06-15">June 15, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">From the Legislature of Illinois the Bohemian Justice of Peace for Chicago Nominated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-06-15">June 15, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE LEGISLATURE OF ILLINOIS THE BOHEMIAN JUSTICE OF PEACE FOR CHICAGO NOMINATED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Springfield, I11., June 14th. The proposed Bohemian Justice of the Peace, Ed. A. Fischer, was today unanimously nominated in the session of the Senate. He obtained the renomination as a proof of good will to the Bohemian nationality, which deserves for its honesty in the district, to have at least one Justice of the Peace, who speaks Bohemian and can be of much benefit to our countrymen, who do not possess the English language. The Governor sent his, (Mr. Fischer's), name to the Senate without any hesitation and the Senate sanctioned it. Many thanks for it to the Judges, to the Governor, and to the Senate. We are completely convinced, that this office was reached in a most honest way, to the desire of the Bohemian nationality, and to prove that the concerned official and political circles are taking care of Bohemians, respecting them and wished to do something in their favor. We should remember it forever. It is a disgrace for all these renegades who, knowing that they can have no hope to reach this office, have worked with all their power against the possibility of its being obtained by the Bohemians. We will remember it, too, when the suitable time comes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
