<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs for the Third Loan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS FOR THE THIRD LOAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If there is one part of the population here which has a particularly urgent reason to do all that is in its power to support the United States in her pursuit of victory, it is the Czechs. For us, victory means the fulfillment of our longings, the crowning of our efforts. Victory will give us not only what the United States is battling for, but also what our brothers in the old motherland are suffering relentless persecution for, and for what they are sacrificing their material goods and even their lives.</p>
   <p>The task now before us is to contribute to the success of the Third Liberty Loan. This duty ought to appear easy to every one of us, and everyone should fulfill it as well as individual circumstances will permit. He who ignores this obligation gives a poor demonstration of his American and Czech patriotism, and at the same time, shows that he cannot perceive what is to his own best <pb facs="5418478_2_0596.jpg" n="2"/>interest. Even one who has no ideals but thinks only of his own selfish purpose should hasten to invest his savings in war bonds, because they are the safest investment in the world, and because they bear 4½ per cent interest, which is more than any bank could pay.</p>
   <p>Let us, therefore, buy as many bonds as we can. Not only that, but let us speak to our friends and acquaintances about this on every possible occasion. Let us bend every effort toward this purpose.</p>
   <p>The liberty and prosperity of the United States, into which we come to seek a better and happier life, is jeopardized by the possibility of victory for the Teutonic tyrants. The Czech nation is doomed to perish if it is forced to remain within the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, which has become nothing but the footrest for Germany, whose intention it is to create a "Central Europe" in which everything would be destroyed that is not German and does not serve German purposes.</p>
   <p>For us, this struggle is not only a matter of our liberty, but of our very life. <pb facs="5418478_2_0597.jpg" n="3"/>Mankind's most precious goods are endangered. Can anyone, in a moment like this, hesitate to make extreme sacrifices to rescue them? There is, in fact, no sacrifice involved in the bond investment, for the money is used to everyone's best material advantage. Can any man be so shortsighted that he cannot discern the safest and most profitable investment available?</p>
   <p>Let us reduce our expenditures for necessities and pleasures so that we can afford to buy Liberty bonds. The majority of us have been living as if we were not involved in the most terrible war the world has ever seen. We should begin to grasp the meaning of this war time and adapt our ways to it. Let us better our own selves and prepare for the purification which will be one of the natural issues of this war affecting the entire human society.</p>
   <p>The success of the bond sales will insure victory for the arms of our Republic and its allies. The armies in which our boys are fighting have to be fitted out with arms and provided with food and clothing. This is necessary to achieve victory. Very much depends upon the food our soldiers get, what care they are <pb facs="5418478_2_0598.jpg" n="4"/>given if wounded, and in what condition they will come back to us. We who live in comfort here are called on to provide the means for the armaments and the best possible care and comfort for our warriors. They are sacrificing their lives for us and for our homeland. They, in turn, do not ask any more of us than to lend money to the Government with perfect safety and good interest rates. Is it possible to find a single person unwilling to do even that little?</p>
   <p>Articles have been appearing in some English language papers in which the Government is urged to compel new immigrants to assimilate with the American element in the shortest possible time. They demand that the immigrant forget his native land and maternal language and suddenly transform himself into an English-speaking American. The sincerity of the immigrant is being questioned on every hand. The advocates of these measures, of course, have the Germans in mind, in the first place. However, other nationalistic immigrant groups would be equally hit by the respective laws without any discrimination or exception. The immigrants will have to wrest the weapon from the hands of these jingoistic fanatics by constantly proving their loyalty to this country and <pb facs="5418478_2_0599.jpg" n="5"/>unflinchingly displaying their patriotism. Joyfully they will have to shoulder the burden which this war has placed in equal measure upon all adherents of this country. They will have to show that they have thoroughly grasped the present needs and efforts of this country.</p>
   <p>In these ominous times, when the very foundations and the existence of the country are jeopardized, the Government is empowered to command and designate the means necessary to avert the danger. Our Government has not made use of this power as yet. It merely asks our help and rewards those who provide it with ample interest for the loan. Financiers are predicting that the Liberty bonds of the third issue, bearing 4½ per cent now, will sell immediately after the war from $125 to $135 dollars for the one-hundred-dollar denomination.</p>
   <p>Our fellow countrymen in the old homeland have been forced to invest their money in enterprises which promote the war that is designed to destroy their rights and hopes forever, and they are well aware of the fact that the Austrian war bonds will never bring any returns.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0600.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>How they would envy us--we who are in a position to lend money and support a war which is certain to insure liberty and free development to the Czech people, to all small nations, to mankind all over the world; and, moreover, our investment is perfectly safe and is bearing handsome interest!</p>
   <p>Once more we want to impress you with this truth: If there is any stratum of the populace of our United states more under obligation to do everything that is within its power to help win victory for America and its allies; if there is a nationalistic group here which should put every pecuniary effort into purchasing Liberty bonds--it is we, the American Czechs, We sincerely hope that the bond campaign will be a brilliant success which will show that our patriotic duties have been comprehended and fulfilled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
