<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-02">Apr. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">For Annexation to Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-02">Apr. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FOR ANNEXATION TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annexation of the Town of Cicero to Chicago will be voted upon at next Tuesday's election. A large part of Bohemian Oak Park, Morton Park, and Hawthorne lie in that town. The Bohemian element in this section is markedly strong, and will continue to grow stronger. In Chicago, at such election, a majority is usually given in favor of annexation, but the inhabitants of the suburbs, for various reasons, often are opposed to it. In order that the citizens of Cicero might be thoroughly acquainted with the benefits to be derived from an annexation to Chicago, a committee was formed there. Through meetings and handbills, this committee is endeavoring to convince the citizenry that it will be decidedly to their advantage if they join the City of Chicago. The following benefits will accrue to them as pointed out by the handbills: First: they will receive lower rates for gas. They now pay one dollar per thousand cubic feet, and if they belonged <pb facs="5418478_2_0127.jpg" n="2"/>to Chicago they would pay eighty five cents, and if Chicago gets a seventy cent rate, it would also apply to Cicero. Second: telephone service would be cheaper, without any extra payment whatever, and connection could be made with about 200,000 customers of the telephone company. This would be of great advantage to Cicero businessmen, and for all who have business transactions in the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Third: they would get water rates cheaper. They would not have to pay for watermeters, and for the laying of watermains.</p>
   <p>Fourth: if Cicero joined Chicago, it would not be a neglected part of the City of Chicago, if it did not wish to be. The repairs and paving of streets would go on as rapidly as the owners of property desired. Fifth: five cent car fares and universal transfers to all parts of Chicago would benefit the town immensely, and aid in increasing its population. Under the present unsatisfactory conditions, <pb facs="5418478_2_0128.jpg" n="3"/>no one cares to build, and new tenants are not moving in, but on the contrary, people are leaving Cicero to come back into the city limits of Chicago. Also it is claimed that through joining Chicago, it will be easier to make loans for building purposes at lower interest rates, that taxes will not be increased, and that there will be better protection in case of fire.</p>
   <p>As can be seen, the reasons for joining are excellent. We know of no reasons against it, and cannot express an opinion on that point. We think, however, that our countrymen in Hawthorne, Morton Park, and the eastern part of Bohemian Oak Park, will act for their own benefit when they make a cross mark in the square on the small ballot after the words "For Annexation of the Town of Cicero to the City of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
