<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">April 1st, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Day in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SVORNOST</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">April 1st, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Day in Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To-day is indeed a big day in Chicago, the like of which, for importance and significance, has never before occurred in its history. Yes, and for us Bohemians living here, this day surely is also very significant. Politics here has become almost altogether an occupation of the most dishonorable wretches among the people.</p>
   <p>Whoever applies himself to politics is forced down to the lowest degree of contempt and degradation, for it seems that politics can not countenance an honorable man whether he be Republican or Democrat.</p>
   <p>The more corrupt a member of these political parties was, the more influence he had. He knew the various methods for obtaining money with which to buy votes and power for himself.</p>
   <p>Thievery of all sorts could be accomplished at elections, any knave could be elected, and as it so often happened, the biggest scoundrels were generally elected into the <pb facs="5418478_2_0373.jpg" n="2"/>most honorable positions and profitable offices. These offices they then conducted in accordance with their corrupt characters. No honorable man could be induced to mingle with this political riff-raff in order to work with them to attain some office. Everyone is ashamed of this disgraceful condition and it so happens that among all the politicians and office holders in Chicago, and there are many of them, it is impossible even at high noon and with the aid of Diogenes' Lamp to find an honorable man, in factone steals more than the other-one is more deceitful than the other-and the thieves are never brought to justice.</p>
   <p>This is the kind of example honorable citizens had before them, they saw it in all leaders- in all officials- What kind of citizens could they be? Conditions gradually became worse year after year. When the Republican party was in power they stole. When the citizenry took notice and ousted them by electing Democrats, the Democrats did more stealing than their predecessors. The citizenry finally discarded both the parties by electing the so-called People's Party only to find the same brand of politicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0374.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They were no better than either the Republicans or Democrats and the thieving continued.</p>
   <p>Law abiding citizens, whether they had anything or not, were forced to pay for all this and to carry an immense burden. In no way were they able to accomplish any reforms so that they might have some relief from these excessive burdens.</p>
   <p>The Political parties in Chicago tremble to-day before the Socialists, before the poor, before the workingmen. They tremble, not with feat that these citizens will come on the morrow with clubs to break windows and to pillage stores, but because hence forth no matter how few Socialists are elected they must stop their nefarious practices. They know that their trickery will be exposed, that they will be watched and will not have free reign as they previously had. They fear the honesty and sincerity which will replace their dishonesty and insincerity. With honesty these old politicians wont get far; it would hardly pay them to have themselves elected. Honest citizens to work! One for all and all for one. To-day we will do our duty and we will continue to work until honesty and justice shall prevail throughout the land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
