<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-10">Mar. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Women Voters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-10">Mar. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR WOMEN VOTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Tuesday, March 12, is general registration day for all voters who have moved since the last registration day, and for persons who have reached the legal age. This occasion is very important to us women, as it gives us an opportunity to materially influence the results of the April election which will send the representatives of each ward into the City Council. It is the duty of every consciencious woman who enjoys the privilege of voting to cast her vote for a candidate according to her best judgement.</p>
   <p>The housewife is confronted with this question: What attitude to assume in these times when total prohibition is threatening to engulf our city? Reformers are promising a beneficial change of conditions. We will have to scrutinize these promises carefully, particularly from the standpoint of the taxpayers of our city. Can those apostles of prohibition perhaps explain to us how the budget of the city is to be balanced when seven million dollars in saloon <pb facs="5418478_2_0082.jpg" n="2"/>revenue will be missing? Experience teaches us that some people are expending large amounts of money to deprive the worker of a refreshing drink to which he is accustomed during his hours of rest and relaxation. These people are those who oppose the payment of taxes that are properly assessed in proportion to their income and assets. How much more will they loath to pay increased taxes due to the decrement in the city revenue caused by the closing of saloons? Those same people argue that when no money is spent for alcohol more money will be available for increased taxes? What about those empty places of business during this time? What is waiting for the man who is not in a position to pay the mortgage on his home?</p>
   <p>Thousands of people find occupations in the saloon business. They support families. Their means of livelihood is jeopardized by the menace of prohibition. Should we not become interested in their situation? Women voters! It is our duty to give this issue our careful attention and vote accordingly!</p>
   <p>The committee on resolutions of the J. C. D. (Jednota Ceskych Dam, Czech <pb facs="5418478_2_0083.jpg" n="3"/>Ladies Association).</p>
   <p>(Signed) Marie Liska,</p>
   <p>Marie Smrcka</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
