<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-13">June 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Americans Respond</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mass Meeting Identifies Itself with Hopes of Old Homeland (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0896</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0896.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-13">June 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH AMERICANS RESPOND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mass Meeting Identifies Itself With Hopes of Old Homeland (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Most of our readers have read the news about the Czechs in the old homeland and of the heroic stand which they and their representatives in the Austrian parliament have taken in defense of their rights to independence.....In vain were feeble attempts made by Emperor Carl to lull the Czechs into peace, and all kinds of promises came too late. Our brothers across the sea need our wholehearted moral support in their struggle.</p>
   <p>This much-longed-for manifestation of sympathy was announced in the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion, 26th Street and Albany Avenue, last night, where a mass meeting was held under the leadership of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics...The enthusiasm of the crowd was high, although the attendance should have been larger.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0897.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the president of the Czech National Alliance arrived some-what later, the meeting was opened by Mr. Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary. He acquainted the audience with the situation in Austria, voicing the complete agreement of the Czechs in America with those in Czech lands. His words drew tumultuous applause. He introduced Mrs. Anna Stolfa as a representative of the Union of Czech Ladies and the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Sisterhood of Aid Societies). She assured the assembly of the ardent co-operation of Czech women.....</p>
   <p>Dr. Rudis-Jicinsky, the next speaker, pointed in a few words to the national activities of the Ceska Obec Sokolska (Czech Sokol Community) and particularly to their quick response to President Wilson's call for volunteers for Uncle Sam's forces. He did not fail to admonish the parents of Czech children to send them to the Sokol gymnastic societies to replenish the ranks which have been thinned by many enlistments of Sokol volunteers.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. Straka of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics followed <pb facs="5418478_2_0898.jpg" n="3"/>Dr. Jicinsky upon the platform. His ideas conveyed the need for unity of all Czechs, regardless of creed, when so important an issue as the independence of the motherland is before them. He reminded the throngs of the beautiful and impressive parade at the last Chicago World's Fair when all Czechs marched in one rank and file to show their solidarity.....</p>
   <p>Dr. J. F. Smetanka then spoke for the Czech Protestants and the Czech National Alliance. Referring to President Wilson's promise to consider the small nations now subjugated, he declared himself for the liberation of any small nation demanding independence.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Rudolph Vlodek, speaking for the Czech National Socialists, declared that his faction has always looked up to the liberation of the Czechs as a national ideal. Tony Novotny, the next speaker, forcefully upheld the liberation of the Czechs and the destruction of Austria because it is made up of enslaved nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0899.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Tvrzicky thanked the group for their wholehearted response. He then read two messages, one to be sent to the Czechoslovak army fighting against the Austrians in Russia, the other to Professor T. G. Masaryk, now in London, England. The letter to the Czechs and Slovaks assures them of the unity of the Czechs with kindred nations in Czechoslovak lands and acknowledges the Czechoslovak National Council as the highest tribunal in their national affairs. In the letter to Professor Masaryk, respect and loyalty are expressed to the undaunted leader....</p>
   <p>Two other messages were sent; the first to Senator William S. Kenyon, Washington, D. C., thanking him for the interest he is taking in the cause of Czech liberty and calling his attention to the Czech patriotic uprisings in Austria; the second to President Woodrow Wilson voices deep-felt gratitude for his promise to help the small nations and expresses the fondest hopes that when the moment arrives, the President's mighty influence will be exerted in favor of Czech liberation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
