<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To All Sincere Czechs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL SINCERE CZECHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There never was a time more portentous than the present when the liberty and independence of our dear nation is at stake. Who would not feel attached to his nation? Let us observe how people of other nationalities make sacrifices in order to see their old homelands liberated. And how about ourselves? Should we remain inactive and wait patiently to see what fate has in store for us? Certainly not! We have to do something. How should it be done? By joining the Czech National Alliance. In our community there are many thousands of good sincere Czechs. It is to them that we are addressing ourselves:</p>
   <p>Become members of our district of the Czech National Alliance and work with us for our beloved old homeland. This is an epoch weighted with historical significance. Our boys are shedding their blood on every front on the side of the Allies. They are giving themselves for the cause of liberty. What about us who stay at home?</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0821.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is surely no one among us who would dodge work. Many of our people have indeed proved their willingness and love for the old homeland. The Czech "California" district has done good work since its creation, but there is more work awaiting it. We are counting upon the good will of all Czechs.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Slavoj branch of the Czech National Alliance has donated a considerable number of building lots to the Czech "California" district of the Czech National Alliance. These lots will be sold to members of the Czech National Alliance for the benefit of that organization. Booklets giving individuals title to the lots may be purchased from Mrs. A. Mayer, Chicago Dairy Company, 3948 West 16th Street, from 9 to 5 P. M., or at the home of Mrs. Helen Celba, 2523 West 22nd Street, every evening. The membership card of the Czech National Alliance must be presented before the purchase can be made. Another enterprise is the raffle of a piano, for which tickets are obtainable from Mrs. Anna Novak, 4002 West 22nd Street.</p>
   <p>Meetings of the district organization are held every second and fourth Monday at Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
