<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-25">Mar. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Americans for Their Imprisoned Soldiers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-25">Mar. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH AMERICANS FOR THEIR IMPRISONED SOLDIERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are active not only in America, in London, in France, and in Russia but in many other countries. We are engaged in organization and in publicity necessary for the proper information of nations of many tongues in our fight for the independence of our people. There are more than 35,000 Czech fighters on the Russian front alone; there is the Czech legon in France, and new regiments are being formed in England and in Canada. These are the results of untiring labor, toil, and trouble.</p>
   <p>We intend to organize in order to help the suffering Czech soldiers on the various fronts, who are groaning under the hardships of imprisonment: First, we want to evoke the interest of the Czech-American public. We are planning the creation of a "Prisoners Auxiliary Department," which <pb facs="5418478_2_1106.jpg" n="2"/>shall be composed of representatives of the Czech National Association (C. N. S.), representatives of the present Auxiliary Department, and female members of all Sokol and other national organizations. The entire action should be approved by the C. N. S. (Czech National Association) and supported by our Czech women.</p>
   <p>A similar organization should be put in charge of a thoroughly regulated agitating enterprise, in order to provide the material necessary for carrying but our purpose: underwear, clothes, shoes, and other articles. Individual addresses of Czech prisoners may be sent to the more prosperous families, in towns and in the country, who consent to send useful gifts to the soldiers, occasionally or regularly. The methods to be used in the distribution of necessities will be discussed in a meeting to be called in Chicago at an early date. Numerous members of each of our ladies' national organizations, and others are expected to appear. All of you extend help to the Czech prisoners, in the name of our nation and of humanity itself!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
