<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-09-03">Sept. 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Democrats in Cook County.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-09-03">Sept. 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN DEMOCRATS IN COOK COUNTY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2 - The new organized political club, Bohemian Democracy of Cook County, held its second meeting in the quarters of the Democratic Club Bohemia, Blue Island Avenue and 18th Street. Steps were taken at this meeting to insure the best representative in the political field and various other benefits for the Bohemian Democratic voters at the coming election and those to follow were also considered. The chairman of the new club is C. Fiala, and J. Mayer is the Secretary. The committee appointed at the previous meeting to formulate rules, by-laws and a platform, introduced its findings in these matters and, after minor changes, the committee's formulations were approved at yesterday's meeting. A brief summary of the approved Democratic platform will be introduced at the next meeting and published in the daily papers, together with a suitable proclamation to the Bohemian voters, whose cooperation at the coming election will be requested, so that Bohemian candidates for various offices may be victorious. Various committees were appointed, among which, first place was accorded to the committee of fifteen members, entirely composed of Vice-Chairmen, who represent the fifteen wards where <pb facs="5418478_2_0135.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemian voters live. Financial, registration, hall, speakers, publicity, entertainment, committees were also appointed. The various committees were instructed to work energetically toward their indicated purpose, in order to assure offices for the Bohemian candidates.</p>
   <p>Many speeches will be given before the election, to inform the Democratic voters of their duties towards themselves and towards the candidates, for success for one will be success for others. Any citizen of democratic inclination can become a member of this new organization.</p>
   <p>At the close of the meeting mention was made, that some Bohemian voters were in doubt about the registration this Saturday, thinking that their previous registrations are still valid. In this they are mistaken. All voters, without exception, whether they were previously registered or not, if they wish to vote in the fall elections, absolutely must re-register this Saturday or they will not be eligible to vote.</p>
   <p>The old registration lists are invalid and a new registration is required. <pb facs="5418478_2_0136.jpg" n="3"/>Whoever has the success of the candidates at heart, should not forget to register tomorrow, that is, on Sept. 4th. Whoever cannot do so tomorrow, will have another opportunity to do so, on Sept. 14th, which will be the last day of registrations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
