<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-02-08">Feb. 8, 1882</date><title level="a">Chicago Bohemians, Their Representatives in Public Offices</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-02-08">Feb. 8, 1882</date><title level="a">CHICAGO BOHEMIANS, THEIR REPRESENTATIVES IN PUBLIC OFFICES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For many years Chicago Bohemians were unable to attain even the most minor public office, and only in recent years, namely during Mayor Harrison's term, has there been any change in regards to this matter so as to encourage us to have expectations for the future.</p>
   <p>Chicago Bohemians, today, have their own representatives in practically all public offices. They have their own officials, both honorary and paid, and there is not another city in the United States where they can boast of so many Bohemian officials as we have in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Let us take for example the Honorary positions, and there are many of them, whose holders render their services without pay. On the School Board, one of the most important admisistrative bodies, we have the able countryman of ours, Lawyer Adolf Kraus, who will, no doubt, very soon have the opportunity to prove himself an able defender of Bohemian interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Chicago Public Library is an institution, in which every nationality can consider it an honor to have it's own representative. The interests of Chicago Bohemians are looked after in a deserving manner by Mr. L.W. Kadlec.</p>
   <p>Not long, to be sure, but at any rate, we have our own Bohemian Justice of the Peace, on the North Side, Mr. E.A. Fischer, who was given this position to satisfy the requests of Bohemians.</p>
   <p>Now let us see what conditions exist among our paid officials. We have, in the service of the Public Library, three appointees, and there may be more soon; they are Leo Meilbek, F. G. Novy, and W.A. Purer. In the City Water Department we have two officials, they are V. Kasparek and Adolf Chladka. In our public schools, we have four women teachers, the Misses Purer, Fischman, and the two Stieger sisters.</p>
   <p>In the Unites States Custom House we have, as a clerk, Josef A. Novak. In the Police Department we find three countrymen; they are Fr. P. Barcal, Ant. Kakuska, and J. Vanata.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0223.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the Fire Department we have Mr. J. Kamen. Even in the Post Office we have Fr. Kohout, who is a mail-sorter and Josef Vaska and Anton Lajicek, who are carriers.</p>
   <p>Chicago Bohemians are deserving of better representation in public offices, but since it was neglected for so many years, it will take some time to accomplish.</p>
   <p>The political activity among us is not so energetic as it could be, but even that is somewhat improved for, whereas, there formerly were only about three hundred of our countrymen taking an active part in politics, there now are that many thousands.</p>
   <p>That which is not, may yet be. Chicago Bohemians will not cease striving for political recognition, and if activity in this respect is continued everywhere, as it is in Chicago, Bohemian Americans will not be forced to complain that they are being neglected and pushed aside.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
