<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-02">Jan. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">On Behalf of the Little Bees</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-02">Jan. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ON BEHALF OF THE LITTLE BEES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vcelky (Little Bees), a ladies' auxiliary of the Czech National Alliance, have fully grasped the meaning of their task, and the results are becoming evident. It seems incredible that the Little Bees have been able to accomplish so much in just two months preceding Christmas. They have delivered at least 750 articles of charity. Every evening except Saturday they work in the Vojta Naprstek School.</p>
   <p>It is a pleasure to see the School. Every picture reveals how love for the old homeland is being instilled into the minds of the pupils. Almost every one of our aged women works for the cause. It fills our hearts with deep emotion to see a woman who is old, feeble, and wrinkled carrying wool from the school building, and to hear her say: "Well, I also am able to work."</p>
   <p>We expect that after New Year's Day many will join the Little Bees. We implore all women to assist us, either by working or by financing our <pb facs="5418478_2_1619.jpg" n="2"/>charitable enterprise. Think of the sacrifices our boys are making! Will Czech America forsake them? Will it leave them suffering from cold storms and biting icy gales?</p>
   <p>Very much depends upon ourselves in these times. It is up to us to determine what work we will perform. We know that wool is hard to obtain. In some country districts very little wool is available for our women's charitable pursuits.</p>
   <p>If you need wool, write to the headquarters of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago. The Little Bees will see that you are supplied with material. Help! Help our most noble souls, who stand today with the Czechoslovak Army in France.</p>
   <p>Best wishes to all Little Bees, our sisters. Success to all friends and workers of the Czech National Alliance, particularly to the readers and editors of the Denni Hlasatel.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1620.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On behalf of the Little Bees of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Signed: Sophie Majer</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
