<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-03">Oct. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Coming Amendment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Sunday Causerie)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-03">Oct. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMING AMENDMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Sunday Causerie)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, October 2, 1921.</p>
   <p>When the Nineteenth Amendment was being drawn up, a number of miscellaneous trifles were overlooked and these oversights are to be corrected now. There are always things that legislators forget when they make new laws. Some of them are found to be not severe enough, and some to be too severe; at times just the opposite is achieved of what had been attempted. Then again, it appears that the law is useless and unnecessary, but to change laws that are in effect is, as a rule, much more difficult than to enact them. Some laws cause no particular difficulties in scrapping them, but it is extremely difficult to throw a constitutional amendment into the garbage. The Nineteenth or "Women's" Amendment....was to be changed, but it so happens that amendments cannot be as easily altered as skirts when they become out of style, and therefore a brand new, much better amendment is to be adopted. The <pb facs="5418478_2_1613.jpg" n="2"/>National Women's party has declared that by all means it must have a Twentieth Amendment--to make an even number of them, perhaps--and so since, it must, it will have it. There is nothing to be done against such a "must" affair, so Congress had better pass it quickly and submit it to the legislatures, and be done with it. This will prevent the picketing around the White House and the Capitol such as was going on when the congressmen could not agree as to whether the Nineteenth Amendment should be passed, or not.</p>
   <p>So we shall have a Twentieth amendment to the Federal Constitution which is expected to give to women all the rights and privileges they do not yet possess. They say that the Nineteenth Amendment was nothing but a halfway measure; that some states still have their particular property, family, and political laws of their own which favor the men, and that this is an injustice which must be corrected. Women want equal rights to own and dispose of property, equal rights to enter contracts independently from and without consideration of the man, the right to be elected to jury duty, and also the right to select a home. This last is particularly significant because the Scriptures say that the woman should <pb facs="5418478_2_1614.jpg" n="3"/>follow the man, and the state laws decree that a woman's home is where her husband's home is. The amendment is to give each the right to go his or her way, unless laws could be changed so that it would become the man's duty to follow his wife. In brief, the amendment is to do away with everything that would indicate that woman is dependent on the man in any way whatever.</p>
   <p>The adoption of this amendment will be woman's final great victory over her eternal enemy--the man. It will make for a law-manufactured equality and justice, and the suffragettes will need nothing more for complete happiness except--some of them, the older ones--a man. There is very little difference even now between the political rights of men and women. Women have the right to vote, to run for offices, to be elected, if a majority of the sex that used to be called the stronger one, agree. Many women hold important city and county offices; we even have a Miss Congressman, and who knows but that the next, if not the present, generation will not see some Miss President? It is no longer a question of right. All that is necessary is that the voters are so minded to put a suffragette in the Presidential chair. Hence women have all the rights <pb facs="5418478_2_1615.jpg" n="4"/>that men have, and a few more. Men have just a bit more to say in family and social matters, but they also have a few more duties. Man's duty is to provide for wife and children. When he fails all the wife has to do is take him to the familiar branch of the Municipal Court, and there they will give him a thorough explanation as to what he is to expect if he should not work steadily and turn the pay envelope over to his wife. When she sues for divorce, the court awards her alimony or, if that is mutually agreeable, a settlement. But if a man should be out of work and his wife happened to have some private and adequate income, could he make her support him? Of course not. Or, should he be suing for divorce, could he demand alimony in case the wife happened to have some private property and he none? Again, of course not. The wife could give him something voluntarily, but there is no law anywhere that could compel her to do so.</p>
   <p>No doubt the majority of women are satisfied with this state of affairs, but not the pugnacious American suffragettes. The average woman does not want anything else but to have a good husband who takes proper care of his family, <pb facs="5418478_2_1616.jpg" n="5"/>and she is glad to give him all the rights and privileges she is to be given by the Twentieth Amendment. But among the suffragettes there are also some who have neither a husband nor a family, and these need protection. They are sure to get it, and life will become much more interesting. Men will definitely make up their collective mind and demand equal rights also in all family and social respects. Everything will be fifty-fifty. When a young fellow invites a girl to go to a show, each will pay half of the expense. If they go to supper after the show, she will pay half of the check, and he will pay the other half. And when they get married each will pay half of the license and the marriage fee. Why not? The Twentieth Amendment will give them absolutely equal rights and impose on them absolutely equal obligations. To be sure, there must be equality also in the matter of the invitation, so this time the boy will take the girl to a dance or a show, and next time the girl will take the boy. When they go to housekeeping, they will pay for the furniture fifty-fifty, and when it comes to a divorce, the husband's lawyer will demand something in the way of alimony for his client, and if the wife will not pay, she will move to the county jail. That is what happens now to the man, and once the Twentieth Amendment is passed, <pb facs="5418478_2_1617.jpg" n="6"/>the woman will be treated in the same manner. And should we have another war some day women will be drafted, as well as men, because it would be against the Twentieth Amendment to give one the advantage over the other.</p>
   <p>Of course, it is quite possible that the suffragettes do not want to take everything so literally. They may not have it in mind to deprive the man of all his responsibility; perhaps all they want is some more rights for themselves and complete independence from the man. When they get that, the weaker male sex will be in a position to try to assert itself and demand a twenty-second amendment that will take better care of the men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
