<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-27">Sept. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Belgian Delegation in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-27">Sept. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE BELGIAN DELEGATION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the delegation sent by the Belgian nation to the President of the United States with a protest against the cruelties and wanton policy of destruction by the Germans in the occupied parts of Belgium arrived in Chicago yesterday at 10 A. M. Its members are: Minister of justice, Mr. Henry Carton De Viart; secretary to King Albert, Count Lichtervelde; minister of foreign affairs, Mr. Emil Vandervelde; and one of the world's foremost workers in the Free Thought movement, Mr. Paul Hymans.</p>
   <p>Immediately after their arrival in Chicago, the commission was besieged by newspaper reporters who were trying to learn something about the war, the possibilities of peace, and the delegates' opinions on these questions. But the commission definitely refused to enter into any discussion on topics which could be designated as unneutral, and they limited their remarks to their admiration of America in general and Chicago in particular.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the evening, in the reception hall of Hotel de Jonghe, the delegation of Chicago Bohemians was presented to the Belgians by the Belgian consul of Chicago, Dr. Cyrill Vermere. The Bohemian delegation consisted of Messrs. James F. Stepina, Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal, Jos. Holpuch, Dr. Ludwig Fisher, and Jaromir Psenka, who placed in the hands of the representatives of the Belgian nation a memorial document printed in the French language about the situation, desires, and rights of the Bohemian nation, and an expression of the warm sympathy and true admiration of the valiant Belgian nation by American Bohemians.</p>
   <p>The Belgian delegation left Chicago the same night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
