<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Impractical State Administration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IMPRACTICAL STATE ADMINISTRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many complaints are being voiced against the inefficiency of our city administration because the administration consists of various bodies, each of which conducts its business independently, without regard to other similar bodies. This method results in inefficiency and waste that would be eliminated if all the functions of these groups were concentrated in the Municipal Council. These complaints are not new. In fact, they have been discussed on many occasions in the past, but we hardly ever hear such complaints against the antiquated system of our state administration, which is just as bad, or worse. The taxpayers may not notice this waste, because the seat of the state administration is far away from them and therefore escapes the attention it should by right have.....</p>
   <p>During a long period of years our Springfield government has created a large <pb facs="5418478_2_0350.jpg" n="2"/>number of councils and commissions in order to provide "soft" jobs for politicians to whom it had owed favors and upon whose favors it depends for reelection. These commissions spend money which must be collected through taxation, and it is again only the voter who pays. Hardly any session of the legislature fails to appoint a new council or a new commission. The Governor then appoints a number of commissioners, each of whom in turn appoints a number of clerks and inspectors, whose main task seems to consist of collecting their pay check every month. In addition to this, it frequently happens that those who are appointed on such commissions are no experts, as one should expect but men fully unacquainted with the work they have been appointed to do. Just recently, these comments have been made about the State Agricultural Commission which,obviously, should consist mostly of farmers, but in which the leading members are men who have never had anything to do with farming and therefore cannot be considered farming experts.</p>
   <p>But even this is not the principal fault of the system of commissions. Its main fault is the fact that there are too many of them. We now have 139 such commissions, and if nothing will be done about it the chances are that their <pb facs="5418478_2_0351.jpg" n="3"/>number will continue to grow. Each of these commissions has certain duties which it performs independently and without consideration for other commissions, departments, or councils. Thus, frequently two or more of them work at cross-purposes, one against the intentions of the other, or their work overlaps. They maintain offices in Chicago, in Springfield, and perhaps in other places, and our public affairs are conducted in a way that could not be tolerated in any private enterprise, unless it was purposely working toward bankruptcy. Their methods cause the taxpayers unnecessary expense which could easily be avoided if a more sensible system of state administration were introduced, and if several of the existing commissions would merge, and thus the work could be properly centralized. This suggestion was discussed during the recent session of the state legislature, and upon the initiative of Senator Haye, a special committee was appointed whose duty it is to study this question thoroughly and in the next session propose the best methods of changing and simplifying the whole system. One member of this committee is Professor John A. Fairlie, of the University of Illinois, who is a student of questions involved in the contemplated change. After long deliberation, the committee agreed upon a proposal, <pb facs="5418478_2_0352.jpg" n="4"/>according to which all the expensive commissions would be dissolved and all work concentrated in the hands of a few groups directly responsible to the governor. The proposal is particularly interesting because it recommends the establishment of a kind of Governor's cabinet, somewhat on the order of the President's cabinet, along whose lines it is evidently patterned. The governor of our state would have a cabinet composed of several officers, or secretaries, who would be entrusted with the various phases of government. These would be: Finance, education, charity, prisons and houses of correction, public works and buildings, agriculture, mines and works, commerce and industry, elections, justice, and military affairs. All together there would be, then, eleven departments which would take over all the work now being done by the 139 commissions, as far as this system would be found in compliance with the state constitution. The committee would propose, it is said, still more radical changes, but our present constitution makes them impractical. They would be possible only after the adoption of certain constitutional amendments. This would involve most difficult and tedious proceeding at best, provided that the legislature could <pb facs="5418478_2_0353.jpg" n="5"/>be moved to permit such reforms. Hence, a change of the Illinois constitution appears almost impossible. In other states of the Union, constitutional conventions are being called which adopt amendments that make their constitutions more up-to-date, but something of that kind is inconceivable as far as Springfield is concerned. Therefore, it would be hopeless to expect anything more radical than a cabinet of eleven members, or eleven departments, which would take over the work of all existing commissions.</p>
   <p>Nobody doubts that such a change would be most profitable. The state administration would be put on something more of business basis, which would mean large savings. The state administration now has many offices in Chicago only, with a large number of clerks and other employees; its business is chopped up into so many pieces that it is impossible to expect that it could be conducted properly. Very little is accomplished, and what is done is not done well,although the machinery costs a great deal of money. In addition to all this, there is nobody who would be responsible for the work that should be done. According to the above-mentioned proposal, all work would be simplified,and the head of each <pb facs="5418478_2_0354.jpg" n="6"/>department would have to account to the governor for all of his actions. The public realizes the need for reform, but that does not yet mean that a reform will be made. Our voters should see to it that such elements in our legislature that are favorable to reforms are encouraged and forced to action by all means that are at their disposal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
