<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-30">Mar. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Evil Worse Than War</title><title level="a" type="sub">Victory of Prussian Militarism (By the Press Bureau of the Czech National Association)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-30">Mar. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN EVIL WORSE THAN WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Victory of Prussian Militarism (By the Press Bureau of the Czech National Association)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There has risen here, especially since the tension between Germany and the United States has begun to grow, a propaganda whose battle cry is "Peace at any price!" Many of these voices sound in discord, tuned partly to the jingle of the German mark, and partly to the sympathy desired by the Germans, but woefully lacking in our country.</p>
   <p>These propagandists are not in the pay of American capitalists, and yet their activities are sure to cost many millions. No one ever hears of a public collection for them. Politicians, statesmen, the intellectuals, not to mention the workingmen, do not contribute to their funds, and yet....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1100.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While thousands of telegrams and appeals flooded the United States to be followed by another ten thousand intended for the President and Congress, we established the fact that though no resolutions against War had been passed by our Czech organizations, telegrams from many places were foisted upon Washington. These messages might be interpreted in a sense that the Czech workingmen are pro-Austrian and pro-German, and that they are totally indifferent to the fate of a nation which depends on the defeat of Germany.</p>
   <p>Great numbers of men and women, known among the people from their public activities, were sent innumerable telegrams calling upon them to send messages and resolutions to the President and to protest against War, either personally or representing organizations, single, or in entire groups.</p>
   <p>Editor's Note: Why cannot the Czech National Association identify the <pb facs="5418478_2_1101.jpg" n="3"/>writers? We know that in Chicago there were meetings held against the War, and that there had been Czech participants and speakers. We did not keep silent, but wrote about it. We are not afraid to expose these conditions again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
