<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-29">Nov. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">We Cannot Understand That Slav Nation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0766</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0766.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-29">Nov. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WE CANNOT UNDERSTAND THAT SLAV NATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Reports reached us a few months ago that the Polish block of the Austrian Parliament refused to vote for the war budget of the Monarchy. In the first shock of pleasant surprise we wrote in this column, commenting joyfully on the action of the Poles, for it meant undisguised opposition to the Austrian Government. It showed us that the Poles have finally assumed a definite attitude in the present struggle of nations.</p>
   <p>"However, the events following proved that our rejoicing was premature. News arrived from Vienna to the effect that the Polish block rescinded its decision and is determined to vote for the war budget. This is in return for some concessions made by the Austrian Government in regard to the Polish population of the Austrian province Galizia. This latter decision <pb facs="5418478_2_0767.jpg" n="2"/>saved the face of the Austrian Government. A refusal by the Poles would have shown the world that the majority of the population under the Monarchy is actually opposed to the government. It was Representative Daszynski, Socialist, who betrayed the Poles into the agreement with the Austrian Government.</p>
   <p>"How the Germans reward the Poles in the meantime for their acquiescence is glaringly illustrated by the following article from Frederick Wolcott, American newspaperman. It depicts the sufferings of the Poles in unmistakable terms.....</p>
   <p>"Lo and behold the Germans--that same nation to whom the Poles are offering aid and comfort! It is the same nation for whom the Polish premier, Kucharzewski, is about to organize a Polish army against the Allies, and, <pb facs="5418478_2_0768.jpg" n="3"/>no less, against the United States, which is wasting so much useless sympathy on the Poles. Such is the behavior of the Polish premier, who, being a professor of history, ought to be among the first to expose the real enemy of the Polish nation. 'To understand is to excuse,' says a French proverb. We, however, shall never forgive the Poles, for the simple reason that we cannot grasp the sense in their actions."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
