<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-12">May 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To All Bohemian Women!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-12">May 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL BOHEMIAN WOMEN!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sisters!</p>
   <p>In these days when our people, the people of John Huss, is forced to remain silent in its native lands, we, the free daughters of this great republic have a [sacred] duty to perform. Our common Mother calls! Thousands of Bohemian mothers grieve for their fallen, thousands of them, with aching hearts, expect the fatal news from the battle front, thousands of them writhe in anxiety about their sons. All of them are looking forward to the day that will end this terrible war.</p>
   <p>On behalf of these hundreds of thousands of afflicted Bohemian mothers, we ask all Bohemian-American women: Come and help, so that the sacrifices of Bohemian mothers in the old country may not be in vain! Come and work with us, so that our common Mother, our greatly suffering native land, may attain, in return for sacrifices, the greatest national attribute, liberty, and a government by the people in the Bohemian lands, both of which are necessary <pb facs="5418478_2_1642.jpg" n="2"/>for a permanent peace. Remember that with the exception of Scandinavia, Bohemia was the only country to elect a woman to its diet, thus indicating that the Bohemian people recognized woman's right to political work and full status in public life.</p>
   <p>Let us help the nation that has always fought for freedom of conscience and human progress! Participate in the political action of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance), the aim of which is the liberation of Bohemia, Moravia, Silesia, and Slovakia.</p>
   <p>We are calling a meeting of all Bohemian women, members of benevolent sister-hoods, Sokol organizations, as well as all those unaffiliated to be held in the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Pomocne Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) on 18th and May Streets, May 14, at 8 P.M. Be sure to come and help work side by side with the men, toward the goal of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, and hand in hand with them, prove that Bohemian women are just as able national workers, as are our men, that they are able to co-operate and <pb facs="5418478_2_1643.jpg" n="3"/>sacrifice for our common Mother in this year of John Huss.</p>
   <p>Anna Stolfa, chairman,</p>
   <p>[of a committee of seventeen women].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
