<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-22">Sept. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to Czar Nicholas</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article by the correspondence Bureau of the Association of Bohemian-American Journalists)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-22">Sept. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO CZAR NICHOLAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article by the correspondence Bureau of the Association of Bohemian-American Journalists)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the chairmanship of Professor M. I. Pupin, Serbian honorary consul in New York, a meeting of the representatives of all Slavic newspapers and central Polish, Russian, Bohemian-Slavonic, Serbian, etc., organizations was held in New York. The representatives met on September 15 and approved the text of a proclamation which will be sent to all central organizations of Slavic peoples for signatures and then will be delivered to the Russian Ambassador, who promised to give it to Czar Nicholas. The manifesto reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"HIS IMPERIAL MAJESTY, NICHOLAS, CZAR of all the RUSSIANS</p>
   <p>"Your Imperial proclamation to the Poles has thrilled the hearts of all the <pb facs="5418478_2_1495.jpg" n="2"/>Slavs and particularly all the Slavs of the United states of America. It is a message of brotherly love which Great Russia cherishes for her Slavonic brothers in Russia and in other lands. This love is the strongest guarantee that the dawn of Slavonic freedom has arrived, when every Slav will be free to worship the God and to speak the language of his forefathers, and to work out the destiny of his national existence in his and individual way. By your imperial proclamation Great Russia offers her strong and brotherly hand, and now we are grasping it, fully confident that we are grasping the hand of our great and powerful Slavonic brother who loves us, and who will help us to gain a worthy place among the free and independent nations of the world.</p>
   <p>"We assure your Imperial Majesty, and through you we assure our Slavonic brothers of Great Russia, that the Slavs will never for the great sacrifices which the brave Russian Army has made for the freedom of the Slavs and we promise eternal love and loyalty to the Slavonic cause which Great Russia is championing.</p>
   <p>"The Slavonic brotherhood of the United States of America."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
