<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-21">July 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-21">July 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States Government insures its soldiers in amounts of from one thousand to ten thousand dollars. Not only that, but the Government has also taken steps to protect the soldier from losing the insurance to which he is entitled by his brotherhood.</p>
   <p>It would be of interest to us to know to what degree the American soldier is using this protection; for we think that only a very small number are doing so. According to the law, no American soldier can be excluded from his brotherhood, nor can his insurance be cancelled. This applies for the duration of the war and one year after; but after such time the dues on the soldier's policy must be paid up lest it become invalid.</p>
   <p>We believe that these strict regulations will not have to be applied often, because many brotherhoods are paying the dues for their soldier members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some of the soldiers pay themselves, while relatives pay for others. The American soldier receives higher pay than any other soldier in the world, and there is enough money left for him, even after his military insurance dues and monthly allowance for his dependents are deducted.</p>
   <p>We have yet to hear of an instance when a Czech-American soldier was excluded from his brotherhood for non-payment of dues--and we hope it will never happen. In case a soldier should find himself in such a predicament, he should stand upon the right given him by the new law. Our Czech brotherhoods have been taking a real patriotic attitude, and are accommodating their soldiers in every way. The Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnot (Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society), for instance, relieves its soldiers from the payment of all but dues on death benefits, and we are certain that other organizations treat them in an equally brotherly manner.</p>
   <p>We should think of what is being done for our boys who joined the Czechoslovak <pb facs="5418478_2_0500.jpg" n="3"/>Army, whose ranks are constantly growing. There are probably only few who do not belong to some organization or other. The United States Government does not guarantee them any insurance, and their pay is rather small, so that they may really get into trouble about their dues; and this could easily jeopardize their insurance. We do not predict that this case will arise. It is possible, however, for the soldier of the Czechoslovak Army is not taken care of as well as Uncle Sam's men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
