<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">Sept. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Liberating Action</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">Sept. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE LIBERATING ACTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There has been a great deal of debate and discussion about the events in Europe. Among Bohemians, all of these events are being discussed with particular reference to the old country, and hundreds of various assumptions are being voiced as to what is going to happen if Austria and Germany are defeated in the present war. Many people talk and newspapers write about the historic moment that has come for the Bohemians, a moment whose importance should be clear to the whole nation.</p>
   <p>We admit that there is some truth in this; we admit that there is a great deal of truth in this. A historic time has come for our nation, and its future destiny cannot be ignored by us, even though we are far away from our nation's homeland. None of us can remain indifferent; we all know that. But on the <pb facs="5418478_2_1487.jpg" n="2"/>other hand, we should hate to see any premature, childish action, because neither could help the Bohemian cause, and both could do a lot of damage.</p>
   <p>As far as we know, there exists a Bohemian-American liberating movement. We are by no means hostile to this action. Every one of the us would be happy to see his native country free, to see that it has all the rights and privileges to which it is entitled; but on the other hand, we wish to call attention to a few points which give that action a character which is, to say the least, rather peculiar. We want to send advice to the old country, a country where there are many serious, smart, and intelligent men, and in doing this, we forget that while we are giving advice to others, we do not know how to advise ourselves. Let us first straighten out matters in our own midst and then try to straighten out things in the old country after we have shown a degree of success here in our own house. Not until then can our efforts be looked upon as serious and promising. We have been working here for fity years and so far have been unable to endow our living here with a certain, definite form, a definite direction.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1488.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore it is right to believe that in a case which concerns not only a branch of a nation, but the nation itself--a nation that has strong and sound foundations--we could give form and direction to that nation in the brief space of a few months? We doubt it.....And if we continue working in that direction, we are undertaking something, which we must know in advance, that is beyond our strength. Let us not overestimate ourselves, but let us rather realize that we do not have sufficient energy for our own small local affairs, and that we certainly do not have sufficient energy to conduct the affairs of the whole nation. They still have energy in Bohemia, and they will show it when the proper time for it comes.</p>
   <p>And let us admit something else: We lack not only energy, but we also lack intelligence to undertake any action that would command respect. As an example, let us consider this trifle: We have on hand many letters deriding and abusing us because we carry war news which is unfavorable to Austria. We are accused of being poor Bohemians because we continue to write against Austria, which, <pb facs="5418478_2_1489.jpg" n="4"/>according to our news, is losing the war, while we write about the Serbs, Russians, and Montenegrins as continuous victors. With such people, such Slavs among us, is it possible to undertake any action or to rely on their support--Slavs who see their future in old Austria, under old Austria's conditions?</p>
   <p>Just recently we had a visit from a "true Bohemian" who could not find strong enough language to threaten us for the way we write about Austria. He will show us, he said, that there are still good Bohemians and Moravians, and they will know how to stop our impudent language and our attacks against Austria. We are lying, he said, when we say that Austria is losing and Russia is winning, a condition which puts us, Bohemians, to shame. When we asked this enlightened Slav why he doesn't tell this to our English-language newspapers from whom we obtain all our war news, he replied that he gives a piece of his mind to whomever he wants to give it, and that is, in the first place, to the editors of the paper to which he subscribes. A great many of his friends, he said, are <pb facs="5418478_2_1490.jpg" n="5"/>strongly opposed to the way the Bohemian papers write about the war, and they will not tolerate the continuous attacks and offenses against Austria.</p>
   <p>Now, is that not characteristic? Does it not plainly show how immature a certain part of the Slavic people in America are? Is it with this kind of human material that we must work for the liberation of our country? If we were to tell this to other people, they would not believe it was true. But it is. Is it not enough to break one's heart?</p>
   <p>We have evidence to this effect, and we can readily believe that among such people, there are many Slavic patriots who would be busy going to the consulate and enthusiastically informing everybody there about each step that is being taken for the liberation of our old country, and the Austrian government would know all about the action before everything could be attempted in Bohemia. That, we believe.</p>
   <p>It is our suggestion, therefore, that anything is to be done for our old country, <pb facs="5418478_2_1491.jpg" n="6"/>let us, in the first place, collect contributions. Then let us collect more and more contributions. Nothing will be more sorely needed in the old country than money. There will be not hundreds, but thousands of widows and orphans of our soldiers; there will be many careworn mothers who lost their only support, their sons, in the war; there will be many people of all kinds whom the war has brought to the verge of misery, starvation, and despair. Let us do some heavy liberating alone these lines, and we shall have a lot of work to do--work that will be remembered someday by the entire Bohemian nation. Let us be good Samaritans; let us be humans; and let us forget political actions. Let us leave that for those in the old country who know how to go about it--to our leaders there, to our members of the parliament, all of whom will be in the right places at the right time and will know what to do and how to do it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
