<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-22">Mar. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs Work for War Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-22">Mar. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS WORK FOR WAR BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Czech section for the promotion of war bond sales took place in the offices of Cermak and Serhant, realtors, 3347 West 26th Street, last night. Their lively participation in the campaign convinces us that Czech interest is growing by leaps and bounds, and that the splendid showing they made in the first two campaigns will be excelled in the third. The Czech population's response in the second series brought forth such brilliant results that authorities used the Czechs as examples for all other nationalistic bodies. The system employed in the second campaign proved so effective that it will again be used.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chairman of the campaign committee, opened the meeting in which Mr. Salat, secretary, and other members of the committee presented suggestions which were thoroughly discussed.</p>
   <p>"We must dispose of all the business immediately on hand, even if we stay until <pb facs="5418478_2_0615.jpg" n="2"/>morning," Mr. Cermak cautioned. The meeting did last until midnight, at that.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vaclav Vanek and Jaroslav F. Smetanka reported on publicity. Mr. John A. Cervenka is chairman of the speakers' committee and Mr. Jos. F. Bolek is secretary. All of the committees were enlarged by the advent of new members. Mr. Cervenka declared: "In order to avoid misunderstandings, I wish to warn all those who want to be placed on my committee that I have no use for people who do not intend to work constantly and persistently. There will be a great deal of work to do, and it will have to be done. I shall not wait until I am asked to supply a speaker. I am going to keep an accurate list of all meetings to be held and shall send speakers there. All of these speakers will have to submit a weekly report showing where they spoke and, if possible, to how many people. I entreat those named to my committee to resign if they do not intend to devote all the time to the work that will be asked of them."</p>
   <p>Mr. Cervenka's statements, of course, refer to all other committees as well; they were generally accepted in that spirit.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0616.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Messrs. Jan L. Novak and Joseph J. Janda, representing aid societies and brotherhoods, assured the meeting that their organizations will do everything in their power to co-operate with the committee. Messrs. James F. Stepina and Frank G. Hajicek, members of the bank and brokerage committee, spoke in a similar vein. The committee on lodges and associations, represented by Messrs. Jos. A. Smejkal and F. J. Adam, reported that they had sent out letters to all organizations asking them to nominate one member who would see that his unit is doing its duty during this third drive.</p>
   <p>Members of other committees reported on work they have accomplished and accepted new duties which were assigned to them. The men were: Judge J. Z. Uhlir and Jos. A. Holpuch, the committee on schools; R. W. Dvorak and M. Straus, the committee representing businessmen who are going to arrange a propaganda parade in the near future; Messrs. Otto Kerner and John Toman, members of the committee on industries, in whose factories many meetings will be held for the Czech workers. Members from Town of Lake and Cicero also reported on their activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0617.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Members of the committee on exemptions declared that all those who, for various reasons, have not become soldiers will be urged to buy as many bonds as they can, and so help toward victory. Dr. Ludwig J. Fisher, of the Czech National Alliance, and Reverend Kestl, of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, stated that they are about to name leaders of their organizations for every county branch in the Seventh district, to which Illinois belongs. These leaders will keep in contact with each other for better co-operation in the drive.</p>
   <p>It was also resolved that plans for a mass meeting of our people should be formulated at the next meeting of the Czech section of the campaign.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
