<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-02">Apr. 2, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">[Demand Candidates Oppose the Fifty Franchise]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-02">Apr. 2, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">[DEMAND CANDIDATES OPPOSE THE FIFTY FRANCHISE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few sincere words to Bohemian voters of Chicago: The coming period of the new elections to the City Council moves me to address to the voters of our own nationality a few sincere words - not as a partisan, but as an honorably minded citizen who sees with sorrow how all morals decline among us in regard to politics.</p>
   <p>I have watched closely, until the present time, how the various candidates seek the confidence and votes of their constituents, but I have not found one who would touch on the main subjects which are being contested at this coming election or would make a positive declaration about them.</p>
   <p>In the last legislature the so-called Allen Law was passed, which empowers the City of Chicago to give privileges to street railways and other concerns; not, as previously, from one to twenty years, but from one to fifty years. As is known, the honest and sincere elements of the local citizenry have worked hard, with Mayor Harrison as leader, to defeat this proposition, so that it would be impossible for future City Councils to lengthen such privileges. But the influence of the corporations concerned was able to overcome the <pb facs="5418478_2_0363.jpg" n="2"/>endeavors of our mayor and this dangerous proposition became a law.</p>
   <p>What is more natural than that the corrupt elements, who were able by dis-honorable methods to make the legislature do their bidding, should now concentrate all their efforts to have a more favorable majority elected to the City Council and enable this abominable Allen Law to have unobstructed passage? They have the law - it certainly cost them an enormous sum, therefore, they are now trying to have the bribed majority of the City Council put this law into practice; that is at the earliest opportunity - to turn over our streets not for a new ten or twenty year period but immediately for the entire fifty years and thereby enslave our city for the entire fifty years to their despotic extortion.</p>
   <p>Would you Bohemian fellow citizens want to allow this to happen by voting into the City Council people who are probably nominated for just such a purpose? I believe and hope that such is not the wish of any one of us and therefore I propose that safeguards be provided at this time as follows:</p>
   <p>Have each of the candidates from whichever ward who are presented to you for <pb facs="5418478_2_0364.jpg" n="3"/>election, give you an oral or written declaration that, on his honor, he will not vote for any proposition which in any manner would make this ruinous Allen Law effective in Chicago; that, in fact, he will never vote in our City Council for giving street privileges to anybody under whatever pretext, for more than twenty or twenty-five years at the most.</p>
   <p>Let us have as a watch word at this year's election the following: No one shall receive our vote who does not fulfill these requirements, and anyone of the elected who betrays this trust will be covered with shame and be rejected in the future by his constituents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
