<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-12">Jan. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czecho-Slavonic Division Allied Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-12">Jan. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHO-SLAVONIC DIVISION ALLIED BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who have known the Coliseum from diverse affairs arranged in it, will think themselves spirited away into the realm of "One Thousand and One Nights" when they enter this most spacious hall in Chicago to visit the Allied bazaar. A transfiguration seems to have taken place there.</p>
   <p>The iron structure seems to have vanished, for it is buried under a wealth of flowers, flags, and other decorations. Uncounted multitudes are surging through the building, all in a joyous, happy mood. The visitor is becoming aware that charity has taken quarters here. The Allied bazaar is the greatest humanitarian enterprise since the outbreak of the World War, and the proceeds from it are to go to alleviate the sufferings of the people in the countries smitten by the tragedy of the international bloodshed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1157.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bazaar is to last till January 20, and for every day a splendid program has been prepared. The hours are from 1 P.M. to 11 P.M.; in the cabaret side-room till 1 A.M. Among the many who have helped build up the bazaar there are to be found ladies of the European artistocracy from the allied countries and those associated with these. But the greatest number of helpful men and women came from the ranks of the nations directly involved in the war; the Czechs and the Slovaks are, therefore, represented by impressive numbers and in a dignified manner.</p>
   <p>The Czecho-Slavonic division consists of two parts; i.e., two tents in which our ladies are exhibiting gifts of the most appropriate kinds, as embroideries, tid-bits, etc., so that the tents are, so to say, little fairs for our women's handicraft. The objects are conspicuous through their gay colors and prove more attractive than many other exhibits much <pb facs="5418478_2_1158.jpg" n="3"/>more precious at first sight. Groups of young women in national costumes lend the Czecho-Slavonic division so much more character.</p>
   <p>The Czecho-Slavonic division is supervised by a joint committee consisting of members of our largest organizations. About forty ladies have burdened themselves with the task of tending to the visitors of our exhibition. A special program is being prepared for Saturday under the direction of V. P. Cerny, music pedagogue; the performances will take place in the cabaret side-room. It is to be noted that the ladies' section of the Pilzen Sokol was most generous with gifts for the bazaar, many of these of high value. They are all products of industry and skill, and it is to be expected that more will follow from other organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
