<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-06">May 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">In Protest against the Barbour Bill</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-06">May 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IN PROTEST AGAINST THE BARBOUR BILL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Czech branch of the United Societies was held in the hall of Sokol Chicago, 24th Street and Kedzie Avenue, Friday evening, John A. Červenka presiding. It was a large assembly of men and women, well known for their activities in the Chicago Czech community. Mr. Joseph Stastny functioned for Mr. Anton J. Čermák, secretary of the society, the latter being prevented from attending on account of some other meeting.....</p>
   <p>The object of the meeting was a discussion of the Barbour bill which prohibits dances or entertainments of any kind in which more than four persons take part, and where alcoholic beverages are served. This bill is a crude, ruthless attack on personal liberty, and blue-nosed moralists are making <pb facs="5418478_2_1561.jpg" n="2"/>strenuous efforts to make it a law. It has not been given due consideration by the judiciary committee, which closed its eyes, and after recommending it, sent it to the Senate where it passed. The moralists, be it well understood, had produced witnesses of dubious reputations before the legislative body. Among these were several paid prostitutes who testified that entertainments where liquor was served had started them on their road to delinquency. During the discussion, it was brought to light that Miss Napieralska, secretary of the Polish Women's Alliance had appeared before the judiciary committee and pleaded for favorable action on the bill.</p>
   <p>The United Societies also had their spokesmen before the judiciary committee. They were headed by Mr. Jandus, who appropriately protested against the curtailing of our personal liberty, advancing the fact that the city ordinances are perfectly sufficient to bar indecent entertainment.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1562.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The House is going to vote on the bill next week. Representative Joseph Placek is still holding out some hope that the bill may not pass. Nevertheless the meeting resolved to send urgent appeals, individual or collective, to all Representatives to thwart the passage of the pernicious bill. Representative Plaček further made the announcement that a petition sent to the House in favor of the bill was signed also by our "liberal-minded" Judge Fisher of the Municipal court, whom the Czechs have so staunchly supported during election, and who, so to say, owes them his office. Mmes. Velik, Ženišek, and Shejbal, representing various Czech women's organizations announced that energetic demands had been made on the Representatives for the rejection of the Barbour bill .....</p>
   <p>It was finally resolved to start concerted action which would combine the forces of all Czech societies for a monster protest. Mr. Bolek then took occasion to voice a complaint against some men of social or political prominence who had given themselves the air of rabid foes of the bill, <pb facs="5418478_2_1563.jpg" n="4"/>but who, when they were called on for action, responded by resting their hands upon their laps, and made themselves conspicuous by their absence.</p>
   <p>The meeting adjourned after an arrangements committee had been appointed for the United Societies convention, to be held in the Bohemian National Hall, May 29.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
