<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-27">Oct. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Call Issued by the Bohemian Freethinkers of Cicero</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-27">Oct. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A CALL ISSUED BY THE BOHEMIAN FREETHINKERS OF CICERO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends and citizens of both sexes! Whenever our liberty, which is guaranteed by the Constitution of the United States, is threatened, the free-thinkers are ready to defend it, no matter what their political party may be. The people are entitled to learn about danger impending in order to be able to combat it successfully. The citizens of Illinois will on December 12, 1922 have an opportunity to vote on the proposed new revision of the State constitution. Among other provisions, which form the parts of the new revision there is one which says that it is not in contravention of the [spirit of] the constitution of the State to introduce the teaching of the Bible into the public schools.</p>
   <p>The liquor prohibition was introduced against the will of the people, and <pb facs="5418478_2_0060.jpg" n="2"/>no thinking individual can agree with it, for it caused more alcoholics, more social and family disorganization, more murders, and more deaths than occurred before it was imposed. We have already had enough of the emasculation of our liberty for the benefit of a few individuals. We have had enough of the evils which hooded sectarians have prepared for us under various disguises.</p>
   <p>It is because of these facts that the Mistni Sdruzeni Svazu Svobodomyslnych Cicero (local branch of the Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers of Cicero) have undertaken to hold a public mass meeting on Sunday, October 29, 1922. The meeting is to take place at 2 P.M. in the large assembly hall of the T. G. Masaryk School, West 22nd Place and 57th Avenue, Cicero, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Every feature of the proposed new revision of the State constitution will be properly explained to the people. There will be good speakers there who will <pb facs="5418478_2_0061.jpg" n="3"/>address the meeting in English and in Czech. The program will also provide entertainment.</p>
   <p>Admission will be free. Therefore let all the citizens of Cicero and vicinity attend this meeting.</p>
   <p>Frantisek Suchy, president</p>
   <p>Frank Krupar, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
