<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-18">Oct. 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Lodges Push Bond Sale</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-18">Oct. 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH LODGES PUSH BOND SALE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czech committee which was organized some days ago for the purpose of boosting the sale of bonds for the Second Liberty Loan, sent out its members to stimulate interest among individuals, business houses, lodges, and clubs in the Czech districts of Chicago. Those men submitted the first report on the results of their survey to the committee in a recent session. The report was very favorable, stating that not one organization, whether it be a building and loan, brotherhood, aid society, or glee club, refused to invest at least part of its funds in the Loan.</p>
   <p>The Česko-Slovanská Podporující Společnost (Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society) took the lion's share in these transactions, and the credit for this progress is attributed to Mr. Joseph A. Šmejkal who zealously visited the <pb facs="5418478_2_0799.jpg" n="2"/>meetings of the various lodges of this aid society, urging the officers and members to buy the bonds. The amounts range from $100 to $1,000.....</p>
   <p>Three Czech ladies' societies bought bonds for $800, according to reports received up to today.</p>
   <p>Three Czech Odd Fellows lodges bought bonds together for $3,800; two Masonic lodges bought bonds together for $1,000; three Catholic associations invested $1,550.</p>
   <p>Czech business firms responded as follows: Employees of Bursík &amp; Krupka, $650; California Manufacturing Company, $2,300; People's Fuel and Supply Company, $1,000; 26th Street Businessmen's Association, $2,000; City Sanitary Dairy, $2,500.</p>
   <p>Messrs. John L. Novák and Joseph J. Janda announced a total subscription <pb facs="5418478_2_0800.jpg" n="3"/>of $10,900 from nineteen Czech building and loan associations.</p>
   <p>Judge Jos. Uhlifr and Mr. Joseph Holpuch reported on a meeting which was called by them and attended by 1,500 principals and school teachers, all of whom promised to co-operate by explaining to school children the advantages offered in the bond issue, thus indirectly inducing the parents to buy bonds.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that all Czechs thoroughly understand the importance of the bonds for the preservation of liberty here and the attainment of independence for the old homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
