<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Powerful Demonstration</title><title level="a" type="sub">Parade and Meeting Attract Thousands</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A POWERFUL DEMONSTRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Parade and Meeting Attract Thousands</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If there were any who had the slightest doubts about the friendly feelings of the Chicago Czechs for the Allied nations, or about Czech loyalty to the United States, their misgivings or suspicions were allayed and converted into confidence by the parade which led through the streets of the "Czech California" district and the subsequent meeting held in the auditorium of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, South Lawndale Avenue and West 26th Street, yesterday. The spirit of genuine patriotism was so strongly manifested that it made the heart of everyone who witnessed the events throb with emotion.</p>
   <p>The Auxiliary, composed of citizens of the Thirty-fourth and Twelfth Wards, was the sponsor of these two patriotic demonstrations, the purpose of which was primarily to show to our Chicago Czech boys who enlisted last Wednesday for service in Uncle Sam's Army that they will be remembered, encouraged, and aided whenever help is needed. The Auxiliary succeeded in this, for <pb facs="5418478_2_0744.jpg" n="2"/>many soldiers were given furloughs and thus could participate in the festivities. They had taken part in the great parade held in the city last Saturday. Members of the Auxiliary, including Alderman John Toman, Anton Vanĕk, Anton J. Čermák, chief bailiff of the municipal court, and Judge Otto Kerner, had appealed to the military authorities to grant the soldiers a furlough for Sunday so that they could be present at yesterday's (Sunday's) manifestation. The request was granted and, in addition, a military band was placed at the disposal of the Chicago Czechs. Officers of the United States Army joined the marching columns headed by Colonel Chas. R. Howland.</p>
   <p>The marchers started from the home of Sokol Chicago. The parade began at 2 P. M. led by a squad of mounted police and a group of policemen from the Lawndale Avenue station under the personal command of Captain Ptáček. Mr. Otto Pelikán was marshal. He was followed by Boy Scouts with their commander, J. A. Sokol. Then came the band of an artillery regiment called The Czech, because it consists mostly of soldiers of Czech descent. The Pomocne <pb facs="5418478_2_0745.jpg" n="3"/>Občanskĕ Vyborý (Citizens' Auxiliary Committees) of the Twelfth and Thirty-fourth Wards were next, headed by their chairmen, Anton J. Čermák and V. Jelínek. The recruiting commission for the 27th and 83rd divisions was led by Messrs. Baumruck, Anton Vanĕk, A. Rezím and Dr. Žábokrtský. They were joined by such leaders in our civic life as Alderman John Toman, Judge Otto Kerner, Mr. Novák, and Judge Joseph Uhlíř of the municipal court.</p>
   <p>The hub of the parade was formed by the soldiers with Colonel Charles R. Howland and other officers of the United States Army. They and the other soldiers had come from the military training camp at Rockford, Illinois; they all had taken part in the parade held in the downtown district yesterday.</p>
   <p>The marching columns did not have to worry about how to attract the attention of the people. The men were wildly acclaimed by the throngs who lined the sidewalks or watched from their houses. This assured our soldiers that they will not be forgotten when they face the enemy to fight for world democracy. They are leaving, but they take with them the heartfelt wishes of millions of <pb facs="5418478_2_0746.jpg" n="4"/>Americans for victory and a happy return. There were about two hundred to two hundred and fifty soldiers who were hailed by the throngs. Men waved their hats, and women waved their handkerchiefs or lifted up their children so that they might wave. Our brave men marched on with a firm military step befitting a soldier. They appeared undisturbed by the loud demonstrations of friendship and good will, yet their hearts must have been filled with strong emotions and their memories overflowing with thoughts they would never forget.</p>
   <p>The scenes of enthusiastic welcome were repeated in every stage of the parade, whether on Kedzie Avenue, 22nd Street, Whipple Street, 25th or 26th Streets, Central Park Avenue, 28th Street, Crawford Avenue, or 26th Street again. The march as far as 42nd Street was omitted, because the furloughs of some of the soldiers were limited.</p>
   <p>The parade came to a halt at the home of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs. There a large crowd had assembled even before the parade began, and the auditorium was filled <pb facs="5418478_2_0747.jpg" n="5"/>to the last place. As a safety measure the police locked the doors, in accordance with the city ordinance. Thousands tried to enter but had to content themselves with standing outside. However, due regard was shown to one part of the participants in the parade, for reservations had been made for them. At 3 P.M. our soldiers entered the hall while the strains of the "Star-Spangled Banner" filled the air. They were, however, compelled to leave immediately afterward, to the utmost regret of everybody, for duty bade them leave Chicago for Camp Rockford, and the military band left with them. The welcome extended to our soldiers had thus in reality become a farewell.</p>
   <p>The business proper of the program was then begun. Mr. V. Jelinek, chairman of the Auxiliary committee of the Thirty-fourth Ward, presided, and introduced the first speaker, Colonel Howland of the United States Army, who expressed his desire to be regarded as a soldier rather than a speaker. A stormy welcome was given this sincere friend of the Czechs. In terse sentences, characteristic of the stern commanding officer, he declared that <pb facs="5418478_2_0748.jpg" n="6"/>he was glad of the fact that the majority of the men in the military unit commanded by him were Czech. His men, he declared, are soldiers, body and soul, whose hearts beat for America, the Allies, the Czechs, and the Poles. They will help to liberate the small nations and will accomplish this by their loyalty to this country, which has become their new homeland either by their own selection or by that of their parents. Colonel Howland openly declared himself to be a representative of the American Army who sincerely stands for the liberation of the small nations, particularly of the Czechs and Poles, whom he knows as people of the right sentiment, undaunted and deserving of liberty. The time may be near, he said, when he and his men will face the enemy upon the battlefields of France. No one of his soldiers dreads that moment but, on the contrary, every one is eagerly anticipating it, if for no other reason than to return victorious very soon.</p>
   <p>These few words had a magic effect upon the audience. Everybody, particularly mothers and wives, was convinced that the Colonel was a stern leader of his soldiers, true enough, but a good friend nonetheless. He was acclaimed <pb facs="5418478_2_0749.jpg" n="7"/>with great ardor when he and the rest of the army officers were leaving the hall early, in order to be in Camp Rockford on time.</p>
   <p>There were three young army officers of Czech descent who were given a place of honor among the guests and Chicago Czech leaders. They were First Lieutenant George Engelthaler, Second Lieutenant Ed. Ptacek, son of Police Captain Ptacek of the Lawndale Avenue station, and Second Lieutenant A. Lang. All the officers were the guests of the Ceska Beseda (Czech Circle) yesterday noon.</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Perigord of the French Army was introduced. He related some of his experiences on the battlefields. He described the sufferings that France had to endure, and he declared that his country is ready to hand over to America the banner of liberty--to America, the stronger, mightier country, which will carry the emblem of freedom for the Czechs, Poles, and other Slav nations that are under the heel of Austria today. He called attention to German propaganda which is attempting to impede the war activities of the <pb facs="5418478_2_0750.jpg" n="8"/>Allies. The armies that America is building up now will guarantee not only ultimate victory, but lasting peace as well. He consoled the mothers and wives of those soldiers who will return no more, and assured them that the heroes' graves will be under the tender care of French wives and mothers. The French guest spoke with great ardor, and when leaving was honored with wild applause.</p>
   <p>The next speaker, Clarence Darrow, attorney at law, was welcomed so loudly that it was obvious he was well known to the multitude. He declared that it was unnecessary to expound to a Czech audience the significance of this war, and he expressed the desire to see all of America take the same attitude. He was pro-Ally long before the United States declared war. He was well informed of Czech regiments in the Austrian Army and their going over to the side of the Allies. He also knew of many cases in which Czech courage was given full credit for its contributions to victory. The Czechs, he said, can be found on every front in Allied military units. While politicians in our United States were still counting German votes, the Czechs <pb facs="5418478_2_0751.jpg" n="9"/>were sending their sons into the Canadian Army to fight for the liberation of their subjugated people. The Czechs all battle shoulder to shoulder--Catholic, Freethinker, and Protestant; they struggle for a better future, for the liberation of the body and soul of mankind.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jaroslav Smetanka spoke only a few words because of the lateness of the hour. The manifestation was an event which will be remembered by Chicago Czechs for a long time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
