<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-06">Sept. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To the Bohemian People in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-06">Sept. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE BOHEMIAN PEOPLE IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The European war and its consequences have gravely affected the Bohemian nation. Thousands of our men are forced to fight side by side with their oppressors against other people of Slavic blood--and misery with despair has spread through the Bohemian lands. We have to help, and the first thing that has to be done is to organize the solicitation of funds that can be sent to Bohemia as soon as conditions develop under which it will be possible to mitigate, at least to some extent, the suffering of our people. Thus, the solicitations now conducted by and on behalf of the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee) will be continued.</p>
   <p>The next thing to do is to follow the developments carefully and with deliberation and to take advantage of every opportunity that would make it possible for us to start any action toward the improvement of conditions <pb facs="5418478_2_1504.jpg" n="2"/>in Bohemia and the liberation of our nation, which has been oppressed for centuries.</p>
   <p>Finally, we must keep on informing America, through frequent articles and special publications, about the situation of our nation, its aims and aspirations, as well as disproving silly lies which are being disseminiated by our age-old enemy through the American press in these times. Collections for this work will be conducted, by the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance).</p>
   <p>In order to bring all this to a successful conclusion, two things are necessary: Organization and voluntary discipline. It is necessary to concentrate our efforts and proceed with unanimity and purposeful self-assertion. To this end, three bodies have united: The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), the Cesko-Slovansky Cerveny Kriz (Bohemian-Slavonic <pb facs="5418478_2_1505.jpg" n="3"/>Red Cross), and the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau). They have formed the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni which, through its various committees that are to be organized will plan its work and work its plan in accordance with the outlined program.</p>
   <p>These bodies do not expect to play the part of a schoolmaster for the Bohemian public and become its self-appointed ruler. They have agreed to undertake these difficult tasks in the hope that the Bohemian public will recognize the necessity for organized effort, and that it will go along with these bodies in the conviction that when the opportunity of helping our brothers in Bohemia arrives, our voice will be heard only when it will be the voice of a great, united, and disciplined whole.</p>
   <p>Let us not run the risk that this great, momentous period, which seems to be promising a new dawn even to our enslaved nation, may find us immature and small.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1506.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The funds resulting from any collections should be sent, together with an indication of the purpose for which they should be used, to Treasurer James F. Stepina, at 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, or to any one of the Bohemian newspapers.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada: Mr. F. Stanek-Bujarek, Jaroslav J. Zmrhal.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar: Emanuel Beranek, vice-president, Jaromir R. Psenka, secretary.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Slovansky vy Pomocny Vybor (formerly the Cesko-Slovansky Cerveny Kriz), J. F. Stepina, president; J. V. Nigrin, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
