<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Buy Liberty Bonds</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">BUY LIBERTY BONDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czechoslovaks are fighting not only at the front, but at home as well. The Czechoslovak name has won such repute that it is being mentioned in the present campaign of the Fourth Liberty Loan. The Chicago Daily Tribune printed an article in last Monday's issue, which is remarkable enough to attract the attention of all our fellow countrymen. It reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Instead of standing up for the Liberty Loan, we are lagging. The quota of $6,000,000,000 equals only one-tenth of the national wealth of the country. If we do not make any headway, it may happen that the Kaiser will.</p>
   <p>"Among the reports reaching us, two command our attention. The State of Iowa has oversubscribed its quota. In Bohemia, people are drawing up their last wills and are making last arrangements. These are two items far removed from each other.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0409.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yet the work involved arouses our deepest interest. Iowa is a predominantly agricultural state. During the Third Liberty Loan campaign, we, who consider ourselves to be real metropolitans, took many a fling at the farmers, accusing them of slackness in bond subscriptions. We attempted to show them how we, people from the great city, knew the right way.</p>
   <p>"A man whose interests are close to those of the farmer's writes: 'Whether this be true or not, it has incited the farmers' ambition so that they vie with all others in subscriptions now'. What do you think of this?</p>
   <p>"Czech patriots are making their testaments. This is a real act of patriotism. They are making their testaments, because Czech independence cannot be achieved without danger to those who are fighting for it. Liberty and independence have to be purchased at a high price. We, at home, are in a position to secure liberty, and draw 41/4 per cent interest at the same time. Others are making their testaments to attain the same result. Think of it!"</p>
   <p>We wish to add this: Think of it, you of the Czechoslovak branch in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0410.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Compare what you are accomplishing with what our brothers in the motherland are doing. Ponder whether you will be able to look into their faces and say, after the war, that you have done all in your power to win and preserve liberty for the motherland. Consider what they might say if you had not even dedicated your money to the cause. Money which bore interest while it was perfectly secure, whereas they were ready to give their lives. Think it over and act! Buy bonds with the last dollar to your name!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
