<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-07-06">July 6, 1880</date><title level="a">Bohemian Political Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-07-06">July 6, 1880</date><title level="a">BOHEMIAN POLITICAL CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday at a private meeting of several Bohemian citizens of the Republican, Democratic and Socialist Parties, there was organized a Bohemian Political Club. The main purpose of this meeting was to discover if possible, ways and means of injecting more life into the political activity of the Bohemians in Chicago, so that the lack of interest prevailing in the past might be overcome and that we might prove ourselves to be a live political force which is to be reckoned with and respected by other nationalities.</p>
   <p>The main objective of this club is to protect the interests of Bohemians and to achieve such strength as to assure the election of Bohemians into the various city offices, where they are needed so that we will not have to beg for our lawful rights.</p>
   <p>It was decided to call two public meetings of Bohemians, one on Saturday night in "Tel. Jed. Sokol" (Gymnastic Union Sokol) hall, the second to be held early next week in the 6th Ward.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0052.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To these meetings will be invited all citizens, without regard to political parties, so that there might be a public discussion as to what would be the best for all concerned and whether there is a possibility of uniting all forces in the interest of the Bohemian nationality. For the purpose of calling these meetings a committee of three citizens was appointed, Fr. Kohout, Fr. Stejskal and A. Pregler. They were instructed to announce the meetings and procure the necessary halls as reasonably as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
