<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Czech Lawyer's Brilliant Career</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECH LAWYER'S BRILLIANT CAREER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>František [Frank] Pošvic is one of the younger generation of Chicago Czech lawyers. The success he achieved in his profession has often been the subject of our articles.</p>
   <p>He was born in Chicago in 1884, the son of Chicago Czech pioneer settlers, who came here in 1878. After his graduation from Throop School, he located in our Plzeň [Pilsen] district. He worked as a bookbinder, and later was employed by Marshall Field &amp; Company.</p>
   <p>In 1900, he began to work in the offices of Rubens, Dupny &amp; Fischer, at that time one of the biggest lawyers' offices in Chicago. During the day, young Posvic found time enough to review the lessons taught at the Gregg school <pb facs="5418478_2_1742.jpg" n="2"/>in which he had enrolled, and which he attended evenings. A course at the Y. M. C. A., which normally takes four years to complete, he finished in two years and a half. After this course, which made up for his lacking a high school education, he entered Kent Law School, a branch of Lake Forest University. He graduated in 1909. He had passed the examinations even before his graduation. The courts of the State of Illinois then awarded a diploma to him which entitled him to membership in the Bar Association [which one, is not said in the article]. Few students can boast of a progress like this.</p>
   <p>His initial success as a lawyer was so pronounced that when a group of older lawyers consisting of Messrs. De Witt, C. Jones, Otto F. Ring, and John M. Bryant formed a partnership, he was taken into the firm where he remained until 1912.....He formed several other partnerships, and finally established himself independently. Among his clients were such big concerns as A. Holpuch Company, building contractors, the Merchants' Wholesale Grocery Company, the latter a purely Czech-American concern, and many others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1743.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Pošvic represents the legal interests of the Bohemian Orphanage and of the Bohemian Old People's Home.... Mr. Pošvic was a lawyer for the Austro-Hungarian consulate up to the time of the break in the relations between the United States and the dual-monarchy.</p>
   <p>In his private practice, Mr. Pošvic has devoted himself to jury cases.... in which he has won many a brilliant success.</p>
   <p>His private life is absorbed with manifold social activities. He is a member of the Plzenský Sokol [Pilsen district Sokol gymnastic society] and many other Chicago Czech clubs and societies, among them is the Czech-American Masonic lodge, Club Dobrovský; he is also a member of the Hamilton Club and Phi Alpha Delta brotherhood of lawyers. He was elected president of the alumni of the Kent College of Law; he being the first among our fellow-countrymen to be thus honored; he had been vice-president and secretary before.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1744.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Pošvic lives with his wife, Mrs. Irene M. Pošvic, and daughter, Dorothy, at 4024 West 22nd Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
