<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Boys to Depart Saturday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czechoslovak Committee)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR BOYS TO DEPART SATURDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czechoslovak Committee)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enthusiasm evoked by the arrival of officers of the Czechoslovak Army in France has borne fruit in the form of numerous enlistments for voluntary service. More and more of our boys have entered our army during the last week. One group came from Nebraska last Tuesday and went sight-seeing in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Military Committee for the Czechoslovak Army has been exceedingly busy these days. Lieutenant Holy and Vojta Benes, school teacher, visited Racine, Wisconsin. The lieutenant, accompanied by the Reverend Vaniscak, recruited twenty-seven Slovaks in Joliet, Illinois, last Monday.</p>
   <p>At a large meeting in Town of Lake, last Tuesday, seventeen men signed up as volunteers, after Vojta Benes, the Reverend Vaniscak, and Lieutenant Holy had <pb facs="5418478_2_0504.jpg" n="2"/>addressed the meeting.</p>
   <p>We are going to bid farewell to our Chicago boys, to those from Town of Lake, and to some from Cedar Rapids, next Saturday. There will be about fifty of them. Czech Chicago will see them off in true brotherly spirit. All these volunteers are to assemble at the hall of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Saturday, July 20, at 7 P. M. We are requesting our ladies and businessmen to contribute some tasty morsels for the boys. This concerns especially our butchers and smoked meat dealers. The ladies might bake some cakes and make coffee. They should announce their intention of doing so at the office of the Czech National Alliance. Mr. Suchy's band will play, and Brother Linhart, the first Czechoslovak here who has become a war invalid, will address the recruits, who will then leave at about 10 P. M.</p>
   <p>We call on our Czechoslovak public to appear in large numbers to give our boys our last greeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0505.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For the Czechoslovak Committee:</p>
   <p>F. Rubec,</p>
   <p>V. Benes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
