<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-28">June 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Do Our Duty to Retain Our Reputation as Good Ratriots</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0512</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0512.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-28">June 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S DO OUR DUTY TO RETAIN OUR REPUTATION AS GOOD RATRIOTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is up to the Czechoslovaks to show the world that we are known, and not without good reason, as being among the most faithful patriots of this country, and that we are citizens of whose loyalty there cannot be even the remotest doubt.</p>
   <p>Today is designated as the "War Savings Stamps Day". The whole country is astir, and many millions of dollars are expected to change hands in the purchase of War Stamps. Should we stay behind? Should it be said of us that we are lagging, although until today we have always been first in everything? Certainly not! Just as we oversubscribed our Liberty Bond quota, and as we were among the most generous of contributors for the Red Cross, so, the same token we shall score one hundred percent in the purchase of War Stamps today. Allow no one to say that he has done enough; for this is a flimsy, worthless excuse, used simply because we, here, have not really accomplished anything.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0513.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have not made sacrifices or suffered from lack of anything. If we bought War Bonds we have merely invested our money in the best possible way. If we buy War Stamps, we are again doing nothing more than depositing our money in a safe spot.</p>
   <p>Those who are really making sacrifices are our boys, who are fighting in France for universal determination. We are expected to do all in our power to follow their noble example. Our soldiers expect it from us, for it will make their struggle less hard. Is there any one who would hesitate? Most decidedly not, for one must not and cannot be among the slackers.</p>
   <p>Extensive preparations have been made for this "War Savings Stamps Day" by the Czech branch of the agitation committee. Mr. Anton J. Cermak, chairman, and Mr. J. J. Salat, secretary, are conducting business in the offices of the Czech branch at 3342 West 26th Street. They have enlisted a number of our ladies <pb facs="5418478_2_0514.jpg" n="3"/>who will tend to the tagging. These patriotic women will busy themselves on every corner of the streets in Czech communities all over Chicago. Other workers will form "flying squads," and go to places of business and wherever people chance to be in numbers. Still others will call at every house in our Czech wards--they will not omit a single home.</p>
   <p>It is obvious that every phase of the drive has been taken care of and that everything should roll off smoothly.</p>
   <p>He who buys one War Savings Stamp for $4.17 will be given a "tag badge". Also, those who complete their "thrift stamps" up to the required amount will obtain the War Stamp and the tag.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
