<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Committee Reports on Enlistments</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITTEE REPORTS ON ENLISTMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first meeting of the military committee under the management of the Bohemian National Alliance met in the offices of the latter yesterday. This committee takes care of all the cases in which Czechs may enlist for service in the Czech regiment which is being formed in Chicago, and which will be placed at the disposal of the government. Members of Czech-American Sokol organizations and of the Bohemian National Alliance were present.</p>
   <p>Doctor Smetanka and Doctor Vosatka had visited Captain Kenney, of the United States Army, in order to discuss the work connected with the recruiting of men for the Czech regiment. They reported to the committee about their visit. Captain Kenney received them very kindly, and remarked with a smile, that he is just about to believe in telepathy, for he had been pondering about the means of getting in contact with the <pb facs="5418478_2_1070.jpg" n="2"/>Czechs in the United States for the purpose of increasing the Army which the United States will need now. He stated that the requirements as to the knowledge of the English language will not be stretched in the cases of the Czech recruits. There will, however, be demanded a certain degree of school education. He received with great joy news that the Bohemian National Alliance will call a mass meeting in order to explain to the Czech populace the seriousness of the situation, and to promote recruiting. Captain Kenney announced to his visitors that he will be present at the mass-meeting.</p>
   <p>One of the first men offering himself to Uncle Sam was Doctor Vosatka, who submitted to an examination, and will wear the uniform beginning with tomorrow. He will, however, be permitted to help in the preliminary work for the creation of the regiment.</p>
   <p>There was a debate after Doctor Vosatka and Doctor Smetanka had finished. <pb facs="5418478_2_1071.jpg" n="3"/>The favorable impression which the work done by the military committee has created in the Czech community was discussed with satisfaction. It was resolved to call a public meeting in the hall of Sokol Havlicek Tyrs, on Lawndale and 26th Streets, for Friday evening. The rent of the hall will be paid for by generous patriots. Pictures of army life and army weapons will decorate the walls. In accordance with suggestions offered by Captain Kenney, a recruiting station will be opened in the Bohemian settlement of Chicago, and in one of the gymnasium halls selected for that purpose. The establishment of a school is being considered where those Czechs can replenish their knowledge, who fear the outcome of the examinations conducted by the United States Army. Captain Kenney calmed the committee in respect to the examinations by promising to do all he could to ease the enlistment for those deficient in education.</p>
   <p>Frana Klepal, member of a Sokol organization, reported what he saw of <pb facs="5418478_2_1072.jpg" n="4"/>Czech recruiting when he traveled through the United States. He said that many fellow-countrymen who he had urged to join the Czech regiment took the next train going north to enlist for service in the Canadian Czech battalion. They claimed that was a surer way to get into the Army than to wait until the Czech regiment in the United States is complete. He further stated that enthusiasm among the Czechs all over the United States is running high, and recruiting is being sponsored in all Czech communities. He, himself, is going to stay in the United States for a few days only, then to enter the Czech battalion in Canada, thus fulfilling a previous promise, which kept him from joining the Czech-American regiment. He has, in the meantime, received an invitation to a great rally to be held at Cedar Rapids, Iowa, at which many are expected to enlist.</p>
   <p>Mr. Turzicky told the committee about his agitation lecture in St. Louis which netted fifteen recruits. Similar successes were recorded in <pb facs="5418478_2_1073.jpg" n="5"/>Detroit, Michigan, Milwaukee, and Racine, Wisconsin. Mr. Turzicky's activities will also take him to St. Paul and Minneapolis, where big recruiting meetings are to be held. (List of those who signed up for enlistment follows).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
