<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Help the Farmers in the Harvest</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal to Czechoslovak Laborers in the Cities (From Iowa, Nebraska, and Kanses farmers)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1668</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1668.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HELP THE FARMERS IN THE HARVEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal to Czechoslovak Laborers in the Cities (From Iowa, Nebraska, and Kanses farmers)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most joyful, but also the busiest time has come for us--harvest time. Our very existence depends on it. Not only our own, but also that of the starving people in the desolate war-ridden countries of Europe.</p>
   <p>In addition to the destitute in the ravaged and looted lands, thousands of our sons, brothers, and friends, not only in Uncle Sam's army, but also in the Allies' armies abroad, are confidently hoping that we shall be able to supply and feed them during the time of war. In fact, a great part of the world is turning toward our country for help.</p>
   <p>Thousands of our farmers' sons are now on the battlefield. They used to work in the harvest, but now they are fighting the enemy.</p>
   <p>Those who stayed at home, and are able to work, should take the soldiers' places. <pb facs="5418478_2_1669.jpg" n="2"/>Our people know farming, for the most part, and therefore they could render efficient service.</p>
   <p>Help our farmers! The change in occupation will be of advantage to you. The wages are not only good, but are really extraordinarily high. You will see new parts of the country. You will like it so that you may even remain, and settle down on a farm.</p>
   <p>Those of our fellow countrymen who wish to help their relatives or friends should write them immediately. They ought to consider, however, that work on that farm is not easy during harvest time, and that unless they are strong and helpful they will not only be of little use, but also may even become a burden. It is sheer nonsense to say that everyone in the city should go and help the farmer. Only people who know nothing of working conditions in the country would express such a thought, and so let only the sturdy boys go, those who can brave the task!</p>
   <p>Do not allow yourself to be enticed by the promises of various agents; and do <pb facs="5418478_2_1670.jpg" n="3"/>not go to strange places without a certain guaranty. Remember, also, that you are not starting out to make money only. Your efforts should be bent toward extending help. Many who are money minded lent an ear to exaggerated promises, only to find that there was absolutely no work to be obtained in some districts. Besides having been disappointed, they may have lost the money invested in fare and traveling expenses.</p>
   <p>Those who are willing, ready, and fit may inquire at this address: V. F. Jelinek, 1409 Garfield Street, Omaha, Nebraska. Enclose a three-cent stamp for return mail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
