<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-30">May 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[A Cold Reception]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0926</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0926.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-30">May 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[A COLD RECEPTION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convocators of the peace meeting which was held last Sunday have surely become convinced that they were used as the tools of a faction of Chicago Socialists, who have assumed the task of weakening as much as possible every measure taken by the United States of casting doubt upon the Government's motives, and so indirectly giving aid and comfort to the Germans. They all belong to one party, and are rabid Germans. This was evident in the reception they gave some of the speakers, whose sincerity and sterling patriotism cannot be questioned, as for instance, Miss Mary McDowell and Robert M. Lovett, Dean of the University of Chicago. Their speeches were not appreciated, as they reminded the audience of the aims of the War, the establishment of democracy, and the liberation of the small oppressed nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0927.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Socialist speaker, Mr. Steadman, on the other hand, drew frenzied applause as he attacked our Government, and called Congress a servant of J. P. Morgan, Schwab, and also of the small nations.</p>
   <p>The German Socialist paper, Arbeiter-Zeitung, quotes Steadman as ridiculing the idea of democracy and liberty, in pointing out the oppression of the Congo districts by Belgium, and of India, Ireland, and other countries by England. The much hated Prussian militarism, Steadman is quoted to have declared, is being introduced right here under "The Star-Spangled Banner" with all the concomitant taxes and other burdens for which the "fools of later generations" will have to pay.</p>
   <p>While Steadman thus harangued the crowd, he utterly omitted to mention the crimes perpetrated by the Germans, not only against the nations with which they are at War, but against neutral countries, and against their own as well. He continued by trying to explain why the United States entered the War. The Allies were losing, and England declared that it would not be <pb facs="5418478_2_0928.jpg" n="3"/>able to pay back the loan. It was feared this would cause a nationwide panic here. To prevent it, America declared War.....</p>
   <p>The wild applause which this kind of ranting evoked from the audience probably opened the eyes of Miss McDowell and Professor Lovett. They could see for themselves in whose behalf really they convoked the peace meeting. This may serve as a warning not to do it another time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
