<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-26">Apr. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Promotes Himself to Lieutenancy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0994</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0994.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-26">Apr. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PROMOTES HIMSELF TO LIEUTENANCY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A combination of craving for the glamour of the uniform and patriotic exertion, to help in recruiting our Czech young men, brought our fellow countryman, Eduard Fritz, in contact with the Federal authorities. The latter, luckily for the young man, made a very sane diagnosis of the case so that no harm came forth.</p>
   <p>For several days, a young man appeared in the Pilsen Sokol recruiting station daily. He was dressed in the uniform of a lieutenant of the United States Cavalry. His pleasant approach and correct behavior made him liked by the young men with whom <pb facs="5418478_2_0995.jpg" n="2"/>he conversed in a jovial manner, and whom he urged to enlist, depicting to them the charms and values of army life. Sergeant Vosatko, of the United States Army, in charge of the recruiting station, did not at first pay much attention to the presence of the young "officer"; In fact, he seemed pleased to see someone stimulating the ambition of the future defenders of the country, for this eased his own burden.</p>
   <p>The "lieutenant" began to feel at home in the station. One day he brought along a sword with a silver hilt which he declared he had received as a token of popularity while serving in the cavalry of the militia. Using it as a symbol of his military distinction, he taught the boys in the station, and also in a nearby saloon, the rudiments of military drill, lining them up, and raising his voice in true commanding manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0996.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Kuzel, who is directing the civilian affairs of the station, in inspecting the sword, found two letters, K. P. (denoting Knights of Pythias) engraved upon the scabbard and pointed out to the young man that no officer would wear a similar weapon. Fritz declared the latter to be merely a gift which was meant as a decoration. This explanation satisfied Mr. Kuzel apparently, but it did not convince him.</p>
   <p>It was further noticed that the "lieutenant" contradicted himself frequently, and so it happened that two United States secret service men brought him before United States Commissioner Mason. After an investigation, he was turned over to Federal Judge Landis. The latter took into consideration the fact that there was only one serious charge, that of unlawfully representing himself as a United States officer, pending against Fritz. Favorable evidence also was presented, <pb facs="5418478_2_0997.jpg" n="4"/>showing that the self-styled "officer" had been discharged from the militia on account of poor eyesight, and when War was declared by America, he had tried three times unsuccessfully to enlist for service. Urged by an ambition to do his bit, he resolved to propagate enlistment among his people, and edged on by his liking of a uniform, he had dressed as a lieutenant. The court adjudged him to be a dreamer, who foolishly got himself into trouble, put him under a light bond, set him free with a warning, and expressed the hope that after this temporary mental aberration, he will find an outlet for his befogged idealism other than trying to bamboozle the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
