<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-24">July 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Sad Memories Anent the "Eastland" Disaster</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-24">July 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SAD MEMORIES ANENT THE "EASTLAND" DISASTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July 24 is a day of mourning for our city, and particularly for our Czech settlement. It evokes memories that penetrate deep into the hearts of our Czech families, memories of untold grief to the survivors, and of blasted hopes.</p>
   <p>Today is the third anniversary of the disaster that befell the excursion boat "Eastland" while she was about to carry a merry crowd of passengers to a picnic arranged by the Western Electric Company, at Hawthorne, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Probably every one remembers how on that fateful Saturday morning the news flashed through the entire city that the "Eastland," chartered by the Western Electric Company, had capsized in the Chicago River, close to the Clark Street bridge. Nobody even dreamed that this news item was the distressful story of <pb facs="5418478_2_1601.jpg" n="2"/>how over one thousand men and women, most of them in the full bloom of youth, had lost their lives. When they had heard the details, people could not understand how so many lost their lives while the boat was so close to the pier, even though it had capsized. Later, however, these news reports were verified by eye witnesses.</p>
   <p>There was great alarm and anxiety in our settlement, for there was hardly a block from which one or more of our people had not boarded the boat. While in some houses there was jubilation when members of the family returned safe, in others gloom and fear increased as the beloved ones failed to appear. Hundreds hastened to reach the scene of the catastrophe, only to learn the heart-rending truth.</p>
   <p>Today, now that time has demonstrated its healing power, and our grief has partly subsided, we recall the processions of carriages drawing toward our Czech cemeteries. Our settlement, and indeed all of Chicago, opened their <pb facs="5418478_2_1602.jpg" n="3"/>hearts to the suffering survivors. Two families, Sindelar and Novotny were wiped out, as were dozens of individuals from our Czech commonwealth. Their lives were lost; they were victims of the carelessness and utter negligence of others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
