<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Highly Important Institution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A HIGHLY IMPORTANT INSTITUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American people have not,for many years followed the work of any commission with greater interest than that of the Commission on Industrial Relations. This Commission has done more important and valuable work for our laboring people than any other ever appointed in our country. It was therefore learned with a great deal of satisfaction that a permanent Committee on Industrial Relations has been created and will function under the chairmanship of Frank P. Walsh, who, as the chairman of the Commission, has proved himself to be a man of the utmost integrity, justice, and a true friend of labor. The Committee, created some ten days ago at a meeting of the Commission held in New York City, is a body whose creation was necessary in order to preserve the benefits accruing from the work of the Commission. Without it, all these benefits would be lost, because the capitalists have organized an opposition with the purpose of nullifying the results of the work of the Commission, suppressing the publication of its report; <pb facs="5418478_2_1573.jpg" n="2"/>and, in the first place, preventing the enactment of laws recommended by the Commission and aiming at the correction of wrongs which are being committed upon the laboring classes by the capitalists.</p>
   <p>The Permanent Committee has been created in order to counteract these efforts. Its duty will be to exert efforts in Congress toward the adoption of labor legislation, that is, laws which would promote justice toward labor.</p>
   <p>This important institution should be receiving all possible support from labor.</p>
   <p>The Committee has published a statement of its principles and has indicated the means it proposes to use in order to keep labor matters in the foreground of American public questions until the time when the necessary labor legislation is enacted by Congress. Some excerpts from the statement are included in this article.</p>
   <p>The final report of the Federal Commission which ceased to exist August 23, will <pb facs="5418478_2_1574.jpg" n="3"/>be submitted to Congress when it convenes in December. The nation and Congress will then learn officially what has been unofficially known to many citizens for a long time, that is, that an enormous number of American workingmen are receiving wages that are insufficient for decent existence for their families; that the economic strength of employers in industrial undertakings in which labor is not organized, has put them in the position of an economic and political dictator, leaving the workingman a minimum of political freedom, and keeping him in complete economic dependence; and finally, that the only way to the salvation of the labor and the abolition of conditions which are in contradiction to American ideals is the creation of a labor organization headed by leaders selected by labor itself.</p>
   <p>As a result of the interest created by the publication of the testimony taken by the Commission, which has been continually reporting on its findings, the number of citizens who have become convinced of the necessity of steadily increasing the wages and improving the working and social conditions of workingmen <pb facs="5418478_2_1575.jpg" n="4"/>and women has increased considerably.</p>
   <p>The Commission has come to the final and unshakeable conclusion that a permanent improvement can be achieved only by unified and well-organized intervention of all workingmen and women. But the Commission has also reached the conclusions that the citizens in general can help in the solving of the most important and most urgent social and economic problems. American citizens as a body will have to take upon themselves the duty of removing the obstacles put into the way of labor organization by the ruling classes, and of putting up a strong defense of the principle that justice must be done to labor and its representatives.</p>
   <p>This principle was adopted a long time ago by all those who study these important problems and have no interest in capitalist profits; but even they frequently try to convince themselves that they have reason to take a stand against one or another labor union, or to refuse their support or the benefit of their influence to labor in one or another of its struggles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1576.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Permanent Committee states:</p>
   <p>"Our principal duty as we see it after having studied the findings and actions of the Federal Commission is to make sure of true and unbiased reporting on every dispute between employers and employees in the daily press; to make sure that public institutions, such as police, the courts of law, administration officials, and militia, shall act always with complete impartiality both toward capital and labor; and to make sure that the use of machine guns, armed gunmen, killers, and strike-breakers against labor is completely abolished by law.</p>
   <p>"We admit that the great obstacle in organizing the employees of large corporations is the feudal control exercised by such corporations upon the communities in which they have their plants. There, the corporations are engaged in suppressing the freedom of speech and freedom of assembly of peaceful citizens; they maintain a spy system to which nothing is sacred; they force out of the community all persons they deem undesirable, or put in jail, on fictitious charges, persons they do not like. By such actions, the work of labor organizers is made impossible <pb facs="5418478_2_1577.jpg" n="6"/>in such communities. The aim of this Committee will be to break this feudal power of corporations, to expose such abuses, and to continue to work for the protection of the rights of those who carry the gospel of organization.</p>
   <p>"The Committee hopes to accomplish its aims by exposing and calling attention to economic and political evils infesting such communities.</p>
   <p>"The Committee's first action in regard to Congress will be to insist upon permission to print and distribute, free of charge, the final report of the Federal Commission for Industrial Relations, and all the evidence assembled by that Commission in its sessions. When a very large number of men and women interested in social problems in industry shall have read these reports, an understanding will be created which is necessary if public opinion is to do its part in the great task of realizing the ideals we are trying to promote.</p>
   <p>"This Committee firmly believes that it is necessary to create the closest <pb facs="5418478_2_1578.jpg" n="7"/>possible co-operation between organized labor, this Committee, and all other factors, both organizations and individuals, in order to prevent legislation which would be antagonistic to labor, and to achieve the enactment by Congress of laws assuring political and industrial democracy. This Committee pledges [itself] to exert every effort toward this end, and requests the fullest co-operation of others.</p>
   <p>"Any program of national preparedness must be based on the following principles: Nobody must make any profit out of killing people. All factories manufacturing munitions, arms, warships, and war supplies must be under Government control. No military caste must be created. Any new system of citizens' army must be organized upon democratic principles and must make it possible for able workingmen to be promoted to the rank of commissioned officers. Such an army may be used for national defense only, and never against striking labor.</p>
   <p>"The principal Government revenue should be derived from the income tax and the inheritance tax; taxes imposed on necessities of life should be reduced.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1579.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"The courts should be prevented from declaring unconstitutional, and void, laws which do not please the capitalistic class.</p>
   <p>"Jurymen should be selected impartially, from lists containing the names of all voters so that workingmen shall be properly and justly represented.</p>
   <p>"There should be laws specifying as to what is unfair and forbidden competition, so that success in business will not be based on the payment of law wages to employees, upon long working hours, dangerous and unsanitary conditions in shops, or refusal to recognized labor organizations. The Secretary of Labor should have the right and duty to investigate cases of unfair competition and prosecute those firms guilty of it."</p>
   <p>These illustrations will convince everybody of the importance of the Federal Committee on Industrial Relations, certainly there will be no enlightened workingman who will not follow its work with the keenest of interest, and give it all possible support in order that it would meet with the desired success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
