<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Let Everyone Do His Duty!</title><title level="a" type="sub">On the Eve of John Huss Jubilee Let us Prove we are Good Bohemians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">LET EVERYONE DO HIS DUTY!</title><title level="a" type="sub">On the Eve of John Huss Jubilee Let us Prove we are Good Bohemians</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Huss' slogan: "Seek ye the truth and live it" should sink deeply into our minds. How often we hear beautiful talk about patriotism, humaneness, and national duty, and when the time comes to back up this talk with deeds, we neglect the manly action that would be commensurate with our words.</p>
   <p>In these days we learn about how our country is bleeding from the thousands of wounds in the bodies of its sons on the battlefields of Europe; we read that misery and hunger threaten the land deprived of its crops; and we hear how unbearable the situation of the working classes, whose earnings have been stopped by the closing of factories, is becoming. Is it not up to us, we who have been able to escape the Moloch of militarism; is it not up to us, who live in plenty--and many of us in luxury--to put our offerings on the old country's altar, to wipe the tears from the cheeks of the bereft, and to save our youth for what we <pb facs="5418478_2_1497.jpg" n="2"/>hope will be a better life in the future?</p>
   <p>Let every one of us do his duty! Let us not stop with making our own personal contributions, but let every one of us become a propagandist, a solicitor! Only in that way shall we be able to mobilize the seven hundred thousand Bohemians living in the Union; only in that way shall we make the results of our collections worthy of Bohemian America!</p>
   <p>All of the larger Jednoty (associations, orders, etc.) have already been approached, with the result that a majority of them have shown their patriotism by making large donations. Now there remain a hundred independent clubs and societies whose names are not in the directories. We ask them to contact our secretary, who will send them collection sheets immediately.</p>
   <p>As far as the distribution of collected funds is concerned, no decision has been made so far. Money for relief purposes will not be sent before the proper kind of connection is again established with Bohemia, and until we are certain <pb facs="5418478_2_1498.jpg" n="3"/>that every penny will go exactly for the purpose for which it is sent. The distribution proper will be done in co-operation with the Sokols and with Bohemian teachers. Every needy countryman will get some help. Now let us see to it that our funds grow large enough to make that help substantial and sufficient.</p>
   <p>All necessary information, as well as collection forms, may be received from Jaroslav V. Nigrin, 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, U. S. A.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
