<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-14">May 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">For War Savings Stamps and the Red Cross</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-14">May 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FOR WAR SAVINGS STAMPS AND THE RED CROSS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lively workers have not found much time for rest after the Third Liberty Loan drive, and they are not to get it now either. We know, however, that men and women will gladly respond. The task before us during this week is the promotion of the sale of War Savings Stamps and the solicitation of Red Cross memberships and contributions. The Third Liberty Loan campaign has brought much credit to the Czechs, placing them above all other immigrant nationalities here. Our willingness to support the prosecution of the war against our age-old enemies, the Germans, has been recognized in Washington and by the American people in general.</p>
   <p>Exactly as we have become conspicuous by our vigorous participation in the Third Liberty Loan, so now we must excel the achievements of all others in the drive for the sale of War Savings Stamps and for the benefit of that sublime humanitarian institution, the American Red Cross. There is certainly not a single Czech-American who is not, deep down in his heart, convinced that it is <pb facs="5418478_2_0540.jpg" n="2"/>absolutely necessary to support the government in every possible manner. This enormous struggle will save democracy and give liberty to the small nations, among which is our own Czech fatherland.</p>
   <p>Should any one feel like complaining, he should instantly consider that all that we have been doing for the cause up to the present is nothing in comparison with what our boys are accomplishing on the battlefield. They shed their blood for the Starry Flag to keep the enemy from seizing upon our own land. They are dying for that most sacred and noble ideal, for which heroes ever have given their lives, the liberation of subjugated nations. What is our work when viewed beside theirs?</p>
   <p>No one should hesitate to call on our people again and again when help is needed! This pure, patriotic people of ours is fully conscious of its obligation and ready and glad to fulfill it. Every child in America knows nowadays that this is a life-and-death struggle, and that a nation can win only when its people are determined to sacrifice everything demanded--and even more.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0541.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>You are the second firing line, the second army of volunteers, who will contribute to the ultimate victory even as our boys over there, who are dying on the field of honor--on the field of glory.</p>
   <p>All those who worked in the Third Loan drive, precinct captains and their workers, or members of organizations, or individuals, you should all report for work in this great patriotic service!</p>
   <p>For the moment it is the sale of War Savings Stamps which is foremost. We have to admit that we have, to some extent, neglected our duty in the drive for the sale of War Savings Stamps. But we cannot afford to neglect anything or to be outdone by anybody! We must be the first in everything, and therefore--also in this matter!</p>
   <p>All who want to work should report to the Czech Bureau, 3347 West 26th Street, near Homan Avenue (offices of Cermak and Serhant). You will receive cards, which will serve as receipts. You will call on every Czech family in the <pb facs="5418478_2_0542.jpg" n="4"/>neighborhood and try to induce every one of their members to sign a pledge to buy War Stamps regularly.</p>
   <p>Workers of the Twelfth Ward may apply, besides the place mentioned above, at the offices of the two aldermen, Messrs. Joseph I. Novak and Otto Kerner. In the Thirty-fourth Ward you may apply to the two aldermen, Messrs. Joseph O. Kostner and John Toman. In the Tenth Ward the two aldermen are Messrs. F. Klaus and McNichols. In the Eleventh Ward Mr. Morris Sabath will take care of you.</p>
   <p>We are addressing ourselves particularly to the chairmen and the secretaries of our organizations, who can accomplish very much by speaking to their fellow members about the Savings Stamps. How easily and efficiently this can be done is shown by an example:</p>
   <p>The Narodni Telocvicny Klub (National Gymnastic Club), located at 1831 South Racine Avenue, has 203 members, who have unanimously resolved to sign the pledge.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0543.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This is the work of Mr. F. J. Beran, treasurer. There are 23 members in military service at that!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
