<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-12">Dec. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">President Pleased by Telegram</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0719</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0719.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-12">Dec. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT PLEASED BY TELEGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The moment President Wilson had proclaimed the decision of Congress to declare war on Austria-Hungary, the Czech National Alliance took steps to protect Czechs in America, noncitizens, who, it was feared, might be classified as alien enemies, since their status was, theoretically, still that of Austrian subjects. The Alliance, through Dr. Ludwig Fisher its president, sent a telegram to President Wilson in which it asked protection for the Czech non-citizens, at the same time assuring him of the loyalty of the Czech-Americans.</p>
   <p>It was answered by Mr. J. P. Tumulty, personal secretary of the President, in terms of most friendly feeling. It reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Dear Dr. Fisher: The President requests me to acknowledge receipt of the telegram sent by you yesterday, and to convey the sentiment of his deep-felt joy which your communication brought him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0720.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Your telegram breathes the sentiment of noblest patriotism. It is new proof of your dependability in this portentous, serious time.</p>
   <p>"I am instructed to give you the assurance that the President will do all in his power to see just and magnanimous treatment accorded to those who may by right be considered standing outside of this struggle.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"J. P. Tumulty."</p>
   <p>The Czech National Alliance also supplied Congressman Sabath with information to be used in behalf of Czech-American noncitizens.</p>
   <p>Mr. Karel Pergler, vice-president of the Czech National Alliance, intervened in this matter in Washington, D. C., with good prospects.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
