<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">War Savings Stamps Drive</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WAR SAVINGS STAMPS DRIVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....In order to make the campaign more effective, the demonstrations were spread all over the city, which for this purpose had been divided into districts. One of these was the southwest district which has a large population of Czechoslovaks. Two demonstrations were held simultaneously, one in "Czech California," the other in the "Czech Plzen" (Czech Pilsen) district. In both these places our people gave a dignified account of themselves.</p>
   <p>The Czech California event began at the south end of Douglas Park, where thousands of people crowded around the speakers' platform in spite of the rain-soaked ground. The Pilsen district affair centered around Dvorak Park, with a no less enthusiastic response from our people.</p>
   <p>The parade preceding the gathering at Douglas Park was composed of four divisions, one of which had for its starting point Crawford Avenue and 26th Street, the second Crawford Avenue north of Twelfth Street, the third Twelfth <pb facs="5418478_2_0545.jpg" n="2"/>Street west of Crawford Avenue, and the fourth Ogden Avenue east of Crawford Avenue. Each of these sections had [among its marchers] members of many of our organizations, firemen, policemen, and above all, largo numbers of our youngsters who attend school. There were also students from our Red Cross schools for nurses, veterans of the Spanish-American War, and several bands, among which the band from the Grant Park training camp, with many Czech members was conspicuous.</p>
   <p>It may fairly well be claimed that the California parade had a preponderantly Czech character. The speakers were Messrs. F. J. Kubec, leader in the Czech National Alliance, Toll, head of the campaign district, and Schik, a soldier of Pershing's army who is here to recuperate from wounds.</p>
   <p>The corner of Blue Island Avenue and 18th Street was the meeting point of those who celebrated at Dvorak Park. They marched on 18th Street east to Halsted Street, south to 19th Street, and west to Wood Street, whence they proceded east to the Park. This parade was big and colorful, for besides <pb facs="5418478_2_0546.jpg" n="3"/>the Marine Band and soldiers, there was also a strong body of Croatian Sokols, many of our brothers the Slovaks, and children from Dvorak Park led by Director Kodl, representing by their formation the American flag. A multitude was waiting for them at the Park, where ex-Govenor Richard Yates was the principal speaker. County Judge Thomas F. Scully and Mr. William K. Pflaum also spoke. The credit for this highly successful demonstration is due to businessmen and other Southwest Side workers headed by F. J. Bilek.</p>
   <p>The sale of War Savings Stamps made very good progress. Congressman A. J. Sabath was prevented by urgent business in Washington from addressing the crowds. He sent a subscription of $200 for stamps.....</p>
   <p>War Savings Stamps may also be bought from any mail carrier on monthly or even weekly installments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
