<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Political Affairs</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Twelfth Ward Now Has its Candidate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL AFFAIRS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Twelfth Ward Now Has Its Candidate</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great interest was shown last week in the question of who was going to receive the Democratic nomination for alderman of the Twelfth Ward. At the meeting of the ward organization the day before yesterday a candidate was finally chosen.</p>
   <p>The meeting was attended by a large number of citizens from all parts of the Ward. It was agreed that the Ward organization give its support to Josef I. Novak, an ex-alderman who was recommended some time ago. When the numerous other candidates showed a willingness to withdraw from the ticket in favor of Mr. Novak, he proclaimed himself a candidate.</p>
   <p>It is expected that the visit of President Wilson in Chicago tomorrow may have great political significance, and it seems likely that the President will be placed in an unpleasant position by the political squabbles of <pb facs="5418478_2_0268.jpg" n="2"/>the local Democratic factions.</p>
   <p>The Democratic chieftains will welcome President Wilson at the station. They will be headed by the former mayor; this will not be very pleasant to the Sullivan faction, which holds a majority membership in the State committee.</p>
   <p>There does not seem to be any hope that the two factions will come to an agreement regarding the election of delegates to the national convention.</p>
   <p>Both factions will have their individual selections of delegates to the convention. The only thing they have in common is that both factions have nominated Governor Dunne and Senator Lewis, although neither of them are affiliated with either faction.</p>
   <p>The reason for the support of Dunne and Lewis by the Sullivanites lies in the fact that they are the highest Democratic officers in the State <pb facs="5418478_2_0269.jpg" n="3"/>of Illinois, and therefore without doubt will head both factions.</p>
   <p>It seems that Governor Dunne is satisfied with this arrangement. Being a candidate for another term he does not want to antagonize the strong Sullivan faction. He believes that Senator Lewis can only be induced to file his name with the Harrison faction.</p>
   <p>President Wilson could be drawn into the controversy by the fact that the State of Illinois gives the President the right to protest against the delegates and to maintain that the delegates named are not his.</p>
   <p>The President can therefore disown Sullivan or Harrison, or both, and it is said that either the President or his campaign manager will be directly petitioned for an answer as to the faction with which they want to cast their lot.</p>
   <p>That, naturally, would place the President in an unenviable position, <pb facs="5418478_2_0270.jpg" n="4"/>because the State committee, all Sullivan adherents, have already started a campaign in support of Wilson for President, and it would not be easy to refuse recognition to the Sullivanites at the Presidential convention for this reason.</p>
   <p>The managers of the Wilson campaign will try with all their might to avoid the drawing of the President into local disputes; but the question arises how they will be able to do so.</p>
   <p>The question of the right of women to vote for delegates to national conventions will no doubt be presented to the State Supreme Court for a decision.</p>
   <p>Judge Scully appealed to the attorney of the Election Commission for an opinion on the right of women to hold delegate credentials at Presidential conventions. Judge Scully holds that the women have that right.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0271.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Regarding the nomination of a municipal judge to fill the position of the deceased Judge Ryan, many names of candidates will appear on the tickets of both factions. Included in the list of candidates are the well-known Czech attorneys Messrs. Vincenc G. Ponic and Jaroslav J. Viterna.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
