<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-25">Apr. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">In the Dawn of Revolutions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-25">Apr. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE DAWN OF REVOLUTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The insane autocrats of Berlin and their servants in Vienna surely did not imagine what unbounded, secret forces they unleashed on mankind when they attacked Servia, and so started the World War."</p>
   <p>"It is through the voice of its greatest statesman since Lincoln's time that the great American Republic is getting rid of the mendacious and deceitful conceptions concerning the real meaning of the struggle in Europe, and, in the nick of time, it is going to the aid of jeopardized liberty of mankind....."</p>
   <p>"The War has ceased to be a conflict between two hostile capitalistic camps <pb facs="5418478_2_0999.jpg" n="2"/>as claimed by our blinded Socialists, if it ever was that at all. The War is one of the revolutionary eruptions which is shaking the foundations of various European states at the present time."</p>
   <p>"It is really unthinkable that the brilliant example of the Russian people should not be emulated by other nations who have up to the present been subjected to medieval monarchistic systems. The gaze of Czech people is naturally directed toward Austria first, within whose boundaries is imprisoned the land of our ancestors, our homeland, from which we were driven by an unbearable political and economic oppression. What effect the Russian revolution has had on our people in the old homeland is hard to tell."</p>
   <p>The Austrian government sees ominous signs for the future, and seeks to appease its peoples. The young emperor has promised to reinstate the <pb facs="5418478_2_1000.jpg" n="3"/>parliament, which had been dissolved at the beginning of the War. No other nation at War had dissolved its parliament. The emperor's promise proves that he scents danger. It is rumored, as much as is allowed to filter through censorship, that Emperor Karl is trying hard to pull Austria from the grip of Germany, and that he is ready for big sacrifices to effectuate a separate peace. "These efforts are, thanks to the Lord, too late...."</p>
   <p>Hopes that Germany also will be seized by the spirit of revolution are beginning to crystallize into reality. The violent labor troubles there have not the real revolutionary character, true enough, but they are heading into revolution nevertheless. The proof for this is given by the fact that the labor strikes were not only ignored, but openly suppressed by the Social Democrats.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1001.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"....The starving German people are groping for democracy through the darkness of autocracy."</p>
   <p>"Verily, we live in a great time, the importance of which we cannot grasp today. Before the War ends, we shall see a changed world which we are unable to visualize now."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
