<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Volunteers' Farewell</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR VOLUNTEERS' FAREWELL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Czech community saw their volunteers off last night in a most fitting manner. The recruits went to Camp Stamford, New York, from where they will be transferred later, by the Military Committee of the Czech National Alliance, to the Czechoslovak Army in France. There were about forty men, possibly more. Mr. Urban, well-known friend of our soldiers, was their host in his place at 26th Street and Springfield Avenue. After that, they gathered and marched on 26th Street to Kedzie Avenue to the home of Sokol Chicago, Kedzie Avenue and 24th Street.</p>
   <p>The recruits were mostly men of more mature age, men who are determined to offer their lives for the old homeland now when personal service and sacrifice are needed most. They strode proudly, headed by a band and accompanied by members of our Military Committee. They all gloried in the consciousness of doing their duty, and they were loudly and enthusiastically <pb facs="5418478_2_0485.jpg" n="2"/>acclaimed by the crowds on the streets. They were saluted by "Na zdar!" (good luck!) by many whose duty lies in a different direction but who are fully aware of the sacrifice these men are about to make.</p>
   <p>The recruits were awaited in the Sokol Chicago Hall by throngs of men and women most of whom had come in response to an appeal by the Grand Lodge of the Taborite (Taborites), which arranged the farewell.</p>
   <p>The Czech Workmen's Singing Society initiated the event with "The Star-Spangled Banner," after which the secretary of the Grand Lodge, Mr. V. Richter, introduced the speaker, Dr. A. Mueller, who delivered a brief, but hearty, address in which he praised the Taborites and their relation to the significance of the day. His words were received with much applause. Afterward little Miss Sramek from the Opatrovna (Kindergarten) recited <pb facs="5418478_2_0486.jpg" n="3"/>a poem "My Colors, Red and White," being followed by the Workmen's chorus, which rendered "Kdo Jste Bozi Bojovnici" (Ye Soldiers of the Lord). At the last strains of the chorus the recruits began to march into the hall, greeted by stormy applause. They assembled in the front of the auditorium. First Lieutenant Holy, of the Czechoslovak Army, spoke on the Taborites of old and those of today. Professor J. Zmrhal spoke in English, referring in a very flattering way to the speaker who followed him, Dr. Knapp, editor of the Chicago Journal, who has written many articles on the Czech nation, thus helping to spread information about it. Dr. Knapp spoke of Professor Masaryk in most appreciative terms, likening him to the famous Italian statesman, Cavour, through whose good offices England and France came to the aid of endangered Italy, and helped chase the Austrians from Northern Italy, while Garibaldi fought them in the South. He did not forget the Czechoslovaks in Siberia and in Russia, but praised their determination and courage in fighting for their ideals. These they upheld even from the very moment when they were forced to join the Austrian Army, <pb facs="5418478_2_0487.jpg" n="4"/>which army they left at the first opportunity to surrender to the Russians, in whom they saw help against the age-old oppressors of their nation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vojta Benes informed the gathering that, according to news from Paris, Alice Masaryk was sentenced to death. This announcement caused obvious consternation. (According to later news it was "the sister of General Masaryk," Milada Jarusek, of whom we reported several days ago.)</p>
   <p>After the Workingmen's chorus had sung the American anthem, J. T. Smiricky, organizer of the Grand Lodge, thanked the gathering, and the recruits departed for the railroad station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
