<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-04">Mar. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From the Jednota Ceskoslovenskych Inzenyru</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-04">Mar. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE JEDNOTA CESKOSLOVENSKYCH INZENYRU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czechoslovak engineers who are active in the various technical departments of the many factories and other industrial concerns of Chicago were meeting regularly for the purpose of giving such information to the members as would prove of value in their work; at the same time they aided their professional confreres who have just arrived from Czechoslovakia and were in need of a job.</p>
   <p>Of late many requests have been arriving from the professional organizations in the old homeland; our activities increased, and as a result it was decided to place our hitherto irregular existence upon a firmer foundation. Thus the Jednota Ceskoslovenskych Inzenyru (Union of Czechoslovak Engineers) was called into existence, its avowed purpose being to organize professional [Translator's note: Civil, mechanical, electrical, and other engineers] technicians and specialists, to supply them with any necessary information, <pb facs="5418478_2_1715.jpg" n="2"/>to support and to further any professional contacts which might be established between the American and Czechoslovak industries; to serve as counsellors during projected study trips--that is, to those men who came from Czechoslovakia on a professional visit to the United States, etc. The Jednota Ceskoslovenskych Inzenyru also took advantage of Mr. Jaroslav Franek's trip to Czechoslovakia, giving him credentials to that country where he is to study ways and means of making our connections functional. Mr. Franek is to effect a contact with technical organizations, with the proper officials in the ministry of the Czechoslovak Government, and with individual manufacturers.</p>
   <p>The Jednota Ceskoslovenskych Inzenyru counts on the moral support of its countrymen who are technologically employed.....</p>
   <p>For the Jednota Ceskoslovenskych Inzenyru</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank J. Vodicka, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
