<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-01">Feb. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial View of Our Governmental System</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-01">Feb. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">EDITORIAL VIEW OF OUR GOVERNMENTAL SYSTEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.4--We Americans have many faults and deficiencies in our political institutions of which we may become aware by observing the political systems of other countries. At present the election in England occupies the attention of the entire world and offers an opportunity for comparison with our own elections.</p>
   <p>The English enjoy the great advantage of fewer elections. Besides their parliamentary elections they have municipal elections and no more. We have a presidential election every four years, congressional elections every two years, and state elections besides. All this creates such confusion that the constituency really does not know which election is most important. Is it the election of the President who administers the government of the whole country or the election of the congressmen who make its laws? On account of our interest in one election we may overlook another which is more important.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1604.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As for a parliament, the dissolution of it is dangerous, if it is the arbitrary act of a ruler, as in Austria or in Germany; on the other hand, the dissolution by the parliament of a cabinet, which is responsible to the people, is highly beneficial to the country. We in America elect a President for four years and congressmen for two years and then let them do as they please. It is different in England. The parliament is elected for a time which is practically indefinite. Although the law fixes the duration of the activity of each parliament at six years, no instance is remembered of a parliament's lasting so long. The government invariably dissolves the parliament when a measure of higher importance is being debated if it is not sure what the nation's attitude is toward that measure. In other words, the cabinet asks the constituency for advice. If the government is for the measure, and the opposition is against it, the people decide. If they vote against the measure, the opposition wins, and the ministry changes. Similarly, the cabinet falls, if it fails to obtain a vote of confidence from the parliament.</p>
   <p>This indicates a responsibility of the ministry to the people as absolute as can be obtained in these days. A similar system, if not precisely the <pb facs="5418478_2_1605.jpg" n="3"/>same, is in use in France and to a certain extent in Italy and other countries.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that our American government is bound by no such responsibility. No leader of the opposition can here occasionally defeat the government and thus keep a check on its actions. It is the common belief in our country that the President and the Congress are responsible to the voters. This belief is erroneous; once elected, they cannot be recalled. They are allowed to stay in office and cannot be unseated until their terms expire. This, of course, does not mean anything like absolute responsibility.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
