<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-29">Apr. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Last Opportunity, Maybe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0975</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0975.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-29">Apr. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A LAST OPPORTUNITY, MAYBE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have printed an abundance of articles on the advantages of early enlistment for service in the United States Army and Navy. We have also pointed out that the large number of enlistments by our young Czech-American men will have a decisive influence upon the attitude of the federal authorities towards us. We have also emphasized that such enlistments will help to keep the Czech-Americans together in one military unit. During the first days of enthusiasm, much was spoken about it, and exertions were made toward the creation of a Czecho-Slovak regiment, which, however, failed to materialize. The officers of the United States Army thereupon assured us they would see to it that Czecho-Slovak volunteers were concentrated in certain companies at least. Judging by letters received by us from our volunteers at Jefferson Barracks, Mo., these promises have been fulfilled wherever possible. In accordance with the latest orders from the War Department, volunteers shall not be kept here until they form a group, but they must be sent immediately to the training camps. The probable reason for this may be an impending introduction of compulsory service.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0976.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nevertheless, Captain Kenny, of United States Army, chief recruiting officer for the Chicago district, succeeded in winning the permission for Czech recruits to stay in Chicago until their numbers have grown sufficiently large to be transported to the camps in a body. The permission will not be effective until next Monday evening. This seems to be the last opportunity for our volunteers to serve the United States together with their fellow-countrymen.</p>
   <p>The Czecho-Slovak volunteers are being greeted at Jefferson Barracks with great enthusiasm, and they are treated with utmost consideration. Many letters testify to this.</p>
   <p>The United States Army officers are experiencing one difficulty with the volunteers. They find it difficult to pronounce the Slavonic names, but in their commands at mess, tattoo (lights out!), and taps, they refer to them as "The Czech Soldiers."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
