<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-08">May 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Beautiful Words, but Mere Words</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0958</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0958.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-08">May 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BEAUTIFUL WORDS, BUT MERE WORDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the articles in last Sunday's Fackel, organ of the German Socialists of Chicago, is replete with beautiful sentences. Were that paper representative of the Germans, or at least of a majority of them, there would be some hope for us that the War is nearing its end, and that universal brotherhood is at our door. How contradictory, however, to the spirit of the article is the sentiment of the Germans here, and of the German Socialists in particular! These people proclaim ostentatiously to stand up for the Government, but do nothing towards the attainment of peace, of a permanent peace, which would bring about the liberation of the nations groaning under the German yoke, and so create a guarantee against the possibility of <pb facs="5418478_2_0959.jpg" n="2"/>another War.</p>
   <p>The article reads: "The War is killing thousands of thousands, and maiming millions ..... What is the cause of this? The War is the fruit of our capitalistic social order, and of the imperialistic aspirations of those above us ..... Hatred among the nations, that ugly-trait, is the immediate result of greed for money and lusting after power on the part of the masters. How far this enmity has progressed is hard to depict. No country was spared from it ..... Should this hatred be spread over the United States also ?....Let us have no room for hatred; men of reason cannot become infected with it. The ruling classes use it as a means to induce the people to allow themselves to be torn to pieces to the advantage of the rich....."</p>
   <p>The Fackel thus condemns hatred, and we agree in essence that nations should not hate each other. What ought to be hated, however, are the <pb facs="5418478_2_0960.jpg" n="3"/>bad, pernicious qualities of certain nations, and these nations must be taught to cast off these characteristics, so as to become different and better, instead of striving to destroy brotherhood by hatred.</p>
   <p>The Germans of the German Empire, as well as those of Austria, together with their Allies, the Magyars, have not taken any steps to allay hatred among nations. On the contrary they have done everything in their power to stir it up to the highest pitch, and profit by the consequences..... The Germans of Austria-Hungary, and the Magyars, constantly used violence against the Slavonic nations, which nations were treated as underdogs in their own homeland. By this policy, they sought to win the good will of mighty Mother Germania, and use it to promote their aims toward a dominating position over the Slavonic majorities. And further, when the latter sought redress, the Socialist representatives in parliament opposed them, though they were the leaders in the movement for brotherhood, equality, and justice. The result was that the Germans <pb facs="5418478_2_0961.jpg" n="4"/>always were in the advantage, and the Socialists had to drag along behind them....</p>
   <p>Prussian militarists, not the German people, are hated by the American nation. If the Germans could divorce themselves from the allegiance to their bad principles, hatred would vanish, and the War could be terminated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
