<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-02">Jan. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Aliens Who Seek Exemption from Military Service]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-02">Jan. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[ALIENS WHO SEEK EXEMPTION FROM MILITARY SERVICE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All our fellow countrymen who are not citizens, and who on that ground ask for exemption from military service, are, thereby, proclaiming themselves to be "alien enemies". They ought to think the matter over very thoroughly before deciding to take the step. By asking exemption they announce themselves as belonging to the "undesirable element", as people who consider the United States to be a country just good enough for making money. They show that they would not make any sacrifices for the preservation of existing conditions or for their betterment.</p>
   <p>These people testify that they are nothing more than greedy egoists and parasites. They should not be astonished if this country seeks to get rid of them at the earliest opportunity. People of that caliber place the interest of their insignificant ego above that of the American people. They place their <pb facs="5418478_2_0696.jpg" n="2"/>interest above that of the Czech people from which they issued, and also above that of all mankind to whom victory over the Teutons will mean a blessing.</p>
   <p>Much has been written and babbled among our people about our Czech and American consciousness. This is the time for a showdown. May the proof be a splendid success which will do us honor and fill us with joy. May it not bring shame upon us, and cast deep gloom over our minds!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
