<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-08">Nov. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Great Democratic Victory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An abstract) [Half-tones one column-ninth of a page each showing the victorious Czech candidates, Anton J. Cermak, Josef J. Mendl, and Adolf J. Sabath; also other non-Czech Democratic candidates such as Edmund K. Jarecki and Robert Sweitzer.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (German)</item>
     <item>IV (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-08">Nov. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT DEMOCRATIC VICTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An abstract) [Half-tones one column-ninth of a page each showing the victorious Czech candidates, Anton J. Cermak, Josef J. Mendl, and Adolf J. Sabath; also other non-Czech Democratic candidates such as Edmund K. Jarecki and Robert Sweitzer.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>.....Thompsonism, which caused so much evil in our city, county, and state, received its mortal wound in yesterday's election and went down in defeat .....But before it breathed its last it caused one more evil; committed one more sin. It combined with the Democrats to effect the defeat of our countryman, Attorney Albert B. Holecek, who was nominated on the Republican ticket as a non-Thompsonian Republican candidate for senator from the Nineteenth district.</p>
   <p>As is well known there is a movement on foot to impeach Thompson's ally, Governor Small, at the next session of the State legislature. The city hall <pb facs="5418478_2_0156.jpg" n="2"/>machinery worked with full force attempting to have the Thompson-Small ticket elected. Mr. Holecek did not belong to that clique, and it was therefore necessary to bring about his defeat. It must be said, however, that there were many of our countrymen who helped that clique and brought about Mr. Holecek's defeat.</p>
   <p>All the Czechs who were candidates on the Democratic ticket were elected..... [Translator's note: There is much repetition of the information already given in the previous issues of this paper about the individual candidates whose names appear on the first page of this translation.].....Two candidates for county commissioner, Mr. F. J. Triska and Mr. Novak, are also our countrymen. Their commissionership would cover all out-of-town county matters. If these two were elected it would mean that the Czechs would have a representation in the county board which would surpass their greatest expectations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
