<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation of Czechoslovak Independence by U. S. Government</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION OF CZECHOSLOVAK INDEPENDENCE BY U. S. GOVERNMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Whereas, the Czechoslovak nation has taken up arms against the German and Austrian monarchies, and has sent its own organized military force under officers of its own nationality, in complete accord and compliance with the rules and customs of civilized warfare, to the battlefield, where a combat is being carried on against the two monarchies mentioned, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Czechoslovaks, in seeking independence in the present war, have given full political authority into the hands of the Czechoslovak National Council,</p>
   <p>The Government of the United States recognizes that a state of war exists between the Czechoslovak force, organized in the aforesaid manner, and the German and Austro-Hungarian monarchies.</p>
   <p>Similarly, the Government of the United States recognizes the Czechoslovak <pb facs="5418478_2_0464.jpg" n="2"/>National Council as the actually warring government endowed with all due authority for conducting Czechoslovak military and political operations.</p>
   <p>The Government of the United States further proclaims its readiness to enter into official relations with the government thus recognized for the purpose of prosecuting the war against the common enemy--the German and the Austro-Hungarian monarchies."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
