<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-07">Apr. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech America Do Thy Duty!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-07">Apr. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH AMERICA DO THY DUTY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Let Shining Examples Demonstrate Loyalty to our New Homeland and to President Woodrow Wilson</p>
   <p>Let the Numbers of Czech-American Volunteers Grow as Impressive as Possible</p>
   <p>Many Czech Girls and Wives Enter the Red Cross Service</p>
   <p>The country is calling on us! Two countries are calling us. The United States, the country which we have chosen of our own volition and in which we have found liberty and means for our existence. The things we did not enjoy in the land of birth, our old homeland. We are sure it will be liberated now that President Wilson has issued his manifesto concerning the rights of small nations, to defend the interests of the United States against <pb facs="5418478_2_1081.jpg" n="2"/>assaults by Germany, and also to win victory for liberty and mankind now crushed under the rule of the German kaiser and his allies.</p>
   <p>The country is calling, and all of her good sons should heed this call. We are under no compulsion now, but we are expected to show how grateful we are for the good derived from her to show how we are loyal not only when times are good, but also in bad times, full of ominous import. The enemy who does not think highly of our defensive power must find out now that he has deceived himself, that by his obstinacy, he has driven the American eagle to spread his mighty wings and with all his power to plunge into the struggle.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that the Czechs will be among the very first to join the <pb facs="5418478_2_1082.jpg" n="3"/>ranks under the Star Spangled Banner. Many enthusiastic meetings and manifestations have proved our sentiment since the beginning of the War; actions should follow.</p>
   <p>Those who volunteer now will enjoy certain advantages of which those will not benefit who have waited until compulsion begins. They will be excellently drilled, which will make them more efficient and, therefore, better protected. If qualified, they will have a good chance to become officers.</p>
   <p>Those who cannot join on account of old age, sickness, or otherwise prevented, can do their bit, and contribute to the winning of victory in <pb facs="5418478_2_1083.jpg" n="4"/>many other ways. They should work faithfully in the place that will be assigned to them through the changed conditions. They should work on farms, striving to increase the produce of the fields.</p>
   <p>It will be necessary in order to insure success that all our affairs be managed in an orderly manner, that public opinion be not roused into disturbances; everybody should live in good relation with his neighbors. If, however, any subversive activities are discovered, then the proper authorities should be notified immediately.</p>
   <p>Our wives and girls, who know so efficiently how to manage their homes, should offer their skill to the Red Cross, and with their nimble, soft <pb facs="5418478_2_1084.jpg" n="5"/>hands, help to alleviate the sufferings which the War will inevitably cause. Our women, who have always played an important part in our national life, will surely not fail us now when they are being appealed to by the American people.</p>
   <p>Let us exhibit unanimity and strength in both our Czech, and our American sentiments. We may consider ourselves happy for being in a position where we can harbor love for both the American and our old country, without doing injustice to ourselves, and without having to conceal or disavow some obligation. This very fact should stimulate us to still more enthusiasm, and doubled efforts, to strengthen the ranks of Czechs in the Army and Navy, so that we will be citizens who can be held up for an example to others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1085.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>When this has happened, we may rest assured that the Czech name will be honored in this country, and that our motherland will be ever grateful to us and also feel proud of us.</p>
   <p>As far as the work in Chicago is concerned, we can inform our readers that preparations in several directions are in full swing. As reported in earlier issues, the American Sokol Community has named a special committee which deals with enlistments, and where there is ample opportunity to show our loyalty. This committee is headed by Doctor Jarka Kosar, who is assisted by several other physicians, members of diverse Sokol organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1086.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Czech National Association is making extensive preparations in the same direction. Mr. Josef Tvrzicky, director of the bureau of the above mentioned association, informs us that he and Mr. Frana Klepal have been authorized by the recruiting committee to work in the country districts.</p>
   <p>The Czech National Catholic League has expressed its eagerness to cooperate. This organization will advise all the Catholics in the United States of the seriousness of the situation. This will be done in a manifesto, in which the United States government will be given a pledge of loyalty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
