<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our First Czech-American Woman Doctor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR FIRST CZECH-AMERICAN WOMAN DOCTOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About a year after the drama, "Benefactors of Mankind" by the German dramatist, Felix Philippi, had been written, and while it was making its way across the footlights of the world's greatest stages, proclaiming the great significance and the priceless value of medical science, there was an unassuming, yet determined woman starting out to study the art of healing, the art of the benefactors of mankind. Far away from her native land, she started out in Chicago at the then famous Bennett College. She had been prompted to wend her way toward medical science by grief suffered through the loss of her own dear child. She is Dr. Anna F. Novák. She sought consolation in dispensing medical aid to other mothers' children.....</p>
   <p>She was born Anna F. Chrz in Mlečic, near Prague, in 1864, and was brought to Chicago at the age of three. Here she was reared under the loving care <pb facs="5418478_2_1747.jpg" n="2"/>of Mr. Václav Topinka. She attended English and Czech schools until she reached the age of eleven, and following the example of others, she began to work as a seamstress while continuing to improve her education. She did not cease to study even after her marriage in 1881 to Joseph Novak, with whom she lives in happy matrimony. The couple's happiness was violently shaken by the untimely death of their first daughter. This turned Mrs. Novák's mind toward studies. The Bennett college, Which merged with Loyola University two years ago, gave her the opportunity to reach the desired goal, doctor of medicine. The diploma was subsequently awarded to her. What was known as the Hooley theatre at that time furnished the scene for a festive graduation ceremony, at which countless floral offerings were presented to the new doctor by numerous Czech-American societies.</p>
   <p>Doctor Novák immediately plunged into vigorous activities as typified in any struggling young physician's life. Her office is located at 2402 South Millard Avenue. She never forgot her Czech descent, and is conspicuous among the workers of the Chicago Czech community....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
