<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-17">July 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Peace at Any Price</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-17">July 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">PEACE AT ANY PRICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Europe, there are very few people of the middle classes who are ignorant of the reasons for the war and the very deep-seated causes of it. In America, this is not the case. American newspaper readers are very superficial. All they read is the "sports" or the "styles," and they do not bother with the rest of the paper, as they are not interested in it. Hence, it is easy to under-stand that most of the people in America are of the opinion that "this war is nonsensical, criminal, and it should be brought to an end at once," or "we should in no way contribute to its prolongation; all exports of armaments should be stopped". They think that war is a thing of such atrocity that nothing can justify it, that everybody who engages in it, or in anyway cooperates with it, is a murderer, and equally a murderer is anybody who does not agree that it should be stopped at once, by any means, and no matter what may be the outcome. Recently an actress of Belgian origin expressed the opinion that the Belgians should have surrendered to the Germans and thus avoided all their present difficulties. Very similar is the opinion of <pb facs="5418478_2_1298.jpg" n="2"/>many Americans, who cannot understand why the Belgians did not let the German Army walk through their country, and in that way obviate all that followed. Of the same opinion were the American women who convened in the Hague in order to bring about peace--at any price. One of them went so far as to say that war is a crime under any circumstances, and that it would be a crime for Americans to wage a war in case an enemy should take New York. It is better to live under a terrorizing, oppressive government than not to live at all.</p>
   <p>Such Americans forget that our country [the United States] has gone through such a crisis herself. It was just about half a century ago when the question arose! Will the United States continue to exist, or will it disintegrate? In November, 1860, Lincoln was elected President upon the principle that slavery should not be abolished but that its spread should be stopped. The Southern slaveholders considered this an abrogation of friendly relations and seceded from the Union. South Carolina was the first state to secede, and was followed by a dozen other states, rich, armed, and well-prepared ones. Gloom seized the whole country. All serious, thinking people <!-- 5418478_2_1299 omitted, duplicate of 5418478_2_1300 --> <pb facs="5418478_2_1300.jpg" n="3"/>advocated appeasement, compromise. Prior to this, for forty years, the North had been "appeasing" the South, always yielding, always obliging. It started with the Missouri Compromise in 1820 and culminated in the Compromise of 1850. After 1850 all Americans desired quiet, peace. The slavery question was disturbing business, was hampering industry, and anybody in the North who would dare to reopen that question would have been sure of an attack from all sides. The question was considered settled, and nobody would touch it. But just the same, there were people who were not satisfied with the way it had been settled. These people firmly believed that peace is of value only when it is based on justice. They would not abandon this principle and voiced it from time to time. And the South was not satisfied either. The Southerners had become accustomed to receiving privileges and their requirements, their appetites grew. Thus it came to 1860 when, after the split of the Democratic party, Lincoln was elected President.</p>
   <p>Then the whole thing started again. There were again demands for peace, for compromise. Many proposals were worked out, of which Crittenden's had the <pb facs="5418478_2_1301.jpg" n="4"/>greatest appeal. He proposed the drawing of a certain line north of which slavery would be unlawful, and south of which it would be permitted by law. The decision in these serious days was up to Lincoln, who would not even consider a compromise. He wrote to Congressman Kellogg of Illinois:</p>
   <p>"Do not talk about any compromise by which slavery would spread. Should that happen, they would be riding us again, and all our work and efforts would be wasted. We should be obliged to start again. Better now than later on."</p>
   <p>To a Southerner he wrote: "In regard to slavery, I am firm. You people think it is good and should be encouraged, spread. We are convinced that it is criminal, and should be abolished."</p>
   <p>The Southern States started seceding, one after the other, and the excitement in the country was great. Crittenden's Compromise was being approved by state conventions, state legislatures, and state assemblies. Such great men as Greeley, Seymour, Douglas, the foremost newspapermen and contemporary <pb facs="5418478_2_1302.jpg" n="5"/>statesmen advocated it, open enemies of slavery were being assaulted by mobs of people, and it appeared quite certain that the compromise would be voted for by a great majority of people, thus averting war for many years to come.</p>
   <p>Lincoln, however, even though not inaugurated until March, was the recognized leader in the North ever since his election. He said again: "In this matter I am absolutely firm. I am opposed to any compromise by which slavery would spread."</p>
   <p>Some more Southern States seceded. People used to say, "Let them alone, let them go." All they wanted was to prevent a war. But Lincoln would not give in. He got together 75,000 volunteers to protect the unity of the Union and thus started a war that lasted four years, cost millions [sic] of lives, but assured unity and security to our country, and recognition of human rights.</p>
   <p>Now, according to the peace-at-any-price sages, Lincoln was a murderer: He was responsible for the war, he brought it about, he would not hear of <pb facs="5418478_2_1303.jpg" n="6"/>ending it before it was fought through to the last drop of blood.</p>
   <p>Where would the United States be now had he accepted a rotten compromise? The same applies to the war in Europe. Criminals are those who caused it, but not those who fight it and who, by fighting it out want to lay the foundation for a future where wars will be superfluous and impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
