<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-04">Apr. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-04">Apr. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everybody should be on his job, everyone should do his duty. Artisans skilled in the manufacture of ammunition should apply for work in the government plants and in private plants, these are to supply our army and navy. Farmers should make special efforts to raise the greatest possible crop of wheat and a maximum of cattle so that the nation and the soldiers who protect our country be properly fed. The railroads should pull every lever to make transportation rapid. Merchants and dealers should transact their business honestly, without any attempts at profiteering. Newspapers are urged to keep the people informed by publishing correct reports, leading them on the right way, the only way that points to the goal.</p>
   <p>Not all of us can become soldiers and sailors, but we all can help toward victory. Our women, also, will have to shoulder obligations the moment the struggle has begun. They will take care of the sick and the wounded <pb facs="5418478_2_1093.jpg" n="2"/>defenders of the country. Those in charge of a household will see to it that the workers, that most important element of the populace, be healthy and strong.</p>
   <p>Scientists, and all those engaged in research work, should strain every fibre of their brains in order to improve our means of defense and so extend their aid in bringing about a swift victory.</p>
   <p>If everyone, or the majority at least, does his duty, the results will be something to fill us with pride.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
