<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-24">Dec. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Women in the Stockyards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-24">Dec. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH WOMEN IN THE STOCKYARDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Herald [Record-Herald?] yesterday printed an article on women employed in the stockyards. It made special mention of two Czech women. One is Miss Anna Špaček, who is head of the department for social welfare in the plant of Thomas Wilson &amp; Company. The other is her assistant, Miss Anna Koutecký. The article is of fair size and is captioned "Americanization of Foreign-born Women in the Packers' City".....</p>
   <p>Until two years ago foreign-born women who were employed in the plant were careless about their habits and appearance. Today these women have acquired a sense of cleanliness and an understanding of sanitary laws. This reflects credit upon Miss Špaček. Although she was born in Bohemia she is an expert in the work pertaining to the welfare department.</p>
   <p>Miss Spacek sees to it that every female laborer takes a shower bath before starting to work. The women are willing to submit to a medical examination <pb facs="5418478_2_1622.jpg" n="2"/>when asked by Miss Špaček to do so. They also take medical treatment if it is necessary. After two years of training they have become genuinely proud of their experiences, whether in buying food or in other problems of everyday life, They keep their homes cleaner in conformity with the instructions received from the welfare department.</p>
   <p>The working women are employed only through the aid of the welfare department. Their conduct is under the department's observation. This applies to conduct in the plant and also in the home.</p>
   <p>A working woman of that plant cannot be discharged by her foreman. Her case is taken before Miss Špaček to be throughly investigated.</p>
   <p>Relations are more agreeable among the women because of this arbitration. The differences among men are mostly due to mere misunderstanding. The women take most of their troubles to Miss Spacek, often private ones such as little love affairs--and her advice seldom fails them....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
