<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-30">Dec. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Ford and the Peace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-30">Dec. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FORD AND THE PEACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is certainly most remarkable that people, who show such a great deal of common sense and practical understanding in one respect, are so pitifully impractical, so terribly blind when they are in a sphere different from their accustomed surroundings. Henry Ford, a man who has been engaging, with such marvelous success in the new automobile industry, who has made many million dollars in it, is certainly no dreamer, no visionary, but a man of the most practical spirit. But his expedition to Europe is such a "flop" that many people cannot but believe that he must have been planning it when suffering from an acute hallucination. Ford has no understanding of Europe, and he has no understanding of this war that the people are waging out of desperation, in order to put an end to unbearable conditions. He has grown up in America and, naturally enough, has for everything the explanation of an American. Of course, there are a few nations in Europe who participate in the war with a great deal of disgust, for <pb facs="5418478_2_1169.jpg" n="2"/>instance, the Bohemian nation, which is being forced against her own will to fight for the obnoxious Austria and its still more obnoxious emperor, against her own brothers. But such a nation is an exception. The majority of them fight for and out of their convictions, a circumstance demonstrated by the fact that even the socialists went into the war and are fighting with enthusiasm. The Germans are convinced that they will save the world with their disgusting culture. The French, who have suffered humiliations for the last fifty years, are convinced that they will finally break the Prussian militarism. The British, who have gone into the war with the least enthusiasm of all, know very well that they are fighting for the very existence of their world-wide empire. The Russians, just as all the other allies, are convinced that it is necessary to abolish the Prussian militarism in order that Europe and the whole world may live in peace. With what heroic enthusiasm the Belgians defended their little country, how valiantly the Serbians fought for theirs, has been sufficiently described by various war correspondents. But Ford knows better: He is convinced that all he has to do is to go to Europe, and ask the soldiers to go on strike, and all will flock behind him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1170.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>How impractical was the way the expedition was organized was apparent right at the beginning. Anybody with some standing of any kind could become its member upon application. In that way, intolerant people came into the expedition, people who fight and argue with one another before the eyes of the whole world, thus negating the brotherliness and love of peace they so zealously advocated and promoted. No doubt Ford had the best of intentions, enough money, and willingness to spend it, but at the same time he had the American fixed idea that money will buy anything and everything. He had no understanding of the way the people think and feel, and that was the principal reason of his failure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
