<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-22">Apr. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Silvestri's Testimony</title><title level="a" type="sub">It Showed That the Austrian Consul Used His Glib Diplomatic Tongue to Dodge Answers (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1011</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1011.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-22">Apr. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SILVESTRI'S TESTIMONY</title><title level="a" type="sub">It Showed That The Austrian Consul Used His Glib Diplomatic Tongue To Dodge Answers (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The offices of the Austrian consulate on La Salle Street resembled a courtroom yesterday morning. Statements had to be recorded there that had a bearing on the case of Dr. Fr. Iska, who had filed several damage suits for libel in print.</p>
   <p>Consul Silvestri, according to the Providence Journal, was under orders from the Austrian embassy in Washington when he paid Dr. Iska two hundred dollars per month as a remuneration for services rendered through the columns of his paper, Vesmir, to the Austrian government. This was quite naturally denied by the consul and by Dr. Iska as well. The latter was eager for the denial by Silvestri to be recorded before the consul's departure from America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1012.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Iska, no doubt, wishes to use the consul's statement in the trial of his damage suits.</p>
   <p>The hearing was conducted by Harry Olson, chief justice of the municipal court of Chicago, who appeared with his cleric, Mr. Miller, and his personal bailiff. Dr. Iška made his appearance with his lawyer; a large group of newspaper reporters were on hand as well as the lawyers of the defendants in Dr. Iška's libel suits. It was to be expected that the lawyers would exert themselves to draw admissions from Consul Silvestri which would prove the contentions of the defendants to be right. Mr. Silvestri, however, succeeded in avoiding direct answers, mostly by resorting to the right of privacy in the affairs of the state represented by a consul.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the hearing developed into a lengthy and elaborate one. Both parties, to be sure, had agreed to regard the testimony as a whole as equally relevant to each of the individual libel suits which had been filed against the Chicago Herald, Svornost, Spravedlnost, and the Česko-Slovanská <pb facs="5418478_2_1013.jpg" n="3"/>Jednota [Czecho-Slavic Union].</p>
   <p>Dr. Iska's lawyer was Mr. Ratkowic, assisted by Attorney Saltiel; attorney Israel Shrimski examined the consul for all the defendants' lawyers.</p>
   <p>The direct examination of the consul brought forth the statement that the Austrian consulate in Chicago had never received any money from the Austrian embassy in Washington for the purpose of paying off Dr. Iška; further, that no letter to that effect had ever been exchanged between the consulate and the embassy. When a letter in English translation was shown to the witness, he declared that he had never seen the document; that none of the consular employees had anything to do with it; that Dr. Iška had never come to the consulate; and finally, that he, Consul Silvestri, had never known Dr. Iška except from one telephone conversation which was held two months ago. Dr. Iška then had asked the consul for the name of some lawyer in Rhode Island, as he intended to file suit against the Providence Journal. Silvestri, with the aid of his lawyer, had thereupon sent Dr. Iška a list of lawyers. At the <pb facs="5418478_2_1014.jpg" n="4"/>same time he had promised Dr. Iška a written statement which could be used to support his libel suits.</p>
   <p>The cross-examination undertaken by Attorney Shrimski in behalf of the defendants in the libel suits proved more interesting. The consul admitted that he was bound by oath to the Austrian government; not to reveal certain items in the transactions with his government; he refused to state whether there are any extra men paid besides the regular employees. At first he evaded Judge Olson's direct question and finally declared he could give no information on the disputed point unless he received instructions from the Austrian government. Attorney Shrimski asked the witness if he, the consul, thought someone else might have paid Dr. Iska. The witness again refused to answer, whereupon the lawyers representing the defendants in the libel suits demanded that the entire preceding testimony be stricken out. The judge overruled the motion, and the consul's statements thus remained a part of admissible evidence.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1015.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the course of further examination, the consul admitted being informed of the contents of Czech-American papers and, therefore, also of what is being printed in Dr. Iska's paper, Vesmir. "In its columns the protagonists of liberty for the Czech people are dubbed crazy fools and rabble-rousers."</p>
   <p>The consul later admitted that, provided he had been authorized by the Austrian government, he could have made payments to Dr. Iska. He made the additional admission that he not only knew of the libel suits filed by Dr. Iska, but that he was eager to know about their results.</p>
   <p>As to Melichar, a collaborator in the Vesmir office, the consul denied ever having sent through him articles prepared for publication in said paper, or having paid him any money. He said that Silvestri also had no knowledge of any money to be distributed among Austrian army officers who had escaped to San Francisco from imprisonment in Siberia. Judge Olson did not compel an answer to the question whether there existed in American an Austrian-financed enterprise engaged in printing and disseminating propaganda. When the session ended, the consul left, visibly relieved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
