<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-08">Dec. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Show Our Loyalty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0731</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0731.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-08">Dec. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET US SHOW OUR LOYALTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Senate of the United States has voted for America's entrance into war against Austria. The House of Representatives will, no doubt, also vote, either unanimously or with an overwhelming majority, for war. This will prove that the peoples of this country are united in the war against the Government of Austria-Hungary. There is among them not one national group which would welcome this declaration of war against Austria with more joy than the American Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <p>Every one of us is acquainted with the fact that the Government in Washington is well aware of, and informed on, our loyalty to this Republic. For this latter reason the glad news is reported from Washington that immigrants of our nationality will, in spite of the declaration of war against Austria (whose subjects they had been), be treated with some indulgence.</p>
   <p>It is, of course, incumbent upon us to show our full accord with the <pb facs="5418478_2_0732.jpg" n="2"/>declaration against Austria, and we ought to do this right from the beginning. We should, at the same time, demand that, as a result of a victorious war, all the nationalities now under the Austro-Hungarian thumb be liberated and freed from the yoke of the German-Magyar governments.</p>
   <p>From the very start we have taken an irreconcilable attitude toward Austria and its dynasty. For the sake of democracy, which we have been defending for centuries; for the sake of our own people and its martyrs, we are duty-bound to call upon the world to pass judgment on the actions of two would-be-dominant peoples who will not give our nations liberty unless we can win it for ourselves.</p>
   <p>The first indication of our victory was the proclamation of the Allied nations that liberty will be secured for the Czechoslovak people and for other nations now under Austria-Hungary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0733.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>America is entering the war with Italy, which has the same aims as we, i.e., the dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy. We must acknowledge our obligation to give Italy our moral support for the time being, until we shall be able to place units of the Czechoslovak Army, now in France, at the disposal of the Italians on their front.</p>
   <p>We have to declare publicly that we consider America's entrance into the war as the initial action in the dismemberment of the Dual Monarchy.</p>
   <p>This is the reason why the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League are sending out a call for a mass meeting which is to be held Tuesday, December 11, in the Pilsen Park Brewery. Representatives of the Jugoslavs, Italians, Rumanians, Poles, and other nations will deliver addresses. Invitations have been issued to representatives of the Allied nations and to prominent American friends of our cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0734.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our voice must be heard in the chief American cities and on the other side of the ocean. It is the duty of the Czechs and Slovaks to be present at the meeting to the last man and woman!</p>
   <p>There will be a parade from the hall of Sokol Havlicek Tyrs; and our volunteers will participate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
