<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Czechoslovak Military Mission</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHOSLOVAK MILITARY MISSION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Army--God's own host, and crusaders of modern times--is covering itself with glory. Messages from faraway Siberia tell of the many obstacles which our army has to overcome in its hard struggle. Czech blood is being spilled for the rescue of Russia from the claws of German militarism and barbarism....Officers from that Czech army have come to the United States on a mission--to call Czechoslovak youth into the fight for the motherland, for honor, and for rights.</p>
   <p>Czechoslovak noncitizens between the ages of eighteen and forty-five may join that army. Week by week numbers of volunteers are leaving for the battlefields. Those prevented by their status as noncitizens from serving in the American Army or Navy should consider it their duty to serve the old homeland, and join the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>Some time ago there arrived one of its first invalids, Brother Linhart. One <pb facs="5418478_2_0511.jpg" n="2"/>of his legs is gone from below the knee. When they pitied him, he spoke like a man of honor: "Do not pity me. I am not ashamed to walk through the streets of Chicago, maimed--one legged. I would, on the contrary, be ashamed to be seen strolling here in good health. That, and only that, would make me feel ashamed." These are the words of a man!</p>
   <p>First Lieutenant Holy, of the Czechoslovak Army, will leave for a lecture tour through the States, to further his mission....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
