<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">"How to Be Victorious"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">"HOW TO BE VICTORIOUS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ardent patriotism was exhibited by our fellow countrymen in the mass meeting held in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Park, 26th Street and Albany Avenue, last night. The meeting was called for the purpose of arousing interest in the purchase of war-savings stamps. It certainly was a complete success, for the attendance was gigantic and the people were highly satisfied. The committee for the propagation of sales for the Twelfth Ward was in charge of the arrangements. The original idea came from the Ustredni Vybor (Central Committee). The band from the Great Lakes Naval Training Station furnished the music by permission of Captain W. A. Moffet. A banquet was arranged for the members of the band, who enjoyed an excellent, genuine Czech dinner catered in Joseph Mattas' restaurant, Trumbull Avenue and 26th Street. Ladies from the Czech society did the honors and served the meals, which were made possible by monetary gifts from businessmen. Besides the Navy men, some guests took part, among them Mr. Nolan and Lieutenant Naismith, who were scheduled to speak.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0651.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among other speakers were Messrs. Pflaum, Chairman; Otto Besserer, vice-chairman; and Dvorak, secretary of the committee; J. I. Novak, alderman of the Twelfth Ward; [A. J.] Cermak and [Joseph] Hajicek.....After the banquet the band marched to Pilsen Park, playing dashing songs and marches.</p>
   <p>The meeting in the pavilion was initiated with the "Star-Spangled Banner" and other patriotic songs.....Mr. Julian Nolan, director of the campaign for the sale of war-savings stamps, was the main speaker. He quoted Abraham Lincoln, who once said that a people at war should not be satisfied with learning about the strength of the enemy, but should find out its own power and resources. This advice, Mr. Nolan said, should be taken by the United States now.</p>
   <p>Czech veterans of the Bohemian American Camp No. 30, U. S. W. W. marched through the hall to the accompaniment of bugles and drums. Numerous musical selections were rendered by soloists of the Marine band and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0652.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lieutenant A. M. Naismith of the Canadian Army related some of his experiences in the war.....He closed his speech with a few flattering remarks about the Czechs, thereby ingratiating himself to the audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. John A. Cervenka, clerk of the Probate Court and chairman of the board of directors of the Pilsen Park Brewery, exhorted the crowd, stressing the necessity for action and urging them to buy war-saving stamps. He gave a clear account of the advantages offered in the purchase of the stamps....He also called on those not enlisted or drafted to do their bit at home and to join the Home Guards. This organization will also give good preliminary training to young men before they join the Army.</p>
   <p>A committee was appointed by Mr. Pflaum, chairman, which is to draft a resolution expressing loyalty to the United States Government. Among the members are Anton J. Cermak, Joseph Z. Uhlir, and Otto Kerner.</p>
   <p>The sale of war stamps was pushed by many ladies who canvassed the hall so efficiently that the financial result of the meeting was more than satisfactory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
