<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-14">Jan. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czech People in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-14">Jan. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECH PEOPLE IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of the latest political developments, we deem it necessary to define our attitude publicly. This war, which was designed to sweep some nations off the surface of the globe and to enslave others, has suddenly turned into a fight for the freedom of nations. Small and subjugated nations, which had hitherto been looked down upon as pariahs in the community of nations, awoke to the recognition of their rights and their significance in human society.</p>
   <p>In the midst of the peal of cannon which was meant to be their death knell, they arose before the world and proclaimed the principles of freedom of nations--principles which will go down in history as the harbingers of a new era.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0682.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There will be no peace until nations are free to decide their destinies. In order to make this war result in a permanent and auspicious peace and not one which would germinate into another still more horrible war, equality must be established among the nations. No nation exists that is too small to be free.</p>
   <p>Such was the appeal of the nations to the conscience of the world. Our nation also rose and took its place before the forum of the world. Our people were gagged in the old homeland, but our country spoke out through the deeds of its sons upon the battlefields. It spoke through the voice of the immigrants whose colonies are scattered over every part of the world and who thus became the delegates of our people to other nations.</p>
   <p>The Czech issue has become an international problem. Unless it is solved, there can be no just peace. This has been our contention, and we have presented proof. By a fair solution of the Czechoslovak question, which is a <pb facs="5418478_2_0683.jpg" n="3"/>part of the problem of small nations, one of the main causes of international strife will be removed. Therefore, it is in the interest of international security to liberate the Czech people.</p>
   <p>It is natural that in advancing this program we have won the sympathies of all democratic forces in the world. The enemies of Austria-Hungary have become our friends. We had one common aim--the demolition of Austria. We felt that wherever the slogan "Democracy must be secured!" was sounded, that was the place where we could find friends, because what we demand for our own nation is something fundamental, which all men require.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding all the friendship shown us by the democratic world, we were nevertheless conscious of this, that liberty for the Czech nation cannot be won by begging or weeping; that it cannot be bought; and that it must not be given as a favor--but that we will have to fight for it, win it, and that we have to prove our right to it by making sacrifices. We have to demonstrate <pb facs="5418478_2_0684.jpg" n="4"/>that the independence of our nation is the result of hard work.</p>
   <p>Yes, we have placed and are placing our hopes in aid from our friends, but for a fundamental guarantee of success we have searched and are searching in the soul of the Czech people themselves.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in spite of all ridicule and suspicion, we have continued and shall continue to follow our path. Our organization was dubbed "the bad fortune of the Czechoslovak nation....because it aggravates the condition of those fellow-countrymen who live under the government of the Austrian Eagle." But we knew that what we are doing is the emanation of the hope and efforts which are burning in the soul of millions who live in Czech and Slovak lands--millions whose hands were shackled and over whom the depressing atmosphere of prison hovered.</p>
   <p>And when from the East there came the great light of freedom; when in holy <pb facs="5418478_2_0685.jpg" n="5"/>Russia there rose the gigantic, victorious wave of democracy which rejuvenated the world by its spirit; when under its effects even conditions in the land of our birth were eased, and our nation could breathe and speak more freely: then our nation spoke through the mouths of representatives of all walks of life and all parties; our nation spoke as a people speaks which is determined to die for its liberty.</p>
   <p>We want liberty! "We, ourselves, want to determine the course of our life! We want our own free and democratic state!" And hundreds of thousands of Czech and Slovak prisoners [who were forced to serve in the Austro-Hungarian Army and were taken by the Allies] are calling for arms to fight for an independent and free Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>The foundations upon which we shall proceed to build the cathedral of freedom are laid! <pb facs="5418478_2_0686.jpg" n="6"/>Czechoslovak democracy has spoken daringly and resolutely to the entire world, just as a nation which is closing accounts with itself on what has been stifling its development for centuries speaks. Democracy has won the Czechoslovak people, and the moment will also come when democracy materializes.</p>
   <p>And for this reason we are determined to follow our ideal persistently. Czech democracy will not be lost and will not perish, even if the fortunes of war should turn. Democracy lives and grows in the soul of the people. It sprang from the beautiful courage of Czech volunteers who go to war again to fight for freedom, after having gone through the hell-fire of battles. Democracy will act even there, where it will raise its victorious banner, and where the flag of the oppressive Hapsburg governments still waves today. He who would destroy Czech liberty would have to annihilate the Czech nation!</p>
   <p>We are not becoming dispirited! We are not losing faith, even if statesmen <pb facs="5418478_2_0687.jpg" n="7"/>and diplomats in whose aid we placed hope do not remember us, particularly when they make official proclamations concerning Austria. Our problem is and will be vital. We would have to lose faith in ourselves--be it but for a second--before we would waver. Only he is lost who has lost faith in himself.</p>
   <p>We certainly feel strengthened by the speeches of Lloyd George and President Wilson, who spoke magnificently about the rights of self-determination of small nations. From these messages there emerges only one result: It convinces us of the necessity for more intensive, daring, and substantial work. We are not battling for the freedom of the Czechoslovak nation alone. We shall fight so that the world can see and know that liberty for the world also means the liberty of the land of our birth.</p>
   <p>The world must become convinced of this by our sincerity. Our actions will have to reflect evidence of our bold determination to prosecute our aims over <pb facs="5418478_2_0688.jpg" n="8"/>the head of the whole world.</p>
   <p>Sluggishness and weakness therefore must not be the governing spirit of today; but, on the contrary, strength and courage which grow out of consciousness of the rights we are demanding must lead us onward. Our liberty shall not and must not be a gift of mercy, for freedom given as a favor is no freedom. Only weaklings build their castles upon mercy and lose faith in their cause whenever fortune changes its fickle sympathy. The world belongs to the strong, and the real soldier proves his quality when the situation is most serious. He does not lose discipline. He does not lose faith. He does not lose pluck. He does not lose the will to win. We hope that the Czechs in this country were not born from a nation of weaklings. We believe in our people, in their courage, in their love, in their sincerity!</p>
   <p>One hundred thousand Czechoslovak volunteers, who once had been recruited into the Austrian Army [and are now fighting in the Czechoslovak and Allied armies], <pb facs="5418478_2_0689.jpg" n="9"/>represent a stronger support of our cause than if the whole world stood behind us and we simply kept quiet.</p>
   <p>And for this reason, each Czechoslovak volunteer represents one of the pillars upon which our liberated nation will stand. And by the same token, every Czechoslovak volunteer means a nail in the coffin for Austrian thralldom. Upon the Czechoslovak Army, that army of action, and not upon promises, be they ever so glittering, will the future of the nation be based. The sympathies of the world for our cause will grow in proportion to the power of the demonstrations of this suffering and sacrificing nation.</p>
   <p>Thus today we know only one aim: Onward into the contest for the liberty of the nation! Therefore we know only one right--the right to an independent life. We know, indeed, that there is not force enough in the world to stem the breaking of the shackles and prevent the resurrection of our nation if its determination is sanctified by the longing of millions who raised the <pb facs="5418478_2_0690.jpg" n="10"/>banner of liberty and democracy before the eyes of the world. We, too, stride under this banner. We know that we are marching toward victory, because We have gained mastery over ourselves.</p>
   <p>For the Czech National Alliance: Dr. L. J. Fisher, president; Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary. For the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America: Reverend I. Kestl, president; F. Sindelar, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
