<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-22">Nov. 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Not Weaken</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-22">Nov. 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">LET US NOT WEAKEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great mass and protest meetings are being held at the present time not only in America, but also throughout the civilized world. Their only purpose is to engender in the masses of the respective nations a powerful flow of sympathy for the South European peoples under the Crescent who were being trodden into the dust, dragged through thorns of innumerable tortures and hardships, abused to death in their Balkan homes, until finally they lifted their fists and shouted defiance, so that all of Europe and the whole world can hear their "Quo usque!...."</p>
   <p>But the Turk did not hear. He did not want to hear. With the rest of Europe quiescent, he wanted to continue his depredations where for centuries he had piled up horror and fear, sorrow, despair, pain, and death.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus, finally, the patience of the oppressed nations gave out and, seeing that Europe's ears were deaf to their cries, they decided to find their own justice. Inflammable material piled up high by the Turk himself caught fire, and the red flames lighted the Balkans with blood. For one side, this light reflected happiness, because it meant the rosy dawn of morning, the awakening of determination and freedom which came within reach for the Slavs in the Balkan.</p>
   <p>And these Slavs, whether they be Bulgars, Serbs, or Montenegrins--who until recently were unknown outside the confines of Europe, and if known then considered something inferior--now have the sympathies of the entire civilized world, with the exception of Germany and Austria.</p>
   <p>These sympathies are even more natural, for the Bulgars, Serbs, and Montenegrins have raised their arms against the Turk not entirely in their own interest, but also in the interest of others. The Balkan Slavs are also fighting for the Macedonians and Albanians. But this latter group, through <pb facs="5418478_2_1520.jpg" n="3"/>a peculiar turn of circumstances, has stood up against them and is on the side of its own hardest oppressors. Today the Balkan Slavs are fighting primarily for human rights in general. They are fighting in order to prove not only to the vanquished Turk, but to the entire world as well, that all nations, even the smallest among them, must be given the right to live--a right which has not been denied to other, perhaps stronger ones. The Balkan Slavs are fighting not only for their own liberty, but for the liberty of the whole world, for liberation from all tyranny, all fanaticism. The Balkan Slavs have opened a new era in history, and their war is a showdown of the traditional concept of Europe's humanity to man.</p>
   <p>This is one of the principal reasons why America sympathizes with the Slavs in this war. It means the end of looking at things from the point of view of Mr. "Status Quo" Mr. "Status Quo" is now a thing of the past. He was an old gentleman, a sickly, debilitated diplomat who unfortunately--or rather, fortunately--let himself be treated by a quack, who, in this case, was the concert of European powers. And this quack gave the almost five-hundred- <pb facs="5418478_2_1521.jpg" n="4"/>years-old diplomat, "Status Quo," a deucedly rotten medicine. "Status Quo" was sick, then sicker, and turning up his eyes, finally let go of his asthmatic soul. He left behind a bereft widow, Turkey; a mother, Germany and a niece, Austria. His daughters, Bulgaria, Serbia, and Montenegro, do not feel particularly unhappy about his death. They do not think the old man was so very kind to them. In fact, they rejoice in seeing the heavy, black-framed obituaries being mailed. In these obituaries we read that the funeral will take place on the other side of the Bosporus in Asia Minor in a few days. His remains will be buried in Allah's cemetery, and, according to the Koran, his soul will go straight to Paradise, there to be entertained forever by light-footed, heavenly houris, mistresses of the Prophet of Prophets. The Requiem Mass for the dearly departed will be celebrated immediately after the burial in the Christian way in the Christian Cathedral of St. Sophia in Constantinople. And while this Lass is being celebrated, the Slavic language will again be heard there for the first time in many, many years. While Turkey, Germany, and Austria cannot avoid accepting quiet condolences, they announced in advance that they will refuse any and all floral tokens of sympathy for <pb facs="5418478_2_1522.jpg" n="5"/>their bereavement. This is a shrewd precaution, we think. Outside of their own premises, there is nobody who would be seen offering flowers, especially not in America.</p>
   <p>The American nation, which has always treasured its freedom and its liberty, will certainly have no sympathy for a nation which has trodden upon the liberty and freedom of other nations, or for such a nation's allies. And Turkey had many allies in Europe whose rotten diplomacy always and everywhere preferred spoils to justice and human rights.</p>
   <p>If, then, America is to offer a wreath of flowers to anybody, she will offer it to the victors who fought so valiantly and bled so profusely for all that is dear to her. She will give them all the help she can.</p>
   <p>Let us, therefore, being Slavs ourselves, not weaken in our sympathies. Standing firmly behind our Slavic brothers, we shall stand firmly behind ourselves. Any support we give to the Bulgars, the Serbs, and the Montenegrins we shall <pb facs="5418478_2_1523.jpg" n="6"/>be giving to ourselves. Let us not forget that. Let us not weaken, but let us continue working for the Slavic Red Cross with all the diligence and energy we can muster. Never mind when somebody says that the war is coming to a close. Never mind, even if the war were to end today and a definite, final peace were to be signed. The Balkans will continue to need help even then, and will be needing a great deal of it. Even then there will be thousands and thousands lying wounded in the hospitals; even then there will be helpless widows, destitute mothers, and orphaned children whom the war robbed of their only provider. And there will be many of them. Every bit of help will be needed--even the least little bit--and every bit of it will be appreciated and gratefully acknowledged. And then, let us not forget the likelihood that another war will break out in Europe soon--the war between Austria and Serbia, for which Austria is getting ready with all possible speed. Austria, the archenemy of all Slavs!....</p>
   <p>It is clear that it is our duty to go on with our collections and to speed up the work. In that way we shall be giving our Slavic brothers not only <pb facs="5418478_2_1524.jpg" n="7"/>financial, but also moral support. Therefore, let us not weaken.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
