<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-09">Oct. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-09">Oct. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Election Commissioner Anthony Czarnecki has sent us a long letter urging the Bohemian voters, both men and women, to register next Tuesday and thus make up for their negligence last Saturday. Mr. Czarnecki says that he studied the lists of registered voters and has come to the conclusion that hardly one fourth of the Bohemian voters are registered. The percentage of registered women voters is still smaller. The Commissioner stresses in his letter the fact that it is absolutely necessary in the interest of the immigrated element, and particularly the Slavic element, for every Bohemian voter to register next Tuesday and thus prove the power of Bohemian citizens in our country. The coming ballot contains the names of excellent Bohemian candidates, and this is one more reason why every Bohemian voter should do his civic duty next Tuesday. Officials of Bohemian nationality have in most cases made a splendid record for themselves, thereby benefiting not only their own nationality, but contributing to a better and more honest public administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0113.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Commissioner Czarnecki points to another fact that merits the attention of every Bohemian citizen. In examining the registration list he has found that there are many people among us who have registered as Austrians, that is, as having been born in Austria instead of registering as Bohemians. This mistake has been the subject of many discussions and it has been generally believed that there is not one Bohemian who would register as Austrian. According to Mr. Czarnecki's letter, however, this mistake still prevails. We urge, therefore, every one of our voters to register as Bohemians. The registration clerks and judges must never object. If our people do not register as Bohemians, they increase the number of Austrian voters in our city which is absolutely inexcusable. We wish to believe that cases of that kind are now only exceptions, but even so, there should be none.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
