<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-19">Apr. 19, 1920</date>,
<title level="a">Frank J. Petru Elected President of Of the Cicero Board of Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-19">Apr. 19, 1920</date>,
<title level="a">FRANK J. PETRU ELECTED PRESIDENT OF OF THE CICERO BOARD OF EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president and three members of the Cicero Board of Education were elected Saturday. The election was a triumph for the Bohemian people; a triumph that was much more significant because Mr. Frank J. Petru and his friends had to overcome many obstacles in some parts of Cicero, such as, in the districts of Hawthorne and Grant Works. In these districts he was worked against in such a manner that defeat could have been expected. The campaign was especially furious in the Hawthorne District and were it not for the Bohemian pluralities in the Morton Park, the Clyde Park, and the Warren Park districts his fate would have been sealed..... Candidates for the office of the president received the following number of votes: Frank J. Petru, 2,943; William N. Jannenga, 2,709; John F. Slapak, 484; Frank J. Horak, 159.....</p>
   <p>Victory for Mr. Petru is a victory for the Bohemian group in Cicero, and let us hope that it will contribute to the improvement of the Cicero Board of Education <pb facs="5418478_2_0160.jpg" n="2"/>and to the introduction of better conditions in the management of Cicero public schools.</p>
   <p>Besides the election for president and members of the Board of Education, citizens also voted on the question of whether or not a public library should be established in Cicero. That a great majority of voters recognized it as a necessity, was shown by the results: 5,269 votes for, and only 752 against.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
