<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-03">Sept. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">German Propaganda of Deed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-03">Sept. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PROPAGANDA OF DEED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That the Kaiser's agents, both paid and voluntary are exerting all efforts to promote the interests of Germany in America to the detriment of our country, and that they are striving to undermine our neutrality has been known for a long time, and it is really surprising that the authorities and the public have been indifferent, or at least very tolerant, toward this savage baiting. This fact is a definite proof of the exemplary patience of the people of the United States. As long as this propaganda was limited to inflammatory news-paper articles and the adopting of baiting resolutions by various German, Irish, and "peace" associations, it was protected by the principle of free press and free speech, which still prevails in this country, at least as long as it is supported by money power. And the Germans do not lack that power. It seems, however, that this kind of propaganda has not had the desired results, and thus, when the United States has refused to be moved by cajolery and silly arguments to prohibit the export of arms and munitions to the Allies, the lackeys of the blood-thirsty Hohenzollern have started a <pb facs="5418478_2_1236.jpg" n="2"/>propaganda of deed and are trying to achieve by dynamite what they failed to do by reasoning.</p>
   <p>It was particularly the affair of the German pastor Kayser (what an odd coincidence in names!), murdered in Gary, that confirmed the spreading opinion that there is a huge conspiracy in existence whose purpose it is to prevent by any and all means the delivery of war material to the Allies. It seems that it was just in Gary where this unheard-of conspiracy had its center from which the activities of agents throughout the United States was directed, agents who have inaugurated a real rule of terror in a number of special industries. A whole series of factories working on contracts for the Allies have been dynamited, resulting in the loss of lives of many Americans, an immense loss of property, and laying off of workingmen. Nothing similar to what the Germans are doing at this time has ever been undertaken by nationals of another country in a neutral state. It is impossible not to believe that that whole race has contracted a case of rabid megalomania, impervious to any argument. In Texas, for instance, a German mail carrier, a man who has been paid by the United States Government for thirty years, and who, no doubt, has lived much <pb facs="5418478_2_1237.jpg" n="3"/>longer in this country, was fired the other day because he stated that in case of war between the United States and Germany he would immediately join the German army and fight against the country in which he has lived comfortably for so many years. Where would the freedom and liberty of the United States be now, if all nations were composed of such despicable individuals? How could Washington, as a British subject, have dared to raise arms against his own ruler if he had taken a similar attitude?</p>
   <p>President Wilson's administration may rejoice because the Kaiser has, formally, agreed to remove the cause of the crisis and revise the methods of submarine warfare, but the fact remains that Germany continues to be an enemy of the United States. The physical cause of the controversy may be removed, but its mental cause, the insuperable conflict of the general principles of thought [Weltaufschauung] remains. The German government is financing and abetting this conspiracy with the typical thoroughness and efficiency that characterize its war machine, a conspiracy that threatens the very foundation of this Republic. The German government, in order to promote the military objectives of the <pb facs="5418478_2_1238.jpg" n="4"/>empire, is financing a conspiracy of high treason in the United States. News-papers, seemingly independent but in reality subsidized by Berlin, are inciting the citizens of the United States to acts against their own government. No means that would serve this purpose have been overlooked by the intelligent criminals on the spree. German propaganda in the United States is apparently conducted by American citizens whose fine susceptibilities are being offended by the export of instruments of murder, and who under the guise of friends of peace, are doing all they can to scare the American Government from protecting its rights against the Huns of the modern era. In reality that criminal propaganda of deed is directed from Berlin and its only aim is to promote the interests of the German military machine.</p>
   <p>In view of the innumerable proofs in the form of documents secured by various newspapers, and the apprehension of German spies and dynamiters by secret government agents, it is hardly possible for our government to continue to ignore such conduct, even if the German Ambassador Bernstorff does call on the State Department with an innocent expression on his face, a smile on his treacherous <pb facs="5418478_2_1239.jpg" n="5"/>lips, and his back bent in humbleness. When a foreign government conducts a criminal campaign of deeds directed against the President, against the Administration, against the Congress, against American industries, against labor unions, against the very unity of the nation, our Federal Government cannot and must not remain passive. When workingmen in factories are being killed off by the Kaiser's dynamiters, it is no less a crime than that of torpedoing ships with American citizens on the open seas. While there may be some excuse for the sinking of enemy ships, even if they have American citizens aboard, who, after all, could select another vessel, there is absolutely no excuse for destroying American lives right in their own country while employed in a business which even the German government has found it necessary to recognize as lawful.</p>
   <p>There might have been some reason for condoning these Germanophile excesses as long as they could be considered the result of fanatical patriotism and partisanship of private individuals; as soon, however, as it becomes apparent that they are the result of well prepared plans of a foreign government, by which they are not only directed but also financed, then the government at Washington <pb facs="5418478_2_1240.jpg" n="6"/>must not remain blind and deaf. There are enough laws in this country whose enforcement would stop such deeds. But because these fanatics, many of whom have sworn loyalty to the United States and now disregard the oath in order to do the Kaiser's bidding, do not obey the laws of the country, it should be quite sufficient to give the German government to understand clearly that German propaganda in the United States is at least as grave an offence against international laws and the principles of humaneness as the attacking of passenger ships. This would cause the Kaiser's agents in this country to realize that the United States is in earnest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
