<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-14">July 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement about the Czechoslovak Army</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Lieutenant Holy)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-14">July 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT ABOUT THE CZECHOSLOVAK ARMY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Lieutenant Holy)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Army is a detached body under the high command of the Allied armies. It fights under its own banner against Germany and Austria-Hungary. In matters of politics it takes orders from the Czechoslovak National Council, which was recognized by the Allies, some time ago, as the provisional Czechoslovak government. A general, designated by the French government, and agreed on by the Czechoslovak National Alliance, is commander in chief of our army. Czechoslovak is the official language. The Army is composed of volunteers exclusively. They enlist for the duration of the war. The nucleus of the Czechoslovak Army was the army formed in France; it is being augmented by volunteers from America. A large Czechoslovak contingent from Russia is on its way to France where it will join the army. Detachments of Czechoslovak soldiers are fighting on the Italian front; they are an integral part of the Czechoslovak Army, which at present counts about 130,000 men.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0507.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Uniforms are blue-gray, with dark blue caps and special Czechoslovak emblems. Soldiers draw twenty-five cents per day. Those higher up receive more. Besides this, every volunteer is paid twenty-five francs per month. No deductions for insurance, support, etc., are made from this pay.</p>
   <p>Wounds, sickness, or death are taken care of just as with soldiers of the French Army, by invalid pension, support of survivors, etc.</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that the independent Czechoslovak state will properly take care of its liberators.</p>
   <p>Every Czech and Slovak in the United States is urged to join this army if he is not in duty bound by his citizenship to serve in Uncle Sam's Army. The age required is between eighteen and forty-five years, and twenty-one to thirty-one for those with only the first citizenship papers, or those in the No. 5 recruiting class.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0508.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the time of his service, the soldier is paid fifteen dollars for the support of his wife, and four dollars per month for each of four minor children, provided that such support is needed. The American Red Cross treats soldiers of the Czechoslovak Army just like American soldiers.</p>
   <p>Return to the United States is guaranteed by law.</p>
   <p>New volunteers may apply at one of the nearest offices of the Czechoslovak Military Committee. After a medical examination they are sent to the splendidly fitted-out Czechoslovak military camp at Stamford, near New York City, and from there to France with the next expedition. All information can be had from our offices, and from the officers of the Czechoslovak Army: First Lieutenant Holy in Chicago, Second Lieutenants Horvat in Pittsburgh, Spaniel in Omaha, and Niederle in Cleveland.</p>
   <p>For the Military Mission of the Czechoslovak Army in the United States: Antonin Holy, first lieutenant in the 21st Regiment of Czechoslovak Sharpshooters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0509.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All Czechoslovak volunteers now with the Canadian or English Army will be transferred into the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
