<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-10">Dec. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Does the President Want to Preserve the Unity of Austria-Hungary?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-10">Dec. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DOES THE PRESIDENT WANT TO PRESERVE THE UNITY OF AUSTRIA-HUNGARY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proclamation of war on Austria-Hungary issued recently by President Wilson has gladdened the hearts of everyone who has grasped the immense importance of this diplomatic step. It has given us new hopes and has instilled greater determination into the Czechoslovak people. One part of the proclamation of the great protagonist of democracy was not comprehended. It is the passage in which the President declares--as he did in the proclamation of war on Germany--"that the United States has no intention of destroying the national entity of states".</p>
   <p>We are extremely glad to have established as a fact that the leading government circles in Washington do not interpret the words of the President as a <pb facs="5418478_2_0726.jpg" n="2"/>denial of the rights to liberty of the small nations which are oppressed now and demand complete independence and freedom. It was not at all the President's intention to say that he would leave Austria-Hungary unimpaired, and still less that he would guarantee its entity.</p>
   <p>What he wanted to declare was simply that all the nations will have to decide their own destinies; in other words, that the nations will have to govern their futures by means of their own strength. He meant to say that the nations will have to put in their claims and stand up for them with determination and make every effort possible to see them realized without waiting for outside help.</p>
   <p>Briefly, the small nations will have to press their demands with their own force in an energetic manner.</p>
   <p>This attitude is quite natural and in full accord with the Czech foreign policy and program of agitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0727.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We may, with satisfaction, dwell quietly upon the fact that our government circles have acknowledged our demands as being just. This is proved by the permission given to us for the creation of a Czechoslovak Army which is to fight on the side of the Allies. We have thus been given an opportunity to fight for our cause and to demonstrate the ability of the Czechoslovak nation to determine its own fate and to act according to its own will.</p>
   <p>The attitude which the President assumes is best reflected in an article in the December, 1917, issue of The Bohemian Review, the official organ of the Czech National Alliance. It is printed in the English language and published in Chicago. [Translator's Note: In the Denni Hlasatel the article is in the Czech language.]</p>
   <p>"Czechs Hail War Against Austria"</p>
   <p>"It was bound to come. The President did his utmost to avoid war with Austria, just as he had tried for two years to avoid it with Germany. All was in vain.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0728.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The rulers of Germany had no regard for the conscience of the world. They attacked America, forcing our President to take the step. And now the rulers of Austria, not heeding the warning by the President to separate from Germany, sold out body and soul to the German demon. These militarists and agitators of Vienna and Budapest have finally convinced President Wilson that they will not reform until they have had a sound thrashing.</p>
   <p>"Citizens of Czech descent are exuberant over the decision of the President and its speedy ratification by Congress.....The President is an optimist in his confidence in human nature; he still believes that the evildoer may be directed to the right path. We, however, who know the stubbornness and astounding subtlety of the Austrian generals and the Magyar magnates, the real overlords of the Dual Monarchy; we who were brought up in Austria cannot share the President's opinion that Austria could be weaned from Germany.</p>
   <p>"We are now sure that these present rulers cannot save their thrones. The Austrian Government is our enemy now, and America will deal only with the <pb facs="5418478_2_0729.jpg" n="5"/>representatives of the various nations that live in Austria.</p>
   <p>"It is significant that the President distinguishes between the "German nation" and the "Austrian nations". This little grammatical differentiation and the careful weighing of the essence of the President's memorable proclamation is dear to the Czechs, who at first were astounded by the words, 'We do not wish to rearrange or to destroy the Austrian-Hungarian monarchy in any way.'</p>
   <p>"The President says nothing about wishing to preserve that unnatural dynastic state. He only declines to imply that America is fighting to disrupt that state, or for any other reason save for the liberty of nations, great or small, and to insure their right to self-determination. The President undoubtedly knows that if no coercion were used by the Austrian Government, the various nations ruled by it would choose an entirely different mode of existence. The Czechs, if given the choice, will live under the republican system."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0730.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This is the attitude taken by the official organ of the Czech National Alliance. Time will prove that its judgment is right, for it is certain that the United States will not hesitate to recognize the demands of the Czech nation. America cannot but approve of the Czechoslovak political program which demands, and will demand, an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>America will extend its helping hand to us in the pursuit of this aim. The Czech National Alliance and the Slovak League will, from the very start, make every effort to keep the United States mindful of its pledge. Of course, every individual will be bound to work toward the realization of the great task before us and America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
