<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Message from the Czechoslovak Army Conveyed by its Officers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A MESSAGE FROM THE CZECHOSLOVAK ARMY CONVEYED BY ITS OFFICERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The same enthusiastic expectancy which awaited our undaunted leader, Professor Thomas G. Masaryk, when he was scheduled to address our people, prevailed when the news spread that representatives of the Czechoslovak Army were coming to Chicago. These representatives had been previously welcomed, but the reception accorded them last night at the Pilsen Brewery Park surpassed all others. A special mass meeting was held for the occasion.</p>
   <p>Four young officers of our army were present: First Lieutenant A. Holy, Second Lieutenants J. Horvat, Oldrich Spaniel, and Miloslav Niederle. Leaders from the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League had expected a large number of Czechs and Slovaks to attend this event, but they were astonished to see a crowd as large as the one that thronged the hall last night. Everyone was anxious to hear from the young officers who had already gone through the brunt of battles, and of whom <pb facs="5418478_2_0516.jpg" n="2"/>each was doing his duty toward his nation. Each of them had also been a soldier in the Austrian Army. Our fellow countrymen were anxious to hear these young warriors explain the formation of the Czechoslovak Army and the purpose of their visit to this country; for they knew that Czech Americans would do their utmost to fulfill that purpose. We are fairly certain that everyone who attended the meeting was entirely satisfied, and departed with a sincere resolution to faithfully work for the cause which means liberty for our people and the establishment of an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>Those in charge of arrangements for this meeting had originally planned to hold it in the pavilion. When this spacious hall became overcrowded, and only a part of the multitude had been accommodated, Mr. Vojta Benes suggested that the meeting be continued in the open Park. The suggestion was accepted immediately.</p>
   <p>Mr. Benes soon announced the arrival of the guests, and at their appearance <pb facs="5418478_2_0517.jpg" n="3"/>the throng broke into a tumultuous "Na Zdar!" (To Success!). Mr. Rubringer's band played "Marseillaise". Mr. Rubringer donated his services for the entire evening. American, Czech, and Slovak anthems and folk songs, as well as numerous fiery Sokol marches, were played throughout the affair.</p>
   <p>The officers, our distinguished guests, were conducted to the platform by leaders from the Czech and Czech Catholic Alliances and the Slovak League, and were presented by Mr. F. Kubec, head of the county branch of the Czech National Alliance. Each of the officers was loudly acclaimed as the names were called. Mr. Kubec took the floor and pointed out that the moment was of extreme significance, for it marked the climax of the proclamation that the creation of the Czechoslovak Army is the crowning of our national patriotic efforts. The speaker pointed out that the best welcome we could accord them would be our aid in the work they are performing.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schustek, speaking for the Slovak League, clearly showed how much our <pb facs="5418478_2_0518.jpg" n="4"/>entire nation now depends on the Czechoslovak Army, and how absolutely necessary it is that every one of us give his fullest support. Mr. J. Straka of the Catholic Alliance spoke in a similar vein. He declared that our Czechoslovak action has reached a stage in which far-reaching reversals may occur almost overnight, and that we have to hasten if we want to take part in the great struggle for the liberation of our old homeland. He also mentioned the proposal for the founding of a Slavonic Legion in America. He again laid emphasis on our obligation to fight for the freedom that we so fervently desire. The applause that rewarded the speaker shows that his words will bear fruit in the form of increased numbers of volunteers for the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>"The Star-Spangled Banner" was played and sung, after which the next speaker, First Lieutenant Antonin Holy, was introduced. In private life he was a professor in the middle grade schools, the last grade of which leads to classical and technical universities in Austria-Hungary. He thanked the audience for the ovation which, he said, he was sure was not due him and his <pb facs="5418478_2_0519.jpg" n="5"/>brother officers, but rather due to the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>"When we were leaving France," the speaker continued, "they asked us to convey greetings and expressions of thanks to their American brothers, and to urge them to join us soon. The Czechoslovak Army has not risen from naught. It is the fruit of the deeds of a few heroes who were the first to shed their blood for our cause upon the battlefields in France and Russia, without even fancying what the results of their sacrifice would be. They went into the fight without guarantees; they merely wanted to demonstrate to the world that our nation is not on the side of the murderer, but on the side of the Allies, and that its struggle, although of a somewhat different nature, is no less the bitter..... Brothers, prove by your actions that you are going with us, forward, to the finish!" The speaker was interrupted by frequent and frenzied applause.</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Horvat, Slovak clergyman, declared that dissensions and antagonisms among parties have lost their significance today, and that we are all united.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0520.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"There are no differences in the Czechoslovak Army. Czechs and Slovaks stand as equals, and shoulder to shoulder, with one aim--to humble the age-old common enemy.....You in America know what liberty means. We want to build the independent Czechoslovak state upon the same principles. We are certain to accomplish this--the Allies are helping us, and God is helping us. The sooner you join us the less we fear that you might come too late....." The speaker was rewarded by wild acclaim which gave promise that enlistments in the Czechoslovak Army had received another mighty impetus.</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Oldrich Spaniel was the next speaker. He reminded the audience of how three Czech regiments won a victory against the Germans just one year ago. They were, the speaker declared, the nucleus of the present army's strength. Lieutenant Spaniel gave a vivid picture of the battles in Russia.</p>
   <p>"It was a significant moment when the first Czech-American volunteers arrived in France. I spoke to them; I know them. There were few of them. You could, <pb facs="5418478_2_0521.jpg" n="7"/>of course, not send more in those times, when America was still neutral. Today, however, our program tallies with that of America, and now it is every Czechoslovak's duty to join our army. Come to us, learn to know us, and you will have grasped the meaning of our fight for liberty in which we all must persist."</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Niederle spoke of three fronts: one in the old motherland, one in the army, and one in America. "This leads to the question of whether we, here in America, are doing as much for the cause as our men in the motherland, our representatives there, and others who are determined to place their heads upon the headsman's block." The speaker admonished his American countrymen not to forget their obligations to their nation. In regard to the military front, the speaker said that the courage with which the Czechoslovak soldier goes into the fight to defend that which is dear to all of us, is sufficient to convince us.....</p>
   <p>Before the close of this memorable meeting, Mr. Vojta Benes urged the gathering <pb facs="5418478_2_0522.jpg" n="8"/>to appear to the last man and woman when 150,000 members of Slavonic races are expected at the Fourth of July celebration in Douglas Park. He also urged them not to forget our women's organizations which work on gifts for soldiers of the Czechoslovak Army. The result of a collection proved that his appeal was heeded by all. Mr. Benes also informed the assembly that twelve volunteers for the Czechoslovak Army are leaving Chicago tomorrow evening, that they will be seen off by the officers, and that our people should be present in large numbers to make the occasion still more impressive. He spoke about the feelings of our people in the motherland, stating that those people would rather see their men dead than to see them come from captivity in Russia, and stay at home at a time when the Czechoslovak Army is being built up! He laid emphasis on the American Czechoslovak's duty to constantly replenish the ranks of our own army in France. Czechoslovak America has promised its leader, Professor Masaryk, to stand behind him.</p>
   <p>The loud assent which Mr. Benes's exhortation evoked showed that Czech-America <pb facs="5418478_2_0523.jpg" n="9"/>is sure to keep this promise. After a few parting words by Mr. Kubec, the meeting was declared closed. The officers were the center of attention. They were surprised by a special detachment of American soldiers, who are undergoing training in mechanics at the Carter H. Harrison High School. The soldiers paid them military honors. Everybody was eager to greet our heroes from the Czechoslovak Army, and everyone wanted to be their host. The officers are the guests of Mr. Hajicek, Czech banker, and were served with a genuine Czech dinner prepared under the supervision of Mr. A. Schnabl at his restaurant on Trumbull Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
