<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-08">Mar. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Celebrate Their Leader's Birthday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-08">Mar. 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATE THEIR LEADER'S BIRTHDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Masaryk Day at the bazaar of the C. N. S. (Czech National Association) was what it was expected to be. More than ten thousand adults entered the gates of the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Company last night. Everyone seemed to be aware that he was not only visiting the bazaar, but that he was about to help honor the name of Masaryk whose sixty-seventh birthday was being celebrated.</p>
   <p>The afternoon was "the children's" of whom no less than 7,000 came in huge bevies. The din from the sea of small voices was almost deafening, but the management and the "mammas" kept everything in good order. The supervision of the children and the care of their safety were in the reliable hands of Mr. Vojta Benes and superintendent of the "Liberal Schools" Mr. Veverka.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1120.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Toward evening the children had barely left when the halls began to become overcrowded again. The cabaret, especially, was filled to the last seat, although it demanded the patronage of the more well-to-do people. But our masses always represent every walk of life, and so there were to be seen our bankers, businessmen, architects, lawyers, physicians, artists, editors alongside of the small trader, workingman, etc. This spectacle filled everybody's heart with joy!</p>
   <p>All of the booths became gradually thronged with newcomers; the supplies were disappearing at a dangerous rate, while the satchels of the patriotic vendors were filled to an unexpected size. The more prosperous fellow-countrymen were of course bombarded from every side, and if they did not leave with their funds entirely depleted, it was not the fault of several hundred ladies who showed the utmost skill in selling their articles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1121.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was a gala day for the "Golden Book." Though there still was room enough for twice the signatures gathered, the total result is considered very good, as many could not gain entrance to the booth of the Czech National Association where the book was open to the generous visitors. Those who most deserve mention as propagators of these contributions are: Mrs. Psenka, Mr. J. J. Votava, Mr. Klima, and Mr. Vojta Benes.</p>
   <p>A separate and most abundant source of patriotic donations was the cabaret. Many of the tables were reserved (list given). Mr. John Cervenka, as on every other day, took upon his shoulders the strenuous work of an auctioneer and realized high prices for the precious and rare articles donated to the bazaar. There was only one who could vie with him in untiring efforts, Mrs. Cervenka who supervised the serving.</p>
   <p>The social and patriotic climax was reached when the orchestra intoned the <pb facs="5418478_2_1122.jpg" n="4"/>two anthems "Hej Slovane!" and "Kde Domov Muj?" Everybody joined in, including those who were born on this soil. The solemn feeling was instilled into the multitude by a speech extemporaneously delivered by Vojta Benes. The words are hard to repeat, but Benes related in his speech the following: "The thought of America, as coming to our aid, cannot leave our people. They all are asking themselves 'Will she come?' A poor man, carrier for a small labor sheet, came here the other day, laid down ten dollars for the good cause, and wrote his name in the "Golden Book." Now he sits in the booth of the C. N. J. and plays the gramophone all evening to the one tune: 'She will come.' On the birthday of the greatest Czech I want to ask those of the more prosperous class 'will she come?'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
