<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-04">Jan. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs Urged to Participate in Allied Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C (Slovak)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-04">Jan. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS URGED TO PARTICIPATE IN ALLIED BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a few days separate us from one of the greatest humanitarian social events. All of you have learned about the Allied bazaar, in which one division is reserved for the Czechs and Slovaks. In that affair, which is to be held in the Coliseum, we will stand in the limelight before a severe forum, in which we will be given the opportunity to demonstrate that we are a mature nation, that we Czechs and Slovaks of Chicago are one solid unit, and that our heart is in the right spot.</p>
   <p>Every Czech and Slovak ought to be supplied with tickets for his whole family by this time. This paper has taken care of their sale and it has otherwise fulfilled its duties by printing a long series of articles for <pb facs="5418478_2_1162.jpg" n="2"/>the sake of publicity for the bazaar. Will this bear fruit? Perhaps every reader of the Hlasatel has bought his ticket by this time; it often happens, however, that the date of the purchase is postponed and time for the advance sale passes. The price for the ticket is only twenty-five cents; it will be fifty cents shortly. Why then wait and pay twice as much when some persons are loath to part with half a dollar?</p>
   <p>In the bazaar there will be exhibited all sorts of weapons, airplanes Allied and German, a replica of an English village, even a Zeppelin, and many other objects worth inspecting.</p>
   <p>The bazaar will not limit itself to the exhibits mentioned; it will <pb facs="5418478_2_1163.jpg" n="3"/>contain articles of manufacture of a great number of countries, and the Czechs and Slovaks will occupy one big tent each. Visitors can make their day in the bazaar a memorable one by buying one of the beautiful souvenirs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
