<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-06">Oct. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs Do Their Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">Organize to Push Sale of War Bonds (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-06">Oct. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS DO THEIR DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Organize to Push Sale of War Bonds (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was a meeting held in the hall of the Lawndale National Bank, Lawndale and Turner Avenues, last night, in which some of our foremost Chicago Czech fellow citizens took part. An organization was formed to stimulate the sale of Liberty bonds and prove that Czechs are real American patriots, determined to see the United States victorious over the rabid Germans. The meeting was called by Anton J. Čermák who represents the Czechs in the committee composed of men of immigrant stock. This group will push the bond sales among the immigrants in Chicago. After Mr. Čermák's explanation of the purpose of the meeting, various committees were appointed. The executive committee consists of Joseph A. Holpuch, chairman, and Messrs. Karel Janovský, Rudolph Schlesinger, Otto Kerner, Frank Petru, Charles B. Pavlíček, Frank Adam, Christian R. Walleck, Joseph O. Kostner, V. Štepina, Joseph Uhlíř, judge of the municipal court, Joseph Triner, J. Adelman, John Jedlan, and Štorkan. The speakers' committee is 
<pb facs="5418478_2_0836.jpg" n="2"/>under the direction of Mr. W. K. Pflaum and Mr. Joseph Bolek. Messrs. John L. Novák and Joseph Jandu are heading the committee which is to urge our Czech aid societies and other monetary institutions to invest part of their funds in the Liberty Loan. Aldermen O. Kerner and John Toman are the directing minds of the committee which will approach Czech industrialists. The publicity committee is headed by Reverend V. Vanĕk, chairman, and Dr. Jar. F. Smetanka, secretary. Other members are A. J. Havránek for the Denní Hlasatel, Mr. Krásný for Svornost, Mr. Kraus for Národ, and Mr. Novak for Spravedlnost. A committee which is to work particularly on the South Side, in the district called Town of Lake, consists of Messrs. Charles Janovský, V. Čálek, and R. Schlesinger. Messrs. Štepina and F. G. Hájíček and their committee will work among bankers and their clients. Orders, lodges, clubs, aid and other societies will be addressed by members of a committee of which Joseph Šmejkal is the chairman and Frank Adam, secretary; other members are Mr. Pavlíček, Joseph Straka, V. Bašta, Dr. Pecival, Dr. Anton Mueller, and Anton J. Čermák. Czech shopkeepers will be visited by Messrs. Dvořák and Strauss and their committee. School children will be instructed in how to inform their parents about the advantages offered <pb facs="5418478_2_0837.jpg" n="3"/>by the Liberty Loan. This will be done by a committee consisting of Messrs. Uhlíř, Holpuch, Král, Nigrin, Luňák, Fučík, and Professor Jar. Zmrhal.</p>
   <p>A "flying squadron" of twelve men will be formed; this group will work from house to house. Only especially lively and energetic people should belong to this group, for a great deal depends upon their accomplishments. The campaign ends October 27, leaving only about three weeks to reach the quota.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
