<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-03">June 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Ammunition Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-03">June 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMMUNITION QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Germans are exerting pressure against the Government with the purpose of causing it to stop the export of arms and ammunition. The Government stands firm, however, for reasons already mentioned many times. One of them is the profit which American manufacturers make on the orders. But that is not so important as the principle involved in this matter. The Government must take the stand that such export is permissible and lawful because it is to our interest that it shall do so. The principle must be defended because we ourselves would be in need of supplies from abroad if we should become involved in a big war.</p>
   <p>This fact was revealed on the occasion of a recent investigation by a Congressional committee, in which General Crozier, head of the Ordnance Bureau, testified.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1346.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The report has not been published because the Government does not care to advertise matters of so far-reaching importance, but it is known that General Crozier presented a dismal picture of the disaster that would threaten us if the United States should become involved in war. Crozier recommended that 65,000,000 pounds of Chilean niter be stocked in the Government arsenals as necessary for the manufacture of powder. Niter is not found in this country, and we have no means of manufacturing it. Our army and navy use three million pounds of powder every year--rather more than that--and the accumulation of so large a stock of niter as that recommended by Crozier will take five years. Our situation with respect to arms is similar to that with respect to powder. We need imports of arms from abroad, and therefore we cannot subscribe to the principle that war materials must not be transported from one country to another.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
