<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">All Well-Meaning People Ought to Act</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_1566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ALL WELL-MEANING PEOPLE OUGHT TO ACT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Barbour proposal, if enacted, will prohibit the sale of liquor in public entertainments. The ensuing consequences for our social life may be easily predicted. In this issue we have called the attention of the public to this matter innumerable times. The Senate of the State of Illinois has already passed the measure, and the majority of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature favors it. The United Societies are leading a stubborn fight against this new insidious propaganda of frenzied prohibition fanatics. In order to assure success in the struggle, all societies and clubs which call themselves truly liberal-minded, and whose interests are at stake, ought to exert pressure upon their representatives and induce them to vote against the proposal. The secretaries of such associations who have not done so up to the present are urged to send (using a letterhead) the following letter to the respective legislators:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_1567.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Barbour Bill No. 281, which is now up for consideration by the House of Representatives is a superfluous measure as far as the regulation of the liquor traffic is concerned. It is a direct blow to the liberties so far enjoyed by organizations of a social character, and threatens their very existence.</p>
   <p>Our Society, an organization of....bona fide members, in existence since...., has always conducted their entertainments in an orderly manner as prescribed by the laws of the State, and we, therefore, ask you to lend your assistance to defeat the aforesaid legislation.</p>
   <p>The various societies are poor men's clubs, and should be encouraged rather than antagonized in their efforts to provide recreation and innocent pleasure for their members and their families.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
