<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-03-08">March 8, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">The Independents in the 8th Ward; the General Meeting of the Bohemians and the Germans; Vaclav Kaspar Nominated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-03-08">March 8, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">THE INDEPENDENTS IN THE 8TH WARD; THE GENERAL MEETING OF THE BOHEMIANS AND THE GERMANS; VACLAV KASPAR NOMINATED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting of the Bohemians and the Germans in Houdkov Hall was very largely attended, over 300 people were present. The Bohemian citizens appeared in large numbers.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by the chairmen of the Bohemian and German Clubs, M. Patera and Finkensieper. The first explained the purpose of this meeting. His speech was translated into the German language by J. Kralovec. A motion was then made to elect a chairman for the day who spoke both Bohemian and German. The motion was carried and Ad. B. Chladek was elected chairman, with Em. Haase and Lussem as secretaries. Another motion was carried that only members of the club had the right to vote at this meeting. There were enlisted at this meeting forty-five new members, the total number of members being raised in this way to 171 names. The result of yesterday's election was made public and read in German, then translated <pb facs="5418478_2_0307.jpg" n="2"/>by Ad. B. Chladek into Bohemian. It was decided that each of the candidates that were present be introduced to the audience which they were privileged to address. Vac. Kaspar was called to the rostrum.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar said, "Citizens, it is not the first time that my candidacy has been proposed by one or the other party or nationality, but I never have accepted the nomination, not because I liked to stand against the people's will, but simply that I decided not to go into politics. I would do the same now too, but the pressure exerted upon me this time by the citizens of this ward was so predominating that it is clear to me it is their most ardent wish. I have accepted the nomination this time. I will serve you, dear citizens, and promise to champion the platform which was presented to me before my nomination. I am not the kind of man who would fight to be nominated, and in case you should be able to find a more eligible candidate, I am ready to resign right now. And to agitate for him with all my influence." (Great applause.)</p>
   <p>The next speaker to be called was J. J. Kestler, who said: "He does not intend to accept the nomination, but he feels grateful and expressed his <pb facs="5418478_2_0308.jpg" n="3"/>thanks for the distinction with which the citizens honored him. He is out of town most of the time and it would be impossible for him to attend to the office duties punctually. (Applause.) He advised the citizens to nominate as candidate a man generally known and of honest character. He informed the citizens that in the 8th Ward a club of English-speaking citizens is in a stage of organization and it would be advisable to defer the nomination."</p>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar was of the opinion it would not do any harm to the cause.</p>
   <p>Mr. Clemens and Finkensieper defended the motion and informed the audience that they had no candidate at present. They suggested eight days delay to be able to find one.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kralovec protested and declared that the purpose of today's meeting was to select the mutual candidate, consequently he demanded that a candidate be selected immediately.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar admonishes the audience that only harmony could bring about <pb facs="5418478_2_0309.jpg" n="4"/>the desired results. He was ready to resign in case he should be the cause of some disagreement.</p>
   <p>Next spoke Mr. Lussem. He rebuked the Germans for their discord in very keen words and was absolutely against delaying the matter. It was his opinion that the German committee had as much time for the nomination of their candidate as did the Bohemians. (Applause.)</p>
   <p>"The Germans," Mr. Lussem then said, "were indolent, they refused to pay attention to the candidates proposed by Democrats or Republicans. If a new club was organized it would be useful for us, if its intentions were honest. Our mutual meeting of today was called for the purpose of nominating a candidate, therefore he should be nominated at once. I doubt whether it would be possible to find a more suitable candidate than Mr. Kaspar. If everyone should work to the best of his ability the whole enterprise would succeed."</p>
   <p>Mr. Kralovec then took the rostrum. He praised Mr. Kaspar and recounted <pb facs="5418478_2_0310.jpg" n="5"/>the benefits if he should be elected. Kaspar was the only man who could compete with Lawler. He made a motion to nominate Mr. Kaspar as the mutual candidate.</p>
   <p>P. Finkensieper proposed to defer the nomination for eight days. Mr. Clemens supported the proposal. Mr. Geringer was against it and stood firmly for an immediate nomination.</p>
   <p>Mr. Clemens was given the floor and said, "Citizens, the first meeting of the Bohemian Club was very weak and it is very surprising to observe today such a large number of Bohemians. My judgment is to delay the nomination to a date when the Germans will be present in a larger number."</p>
   <p>After long debate and many speeches pro and con, it was decided to nominate a candidate at once. Every member was to mark on the ballot the name of his candidate and his own name. The ballots were tabulated carefully. The result of the voting was as follows: Vaclav Kaspar, 129 votes; Kestler, 1; and Boehmer, 1.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0311.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar was called in and the result of the voting was announced to him. He expressed his thanks for the confidence and, in case of his election, he promised to do for the citizens all in his power to merit the expression of confidence of the members present. (Great applause.)</p>
   <p>The mutual committee will have its next meeting the coming Saturday in the American Sokol hall.</p>
   <p>The meeting adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
