<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">New Redivision of Wards</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_2_0076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_2_0076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NEW REDIVISION OF WARDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just recently a plan to divide our city into fifty wards was prepared by the election committee of the Chicago City Council and will be presented in today's Council meeting for approval. The result of this work shows plainly that the interest and wishes of our citizens were a last consideration. Ever since the beginning of the negotiations, it was apparent that the committee was primarily and exclusively interested in securing positions for certain aldermen by shaping their wards in such a way that they would be sure of reelection, and secondarily, they wanted to satisfy several of our city hall politicians. The wards were redivided, regardless of the wishes and wants of our citizens.....</p>
   <p>Citizens of our Tenth Ward will be among those who will be disappointed with this redivision, and they will surely be angry. The committee was expected to <pb facs="5418478_2_0077.jpg" n="2"/>recognize the Burlington and Quincy Railroad tracks as a natural boundary, and to create a new ward of parts of the Tenth and Twentieth Wards and probably also part of the Eleventh Ward. But this did not happen. Instead of such boundaries which would be recognized as just by anyone, the new ward will extend all the way to Polk Street, and on the west side only to Fisk Street. The result of this would be that our Tenth Ward would be torn to pieces and several of our Bohemian and Slovak precincts would be merged with Jewish or Italian districts on the north side of our ward. Also, the natural result of this would be that Bohemian voters of the present Tenth Ward would be left without representation in the City Council, and this old bulwark of Bohemian Democrats would cease to exist.</p>
   <p>Just how the Czechoslovak people of the Tenth and Twentieth Wards will feel about such a redivision can easily be anticipated. Czechoslovak people of the Tenth Ward should, without ceremony, give these politicians who are responsible for such redivision to understand that they are not pleased with everything which is prepared for them against their wishes. They should protest against <pb facs="5418478_2_0078.jpg" n="3"/>such heedless action.....</p>
   <p>Because we are familiar with the sentiment of our Tenth Ward citizens, we can assure those aldermen and politicians who are interested in such unjustified redivision of the Tenth Ward that a great disturbance will be aroused not only in the Tenth Ward, but all over Bohemian Chicago if this ward, which became the foundation of the political strength of the Bohemian element in Chicago, will be bartered away to other nationalities. Therefore, we most emphatically appeal to our Bohemian aldermen, regardless of what ward they represent, to take the necessary steps against any redivision of wards which is not just to the Bohemian voters. If these aldermen will not do this, then they will be called before the people's judgment; they will be questioned without mercy as to why thousands of Bohemian and Slovak voters should be deprived of representation in the City Council, and we are sure that those who betray the interests of our people will be adjudged accordingly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
