<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-05-02">May 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Amalgamated Center Opened Yesterday with Beautiful Ceremonies</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-05-02">May 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT AMALGAMATED CENTER OPENED YESTERDAY WITH BEAUTIFUL CEREMONIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two thousand members of the Amalgamated Clothing workers filled the Auditorium of the Amalgamated, yesterday afternoon, at the occasion of the official opening of the organized clothing workers own home.</p>
   <p>Sam Levin, the manager of the Amalgamated Joint Board introduced President Hillman, who in the name of the Chicago organization greeted all the members present with a very hearty welcome, in their own magnificent home, the Amalgamated Center.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0469.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This building is the accomplishment of the last 18 years, declared Hillman, since the foundation for this beautiful temple was laid and it is a challenge to all enemies and the greatest symbol to all friends of the amalgamated. The building is built not only of brick, lime, and cement, but of the will struggle, and devotion of the members who sacrificed themselves for their organization.</p>
   <p>President Hillman expressed the wish that the members will accept this center, not only as their home, but will make this their spiritual and cultural center by means of which to spread their ideals in the Amalgamated spirit to help all workers in their struggles.</p>
   <p>Alex Tchaikofski's Symphony orchestra played a few numbers, and Louisa Farnland sang romance of "Cavalaria Rusticana."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0470.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The crowd then went across the street to the big Ashland Auditorium, which was filled to capacity with members who came there to celebrate May the First.</p>
   <p>Sidney Rissman, assistant manager of the Joint Board opened the meeting announced the First of May as the labor holiday.</p>
   <p>Sidney Hillman, president of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers told of the strike in Milwaukee where eight hundred Amalgamated members are struggling for the right to be organized, but the bosses there will soon be convinced that they cannot break the Amalgamated, and will be forced to recognize the Union as all others have done who have previously tried to combat the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0471.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>John Fitzpatrick, president of the Chicago Federation of Labor, greeted the Amalgamated members in their new center. He stated that the American Federation of Labor is fighting for a shorter working week of 5 days, and when the workers will be able to produce the work in six hours, the workers will establish a six hour-day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
