<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-04-28">April 28, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-04-28">April 28, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Events in Our Movement.</p>
   <p>In the Jewish S. P. (Socialist Party), there is continual discussion going on concerning the issue of leftist and rightist. Are they organized factions? They have meetings prior to those of the regular branches, meetings in which they come to decisions on various issues and even appoint their spokesman for the evening. They also want a chairman who will favor their speakers. As a result there has developed a party within a party. Naturally, there is a great deal of heated discussions and debates between the leftists and rightists.</p>
   <p>The program of the leftists is brief. The Socialist Party should abolish all demands for immediate reforms, as well as all demands to improve the conditions of workers in accordance with the Socialist platform. In fact, the platform of the Socialist Party should consist of one short paragraph to the effect that the Socialists favor the destruction of the system and the establishment of a dictatorship of the proletariat.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1511.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is to be achieved, not through campaigns, nor elections, nor any political act, but only through mass action such as strikes conducted by the industrially Organized Workers of the World (I. W. W.). According to the leftists philosophy, we need neither wait for the majority of workers, nor hope to organize them politically, and certainly we can not hope to organize all the workers in industrial unions. This, they say, is opposed by the capitalists. What is needed, is a party that should preach revolution and dictatorship of the proletariat. Any minority group, can by mass action destroy the State, and place a Soviet Government in power. This, in short, is the philosophy of the leftists. Why do they complain? Why do they sabotage the Socialist Party, attack its tactics and platform and so seek new Gods? What do they want of the Party? If the Party is no good, the platform and the principles are also no good.</p>
   <p>A new platform must be created, a new platform and new parties; so why do they not organize a new party and leave the old party alone? But this does not satisfy the revolutionaries, for such a step requires energy. They want to create a dictatorship <pb facs="5423972_3_1512.jpg" n="3"/>in their own party and to force all who disagree with them to leave the party so that the leftists will be the Socialist Party. There is a great doubt as to whether they will be successful in carrying through this program.</p>
   <p>The main question however is whether the new Bible which leftists have adopted in so short a time is the true one which Socialists must accept?</p>
   <p>Those who do not lose their heads in stormy times, those who have definite opinions based on facts of life do not allow themselves to be misled without definite convincing arguments. The members of the Socialist Party, whom the leftists declare to be bourgeois and counter-revolutionary, forgive the leftists his attacks because they know that leftists ideas are untrue and based on empty phraseology.</p>
   <p>The old Comrades went through the same period of stress when the Socialist Party split from the S. L. P. and later on the split with the "Impossibles" who were practically the same as today's leftist revolunionary movement, although under <pb facs="5423972_3_1513.jpg" n="4"/>a different name.</p>
   <p>It is necessary however to analyze the claims of leftists and discover, if possible, any basis for their arguments.</p>
   <p>(Continued)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
