<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-29">July 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Dress Manufacturers Begin Negotiations for Settlement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-29">July 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DRESS MANUFACTURERS BEGIN NEGOTIATIONS FOR SETTLEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning, for the first time, representatives of the dress manufacturers' association met with representatives of the union at the Morrison Hotel, to negotiate the peace terms that would prevent the general strike planned by the Chicago dress industry.</p>
   <p>Two meetings were held; one in the morning, and one at noon. Present were lawyer Leo S. Lebaski, his partner, Fenington,and five delegates of the manufacturers' association, on the one hand; Mr. B. Schlessinger, lawyer Peter Sussman, and a union delegation of about twenty workers from various shops, on the other hand. To begin with, the conference busied itself with formulating definite rules for a settlement, and after listening to the general demands of the union, decided to give the association the opportunity to meet this morning, and then, in the evening, to meet again with the union <pb facs="5423972_3_0983.jpg" n="2"/>at the Morrison Hotel in order to reach a decision.</p>
   <p>One important decision that the conference has already arrived at, is an understanding that in case no agreement is reached on certain points at this meeting, the arguments will be referred to a board of arbitration before the strike is called.</p>
   <p>In their opening speeches, both Mr. Schlessinger and lawyer Lebaski expressed the desires of both parties to reach a peaceful understanding regarding all the demands of the union. Later Mr. Schlessinger pointed out, in broad terms, the principle demands of the workers which are:</p>
   <p>1. A forty-four hour work week.</p>
   <p>2. Preferential union shop.</p>
   <p>3. A salary increase of fifteen per cent for all piece workers and four dollars per week for week workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0984.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Also mentioned was the minimum salary: for cutters--$40 a week, drapers--$24 a week, sample makers--$32, examiners--$25, finishers--$18, pressers--$40, and steamfitters--$24 a week.</p>
   <p>The basis of the last agreement in Cleveland, which was settled with the aid of Federal Judge Julian W. Mack, was very frequently cited during the discussion. It appears that the manufacturers will be forced to sign the agreement.</p>
   <p>The committee which represents the newly formed Chicago Dress and Cloak manufacturers' Association, consisted of Herman Spivak, Charles Lowenthal, Mr. Grey and a member of the Doris Manufacturing Company. This committee will report to the association this morning, and at eight o'clock, will return to the conference. Lawyer Lebaski explained that about forty dress and skirt manufacturers belonged to this association. Waist manufacturers are considering joining.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0985.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>About twenty-eight Northwest Side manufacturers, organized in the United Ladies Garment Manufacturers Association, met yesterday at the office of Shulman, Shulman and Abrams, and elected J. Moll of the firm Moll and Coopersmith, as chairman, and A. Heller of Heller and Company, as secretary. S. Loterman, Harry Greenberg, J. Moll, and lawyer Max Shulman were elected as a committee to negotiate with the union. The committee will hold its first conference with Mr. Schlessinger today, at eleven o'clock in the morning, at the Sherman Hotel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
