<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-04-12">April 12, 1920</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-04-12">April 12, 1920</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many unions report their activities in the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The Horse Hair Dressers Union sent out a demand to their bosses, for a raise. The bosses are to answer today to a committee of the union.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Cloakmakers Union reported that the bosses tried to weaken the organisation by reorganizing the workers in their shops, and throwing the union men out of work, but thanks to the union, it did not materialize, so things are not bad.</p>
   <p>He also reported that the union is making preparations for the 20th Convention of the International, which will be held in Chicago on May 3rd.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the shoe-repairers reported that with the help of the union and the United Hebrew Trades, they were successful in obtaining a minimum of $40.00 a week, for the shoe repairers, and some are earning more.</p>
   <p>Mr. Miller, delegate and business agent for the Retail Furniture Salesmens Union <pb facs="5423972_3_0203.jpg" n="2"/>appealed at the meeting of the United Hebrew Trades, that all organizations should help them organize their trade by buying furniture only from stores where members of the union are employed. Mr. Miller pointed out two stores on South Halsted St. that are unionized, Goldenberg's and Harry Wolf's. All the others are unorganized. On the North Side, is Hartman's on Milwaukee Ave, where union clerks are employed.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Painters Union local 521 reported that his union appropiated $50.00 to help the women and children of the deported radicals.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Mattress Makers Union reported that the manufacturers signed an agreement with the union,and the workers gained a raise of $6.00 a week. He also reported that the strike at Schultz and Hirsch is still going on, that the International is financially helping this strike and that the Chicago Federation placed this firm on the unfair list.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Capmakers Union reported that their union is conducting a <pb facs="5423972_3_0204.jpg" n="3"/>strike at the Merit Cap Co. and that the union taxed every worker $1.00 a week to pay larger strike benefits to their strikers. He also invited a committee of the United Hebrew Trades, to represent the workers, at the May 1st celebration and meeting of the General Executive of the Cloth-hat and Capmakers Union of America, at the Douglas Park Auditorium.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Jewish type setters reported that the Jewish news dealers and the United Hebrew Trades were a great help in their last battle.</p>
   <p>The organizer of the laundry workers appealed to the United Hebrew Trades to help them in organizing the workers in the wet wash laundries of the West and Northwest Side. The organizer was assured that everything in the power of the United Hebrew Trades would be done.</p>
   <p>T. B. Simms and a committee of the Central Workers Defense League, appealed to the United Hebrew Trades for help in defending the convicted radicals. It was decided to give him a credential, recommending all unions to help in the defense of the radicals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
