<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-16">July 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Changing the Liturgic Poetry</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-16">July 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CHANGING THE LITURGIC POETRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent discoveries in the so-called trade union hold-ups caused considerable discussion in the general press and among scientific men of political economy. In fatherly love, in articles beginning with a moral confession that they are not only friendly but also devout counselors, publishers have finally come to the conclusion that workers should not permit themselves to be misled by their leaders. Whenever it comes to settling a matter between employers and employees, they (the workers) should heed the advice of impartial people who advocate peaceful arbitration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0385.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From scientific knowledge of political economy, the learned men know that every controversy between employees and employers is detrimental to the worker. Statisticians have, long ago, shown how much the workers lose in every strike even if they win. And even if we delve into large numbers, an ordinary man would come to the conclusion that, if it were not for the racketeers, (the labor leaders who declare a strike practically every other day), the workers would now be thousands or tens of thousands of dollars ahead, and - who knows, - perhaps they would be so rich by now that they wouldn't have to work at all for a livelihood.</p>
   <p>Recently, the "head professor" of political economy, our own Robert F. Hoxie of the University of Chicago, to which the great employer, John D. Rockefeller, gave $100,000,000, submitted an article to a scientific journal which is devoted to political economy and supported by <pb facs="5423972_3_0386.jpg" n="3"/>such lovers of science as Rockefeller and his equals, discussing what he calls "Hold-Up Unionism."</p>
   <p>According to the professor, hold-up unionism develops in great industrial centers where unions make a pretense of friendliness and preach brotherhood between capital and labor. But actually the workers are trampled under the feet of the leaders, and are under the rule of corrupt union bosses whom they cling to blindly, and these labor leaders sell out their "sheep" by making open arbitrations, with concealed threats, and by accepting bribes.</p>
   <p>The great professor does not mention that "hold-up" manufacturers' associations develop in great industrial centers where the large manufacturers wear friendly masks, and preach brotherhood between capital and labor. But behind the mask they seek to corrupt the workers, and <pb facs="5423972_3_0387.jpg" n="4"/>implant fear in them, of their leaders, so that the majority of workers will act like a flock of sheep without a shepherd. This is executed through open arbitration, with concealed threats, by giving bribes in form of the so-called reforms to workers.</p>
   <p>It would be better for both the employees and employers, if these Hoxie's - whose views on conditions come directly from the employer's standpoint-should instruct the employers in philosophy, instead of changing the liturgic poetry, and speaking to the workers whose interests they can not apprehend and whose psychology they can not grasp.</p>
   <p>Let the Gompers' and Mitchell's talk about "hold-up" unionism, and let the Hoxie's talk about "hold-up" bossism, and then they will be chanting the proper poetry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
