<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Community Stage</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Z. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE COMMUNITY STAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Z. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The teachers of the Moses Montefiore Talmud Torah School, who were on strike for higher salaries and recognition of the Hebrew Teachers' Union and the Geverkshoften (a united Hebrew alliance), have now returned to their jobs and are back teaching the children.</p>
   <p>They accepted from the Talmud Torah officials an agreement, signed for a year, which satisfies both groups. The Jewish public interested in the existence of the Talmud Torah will certainly be interested in the following paragraph of the agreement: "The above mentioned teachers have pledged not to join any union or organization which demands its objectives by means of strikes, whether it be a matter of earnings or one of education." Which means that the Union and Geverkshoften <pb facs="5423972_3_1028.jpg" n="2"/>will have no voice in this institution.</p>
   <p>In the other large Talmud Torahs, the teachers are back at their jobs. It appears that the backbone of the organization, which seeks to terrorize the Orthodox community in Chicago, has been completely broken. But we received a notification that in the Marks Nathan Orphan Home Talmud-Torah the two teachers, who are the instigators of all this trouble in the teachers institutions in this community, took advantage of the out-of-town absence of president Herron and superintendent Trotsky, to get into the Home and preach their teachings to the children under the auspices of their Union and Geverkshoft. They boast of possessing a contract for one year, and if ousted will sue the president and directors of the institution and thus receive their pay for twelve months.</p>
   <p>Inquiries by the directors revealed that none of them had given a <pb facs="5423972_3_1029.jpg" n="3"/>contract. Possibly the contract was secured, let us say, from a member of the board of education or from the assistant superintendent. In that case, it was an act put over on the institution, and the Orthodox Jewish community as a whole. This contract is not legal. It isn't worth a smell of tobacco, and the intruding teachers will have to leave their positions sooner than they expect.</p>
   <p>No true Jew or charitable organization in Chicago, will contribute a broken penny for a Talmud Torah which is in the hands of trouble makers, enemies of Orthodox Jewery, and oppossers of Jewish National ideas.</p>
   <p>Oust these union teachers from the Marks Nathan Orphan Home!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
