<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-05-12">May 12, 1923</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>FORWARD</title>,
<date when="1923-05-12">May 12, 1923</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arbitrators agree unanimously to raise the wages of the clothing workers, and organize an unemployment fund.</p>
   <p>Shop chairmen accept a resolution to approve the decision of the board of arbitration.</p>
   <p>Thousands of members of the Amalgamated Clothing workers of America met last night in four different halls. The cutters and trimmers met immediately after work at the Ashland Auditorium, and the other workers of the industry at the same hall in the evening, also in the Schoenhofen and Pilzen Halls. Sidney Ressman was the chairman. Hillman and Frank Rosenblum addressed the cutters and trimmers. Sam.Levin, Sidney Hillman and Stephen Skala addressed the other meetings. All the clothing workers approved the decision.</p>
   <p>Hillman pointed out, that the most important result was the raise in the wages obtained by the board of arbitration, to every one's satisfaction. He also pointed out that the unemployment fund which will dispose of the sufferings during the slack seasons from the <pb facs="5423972_3_0490.jpg" n="2"/>curse of unemployment, and will receive a part of their earnings when they will not be working.</p>
   <p>Joseph Schlossberg addresses the shop chairmen in regard to the unemployment insurance. Schlossberg congratulated the Amalgamated members, on their accomplishment in establishing an unemployment insurance fund.</p>
   <p>The workers can now rest assured that they will not starve in time of slack seasons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
