<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Election Campaign and the Jews</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION CAMPAIGN AND THE JEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great day of election is at hand. In a few days, the American people will decide which party and which person is to be at the head of this powerful republic for the next four years: the Democratic party, with Governor Cox at the head, or the Republican party, with Senator Harding. One's attitude toward one or the other party depends upon numerous factors: economic, political, moral, psychological, etc. Each group of citizens has its own motivating factor which influences its attitude toward the other candidate. We Jewish citizens must have our own position on the great problem which is to be decided on November 2.</p>
   <p>Again we must repeat, that first of all we go to the polls as American citizens, with the interests of America at heart. Regardless of how the <pb facs="5423972_3_1708.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish citizens vote--whether for Cox or Harding--they vote as American citizens for an American president. We must have a clear understanding on that fact, and the great American public must also understand that fact.</p>
   <p>No Republican will dispute the patriotism of Covernor Cox, and no Democrat will contest the patriotism of Senator Harding. We can, therefore, eliminate the question of Americanism so far as the election is concerned because it is not an issue. The Jewish voter must realize that both candidates are equal, so far as patriotism is concerned, and no matter whom he votes for, he will be voting as an American for an American, at an American election. Moreover, he has the right as well as the duty to familiarize himself with his own group interests and to ask: Which of the two candidates, who are both equally patriotic and healthy men, has a more developed sense of justice? Which is more liberal and which of them deserves my vote, not only as a patriotic citizen, but also as a liberal human being and a Jew? The voter also has a right to ask:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1709.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Which of the two parties is more liberal, which of the two parties is more generous, more willing to help, more philanthropic?</p>
   <p>These justifiable questions are answered by the following hard facts. Five years ago, the Democratic administration under President Wilson proposed Louis D. Brandeis for the position of Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States. The entire Democratic party, in this instance, backed the President, whereas the majority of the Republican Senators opposed the appointment of Brandeis and voted against his confirmation as Justice of the highest tribunal in the land. Among the Senators who voted against Louis D. Brandeis, was Senator Harding.</p>
   <p>We do not say that all the Republican Senators who voted against Brandeis, were anti-Semites, nor were they [necessarily] guided by an anti-Semitic motive. Furthermore, we do not know whether Senator Harding was guided in his action by anti-Semitic motives. Let us take it for granted that <pb facs="5423972_3_1710.jpg" n="4"/>Senator Harding's motives were not anti-Semitic, nevertheless, they certainly were reactionary, and if Senator Harding is not an anti-Semite, he is, at any rate, hardly a liberal. America has nothing to expect, the world has nothing to expect, and the Jews have nothing to expect from a reactionary president and a reactionary administration.</p>
   <p>In Ohio State, ninety per cent of all the Jews voted for Governor Cox, and only a small minority of the Jews voted for Harding. The Jews of Ohio know Governor Cox very well and all of them say that he is a thoroughgoing liberal and a true friend of the Jews. Of Harding, no one has yet dared to claim that he is a friend of the Jews. The fact is that Governor Cox is certainly as good an American and as great an American patriot as Senator Harding. Then why shouldn't the Jews vote for Governor Cox, who is known to be a friend of the Jews? Why should they vote for Senator Harding, who is a reactionary and is certainly no friend of the Jews?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1711.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Everybody is well aware of the work done by the Democratic administration in behalf of the Jews in the pogrom-and war-torn countries during the past eight years. The United States was the first country to send an investigating commission to Poland to find out the truth about the pogroms. The sending of the investigating commission alone was a slap in the face of Poland because the Poles have steadfastly denied the existence of pogroms.</p>
   <p>In 1915, President Wilson asked the State Department to issue an order to all American consuls in Poland, Lithuania, the Baltic provinces, and the Ukraine, to investigate the Jewish situation and to send in reports about the expulsion [of the Jews] and the pogroms. Then the Russian government heard about the order, it suggested to its governors and generals on the battlefields that they forbid any "Jewish scandals," i.e., no pogroms and no expulsions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1712.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Democratic administration helped the Jewish relief work and President Wilson issued a special proclamation to the American people with regard to a Jewish relief day. It is not President Wilson's fault that the Poles do not abide by the provisions of the Peace Treaty regarding Jewish [civil] rights. We have President Wilson to thank for the fact that these provisions regarding Jewish rights in Poland, Austria, Hungary, Rumania, and Jugoslavia, were inserted in the Peace Treaty. We have President Wilson to thank for the fact that the Jews of Rumania have finally been emancipated; Rumania abides by the Peace Treaty. What President Wilson has done for Zionism is known to all the Jews in America. If the Jews vote for Harding in this election, they will not only be helping reaction, but they will also appear to be very ungrateful. The Republicans will be the first ones to condemn us for our ingratitude. We, therefore, must vote for the Democratic candidate, Governor Cox, a friend of the Jews, as is President Wilson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
