<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-30">October 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Unions Are Appealing to All Jews of Chicago for Help</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-30">October 30, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNIONS ARE APPEALING TO ALL JEWS OF CHICAGO FOR HELP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strike of the men's tailoring trade which spread so rapidly in all parts of the city, in all probability will continue until they reach a victory. The demands of the strikers, for their rights as human beings, are without doubt right and just, and every right thinking, honest, sympathetic Jew, should not stand aside, but should extend a helping hand to the strikers, by gibing them financial aid in this fight, which is a fight to a finish. These Jewish strikers are struggling hard to win this fight and are depending on the Jews of Chicago to assist them financially until victory is assured. So you Jews in Chicago do not wait, help now, for now is the time when they need you.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1162.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We hope that the Chicago Jews will respond to this appeal and send in their contributions as soon as possible to these brave strikers. You may send your contributions to the main headquarters of the union, 275 La Salle Street, or the office of the Daily Jewish Courier.</p>
   <p>The Western Dairy Company notified the strikers of their willingness to contribute one thousand dollars to their fund. The dairy company is offering 50 cents for every new milk customer gotten up during the strike, in other words, they are satisfied and willing to contribute a thousand dollars for the strikers cause.</p>
   <p>The furniture house of B. Ginsberg &amp; Sons, 1242 Halsted Street, contributed 10 per cent of their last night's sales, which netted $11.75 for the strikers fund. This 10 per cent offer will be repeated tomorrow, Monday. So if anyone wishes to buy furniture please hurry and make his purchase at once, so that the strikers will derive the benefit of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1163.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A very interesting plan was formulated by some of the strike sympathizers. Who is to have the honor of carrying contributions to the Jewish Courier? This honor was sold to the highest bidder, who bid $10.00. The amount of the contributions was $18.00 which was taken in at a celebration of a newly born baby boy on the 8th day of his birth. The celebration was given by Mr. Kopel Gordon, the father of the new-born babe. There were lots of bidders for this honor and as Mr. Rosenbloom was the highest bidder, he was the winner of the honor of carrying the contributions to the Jewish Courier for the strikers' fund.</p>
   <p>Another similar celebration was held at the house of M. Kominski, he being one of the strikers himself suggested this plan and eleven of those who were at the celebration made some very liberal bids for this honor. Even the bosses of the tailoring trade in many shops are also out on this strike, they are too, very busy collecting funds for the strikers, although some of the bosses do not show how they feel about the strike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1164.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Nevertheless you can easily detect which way their sympathy turns. Mr. J. Landerman brought in $5.00 to the Jewish Courier which the collected at the Jefferson business association. Mr. Harry Feldman, owner of a small newspaper stand, brought in $1.00.</p>
   <p>At the conference of the Jewish radicals organizations which was held last Friday evening, it was decided to hold a house-to-house collection to start next Sunday. This organization also sent a representative to New York for the purpose of gathering funds for the Chicago tailor strikers. A big undertaking November 6th, the United Garment workers have decided to take the Lyric Theater on the 6th of November for a benefit theater for the strikers. Mr. Jacob E. Smith of Hirsch Wikwires shop and Mr. Max Ellison of Spitz, enberg &amp; Bros., have been appointed as a committee to solicit advertisements for the program of that evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1165.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Jewish business people will greatly benefit by advertising in this theater benefit program, and at the same time the strikers will derive much benefit of it.</p>
   <p>The strikers are receiving numerous liberal contributions from all sides. The Painters Union with its 9,000 members has pledged everything that all other unions have. The strike committee paid out large sums of cash to the needy. On account of the cold weather, the needs were more than usual, hence the committee had to distribute more funds among the strikers.</p>
   <p>The appeal of the union of the Jewish public of Chicago through the columns of the Jewish Daily Courier, will no doubt bring good results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
