<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-03-19">March 19, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-03-19">March 19, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Tailors on the Threshold of a General Strike.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated Executive gave $1,000 towards this general strike.</p>
   <p>The ready-made clothing manufacturers are taking unfair steps which will only serve to encourage the workers to strike. They discharge active union members, they reject shop committees, who in the name of their organized workers, wish to confer with them, they show autocratic spirits, which many hundreds have sacrificed their lives to combat.</p>
   <p>The workers of Cohn and Riseman, Edheimer and Stein, Alfred Decker and Cohn, Oxford Tailoring Co., Altchuler and Dryer, Lambs and Kuppenheimer's shop, of the Southwest Side, are preparing to strike. The shop of Riseman and Cohn broke their agreement, just recently signed, but this time the union will secure assurance that the victory will be a positive one. The union demands of this firm, now, are a 20 per cent raise for all piece workers, a $4.00 a week raise for week workers, time and one-half for overtime, recognition of the union and the discontinuance of sub-contracting. At Edheimer and Stein, workers were discharged because they are members of the union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0274.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The union demands at Dabi Rosenthal are a 15 per cent raise in salary, likewise at Altchuler and Dryer and at the Oxford Tailors. If the committee of Lamb's tailors, who were sent to Mr. Lamb, does not bring back a satisfactory answer, the tailors will meet with the pocket-makers. The Amalgamated clothing workers are undertaking to fight this battle and assure all the rights and privileges for the Chicago tailors that they have won for the 60,000 tailors of New York, Rochester, Baltimore, Boston and many other cities. The General Executive of the Amalgamated, who have their assemblies here in Chicago, realizing the poor condition of the Chicago tailor, have taken it upon themselves, to make Chicago, as Wilson would say, a decent place for the tailors to live. The General Executive have, at their last meeting agreed to help these strikers with $1,000.00.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow night at the mass meeting of the striking tailors, in the Carmen's Hall, Sidney Hillman, Secretary Schlossberg, John Fitzpatrick, Duncan McDonald, Seymour Steadman, V. E. Cunea and others will speak on what the Amalgamated will do for the Chicago tailors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
