<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-04">Mar. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Injunction against Striking Dressmakers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0802</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0802.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-04">Mar. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">INJUNCTION AGAINST STRIKING DRESSMAKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two small manufacturers' associations yesterday obtained injunctions prohibiting the union as an entity, and the strikers as individuals, from picketing the shops. The injunctions were issued by Judges Sullivan and Paul. The Judges, however, granted the union a hearing concerning a recall of the injunctions. The hearing will take place this morning.</p>
   <p>The second week of the dressmakers' strike opens today, and it looks as though both sides are resolved to fight to the end. Neither of the two sides wants to come to an understanding with the other. The union stands fast by its demands and the manufacturers refuse even to listen to those demands. Meyer Perlstein, leader of the strike, declared yesterday that the union is ready to arbitrate, but the manufacturers ignored his statement. Mr. Perlstein also declared that the sole aim of the manufacturers is to break the union, and that the strike will, therefore, go on until the bosses realize that this is impossible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0803.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yesterday was not a quiet day. Many strikers, mostly girls, were arrested. All were freed on four-hundred-dollar bonds. The following were arrested: Goldie Tesel, Marion Michel, Dorothy Schuchman, Lena Moritz, Rose Luxenberg, Minnie Wiltbaum, Bessie Finkelstein, Leb Green, Benjamin Silver, and Sidney Weiner.</p>
   <p>Marie Shusky of 1531 Haddon Avenue was arrested after a fight between her and Mae Drihoi, of 1847 South 49th Avenue.</p>
   <p>Martin S. Gordon of 4640 North Monticello Avenue, an attorney, was arrested yesterday on Adams Street. He was released on bail at the Clark Street police station. Mr. Gordon did not have anything to do with the strike, according to his statement. He was just walking through the strike district when a policeman, without any cause whatever, arrested him as a picket. He now threatens to sue the city for false arrest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
