<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1919-12-22">December 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Schochetim (Slaughterer of Animals) and Butchers Unite</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1919-12-22">December 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOCHETIM (SLAUGHTERER OF ANIMALS) AND BUTCHERS UNITE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Did you ever dream of a schochet being a worker? That he has connections with workers? No one would believe that a time would come when a schochet could be found seated at a desk wearing a skull cap, recording the minutes of a meeting and acting as secretary of a labor union.</p>
   <p>It is, however, true. The Schochetim of Chicago have organized, and are good union men. Why should they not be? Are they not considered by their bosses in the same category as workers? Are they treated differently than workers?</p>
   <p>Does the boss have any more respect for the schochet's bread, for his education, for his skill, than for the butcher workers?</p>
   <p>From what is heard, the schochet is exploited as much as any other worker. They must dress the chickens, and do not have a regulated working period. The schochet became an ordinary worker, with the difference, that other workers have already gained better conditions and he must begin his struggle now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0211.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nevertheless, there are signs signifying that the schochets of Chicago will be on par with other workers in a short time.</p>
   <p>Since the butcher workers of Local #598 are organized, the business agent, Comrade Atkin, will not rest until every schochet becomes a member of Local #598.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
