<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-10">Mar. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Workers' Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-10">Mar. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS' GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Four months have elapsed since the United Hebrew Trades is in existence in Chicago, and upon underscoring the total amount of its activity, the net results are none too brilliant.</p>
   <p>As we have already mentioned in previous articles, the reason for this can be attributed to the Jewish unions in Chicago, which take very little interest in the existence and activity of the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The necessity of such a body is inestimable. Yet, we must have a profound knowledge of how to run such a body in order to attain desirable results. Unfortunately, the Jewish unions in Chicago do not know how an organization like the United Hebrew Trades should be run.</p>
   <p>Three essential things must be remembered, if the United Hebrew Trades is <pb facs="5423972_3_0391.jpg" n="2"/>to be crowned with success. First, the unions must pay their capitation tax regularly to the United Hebrew Trades, so that there will be enough money on hand to function properly. Second, the unions should have a clause on the agenda pertaining to the United Hebrew Trades. They should also act on the reports submitted by their delegates and determine the value of such recommendations as may be made by their delegates. Third, the most important thing is to elect delegates who are loyal and conscientious trades-union men. The United Hebrew Trades' meetings should, especially, be attended regularly. And one more thing: delegates should be elected for a period of no less than six months.</p>
   <p>If the above suggestions are adopted, the United Hebrew Trades in Chicago will encounter great success, owing to the vast amount of work to be done in both the already existing unionized trades and in the trades which are not as yet organized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
