<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-09">April 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Amalgamated</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Meyer Kaufman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-09">April 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE AMALGAMATED</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Meyer Kaufman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We printed in the Courier last week a notice about a protest and complaint which a group of tailors from the Ederheimer and Stein's shop made to a representative of the Courier against their shop chairman and business agent, accusing them of misrepresenting the economic interests of the tailors and violating the rights of the workers by terrorizing them for daring to protest.</p>
   <p>The representative of the Courier saw Mr. S. Levin, manager of the Joint Board, and spoke to him about this affair. The Courier representative asked him what he thought about that complaint. Mr. Levin stated that he was not in a position, due to certain organizational matters, to discuss this question in a newspaper. He was certain, however, that this affair would be investigated by him and that the guilty ones would be punished if the accusation against them is substantiated by facts which the tailors will produce at <pb facs="5423972_3_0069.jpg" n="2"/>the local meeting. Mr. Levin also stated that he would investigate the terroristic activities and persecutions of the chairman of Ederheimer and Stein's shop against the tailors who do not agree with his organizational work.</p>
   <p>Mr. Levin also stated that he appreciated the services which the Courier rendered the Amalgamated when the latter fought for its existence and needed help. The Courier helped the Amalgamated at the time when no other newspaper in Chicago was doing it. The Amalgamated will never forget it and it is always willing to recognize and appreciate it.</p>
   <p>Here are some more facts about the shop chairman of Ederheimer and Stein's shop, who gained such sad notoriety. It became known last week in the tailoring industry that he, who is under the control of the Amalgamated, conducted terroristic activity against the members of his organization and brother workers because they were not in agreement with his machine. This is not in accordance with true trade union principles of any working class <pb facs="5423972_3_0070.jpg" n="3"/>organization, particularly of the Amalgamated. As soon as the chairman learns that this or that group of workers watches his administrative activity and dares to protest against his actions, he resorts to the use of crooked means against his brother workers and to persecute them.</p>
   <p>It seems, however, that his reign will not last long. The eyes of the workers are opened. There is no doubt that the responsible leaders of the Amalgamated will not permit a situation to exist which hurts the interests of a strong and mighty labor organization which has been built up by such heroism and sacrifice. The acts of the leaders in this affair will also be a warning to others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
