<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Doing in the United Hebrew Trades</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS DOING IN THE UNITED HEBREW TRADES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee from the Jewish Shoe Fitters Club asked the Federation to help them in their demands for the hiring of Jewish shoe fitters in departments where only girls are employed. The Federation determined that the Executive Board should deal with the question and make an investigation. Also, it would see the Boot and Shoe Workers Union in regard to the matter.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of the banquet in honor of Comrade Hanock, reports that the occasion will be a success. Many union delegates and individuals have already reserved plates for the banquet which will be given at Rosenthal's restaurant, Saturday night.</p>
   <p>Delegates - Report of Their Organizations.</p>
   <p>Delegates of the Cleaners and Dyers Union report, that in their struggle to organize the inside workers of the cleaning and dyeing plants,- one firm, D.S. Toirh Cleaners and Dyers, started a <pb facs="5423972_3_0100.jpg" n="2"/>campaign against the Union.</p>
   <p>At first, the States Attorney raided the office and arrested the Secretary of the local, then they indicted six officials of the Cleaners and Dyers and Drivers Union.</p>
   <p>The reason of this indictment is because the Drivers Union, works hand in hand with the Cleaners and Dyers Union to organize the trade, and the bosses are very much dissatisfied with the work of the Unions.</p>
   <p>The delegates of the Jewish Type-Setters Union reported that the Illinois Federation of Labor has adopted a resolution to thank the Forward, for the wonderful conditions the type-setters have in the Forward plant. The Jewish Type-setters receive the highest pay,- $60.00 a week for six hours a day, and time and one half for overtime. The Illinois State Federation of Labor at its last convention, accepted the thanks of the Forward.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0101.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Painter's Union, local 521, reported that the biggest contractors were breaking away from the Landis Citizen Committee, and signing agreements with the Painters District Council. The conditions are better than they have been.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Shochtim Union stated that on Maxwell Street, four non-union Shochtim are working in non-union shops. He asked that the workers bear in mind that unionism comes first, and that it is important to help the Shochtim keep up union conditions in their places of employment.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Amalgamated Cigar Makers Union reported that they have started an organization campaign among the unorganized shops, and the work will bring good results in time.</p>
   <p>The Bakers Union, local 237, elected a new Secretary, brother Masler, and the union is going on with the task of watching the working conditions in bakeries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0102.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The delegate of the Cloak Makers locals, reported that their trade is going through a crisis, that the season was very short, and in order to help the workers over the time of crisis, all the locals set up a relief fund.</p>
   <p>The Theater Committee of the United Hebrew Trades, with the Butcher Worker's Union, reported that the Executive Board determined large unions should be visited, with tickets to be sold for a benefit. Committees have promised to visit the larger unions, through the week, sell tickets for the benefit and help in every way to make their affair a success. It will be held Monday night, at the Palace Theater.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
