<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-24">May 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">International Will Call Chicago Dressmakers on Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-24">May 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">INTERNATIONAL WILL CALL CHICAGO DRESSMAKERS ON STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Meyer Pearlstein, vice-president and general organizer of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union of America, issued a statement yesterday in which he points to the deplorable conditions in dress shops and threatens a strike by all dressmakers if the manufacturers do not yield to the demands of the union.</p>
   <p>"We have called the dress manufacturers to a conference concerning the abnormal conditions existing in the trade, but they have ignored us, thinking that they will succeed in restraining the International from organizing the shops. We have sent out committees to distribute circulars to nonunion workers, but the bosses called the police and had our committees arrested," said Pearlstein.</p>
   <p>He also said that "about five thousand workers, mostly women, are employed <pb facs="5423972_3_0835.jpg" n="2"/>in sweat shops on the piece system, which makes it impossible for them to earn more than fifteen dollars a week. We proposed to the manufacturers that our disputes be submitted to an arbitration board consisting of three persons whose decision shall be binding for both parties, but they did not even answer us. Thus, the only thing that remains for us to do is to strike."</p>
   <p>The Joint Board of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union in Chicago is carrying on a campaign to organize the dress workers who are not under union control. For this purpose, shop meetings are held after working hours in the union office, 180 Washington Street, and during lunch hour circulars are distributed around the dress shop area.</p>
   <p>Several dress manufacturers who do not wish to see their workers organized have turned to the police department, asking it not to permit union men to distribute leaflets to the workers, and the police, obedient to the bosses, are hindering the organizational work of the Joint Board. Many active <pb facs="5423972_3_0836.jpg" n="3"/>members of the International were arrested by police on disorderly conduct charges, but were immediately released on bail put up by Attorney Peter Sussman.</p>
   <p>Miss Jenny Schwartz was arrested twice yesterday for distributing leaflets on the streets. Miss Schwartz said, in the Clark Street Police Station, that the arrests will not deter her from performing her duty as a member of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
