<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-02">Mar. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Blessing of Union Bread</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-02">Mar. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE BLESSING OF UNION BREAD</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If one should attempt, in the future, to write a history of Jewish immigration into America, one would certainly not skip the wonderful records of the Jewish Bakers' Unions. It was accepted even in the old country that baking was one of the hardest and most unhealthful trades.</p>
   <p>We still recall the filthy bakeries kept in the dark, damp basements in the old country. The baker worked day and night, and into each loaf of bread he baked, he kneaded his sweat and his sorrows.</p>
   <p>The Jewish bakeries in America were not any better than those in Europe, in the early days. Wherever there was a dark, damp basement, there was a bake shop. The workers were literally slaves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There were no definite working hours, nor were there living wages. The boss could do almost anything with his employee that he wished. There were more consumptives among bakers than among any other workers.</p>
   <p>From this darkness, from this slavery, grew up in almost every American city Jewish Baker Unions, which have revolutionized the bakers' trade completely. The baker got more suitable working hours, better wages, - enough to make a respectable living for himself and his family. Baker bosses were forced to keep their shops more sanitary and also to improve the ventilation.</p>
   <p>The bread that was now produced by Jewish bakers no longer contained dirt and sweat as in the slavery days. The Yiddish Bakers' Union not only saved its members from consumption, but also made it possible for the public to eat more sanitary and more wholesome bread.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0047.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When the Jewish Baker Union became stronger there was not a labor movement in which it did not participate. It always responded warmly and enthusiastically to the call of oppressed workers. The Jewish Baker Unions all over the country were always among the first to assist with any work possible to make the world a better and more just place in which to live.</p>
   <p>In the past two years when times became worse, gigantic bakeries were opened which hired non-union workers for smaller wages, and so competed with the union bakeries. The union then treated its members justly, and divided the work equally among them in order to eliminate unemployment. Because of the union's fairness towards its members, one ought to realize how important it is to help the union. Each pound of bread bought from the non-union bakers, is helping to destroy the union as well as to take away the means of existence of hundreds of Jewish families, who have succeeded only through long years of struggle and sacrifice in reaching a better living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0048.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every time a union worker loses a day's work, it only helps to strengthen the non-union bakeries. Not only should union and other workers buy union bread, but the Jewish public in general should patronize union bakeries only, in order that the Jewish baker union may be able to keep up and the union workers may not be forced back into the sweat shops under slavish and inhuman conditions.</p>
   <p>We are here appealing principally to the ladies, because women understand what happens when their husbands are without work, or when they get only a few days work that is not enough to make a living.</p>
   <p>Ladies! Please have sympathy and understanding with the wives of the bakers. Buy bread with the union label. Urge your children, friends, and neighbors to do likewise. Please see that bread, which is the foundation of life, and gives us health and happiness, is not the cause of misfortune, poverty, and slavery for your fellow workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
