<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-19">June 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Tailors Must Fight for Democracy in the Shops</title><title level="a" type="sub">Says Sidney Hillman at the Huge Mass Meeting Last Night in the West Side Auditorium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0731</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0731.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-19">June 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TAILORS MUST FIGHT FOR DEMOCRACY IN THE SHOPS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Says Sidney Hillman at the Huge Mass Meeting Last Night in the West Side Auditorium</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The large hall of the West Side Auditorium was packed last night with clothing workers who came to hear Sidney Hillman, president of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union, as well as other officers. They spoke of the danger that threatens the Chicago tailors, especially those working in uniform factories, if they permit the manufacturers to have their way and do not organize. The employers, under the guise of patriotism, are gradually introducing autocracy into the shops, while our sons and brothers are shedding their blood on the battlefields of France for world democracy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hillman was greeted with a tremendous ovation. In his speech, Hillman deplored the fact that the clothing industry in Chicago is not strongly organized and that the manufacturers exploit their workers in a most horrible fashion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0732.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speaker also pointed out that in New York and in other cities, the tailors, through the Amalgamated, all have succeeded in obtaining humane [working] conditions and good wages. Whereas in Chicago we find that many uniform manufacturers send away old experienced workers, and in their place employ people from the street who have never held a needle in their hands, whom they pay from eight to ten dollars a week--the result being that the army of unemployed is growing larger every day. And if these conditions continue, every tailor is in danger of being thrown out of work. This year there will undoubtedly be a slack season in civilian work because the government has already ordered twenty million uniforms.</p>
   <p>But the Amalgamated, said Mr. Hillman, will under no circumstances permit the tailors to be reduced to such a state. The workers themselves, however, must give their support by joining the unions in order to show strong resistance to the unpatriotic bosses. "Since our boys are giving up their lives in France for the sake of Democracy, the workers in our country must therefore fight for <pb facs="5423972_3_0733.jpg" n="3"/>Democracy in the shops."</p>
   <p>In answer to this appeal to join the union, approximately four hundred people registered as members. Besides Mr. Hillman, other speakers included Frank Rosenbloom, who is leaving for Camp Grant, Samuel Levin, and others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
