<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-11">Nov. 11, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-11">Nov. 11, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>M. Wiseman</p>
   <p>1219 N. Paulina St.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Cigar Makers' Union last week called on strike 45 workers of the Spector Bros. Cigar Manufacturers. While it is true that the number of strikers are few, yet the effect on the cigar makers trade in Chicago is not to be overlooked.</p>
   <p>Several shops being controlled by the Cigar Makers' Union were won through strikes. The Spector Bros. has always stood as a fortress which the cigar makers lacked sufficient courage to enter. But finally they have risen to the occasion and have stormed the fortress that stood between them and Spector Bros. A strike was called in which the workers to a man went out to strike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1129.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman of the strike committee, Mr. Philip Raush, one of the intelligent Jewish workers in Chicago, assured us in his speech that the strike would positively be won, since it must under all circumstances be won. The union will exert all its forces for this purpose because all other cigar manufacturers, as well as all other cigar makers regard this strike with singular impatience. If we win, it means that in a short time we will control the entire cigar trade. If not, we lose the cigar trade for the union.</p>
   <p>The demands are: higher wages, sanitary shops, and recognition of the union. The strike is mainly conducted under union discipline. All indications point to an early victory.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1130.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And now that the local Arbeiter-Ring Branches have arranged lectures in the Intelligent Club, a good place to sleep in, we must consider that workman, slaving in sweat shops, in need of decent wages, more air, light and improved conditions, and contracts from bosses and foremen, will be unable to reach this height, much as they would like to have knowledge, culture and philosophy.</p>
   <p>This is an error that can be easily corrected by the committee that arranges these lectures. It is necessarily important that the members of the Arbeiter Ring understand "The Importance of Union Organization," "The Principles of Trade Unionism," "The Political Conditions in this Country," "The Jewish National Question in all its phases," etc. There are many lecturers for these themes and the results would reflect much respect and honor on the Arbeiter Ring.</p>
   <p>Shuchet Ben Harev.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
