<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-29">Mar. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Our Destructive Forces</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-29">Mar. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DESTRUCTIVE FORCES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his address before the Jewish War-Relief Society at the Ashland Clubhouse in Chicago, Mr. Isaac Don Levine, the well-known foreign correspondent of the Chicago Daily News, said among other things: "In addition, the Jewish businessmen suffer from the Jewish Bolsheviks, who are worse than the Russian, [that is] the Gentile communists. The Jewish communists oppress the Jew a thousand times more than the Gentile communists do. This is a fact, and I, for one, [testify to it] even though I came out with the belief that Bolshevik Russia will remain Bolshevik Russia, and the men who are now in power will remain in power. I, for one, have brought out with me a very definite feeling of hostility toward the Jewish communists. I am not speaking of people like Trotsky, who have nothing to do with the Jews. I am speaking of the Jewish communists who are responsible for the law forbidding the teaching of Hebrew, who point to the Zionists as Allied agents, and tell stories about the Zionists suppressing the Egyptian revolution, and call for their arrest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jewish communists are more severe than Lunacharsky, who is a Gentile, and is commissioner of education. Lunacharsky has no objection to the teaching of Hebrew, because the Soviet law says that any group of twenty-five parents may have any language taught to their children that they desire. But the Jewish Bolshevik says Yiddish is the Jewish language and that only Yiddish shall be taught; the majority of the Jews, however, want some sort of a Hebrew education given to their children. Jewish Bolshevism is a deep wound in the Jewish body of Russia."</p>
   <p>If it were not for the fact that Mr. Levine comes from Russia and brings a first-hand report of Russian-Jewish conditions, one might think that he was not describing the Jewish communists in Russia but a certain type of Jewish radical in this country. What is true of the so-called Jewish communist commissars in Russia, namely, that they are more anti-Semitic than many Gentiles, that they are narrow-minded, greedy, immoral, corrupt, conceited, and ignorant, is also true of our pseudo-socialist radicals in this country, and for this reason, there is a sympathetic understanding between these two <pb facs="5423972_3_1472.jpg" n="3"/>groups of scoundrels. That they are men of principle and that they are communists because they believe in communism is to ascribe to them virtues that they do not possess. They are neither communists nor socialists, nor do they suffer from any other "ism;" if they are anything, they are parasites and dishonest parasites at that. They are not only lazy--they are capable of every infamy to keep themselves in circulation and to continue their parasitic life, and neither socialism nor any other "ism" can be wholly responsible for their scandalous misdeeds.</p>
   <p>While we hold no brief for Bolshevism because we do not believe in dictatorship by one class or another, we cannot conscientiously say that Bolshevism in Russia is responsible for our human scum. The true Bolshevik is all wrong in his conception of the state and society, and often holds crazy notions on economics and politics, but there is some method in his madness; but the so-called Jewish communists in Russia, who harrass the Jewish masses and persecute them more than the former officials of the Czar did, are just like their pseudo-socialist colleagues in this country--they are unprincipled, egoistic, <pb facs="5423972_3_1473.jpg" n="4"/>and only out for their own personal advantage.</p>
   <p>Mr. Isaac Don Levine does not exaggerate when he says that these Jewish Bolsheviks are a deep wound in the body of Russia, but we want to add that the Jewish pseudo socialists in this country, although they may not be as numerous as they are in Russia, are also a cancer on the body of American Israel, and it is a pity that many American-Jewish leaders deem it expedient to make political deals with these rascals and to help them exercise a certain influence upon the masses.</p>
   <p>Russian Jewry is helpless and cannot do anything against their parasitic oppressors, but American Jewry is strong and powerful and can rid itself of this plague if it once comes to realize that it constitutes a real menace to American Jewry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
