<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-28">Apr. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">No Jewish Bread on the West Side</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-28">Apr. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NO JEWISH BREAD ON THE WEST SIDE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish master bakers of the West Side are not willing to comply with demands of the Bakers' Union, and three hundred Jewish bakers have declared a strike.</p>
   <p>The Jewish public on the West Side being accustomed to eating pumpernickel rye bread and Jewish bread in general, had to suffer the pinch of hunger this morning, and the Jewish grocery stores lost their bread sales, all of which is due to this strike.</p>
   <p>There is plenty of Jewish bread on the Northwest Side, because the Jewish master bakers in that part of the city have settled with the bakers union. Anyone insisting on Jewish bread may run across town to Milwaukee Avenue and indulge in any kind of food his heart may desire.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1110.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many Jewish people who understand this bread problem are of the opinion that the strike will not last long. However, this is up to, and entirely in the hands of the master bakers. Just as soon as they sign the agreement with the union, so soon will the strike end. But this is not the reason why they refuse to sign with the union. It is not a matter of certain points in the agreement to which they object. It is only the desire to starve out the Jewish public and to make it appear as though the union were at fault. Then they could raise the price of bread. But as a matter of fact, the union representing its members does not demand higher wages or shorter hours. These will remain the same. So the public can readily see that the strike is not the fault of the union, but it is that of the master bakers who desire to raise the price of bread.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
