<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-09">March 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Report of Territorial Conference of the Workmen's Circle</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-09">March 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE REPORT OF TERRITORIAL CONFERENCE OF THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friend J. Kravitz, chairman of the District Organizational Committee, opened the meeting of the Chicago Territorial Conference, Sunday, March 3, at 2 P. M. in the Palace Hall, 1145 Blue Island Avenue.</p>
   <p>After declaring that the purpose of this meeting is to discuss recommendations to the 18th Annual Convention of the Workmen's Circle, and also to nominate 14 delegates as candidates to this convention, he asked for a temporary chairman before the election. Friend Benenson, of branch #162, was unanimously elected as temporary chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman, Friend L. Benenson, called upon Dr. S. D. Spivak, secretary of the sanitarium of the Jewish Consumptive Relief Society, to state his object. He said that the sanitarium of which he is one of the directors, was founded by the consumptive workers; that this institution is of and for the working masses; and that it is not in the hands of the so-called rich contributors. He further said that a general convention will take place in Chicago, May 24, called by the organization which he represents. He expressed his wish that we, as a branch of the labor movement and, also as one of the strongest organizations of the Chicago Jewry, will be represented at this convention through every branch in the city. We agreed to the request and</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1546.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>the delegates promise to introduce the question before their respective branch.</p>
   <p>The Credential Committee reported that of the 42 branches in our district, 35 were represented; that 40 delegates were present; and that the District Organizations Committee is also represented by Friends Kravitz and Levin.</p>
   <p>The following recommendations were proposed at the conference to be recommended to the 18th Annual Convention:</p>
   <p>1. Concerning the clause of the Constitution which does not permit any police, detectives, and saloon keepers to become members in the Workmen's Circle, shall also include hotel proprietors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1547.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. Friend Silverstein proposed that the clause that makes it impossible to appeal to the grievance committee against a charge, which was dismissed by a branch should be abolished in order to have a democratic organization.</p>
   <p>3. The one per cent admission fees shall be abolished.</p>
   <p>4. The educational committee shall send capable lecturers throughout the country.</p>
   <p>5. The cities, with the exception of New York, shall get better educational programs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1548.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>6. The Friend shall be published weekly instead of daily.</p>
   <p>7. The Workmen's Circle shall adopt a better position toward radical schools.</p>
   <p>8. Two or three pages of the Friend shall be published in English.</p>
   <p>9. A special fund shall be set aside to organize English speaking branches.</p>
   <p>10. The general office shall employ two paid officials in every large city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1549.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>11. The Friend shall have more literary reading material in lieu of the present general, specific, and abstract Workmen's Circle news.</p>
   <p>12. The Friend's mailing list shall be improved.</p>
   <p>13. Each important city shall have one paid hospital.</p>
   <p>14. The educational committee shall establish classes in citizenship.</p>
   <p>15. Hospitals and dispensaries shall be established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1550.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>16. A special fund shall be set aside to help build labor lyceums.</p>
   <p>17. Expelled workers shall be accepted by the Workmen's Circle, during the summer month, according to their age when they first entered the Workmen's Circle.</p>
   <p>18. An old age fund shall be established which shall later serve for the establishment of an aged home.</p>
   <p>19. Action shall be taken to help World War Veterans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1551.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>20. The Workmen's Circle shall permit an increase in every insurance policy.</p>
   <p>21. Consumption benefits shall be raised to $250.</p>
   <p>22. Disability policies shall exist in one of our branches.</p>
   <p>After this, delegates were elected to the convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
