<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-04-15">April 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Workers Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-04-15">April 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago ladies' tailors have achieved one of their greatest victories of all time. True, however, this is a moral victory, it is, nevertheless, worth much more than any economic gain, because principle and justice are involved in it.</p>
   <p>The so-called opposition union of the ladies' tailors dissolved last week. The victory of the true Ladies' Tailor Union, Local 71, consists of the disintegration of the opposition union. The very same tailors, with the aid of the bosses, helped organize this "union," in order to destroy the real union and to break the strike which was then in progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The strike was lost, and the traitorous union men thought that they had completed their destructive work, but the devoted, loyal, and conscientious workers did not forsake their own union - the organization built with their blood.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the bosses, as in all strike periods, played up to the sentiments of the weak-minded workers by promising them the "kingdom to come" together with the Leviathan. But all this happened during the strike, when the bosses were in need of scabs. All this happened when they (bosses) thought that the scabs, who were plotting against their own wives and children, their own fellow workers, could always begiven the "run-a-round." But right must truimph. Their promises proved to be merely "hot air," and the traitor remained not only as traitor, but also as a slave, who paid the penalty for histreason in working one hour longer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1142.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now repent and purify yourselves. Apply for membership in the Ladies' Tailor Union, Local 71, an organization which was built for members and by members. It is a union having but one objective: to improve the condition of the workers. Their motto is an eight hour working day. They fight for higher wages and recognition of workers' rights. Do not permit yourselves to be misled again. The bosses' interests consists of more exploitation. Unity should be your ideal. Rally around your union banner, which is the true defender of your interests. Join the Ladies' Tailor Union, Local 71, located at 1125 Blue Island Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
