<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-09-25">September 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Hebrew School Teachers of Chicago Are Striking</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-09-25">September 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE HEBREW SCHOOL TEACHERS OF CHICAGO ARE STRIKING</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, the teachers of the association, hereby declare that when we, -a few weeks ago, gave our demands to the officials of the Hebrew schools and to the Jewish press, concerning a raise in our wages, we did this with the sole object of improving the condition of Hebrew school teachers in the present high cost of living. Our demands were very moderate. We asked for a minimum of $80 a month, an increase of 20 per cent for all those now earning $80; 10 per cent for those earning $100; five per cent for those earning more than $100. Any sensible person can easily understand that, should an increase of 10 per cent be granted, our wages will still remain starvation wages.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, however, knowing the officials of the Hebrew schools and knowing how lenient they are to the teachers, have limited ourselves to these moderate demands. But the officials, apparently want the teachers to starve.</p>
   <p>They did not even answer out demands. But the majority of them formed a syndicate and determined that no teacher can be transferred, which means if a teacher is discharged, he is unable to get another position. They also commenced to using a common trick, such as spreading contempt, hatred, and slander among the teachers.</p>
   <p>These horrible acts, these efforts to rain the character of the Hebrew teachers, to arouse hatred and suspicion of their co-workers, this horrible demoralization of the Hebrew teacher compelled the association to join the United Hebrew Trades and with that support declared a strike.</p>
   <p>We are sure that every father and every Jew, to whom the Jewish child is dear, and the future of the Jewish race, will stick with us and that we will surely win.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
