<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-25">Mar. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Workers Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-25">Mar. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is quite a distance from speech to action, so the saying goes. This is true concerning the raincoat makers strike now in progress in Chicago.</p>
   <p>As we know, a strike has been in progress for the past three weeks at Kunard Shayne and Co., who broke the agreement with the union, and all the strikers are standing pat on their demands and are in the battle line for their rights. But the question is: Why are the workers of Local 193 United Garment Workers, who are employed by the same firm, on these jobs?</p>
   <p>The United Garment Workers' motto is the very same as that of the Ladies Garment Workers, to which the raincoat workers belong; viz, Unity and <pb facs="5423972_3_1112.jpg" n="2"/>Solidarity. So why are they working when their brothers are on strike?</p>
   <p>It is far from speech to action. It seems that no matter what a principle, a constitution and a flag stand for, the fact is they have no bearing on practical life. This is criminal and even nauseous. We can't understand how people can be indifferent when their fellow workers are being persecuted and beaten; when their fellow workers are starving and are in dire need.</p>
   <p>We can't understand why their fellow workers should, at the same time, work, do the same type of work, for the same firm in the same factory building.</p>
   <p>Local 193 United Garment Workers owes the Jewish workers of Chicago an answer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1113.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the same time, it is well worth reminding the Jewish working masses that their support to the heroic strikers is absolutely necessary. May every individual, or every union and labor organization help them as much as they possibly can.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
