<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-02">Jan. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">First Victory for Cloakmakers in Conflict with Manufacturers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-01-02">Jan. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST VICTORY FOR CLOAKMAKERS IN CONFLICT WITH MANUFACTURERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an unostentatious manner, president Schlessinger submitted a report to the cloakmakers about the settlement with the cloak manufacturers. As a leader, and as a responsible official he could not possibly have handled the settlement any better than he did. It was handled in a skillful manner, and it resulted in many good advantages for the cloakmakers.</p>
   <p>It must not be forgotten that what is going on in all parts of the country also goes on in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The organized capitalists, together with the cloak manufacturers, have undertaken no less a task than that of disrupting the unions and establishing an open shop. In some of the large industries, these methods were successful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in other industries, a bitter struggle resulted with millions of dollars spent by the manufacturers in order to carry out their program. An example of these methods against the unions could be observed in the Chicago Stockyards, and in the building trades.</p>
   <p>The cloak manufacturers have not declared an open fight in favor of the open shop. They proposed certain conditions which if accepted by the unions, would leave them as they were without power. The organization would be all broken up, and the cloak-makers would be compelled to fall back into slavery again, just as they were long ago, when they had no union.</p>
   <p>The settlement that was just made for the cloakmakers in Chicago is not an ordinary settlement, for in many cases it strengthens the position of the trade workers and further, it enables the workers to take their stand in <pb facs="5423972_3_0893.jpg" n="3"/>defense of any attack made upon them by the cloak manufacturers from now on.</p>
   <p>This victory also shows that the cloakmakers of Chicago were the first ones to be in a position to repulse the attack of the organized cloak manufacturers.</p>
   <p>Now that the cloakmakers are returning to their work, proud and victorious, they should by all means begin to raise a large fund with which to protect themselves against future attacks. Very often, conflicts between cloak manufacturers and cloakmakers occur again, after the present contracts lapse.</p>
   <p>The Forward congratulates the cloakmakers on their victory, and is proud to have been in a position to help the cloakmakers reach their goal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0894.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Cloakmakers, enter your shops bearing in mind the principle of devotion to your organization, and no power in the world can besiege you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
