<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-27">May 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">All Bakers Will Stop Working at Midnight</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-27">May 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">All Bakers Will Stop Working at Midnight</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Union determines to notify through the Forward, all bakers that they must quit work at 12 o'clock tonight in those shops where the agreement is not signed. Members of the Bosses Association are among those who signed the agreement.</p>
   <p>At a big meeting yesterday afternoon, of the Bakers' Local, 237, the question arose as to what to do about the bosses who have not yet signed the Agreement.</p>
   <p>The business-agent, Joe Weisbaum, reported on the conditions in the Trades, and according to his opinion, the bosses will be forced to sign the Agreement. This meeting was called to determine how to deal with those bosses who have not signed the Union-Agreement.</p>
   <p>The business-agent claimed that some of the bosses have already signed, but at 12-o'clock tonight the old agreement with the bosses expires. Therefore, <pb facs="5423972_3_1202.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Weisbaum suggested that a meeting be called this morning and the list of the signed shops be read, and have the bakers report for work in the Shops that are not signed up, but have them quit work at midnight. A hot discussion developed, and it was unanimously passed to follow the same rule as in the past that at 12 midnight when the agreement expires, they shall quit work. A committee, together with the business-agent and secretary, shall visit all the shops, and see,if the agreement is not signed, that the men shall not work later than midnight.</p>
   <p>It was also determined to hold a special meeting of all the members at 10 o'clock this morning, in the Union hall, to hear the business reports of the shops where they may continue working after midnight. Fifteen bosses signed the Union-Agreement, and in those shops they can continue working after midnight.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1203.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Union notified all the bosses that the Union-office will be open until late at night, and a committee will be there to sign agreements for the Union, with every boss who does not want his work stopped at midnight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
