<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-02">Nov. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">To the Jewish Citizens of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-02">Nov. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE JEWISH CITIZENS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish citizens of Chicago who are marching to the polls today--and we hope that all Jewish voters in Chicago will fulfill their duty as citizens and go to the polls--must remember that today is judgment day not only for the United States, but also for the entire world, as well as for the Jewish people. The whole world now places its hope upon the Unite States; all nations wish for and must have the sympathy and aid of this powerful republic, The United States is in a position to determine the future history of the world for many generations [to come]. If the America people today express their will toward liberalism, their desire to fulfill a great historic task, then America will be liberal and Europe will also be liberal. A liberal and democratic American government will not tolerate the forces of reaction in Europe, nor will it support those reactionary forces. IF the future American government is a reactionary one, then not only will America be reactionary, but Europe will also be ruled by the forces of reaction. In a reactionary <pb facs="5423972_3_1697.jpg" n="2"/>Europe, there is no place for Jews. The Jews will have to immigrate and a reactionary America will not let them in.</p>
   <p>As liberal-minded people, as America citizens, who wish to see this mighty republic strong, great, free, and powerful, and as Jews who desire to help save the Jewish people, you must go to the polls today and vote for the party which has for the past six years shown its friendship and sympathy for the Jewish people, and which has extended recognition to great Jews--you must and should vote for the candidates of the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>The Democratic candidate, Governor Cox, who is loved by all the Jews of Ohio for his sincere friendship and sympathy for the Jewish people, said, a few days ago, to a Jewish delegation in Chicago that if he were elected President, one of his first tasks would be to help solve the Irish and Jewish questions. He declared that those two questions must be settled. Governor <pb facs="5423972_3_1698.jpg" n="3"/>Cox is known in his native state as a man of integrity, and we have no reason to doubt his word.</p>
   <p>The candidate of the Republican party has given no such assurance. He has shown little interest in the Jewish question.</p>
   <p>Governor Cox stands for liberalism, justice, and democracy, and when, with the help of your votes, he is elected President of the United States, then America will become the center of liberalism in the world, and the Jewish people will have a great and powerful friend.</p>
   <p>Vote for Governor Cox!</p>
   <p>In Senator Lewis, the Jews have an old friend. Senator Lewis is a great national figure, an able administrator, a noted jurist, a man of wit and <pb facs="5423972_3_1699.jpg" n="4"/>intellect, and an intimate friend of Governor Cox.</p>
   <p>Vote for Senator Lewis for governor of the state of Illinois!</p>
   <p>In Congressman [Adolph] Sabath, who is a candidate from the Fifth Congressional District, we Jews of Chicago possess a devoted, able, and clever ambassador in Washington. Congressman Sabath is the only Jewish Congressman who works in Washington, successfully and skillfully, in behalf of Jewish interests, and is very influential in all government offices.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath does his Jewish work in Washington on the quiet--without publicity, without clamor--and he does it for the individual who appeals to him, as well as for the general public.</p>
   <p>Express your recognition of Congressman Sabath's successful work by voting <pb facs="5423972_3_1700.jpg" n="5"/>for him today.</p>
   <p>The happiness of the United States, of the world, and of the Jewish people, demand the election of Governor Cox as President.</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis, as governor of Illinois, will be a credit to the state, and Congressman Sabath must be returned as our ambassador in Washington because be is able and willing to perform the great task which he has fulfilled up until now.</p>
   <p>Vote for Governor Cox, for senator Lewis, for Congressman Sabath, and for the other recommended candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
