<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-10-01">October 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Workers Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-10-01">October 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The movement to establish a United Hebrew Trades should be supported by all the Jewish Trade Unions and the sooner it will be organized the better it will be for the Chicago Jewish Labor Movement.</p>
   <p>We have, quite often, emphasized the necessity of a United Hebrew Trades organization, but much to our regret, the Jewish unions are apparently taken up with somewhat more important work than organizing a United Hebrew Trades, i. e. picnics, demonstrations, selling of tickets, etc. And we think that such work demoralizes the activities of the masses so that a great deal of work must be done in order to awaken the zeal to strive for such important work as a United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0437.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We want to call attention before the first organization meeting, to two important clauses upon which a United Hebrew Trades must, in order to prevent identical results of the previous United Hebrew Trades, be built.</p>
   <p>1. Only trade unionists should be represented in the United Hebrew Trades and under no circumstances should any other workers or radical organizations be included.</p>
   <p>2. A United Hebrew Trades, in order that it shall be successful, must do its work in accordance with the principle upon which it is established, i. e. it must be devoted to Trade Union work only, because our experience with the former United Hebrew Trades taught us that as soon as we deviate the work becomes paralyzed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Should the two above mentioned facts be adhered to, then a United Hebrew Trades in Chicago can meet with great success and bring the best results.</p>
   <p>We also wish to mention that there is a balance of $100 from the old United Hebrew Trades' treasury, and to consume this money for any other purpose, would be committing a crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
