<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-02">May 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Thousands of Workers Celebrate May Day and the Dedication of a Corner Stone of Amalgamated Temple</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-02">May 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THOUSANDS OF WORKERS CELEBRATE MAY DAY AND THE DEDICATION OF A CORNER STONE OF AMALGAMATED TEMPLE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Amalgamated Union of Chicago observed a holiday yesterday that will linger long in the memories of approximately ten thousand members who participated in it.</p>
   <p>It was a double holiday: the celebration of May 1st, and laying the corner stone of the Amalgamated Union Temple at Ashland Boulevard and Van Buren Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The traffic was completely stopped for one-half hour on the surrounding streets when the corner stone of the new edifice was laid and Sidney Hillman, president of the Amalgamated Union, delivered an inspiring address to the workers.</p>
   <p>Before the corner stone was laid, the members of the Amalgamated Union celebrated May 1st in the Ashland Auditorium. Mr. Hillman, in his speech, said "Today is the day that the workers of the world set aside a permanent holiday. When this holiday was proclaimed, the greatest desire of the workers was to obtain an eight-hour working day. Now we have it. And now, when this is realized, our object is to take our portion of this fortune. We will not be satisfied until greater and greater progress will be made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We are living now," he continued, "in a time of billionaires, individual wealthy institutions. The workers must see to it that they receive their necessary portion for their labor. We now need a five-day working-week. The Chicago Amalgamated Union is 100 per cent organized now."</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Schlossberg, secretary-treasurer of the Amalgamated Union pointed out, in his talk, that the new building of the Amalgamated is not only a home for the Union, but it is also a great achievement in the struggle that all workers have carried on until now.</p>
   <p>"Do not worry," Mr. Schlossberg said, "over our defeats. Without them we would not be as strong as we are today. And in order to preserve our strength, we must have unity; we must, forever, be on guard."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0478.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Sidney Riasman, acting manager of the Amalgamated Union in Chicago, was chairman of the mass meeting.</p>
   <p>Upon opening the meeting Mr. Riasman remarked that "at present when other organizations delineated from the right path, when the entire labor movement is undergoing a severe crisis, the Amalgamated Union is in its strongest epoch. This is due to the wonderful management of President Sidney Hillman, who bears in mind, at all time, the interests of the large membership."</p>
   <p>The thousands of members adopted a resolution in which they demand a new trial for the two labor martyrs, Socco and Vanzetti.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
