<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-27">July 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Shohatim at the Stockyards and the Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-27">July 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SHOHATIM AT THE STOCKYARDS AND THE UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The attempt to organize twenty-five shohatim employed in slaughter houses in Chicago has been delayed. [Translator's note: Shohatim are individuals employed to slaughter animals in accordance with Jewish law.] About half of the shohatim claimed that it would be difficult for them to enter the union since it is their desire to maintain the honor of the profession. They explained that by joining the union, they would lose most of the privileges they now enjoy at the slaughter houses.</p>
   <p>As the matter now stands, they take their time in the morning, say their prayers, cat their breakfast, and then go to their jobs. Nor do they have to work every day in the week. Sometimes they work only a few hours or none at all, and Friday is a half-day because it is Sabbath Eve. And, as the saying goes, they are not slaves to their jobs.</p>
   <p>Joining the union, they admit, would make the managers and foremen regard them <pb facs="5423972_3_0214.jpg" n="2"/>in the same way that they regard any other worker in the slaughter house. They will have to put in a full day's work, and, if no work is on hand, they must still put in their time.</p>
   <p>The shohatim fear that in winter, things will be worse. They will have to rise at five in the morning as all other laborers do, then say their prayers, grab something to eat and run. They will return home at dusk, even on Friday--Sabbath Eve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
