<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0762</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0762.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Worker's Ghetto (Column of Local Labor News).</p>
   <p>The Pants Worker's Union and their purpose. - 20,000 workers are employed in this trade of which 6,000 are Jews. - Long hours, small wages, and military discipline. - What a Trade Union can do for them. - A Jewish Trade Union Publication. - Its mission.</p>
   <p>"Our purpose will he not only to demand higher wages and a shorter working day, but better and more sanitary working conditions. But first we must maintain our honor and personal well-being."</p>
   <p>Such was the proclamation of the newly organized Pants Workers Union of Chicago. More than 6,000 Jewish men and women are employed in this trade in Chicago. There is a total of 20,000 workers of various nationalities employed in this trade in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Not all workers suffer the same unsanitary working conditions. However, they <pb facs="5423972_3_0763.jpg" n="2"/>all are badly underpaid, humanly mistreated, work very long hours, and are under a strict military discipline in the shops.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is not surprising that the newly organized Pants Workers Union has grown so rapidly. We live in a world where might is right. When one has an opportunity to make money, he disregards his fellow man entirely. This attitude is imbedded in the minds of the pants makers employers. Man is a machine created only to work. As such, he has no senses, no feeling, and no soul. We blame only the worker. Any worker who tolerates such conditions has only himself to blame. It is truly regrettable that workers have not awakened before this.</p>
   <p>The Union is prepared to remedy the situation. Workers! As individuals, you can do nothing. Join Now! Do not delay any longer! The Pants Makers Union is a local of the United Garment Workers, one of the strongest organizations in the American Federation of Labor. Meetings are held every Saturday afternoon at 4 o'clock. Do not fail to be there. Initiation Fee is 25 cents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0764.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The appearance of a Jewish Trade Union Publication has been long heralded. The number of Jewish Workers in Trade Unions makes a publication of this nature absolutely necessary. Above all, Jewish Trade Unionists should be thoroughly informed. This the publication will attempt to do. A publication is a semblance of unity, and unity is what we need most.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Schohet Ben Ha-Rav.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
