<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Dressmakers Union Again Achieves an Important Victory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0964</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0964.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DRESSMAKERS UNION AGAIN ACHIEVES AN IMPORTANT VICTORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dressmakers' union, Local 100, succeeded in signing an agreement, last Thursday, with the majority of the manufacturers in the local dress industry. Yesterday, they scored an important victory when they signed an agreement with the firm of Arthur Wise, 315 West Adams Street, the largest dress manufacturers in Chicago. The recognition of the union by this firm marks the beginning of the end of those firms that stubbornly refuse to recognize the union.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wise, who employs about one hundred and fifty workers, was one of the most important members of the old [manufacturers'] association, which refused to deal with the union. About three weeks ago, all the cutters and pressers of this shop went on strike--the strike which ended yesterday in a victory for the workers.</p>
   <p>It was announced that at the same time that Mr. Wise had signed his agreement <pb facs="5423972_3_0965.jpg" n="2"/>with the union, the following eight independent firms had also signed: Rosen and Swartz, Kempler, White, Greenfield and Wise, Deitsch and Miller, V. B. Reiz, French-American, and Shaffer and Cohen.</p>
   <p>The news of this victory was received with great enthusiasm by all the workers. It gave them new courage to fight against the firms, Philip Klafter, 164 South Market Street, and Sobel, 337 South Market Street, whose workers have been on strike since Tuesday, demanding the same conditions as have been granted to those shops in the [manufacturers'] association which have been unionized. The union leaders explained that these two obstinate firms will get no rest until they recognize the right of their workers to be organized, and grant them better working conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
