<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>.
<date when="1922-01-29">Jan. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Taking Place in the United Hebrew Trades?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Forward</title>.
<date when="1922-01-29">Jan. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS TAKING PLACE IN THE UNITED HEBREW TRADES?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many important questions came up for consideration and discussion at the last meeting of the United Jewish Trades Council. The Shochtim Kosher Animal Slaughterers and Butchers Workers who, until now, have had one union under a charter from the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of America, have dissolved this union and are having separate locals. Both belong to the Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen's Union and to the United Jewish Trades.</p>
   <p>Due to the various differences which come up between the workers and the Shochtim, the butcher workers decided to organize their own local. A committee of the butcher workers met with the Shochtim, discussed the matter of a separate local, explained its necessity and showed their willingness not to sever connections entirely from the original union, for a complete separation would jeopardize the strength of both unions...</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0629.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last Monday afternoon the Shochtim had their meeting which was well attended. They have reorganized under a new charter name, Shochtim of Chicago, given by the Amalgamated Meat Cutters. They have elected their officers for the year. A committee of the United Jewish Trades was present at this meeting to advise both sides to stand united, for that is the only way to protect their interests. Now in order to carry out these principles, it was proposed that the Shochtim elect a committee of five and the Butcher Workers a committee of five, while the United Jewish Trades appoint three delegates, these 13 members to serve as a joint board to look after the interests of both unions.</p>
   <p>The Shochtim adopted these proposals and now we may expect unity and harmony on both sides.</p>
   <p>Last Monday evening the Butcher Workers also had a similar meeting at the Fitzgibbons Hall. The first vice president of the Amalgamated <pb facs="5423972_3_0630.jpg" n="3"/>Meat Cutters Union was chairman of this meeting. A committee of the United Jewish Trades was present at the meeting, who presented the decision of the Shochtim to the Butcher Workers. All proposals were adopted by both unions. Peace and harmony between the two organizations is assured in the future....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
