<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">August 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Cloakmakers Organization Committee Declares a Strike at the J. &amp; K. Manufacturing Company</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0847</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0847.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">August 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CLOAKMAKERS ORGANIZATION COMMITTEE DECLARES A STRIKE AT THE J. &amp; K. MANUFACTURING COMPANY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second strike called by the Organization Committee was at the J. &amp; K. Cloak Manufacturing Company, 26 West Quincy Street, Room 422.</p>
   <p>This shop was operating with non-union workers and doing piece work for very small wages.</p>
   <p>The Organization Committee, A. Gordon, Chairman, has determined to clean out the scab nests that have appeared lately. The Cloakmakers Organization Committee is warning all cloakmakers, to not let themselves be influenced to work in these scab nests.</p>
   <p>At a meeting, Dr. Bramson told of the relief the Ort gave to tradesmen in various countries. Among them was Soviet Russia, for tools and seeds sent there; the professional education that the organization is giving to almost 5,000 children, and the general cooperative relief that was accomplished all over Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0848.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Bramson, also, illustrated his speech by photographs, which will be seen in the Forward tomorrow. The impressive speech of Dr. Bramson roused a strong desire in his audience to become a part of this world wide Ort organization and to build a branch in Chicago. A Provisory Board of nine persons was formed for the development of Ort and draw a large membership of Jews from all of Chicago.</p>
   <p>On that committee are Louis Schaffer, Louis Benenson, L. Hanek, Dr. Lorber, B. Stoliar, Dr. Pomerang, A. Lurie, Dr. Dolnick and B. Shapiro.</p>
   <p>The committee was immediately installed and it elected comrade L. Benenson as Chairman and Comrade B. Stoliar as Secretary. The first meeting of the committee will be held 11 A.M., to-day, at Rosenthal's Restaurant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
