<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-09">July 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Workman's Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1002</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1002.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-09">July 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WORKMAN'S INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general press heaped ridicule and contempt upon the participants in the Mooney General strike calling them uncomplimentary names and incorrectly reporting the facts connected with the event. Still in all the newspapers were forced to point out that the strike was eliciting support throughout the country; and in spite of the unorganized character in which it was conducted exerted considerable influence [in favor of freeing Mooney and Billings].</p>
   <p>It is well known that the strike failed to achieve its immediate purpose. In fact, it did not even attain the stature of a real general strike. Yet, none can deny that the several hundred thousand workers who went on strike for the Mooney-Billings cause yesterday and today aroused the attention of the general public and caused it to become interested in the movement [to free the two men]. Only in this manner can a victory be achieved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1003.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The unorganized Mooney strike demonstrated that thousands of class-conscious workers simply refused to let the matter rest, in spite of the threats of the American Federation of Labor that it would expel any participating union members, and the warnings of the Administration. They cast aside their work and demonstrated to the world that they, like the rest of the civilized world which condemned the [imprisonment of Mooney and Billings] believed that the San Francisco trial was a "falsehood". Moreover, it is clear that the events of yesterday and today attracted the attention of millions and millions of people, thereby, naturally, definitely increasing the number of sympathizers in the movement to free the life-sentenced labor leaders. Lastly, and most important, the strike served to awaken the backward and conservative labor groups under the iron rule of Samuel Gompers and his agents. One need not be too wise to realize that the simple man whom the Federation forbade to join the strike, will, after all, give some thought to the fact that other fellow workers did strike for Mooney and Billings while he, a unionist who holds the cause of the working man dear to his heart, remained at work--and scabbed! If he thinks about these things he will, sooner or later, reach some conclusion. This was, <pb facs="5423972_3_1004.jpg" n="3"/>no doubt, an important objective on the part of the organizers of the strike.</p>
   <p>In short, it appears that the so-called "unsuccessful" Mooney strike was, in reality successful, since it added momentum to the movement to secure justice for the San Francisco labor martyrs. The latter will, at any rate, secure their freedom now that their cause has been taken up by the rank and file members of the labor unions who before the strike did not believe in any other than a "bread-and-butter" strike.</p>
   <p>When the leaders of the Mooney movement plan their second general strike, which will be held during the first five days of September, we hope they will plan the affair in such a manner that its mass character will stand out. The first attempt to stage a Mooney General strike was not bad; the second should be better. Let us bear in mind that the events which took place during the last two days indicated that the class-conscious labor element was revolting against its official leaders--against those who desired to quell the strike. Little by <pb facs="5423972_3_1005.jpg" n="4"/>little, however, following a few more similar uprisings, the American trade unions will free themselves of Gomper's conservatism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
