<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>. 5669.
<title level="a">The Year 5668</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Louis H. Levin</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The American Jewish Year Book</title>. 5669.
<title level="a">THE YEAR 5668</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Louis H. Levin</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his paragraph entitled "Petition," we find the following excerpts dealing with the Averbuch and Chief of Police Shippy incidents in Chicago: "Those who seek the rough edges between Jews and Christians will find an instance here and there to point a moral and adorn a tale. - - - Feeling was aroused by the alleged attempt of Averbuch to kill Chief Shippy of Chicago, who managed to dispatch his assailant. The subsequent rough and unwarranted action of the police towards the inhabitants of the foreign quarter of Chicago brought from Jane Addams a defense of the foreigner in America that our statesmen should take to heart. Circumstances surrounding the death of Averbuch have raised doubts whether he really made an attempt on the life of the policeman, and these doubts remain in spite of an inquiry. Not long after the death of Averbuch, one Silverstein, a weak-minded individual, destroyed himself and another man in New York by exploding a bomb, which was assumed to have been meant for the police; and these two incidents, together with one or two more of the same kind, gave the order by the Secretary of Commerce and Labor directed against foreign anarchists timely significance; but it did not prevent Rose Pastor Stokes from declaring at a public meeting that she preferred the red flag to the stars and stripes. The breaking up of a Zionist meeting in Philadelphia shows how far police suspicion went at the time." (pp.198-199.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
