<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Nineteen Storekeepers from Maxwell Street Sign Agreement with Retail Clerks Union</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NINETEEN STOREKEEPERS FROM MAXWELL STREET SIGN AGREEMENT WITH RETAIL CLERKS UNION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Retail Clerks Union, Local 195, recorded a victory in the struggle of organizing the salesmen and the retail stores of Maxwell Street.</p>
   <p>The salesmen of the Maxwell Street stores, at one time, belonged to the Union but due to certain reasons they permitted their condition to become bad.</p>
   <p>The business agent of Local 195 turned to the workers and succeeded in getting them back as members of the union. Then, together with a grievance Committee of the American Federation of Labor, he approached the bosses of the Maxwell Street stores with the result that 19 store Keepers signed the agreement of the Retail Clerks Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The employees will now work under the following conditions: Fifty-four hours of work per week: and six days a week. The bosses are to employ workers through the union at a minimum scale of $40.00 a week for salesmen; a minimum of $37.50 for pullers and $18.00 a week for a beginner. All workers shall get a weeks vacation with pay.</p>
   <p>All workers, who receive more than the minimum scale, shall remain at the same wages. The salesmen shall not do any portering work. If bosses close their stores for personal reasons, they must pay the salesmen for time lost. The agreement is in effect until April 1, 1923.</p>
   <p>The owners of the Victory Cloak Stores were the only ones who did not sign the agreement with the Union. But there is no doubt that they will sign. It is expected that in a few days all the Clothing and Furnishing stores of Maxwell Street will be Union Stores.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
