<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date><title level="a">The Workers Rightful Claim of Injustice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date><title level="a">THE WORKERS RIGHTFUL CLAIM OF INJUSTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The assertion is now often made in the press, representing the interests of industry and high finance, that the workers have never had as good times as they are having now; wages increased immensely, often double and even treble their former earnings, and they are happily enjoying it.</p>
   <p>From the first glance this assertion seems to be correct. It is true, that the workers now earn more than ever before, that in many instances the wages have doubled, but whether they are happily enjoying it is an entirely different matter. The value of money is its purchasing power, and it is a known fact that the dollar buys less now than it has for the last three years. If the wages of the workers should increase in proportion to the purchasing power of the sinking dollar, the workers, at best, would be in the same position as they were for the last three years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The truth is though, that while the purchasing power of the dollar now averages from fifty to sixty cents, the wages of the worker increased only from eighteen to thirty-five per cent. Workers engaged in basic war industries are the only ones receiving a higher wage rate. In other words: proportionately, the worker now has less than he had three years ago; he is not earning as much as before to be able to pay the present prices for the various essentials. The assertion of the high-finance press is, therefore, one of those half-truths, which are complete lies.</p>
   <p>Nothing is mentioned in the capitalistic press about the fortunes now being amassed by the manufacturers, about the enormous and more profitable business now being enjoyed by them, yet it looks with cross-eyes at the increased earnings of the workers. The real truth is that, despite his increased earnings, the worker now is worse off than before. He is suffering now more than in the good old times, when he earned less but was able to buy more with less earnings than he can now with increased earnings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0297.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This general deterioration in the condition of the worker had to lead to a rift in the relations between capital and labor. The workers are compelled to demand still better wages, i.e. they must demand an increase in wages to make their purchasing power equivalent to that of the last few years. But the representatives of capital, taking into consideration the fact that the workers now earn more than in previous years, do not want to meet the just demands of the workers.If they were able they would suppress the labor movement entirely.</p>
   <p>The case of Alfred Decker and Company and of Rosenwald and Weil is very characteristic. Both firms have large government contracts.     Both firms are now doing an enormous business, but their relationship to their workers is the worst possible. Although the Government favors the organizing of labor and union principles, these two firms did everything they possibly could to work against the liberal spirit of the Government. If they had the power, these two firms would uproot the union principle from their shops. But the union idea is too deeply rooted inside the workers, and the Government is friendly <pb facs="5423972_3_0298.jpg" n="4"/>enough to labor not to allow Alfred Decker and Company and Rosenwald and Weil to carry out their narrow-minded and merciless labor policy. The humane stand of the workers and of the Government has destroyed the plans of these two large capitalistic undertakings. But the workers cannot be satisfied with the victory of the union idea alone, they must also demand increases in wages in order to be able to live as in previous years.</p>
   <p>The claims of the workers, not only against the two above-mentioned firms, but against all the large industrial undertakings, are absolutely just. While the manufacturers are profiting from the changed times, the workers are not gaining by it at all. It is unfair for the industrial magnates to use the present opportunity to gain excessive profits, while the worker suffers more now than in the past. The workers will have to present new demands, which the industrial barons will have no desire to fulfill, pointing out that the earnings of the workers are now much larger than before.</p>
   <p>It must, therefore, be expected that there will be sharp conflicts between <pb facs="5423972_3_0299.jpg" n="5"/>capital and labor. The situation would be simply hopeless if the industrial barons could manage and rule according to their hearts' desire. Fortunately, the Government is not indifferent to the just demands of the workers, and will certainly come to their aid</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
