<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Two Sweater Firms Settle with the Union--Strike Spreads</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0995</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0995.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TWO SWEATER FIRMS SETTLE WITH THE UNION--STRIKE SPREADS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The striking sweater workers have been victorious inasmuch as two firms, the Englewood Knitting Mills, 6340 South Racine Avenue, and the Blue Bird, 1943 Irving Park Boulevard, have given in and have signed an agreement with the union.</p>
   <p>This news was enthusiastically received by the strikers, especially since the "Blue Bird" was considered the strongest prop in the bosses' association. The strikers saw in this settlement the first step toward a complete victory.</p>
   <p>Workers of the above two firms returned to their work and pledged themselves to give the union their entire wage increase of twenty per cent as long as the strike lasted. This news aroused great enthusiasm among the strikers.</p>
   <p>The workers were especially happy because the workers from the Lorens Knitting Mills on Belmont Avenue also left their work yesterday, thus increasing the ranks of the strikers. This firm, as has been stated, exerted every possible effort to keep its workers from joining the union, but these efforts were in <pb facs="5423972_3_0996.jpg" n="2"/>vain. When the Lorens sweater workers supported the strike, the bosses of this firm threatened to get an injunction.</p>
   <p>Though in some localities they were hindered by the police, nevertheless the pickets made a very good showing at all the shops. Boy and girl strikers marched, carrying banners inscribed with the name of each firm, and underneath "Strike on, Keep Away"; these banners helped them to keep strikebreakers from taking their places [in the shops]. The union strike leaders said that the strike was progressing very well and that a speedy victory was anticipated.</p>
   <p>Today at two o'clock at the Geverkshoft Hall, 1142 Blue Island Avenue, a mass meeting of all strikers will be held. Well-known speakers will address the assembly.</p>
   <p>Philip Strauss, 1247 West 14th Street, was arrested yesterday for picketing the Lorens Knitting Mills. He was freed on fifty dollars bail. The trial will take place today in the Sheffield Avenue police station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
