<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-02-01">February 1, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-02-01">February 1, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The manufacturers of Chicago renew their Union-agreement for another year.</p>
   <p>At a meeting of both parties, Comrade Schlessinger succeeded in having the bosses renew the old agreement.</p>
   <p>The organized Dressmakers of Chicago recorded a victory Monday night, in their transactions with the Dress Manufacturers Association. The conference held by the representatives of the Association and the representatives of the joint board of Local 100, at the Morrison Hotel, ended in the Union Agreement being signed by the Manufacturers Association for another year. The agreement was the same as the last one, with the same conditions: a 44-hour week; time-and-one-half for overtime; and no discharging of a Union man without a reasonable excuse; and the same wages as for the last two years.</p>
   <p>Herman Spivak, President of the Association, was the Chairman of the Conference.</p>
   <p>The representatives of both parties signed the agreement. President Schlessinger signed for the International, Julius Ginsburg for Local 100, and <pb facs="5423972_3_0627.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Herman Spivak and Libowsky for the Manufacturers' Association.</p>
   <p>The following were present at the transaction: Spival, Lowenthal, Zeiden, and Greenstein, representing the Association; representing the Workers were: President Schlessinger, Vice-President Schoolman, J. Ginsburg, Organizer for the Joint Board, Local 100; Secretary Brodski, and the business-agents, Barky and Fogel; and the Conference Committee of Local 100, consisting of David Weiss, Dora Lipschitz, A. Galvin, Rebecca Holland, Mr. Kaufman, R. Timer, and A. Gitlin.</p>
   <p>A word to the unorganized Dressmakers: The joint board of Local 100 will start a campaign to organize the unorganized Dressmakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
