<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Ten Thousand Chicago Dressmakers Will Strike Today at Ten O'clock</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0814</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0814.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TEN THOUSAND CHICAGO DRESSMAKERS WILL STRIKE TODAY AT TEN O'CLOCK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long-expected strike in the dressmaking industry was called today, Wednesday. The red circular, which was distributed in the shops, called upon the ten thousand dressmakers to stop working and to begin the general strike. This is the text of the red circular, which the Union distributed today:</p>
   <p>"Brothers and Sisters: Leave your shops in order. Take your tools with you. Do not engage in any arguments with your bosses. As soon as you leave the shop, go at once to the place where your shop meets.</p>
   <p>"We have done everything to avoid the strike. The bosses have forced it upon us. It is time for the workers in the dressmaking industry to make their bosses understand that they cannot break the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0815.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Working conditions must be improved. Wages must be raised. The workers will not return to work until their just demands are granted.</p>
   <p>"Long live the unity of the working people.</p>
   <p>"General Strike Committee."</p>
   <p>The strike was called after a series of attempts had been made by the Union to negotiate with the manufacturers peacefully. The manufacturers did not even reply to most of the union overtures. They did not want to hear the demands of the Union. On the contrary, many wanted to abolish certain points in the agreement which had existed before. This created a situation which made a strike the only possible solution.</p>
   <p>The chief demands of the Union, as we have already reported, are: a five-day work week, a ten per cent increase in wages, and an insurance fund against unemployment, which the Amalgamated Union has already.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0816.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The first picketing will take place today around the shop of the dressmaking industry. Many cloakmakers have stopped working for a day or two in order to help organize the strike, and to help picket.</p>
   <p>It is expected that many shops, where only Union men are employed, will soon settle with the Union. The settlement committee of the Union has opened its headquarters in Room 1614, Morrison Hotel. A bitter struggle is expected, however, in those shops which are not yet organized.</p>
   <p>The dressmakers have the support of all the Jewish Unions of Chicago and of the Chicago Federation of Labor. The opponents of the present leaders of the dressmakers have declared that they are ready to do everything they can to help win the strike.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
