<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is going on in the Workmens Circle. by Morris Ziskind.</p>
   <p>As a matter of fact, very little is being heard of the Workmens Circle. We should hear a good deal about questions of the times, taken up for discussion at our branch meetings, questions that are befitting an organization like the Workmens Circle, but in that regard, all is very quiet. We ought to hear a lot about the tool campaign which is being conducted by the Peoples Relief Committee for Russia and Ukrania; we should hear of the miners' strike, and of the political questions in which the workers should be interested according to the constitution and principles of the Workmens Circle.</p>
   <p>An importand organization which will serve the Workmens Circle is the Credit Union, organized in Chicago by the members of the organization. This Credit Union has undertaken to build an institution which will, in time, be of great assistance to the important activities of Workmens Circle. The money paid in by the members <pb facs="5423972_3_1200.jpg" n="2"/>will be loaned out at a reasonable rate of interest to those who are in need of money. When the organization will expand and will have more capital, this money will be used to build institutions for the interest of the labor masses of Chicago, and the members of the Credit Union will thereby benefit, directly and indirectly.</p>
   <p>The Credit Union is growing very fast, new members are coming in at every meeting, and in time this new Workmens Circle organization will be an example as to what can be done for and through the Workmens Circle when one only wants to do constructive work. Members of the Workmens Circle wishing to enlist themselves in the Credit Union may inquire of N. Shure, of branch 65, or of the manager, in the office of the Labor Lyceum, and receive all necessary information regarding the organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
