<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-25">Mar. 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor Dever Promises to Fire Policemen Who Slugged Striking Dressmakers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-25">Mar. 25, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR DEVER PROMISES TO FIRE POLICEMEN WHO SLUGGED STRIKING DRESSMAKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mayor Dever promised yesterday to a committee of the Chicago Federation of Labor, which reported to him about the brutal action of the police toward the striking dressmakers, that he will discharge policeman Number 3401 for helping to beat up the striker Olga Levin.</p>
   <p>On Saturday morning, Sam Goldin, a strikebreaker, accompanied by a policeman, came in a taxi to the shop at 325 West Adams Street. Miss Levin tried to speak to the strikebreaker, who, instead of replying to her, began to slug her. The policeman assisted him. These facts were told the Mayor by Anton Johansen, in the name of the committee.</p>
   <p>Four strikers were arrested yesterday upon the complaint of Miss Fox, a strikebreaker, that they slugged her. The arrested are J. Lieberman, 25, 1250 South Spaulding Avenue; Bessie Malaki, 22, 857 Webster Avenue; <pb facs="5423972_3_0792.jpg" n="2"/>Bessie Katz, 27, 2235 West Harrison Street; and Rose Ganet, 742 North Troy Street.</p>
   <p>The two Jewish students, David and Eugene Ziskind, who were arrested for picketing, were arraigned yesterday before Judge Helander, who refused to try them. He turned their case over to Judge Sullivan, before whom their trial will take place on March 31.</p>
   <p>Yesterday there was a great number of pickets around the dressmaking shops, in spite of the arrests. On the picket line yesterday were striking dressmakers, students from the University of Chicago, workers from other trades, such as painters, carpenters, and many others, most of them members of the Trade Educational League. This league or active trade-union members is conducting a strong campaign within the Chicago Federation of Labor, for the Federation to fight Judge Sullivan's injunctions. It looks, however, as though the Federation's officials are afraid to take any steps in this <pb facs="5423972_3_0793.jpg" n="3"/>matter and that the members of the league are on the picket line on their own responsibility.</p>
   <p>The committee of fifteen of the Chicago Federation of Labor, together with the Injunction Committee, held yesterday a closed session. The [Injunction] Committee stated later that it plans to bring Mr. Gompers to a big protest meeting against injunctions.</p>
   <p>The Citizens' Committee, appointed by Miss Mary McDowell, Commissioner of Public Welfare, declared yesterday that all attempts to bring to a settlement the present struggle had failed and that the manufacturers were responsible for the failure. The [Citizens'] Committee, therefore, appeals to public opinion to exert its influence to bring about a settlement of the strike.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
