<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-17">Feb. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">800 Cutters and Trimmers Strike at Hart, Schaffner and Marx</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-17">Feb. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">800 CUTTERS AND TRIMMERS STRIKE AT HART, SCHAFFNER AND MARX</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>800 cutters and trimmers employed at the factory of Hart, Schaffner and Marx, 36 South Franklin Street, have rebelled against the Arbitration Board and the leaders of their union, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers. Of their own volition, they walked out on strike, to fight for their demands.</p>
   <p>The strike broke out because of a dispute between the cutters and the firm when the latter made an attempt to introduce a new system in the cutting trade. The cutters have a rule whereby materials of various colors are not to be cut together. This rule was established for the purpose of equalizing the work among all the workers.</p>
   <p>But now that the tailoring industry is in a splendid condition and there is a scarcity of workers, especially cutters, it is said that the firm has made <pb facs="5423972_3_0941.jpg" n="2"/>an attempt to modify somewhat the old tradition of the cutting trade, and has combined materials of various colors for the cutters to cut. The Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union agreed with the firm's proposal to make this change in the cutting trade. The Board of Arbitration also allowed this change.</p>
   <p>Last Friday morning, when the cutters of Hart, Schaffner and Marx, 36 South Franklin Street, came to work and found the new system in operation, they immediately held a shop meeting and at 9:30 A.M., 800 cutters and trimmers left the shop.</p>
   <p>This information was obtained by the Courier's reporter from the general manager of the shop where the strike is going on. When the Courier's reporter sought information from the officials of the Amalgamated, they emphatically denied the existence of a strike in the aforementioned shop.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0942.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"But 800 cutters and trimmers did leave the shop?", asked the Courier's reporter.</p>
   <p>"We did not order them to do so", replied Mr. Sam Levin, "and therefore it it not a strike."</p>
   <p>Later the Courier's reporter sought information from Mr. Sidney Hillman, International president of the Amalgamated, who is now in Chicago.</p>
   <p>"It is not a strike", Mr. Hillman replied, "it is only a 'stoppage'. It is a minor dispute that will be straightened out soon."</p>
   <p>It is quite possible that as a result of yesterday's meeting, the 800 striking cutters and trimmers will return to work today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
