<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-01-09">Jan. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Tailor Bosses Have Changed Their Minds; 1,000 Workers on Strike</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DAILY JEWISH COURIER</title>,
<date when="1916-01-09">Jan. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TAILOR BOSSES HAVE CHANGED THEIR MINDS; 1,000 WORKERS ON STRIKE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About 1,000 tailors have walked out on strike, because the bosses went back on the agreement, and wanted to go back to their former way of treating the workers, before the general big strike,when the tailors were working under the most dreadful conditions.</p>
   <p>The firm of Cohen and Rissman, 5th Avenue and Congress Street was one of the first to settle with the Amalgamated, with a few additional points, including a 48-hour-week. Yesterday, however, the bosses changed their minds demanding that the tailors work 52 hours a week, instead of sticking to the 48-hour contract. The union did its utmost, trying to influence the bosses to avoid the strike, but they met with no satisfactory response. And so, <pb facs="5423972_3_1088.jpg" n="2"/>there being nothing else left to do, 500 tailors, immediately called a strike.</p>
   <p>The same thing happened at the firm of Majestic, Franklin and Congress Streets, which also employs about 500 tailors. The Majestic, at the time of the general strike, also had settled with the Amalgamated. The work conditions with that firm were always very satisfactory. All of a sudden, however, it decided to lay off a large number of its workers and reduce wages, declaring that they could not pay the wages they had been paying. Upon this declaration, the workers responded with a strike. The firm of Schaeffr and Press was also affected by this strike.</p>
   <p>The strikers of Cohen and Rissman are having a meeting at the Cutters' headquarters, 363 W. Madison Street. The Majestic strikers are also to assemble in the hall, from which they will go out on the picket lines.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
