<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-06-04">June 4, 1912</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-06-04">June 4, 1912</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Schulsberger &amp; Sons, packers of meat, have started to slaughter cattle again for the "kosher" meat trade. This is the only packing house to retain an inspector of "kosher" meats all through the time of the Jewish butchers strike. The packing house, yesterday, recalled all the formerly employed "shochtim," the men who do the slaughtering for the "kosher" meat trade and who received their regular wages during the time the strike. The inspectors, however, never were laid off; they kept their jobs as usual.</p>
   <p>The "shochtim" were instructed to get to work at once and to begin slaughtering for the "kosher" meat trade. They immediately began slaughtering just as in the good old times, before the Jewish butchers started with their strikes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1157.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was rumored that all cattle slaughtered, yesterday, for the "kosher" trade would be taken to Cleveland, but this was reliably contradicted. The Chicago Jewish butchers will be in a position to buy this "kosher" meat for their regular run of business. They expect to have their places of business open for the next Sabbath Jewish trade. By Thursday of this week, all Jewish butchers in Chicago will be ready for business so that the housewives may be able to buy their "kosher" meat for the coming Sabbath.</p>
   <p>The Jewish butchers are of the opinion that the prices of meat will have to advance. With this in view the butchers will have a committee appointed of some prominent Jewish citizens to regulate the prices of the "kosher" meat. The butchers are somewhat afraid to tackle the price raising without the advice of the Jewish committee. The butchers themselves are quite anxious for peace, for their aim is always to please the Jewish housewife.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
