<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-12-29">December 29, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Workers Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-12-29">December 29, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKERS GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before in the history of the Jewish workers has there been endured such sacrifices, and have such hardships been suffered, as at present, by most of the five-hundred Ladies' Custom Tailors in their present strike. These Jewish workers' activities in their present plight will, no doubt, go down into history.</p>
   <p>It is over six weeks since this strike was declared. However, despite all the hardships, you will not find a single one of the custom tailor workers who will not stand fast for the cause. They expect to maintain the strike to the very last and live up to their sworn obligation by sticking with their comrades in this fight. This strike will certainly be recorded in the labor history of the Jewish labor activities. We firmly believe that the strikers eventually will emerge victorious, but there is one thing upon which we must depend, that is the full cooperation and help of our sympathizers who realize the struggle that we are up against. We hope that our sympathizers will extend us a helping hand until the strike is ended in our favor. This is the only way we can ever hope to win this fight. This strike is a very important undertaking; it is not only for the betterment of the strikers' conditions alone, but is also <pb facs="5423972_3_1177.jpg" n="2"/>for the good of all workers who are constantly fighting for higher wages, less working hours, and the recognition of unions.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Federation of Labor, until recently acted rather indifferently to this strike, for the simple reason that the strikers were not affiliated with any national union, but recently, it has decided to take a hand in this struggle. The Executive Committee of the Federation has decided to assist the strikers morally and financially. Proper credentials were furnished to the strikers to call on all unions for help.</p>
   <p>The Jewish workers must not rely nor depend too much upon the friendship of the Chicago Federation of Labor. They must, by all means, do all in their power to help themselves. We must not forget that the majority of the five-hundred strikers are in dire need and that they have been struggling for existence for the past six weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
