<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Present Troubles of the Jewish Bakery Workers</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Pozner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESENT TROUBLES OF THE JEWISH BAKERY WORKERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by SOL POZNER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Bakers' Union has had to fight many serious battles during the course of its existence, but never was it engaged in a fight like the present one. This is not open warfare--the organizer of the union calls it "guerrilla warfare".</p>
   <p>The troubles of the Bakers' Union began about two months ago, when the bakery bosses suddenly became "conscious" of the fact that their workers were earning too much money, and, in general, were leading too happy a life. The bakery bosses presented a demand to the union that wages be cut twenty per cent, and that the thirty cents an hour extra pay, which the workers get for night work, be eliminated.</p>
   <p>The demand of the bosses was considered by the workers at a union meeting <pb facs="5423972_3_0889.jpg" n="2"/>and they decided that they could not agree to it. They explained that their earnings were hardly sufficient to support their wives and children, according to the American standard of living, and that an extra thirty cents an hour was not excessive for night work.</p>
   <p>The bosses remained adamant in their demands, and the union began to negotiate with them. Nothing came out of the lengthy conferences between the representatives of both sides. The bakery bosses learned only that the workers would not surrender easily, but would fight to the last drop of their blood for their rights.</p>
   <p>Since they did not have sufficient courage to open a war against the workers by means of a lockout, the bosses began a guerrilla war. They began to ignore all union rules, engaged nonunion workers in their shops, sent the union workers home, began to work themselves in place of their union workers, and so on. The union was at first bewildered by those tactics, but it soon realized what was going on, and began to conduct an energetic defense campaign. A <pb facs="5423972_3_0890.jpg" n="3"/>strike was called in every shop where the union rules were broken.</p>
   <p>Such strikes are now going on in three bakeries. The bakery bosses are fighting those strikes with the same methods of guerrilla war. The bakery bosses have hired a few scabs, they, themselves, work day and night, which, naturally, makes it possible for them to sell bread for a few cents less. They have begun to sell at cheaper prices, and tell their customers that the union called a strike at their places because they were selling bread at cheaper prices.</p>
   <p>The Jewish women can and must support the Jewish bakery workers. The Jewish women must buy bread that has a union label, which is a guarantee that the bread was baked by honest Jewish workers. A union label also guarantees that the bread was baked under union conditions, which means under clean and sanitary conditions. It also means that the wives and children of the workers have bread.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
