<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Tar and Feathers as Means of Agitation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1356</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1356.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TAR AND FEATHERS AS MEANS OF AGITATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The investigation now going on in Washington, regarding the election of Senator Mayfield, promises to bring forth quite a few interesting facts about the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>The charge against Senator Mayfield is that he was elected through the help and criminal tactics of the Klan.</p>
   <p>This charge gives the Senate Investigating Committee an opportunity to learn the nature of the Klan activities, and the crimes that this secret reactionary criminal organization has committed in this country.</p>
   <p>The witnesses who will appear at the investigation are members who have played important roles in the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1357.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From the first hearing, it was learned that the Klan used two effective methods for agitation and propaganda in order to gain new members. These two methods were: flogging, and tarring and feathering.</p>
   <p>These two methods of agitation were applied very systematically, according to the demands of the highest officials of the Klan.</p>
   <p>The objective of these barbaric methods was to impose fear upon the populace in order to lure more people into becoming members of the Klan. A member of the Klan was immune from flogging and tarring and feathering. People who never would have joined the Klan, have done so to avoid being flogged and tarred and feathered.</p>
   <p>One of the witnesses, Mr. Kimbra, an important official of the Klan, was expelled from the organization for being against their barbaric agitational <pb facs="5423972_3_1358.jpg" n="3"/>methods. The same Mr. Kimbra states that the Klan used even worse criminal tactics. He denounced the Klan as a criminal clique which will commit any crime, including murder, to attain its goal.</p>
   <p>This is only the beginning of the investigation, and it has already uncovered sufficient evidence to indict the Klan as a band of criminals and murderers. But there are other witnesses, people who helped organize the Klan and were its officials, and they have plenty to tell.</p>
   <p>It is rather difficult to predict what verdict the investigating committee will render,but this is not the most important task of the investigating committee. Even if the votes of Senator Mayfield are not validated, he will nevertheless be discredited because of his connections with the Klan. More important than that is the fact that the loathsome and criminal tactics which the Klan uses are being unveiled to the American public. It is also important that the Klan should be discredited and that the public shall become aware of the menacing criminal clique the Klan represents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1359.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At any rate, it appears that the grave danger of the destruction of the little freedom left in America by the Klan, is gradually disappearing.</p>
   <p>Originally the Klan provoked a fear of its expansion over all America; lately, the Klan has not only ceased growing, but has started to retrogress. Its terroristic methods of flogging, torturing and murdering, helped the Klan spread fear over the population in every community that it penetrated in order to enroll new members, but the inside corruption and graft on the part of the leaders of the Klan, and the constant wars among themselves concerning the division of the graft, brought about such demoralization in its ranks that it caused the downfall of the organization.</p>
   <p>We are thankful for the petty inner conflicts, since they enabled us to learn of the horrible crimes the Klan has committed. It is the old story: when thieves quarrel, the truth is exposed to the public.</p>
   <p>It is true that many of the Klan's crimes and some facts of its inner corruption were openly published, but the facts that will be uncovered by the Senate Investigating Committee will have a much better effect. A Senate investigation <pb facs="5423972_3_1360.jpg" n="5"/>carries an official character, and from the revelation of one fact by the Senate Committee, the Klan will suffer a good deal more than from the publication of an expose by a newspaper.</p>
   <p>The Klan, within a short period of time, reached a very high degree of power and influence. It grew with the speed of a forest fire, but it has started falling with the same speed. It cannot be expected that such an organization will disappear entirely because of the mighty blows it may receive from the Senate. But the danger that has penetrated America, is without a doubt gradually diminishing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
