<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-09">Dec. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Workmen's Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-09">Dec. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WORKMEN'S GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday evening, December 6th, the Charter Festival of the Knitter's Union was celebrated in the Palace Opera Building. The celebration was to consist of a concert and mass meeting. Those who came for the concert were disappointed because the members of the Progressive Dramatic Club failed to come, but those who came to honor the Charter Festival, had a very pleasant evening.</p>
   <p>Several speakers addressed the gathering. Brother Ziskin, manager of the Yiddishe Arbeiter Welt, spoke in Yiddish, discussing the importance of loyalty to the union. As a former wage-earner he was able to portray conditions, in a way appealing to accord those assembled, so that everyone understood he was absolutely correct. After him followed Brother Minor, a member of the Young American Socialist League, who spoke in English. He, too, dwelled on the importance of being organized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0399.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The third speaker was Brother Kaufman, secretary of the United Jewish Alliance, who asked all knitting workers present, not unionized, to join the union.</p>
   <p>His appeal was effective and many workers joined.</p>
   <p>During the meeting a telegram was received from the Philadelphia Knitter's Union, in which they sent salutations to the Charter Festival and wished them success.</p>
   <p>The union will now meet every Monday evening. It is now making preparations for a concert and ball to take place Saturday evening, January 10, 1914, in the Workingmen's Hall, 12th and Waller Streets.</p>
   <p>Fellow workmen, do not delay; come and join the ranks of the Knitter's Union and help improve your condition. The initiation fee will soon be increased; dues are fifty cents. Come and help build a fortress to shield you from your employers. Come and bring your co-workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
