<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-03">July 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Manufacturers Believed to Have Agreed to All Demands</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1015</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1015.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-03">July 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">MANUFACTURERS BELIEVED TO HAVE AGREED TO ALL DEMANDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a one day general strike, it appears that Chicago cloakmakers have won a victory and will therefore, by all appearances, return to work joyfully early next Monday morning.</p>
   <p>Immediately after thousands of workers left the cloakmaking shops, the manufacturers assembled at the Morrison Hotel to confer with the union representatives. Judging from the negotiations that were taking place, it became apparent that the strike would soon be settled. It was agreed that another meeting should be held in the evening to make final adjustments.</p>
   <p>The committee, consisting of President Benjamin Schlesinger, H. Skulman, vice-president of the union, and Samuel Lefkovitz who came here from New York especially for this purpose, is to confer tonight with representatives of the manufacturers, and they will complete all the final <pb facs="5423972_3_1016.jpg" n="2"/>details of the settlement. According to Mr. Schlesinger's statement, the workers will probably return to the shops Monday.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, President Schlesinger addressed various groups of enthusiastic members assembled in the Down-Town district, the West Side, and the Northwest Side. Everyone listened attentively to the speeches regarding negotiations with the employers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schlesinger spoke of the final conference which was to take place last night and told all workers to come today at ten o'clock in the morning to the Car Men's Auditorium on the corner of Ashland Boulevard and Van Buren Street where all points of the agreement will be placed before them for ratification.</p>
   <p>Before leaving for the conference, Mr. Schlesinger gave the following explanation to a reporter from the Courier:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1017.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"As the situation now stands, a settlement is at hand. I am certain that the manufacturers will arrive at an agreement on all of the problems of the scale (wage scale), and I am therefore led to believe that next Monday morning the workers will return to their work with a song."</p>
   <p>Throughout the city everyone marvelled at the mannerly method in which the strike was conducted. There was not even so much as a sign of a disorderly scene. All cloakmakers, at ten o'clock sharp, left their shops en masse to gather in the various halls.</p>
   <p>Unusual enthusiasm prevailed among the workers--enthusiasm which was significantly strengthened by the appearance in the hall of workers from Dudley B. Palmer, Adams Street near the River, and also those from the Moses firm. The shops of these two firms, which are considered among the largest in the local cloakmaking industry, were not completely organized until yesterday. The fact that these workers also joined the strike was <pb facs="5423972_3_1018.jpg" n="4"/>therefore acclaimed as a great victory for the union, although six or seven years ago the Palmer workers lost a long strike. Besides the above-mentioned workers, over a hundred nonorganized cloakmakers joined the strike.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
