<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-09-16">September 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Communists Renew Their Terror against Cloak Makers, Brutally Beat a Communist Working Girl</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-09-16">September 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTS RENEW THEIR TERROR AGAINST CLOAK MAKERS, BRUTALLY BEAT A COMMUNIST WORKING GIRL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The former Communist officials of the Cloak Maker's Joint Board began using similar gangster methods, yesterday,which were applied by their "comrades" in the New York Cloak Market.</p>
   <p>Seeing that they are loosing out on all fronts, they started to beat up the members who refuse to be dictated by their cliques. they have brutally beaten Miss Tillie Schnell, 1226 S. Crawford Avenue; and seized her purse containing thirty dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Schnell is employed at Kay Bros. Shop, 228 S. Market Street, in the same building where the Communist tried to stage a fake strike, at Hyman Bros.</p>
   <p>The police,who arrived at the scene, arrested Miss Florence Korn, Rose Kaplan, Ida Rothstein, Dora Lifschultz and B. Rooner.</p>
   <p>Florence Korn was immediately set free and Miss Kaplan is charged with knowing where the pocket-book is, and she is being held under heavy bail.</p>
   <p>Judge Fetcher fined Jamposky and Resnick, two sign bearers, $200 for violating the court orders by interfering with the International in its organizational work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Communists manufactured a fake strike, hiring two hoodlums from Madison Street to picket Hyman Bros. Shop, informing pedestrians of a strike when in reality there was no strike. They only seek to split the Cloak and Dress Makers Union.</p>
   <p>The Communists, yesterday, admitted that they are lost and bankrupt. They have, until now, lied - through their blackmailing press, claiming control of the Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
