<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Workmen's Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0992</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0992.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WORKMEN'S INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strike of the sweater workers has undoubtedly a very good chance of being absolutely successful, The Knitters Union, though a comparatively young organization, has, in the short span of its existence, won the confidence of all workers in the industry that fall within its group. When this union decided to improve the conditions of the sweater workers, it knew it could depend upon the workers self-determination to fight for their demands. Thus, when the strike was called early Monday morning, the union certainly had the opportunity to discover just how correct its assumptions were regarding the workers' unity and determination to fight. The sweater workers responded enthusiastically, and left their work. Such responsive workers cannot possibly lose any battle.</p>
   <p>Characteristic of the strike is the fact that it is actually a fight for a principle, a fight for the recognition of the union. The majority of the bosses <pb facs="5423972_3_0993.jpg" n="2"/>were prepared to grant demands for a forty-four hour work week, increased wages, etc., but they stood firm against recognition of the union. It was a false assumption to think that the sweater workers, who are profoundly class-conscious, and are brave fighters, would stop at the most important of their demands--their right to be organized and their right to collective bargaining. The struggle for this principle actually brought on the strike.</p>
   <p>Manufacturers should see that it is not to their advantage to prolong the struggle. After all, they must realize now that their workers are not alone in this strike, but are supported by all local Jewish workers, principally the Amalgamated Textile Workers of America. This organization has gained quite a reputation for itself because of its many victories in the eastern states, and will here too, in Chicago, seek to lead the strike to a successful conclusion. It would, therefore, be better and healthier for everyone <pb facs="5423972_3_0994.jpg" n="3"/>concerned if the bosses would yield and would not prolong the strike.</p>
   <p>Some manufacturers have already made a good beginning by signing an agreement with the union. We would like to believe that all the others will soon follow their example.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
