<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">International Hat and Cap Makers Union Takes Over Leadership of Cap Makers Strike in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">INTERNATIONAL HAT AND CAP MAKERS UNION TAKES OVER LEADERSHIP OF CAP MAKERS STRIKE IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Strike Committee of the Cap Makers Union determined to depose the Communist Executive and their chairmen from the committees that have prolonged the strike for a period of four months and have made it impossible to bring about any settlement with the manufacturers.</p>
   <p>The Strike Committee came to the conclusion that the Communists, who controlled the Executive Committee of the Union, and who were chairmen of all committees which controlled the leadership of the strike, were responsible for preventing a settlement; and they gave over the leadership of the strike to their International with President Zaritsky at the peak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Communists tried to defend themselves, but all their excuses were controverted by facts and proof which were written black and white by the same Communists and their ugly press.</p>
   <p>International President Zaritsky, and general secretary-treasurer, Roberts, were present at the meeting of the Strike Committee and promised to apply all the powers of the International to settle the strike and procure the cooperation from the organized labor movement to help the Cap Makers in their struggle to preserve the existence of their Union.</p>
   <p>In the charges against the false leadership of the Communists it was shown that, from the very beginning of the strike, they have more fiercely combated the president of the International than the Cap Manufacturers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
