<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-11">Aug. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From Workmen's Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0958</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0958.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-11">Aug. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM WORKMEN'S INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fight which has been developing among the cigarmakers throughout the country, would certainly not have had to reach such gigantic proportions, if the International had possessed other, more progressive leaders in the trade-union movement. The International, during the many years of its existence, has accomplished little in the way of organizing. Instead of striving for better working conditions, or for a better livelihood for the cigarmakers, this organization provided the workers with death benefits. This was one of its most important functions. The result is that the organizing of the cigarmakers has been sadly neglected; the workers are unorganized, the exploitation is great, and conditions are terrible. As a result, the cigarmakers who are striking today for a fifty per cent increase, will earn, even after the increase is granted, only sixteen dollars and fifty cents a week. The present average wage in the cigar industry is not more than eleven dollars a week. In the last fifteen years, cigarmakers <pb facs="5423972_3_0959.jpg" n="2"/>have received two increases, amounting to twenty per cent all told, while at the same time, wages in other industries, increased about seventy-five or eighty per cent. In addition, there was the increase in the cost of living. Almost all the cigarmakers do piece work. The worker was always forced to compete with the rising cost of living. And in the race, the high cost of living won, because it rose two hundred per cent in the same time that the cigarmakers' wages rose only twenty per cent. Even official government statistics show that the prices of staples have risen, on the average, about eighty-eight per cent. If you consider the basis foodstuffs, you will find that their rise [in price] has been greatest. The same statistics show that flour rose about one hundred and twenty-five per cent, and potatoes, one hundred and eleven per cent. Bearing this in mind, is it any wonder that the Chicago cigarmakers stand so firmly in their fight for a better livelihood? Will anyone dare to doubt the justice of their demands? Is it not obvious that they will win in the end?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
