<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-01">Aug. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Sweater Manufacturers Withdraw from Injunction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0979</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0979.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-01">Aug. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH SWEATER MANUFACTURERS WITHDRAW FROM INJUNCTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We will never be partners to a false injunction founded on the lies of bolshevism, anarchism, and other insinuations." This statement was made yesterday by the three Jewish sweater manufacturers, Mr. H. Newberger, Mr. Gortshakov, and Mr. Delson, whose workers now are on strike for the recognition of their union. The workers' enemy, lawyer Dorley Taylor, in the name of these manufacturers, wrote the petition for an injunction which he brought before Judge Pinkney of the Superior Court. The judge will decide today whether or not the sweater manufacturers association should receive such an injunction.</p>
   <p>Mr. Newberger, owner of the Royal Knitting Mills, 846 West Jackson Boulevard, explicity told his lawyer, Oscar M. Wolf, that his name must be stricken from this petition founded upon such insinuations against Jewish workers. Mr. Gortshakov, owner of the Western Knitting Mills, 1144 Blue Island Avenue, as well as Mr. Delson, 1754 Milwaukee Avenue, both declared that they had never authorized anyone to sign their names to a petition for an injunction which <pb facs="5423972_3_0980.jpg" n="2"/>they had no idea of obtaining. The above-mentioned are the only Jewish manufacturers in Chicago's sweater industry. Their withdrawal from the injunction naturally adds to the hope of an immediate settlement with the union.</p>
   <p>Lawyers Saltier and Rosen, representing the workers, will appear this morning for the third time before Judge Pinkney in their effort to prove to the court that this petition for an injunction must, according to law, be drawn up by an individual firm, and not, as Dorley Taylor presents it, as a joint petition. It is also possible that they may succeed in entirely preventing an injunction from being issued at all.</p>
   <p>The strike situation, is thought to be promising. J. Mosti, general secretary of the Amalgamated Textile Workers, came here yesterday, from New York, to carry on the strike. In his statement, he says that the Amalgamated, with its one hundred thousand membership, is now actively participating in this fight of the Chicago sweater workers for a forty-four hour work week, a wage increase of <pb facs="5423972_3_0981.jpg" n="3"/>twenty percent, and the recognition of the union. This fight will certainly end in victory. The Amalgamated he also declared, will, from now on, finance the strike.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow, at 1:30 P. M. Mr. Mosti will address a mass meeting of the strikers at the Geverkshaften (Alliance) Hall, 1145 Blue Island Avenue, which all sweater workers are expected to attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
