<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-25">March 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Organized Working Class and the Charity Institutions</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-25">March 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORGANIZED WORKING CLASS AND THE CHARITY INSTITUTIONS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Friday's issue of the Forward, a resolution by Mr. Turowlin can be found informing the workers of Chicago to organize charity institutions in order to avoid the capitalistic charity institutions, in time of need. Such a proposal is always in place. Although the working masses can be charity proof, if they belong to the trade union.</p>
   <p>The trade union, if all workers belong to it, is able to gain for the workers not only a living for the present, but also an old age pension when one becomes unable to work. The strong organized trade union can also provide its membership with sick benefits, with consumptive hospitals, and also with cultural institutions, through which the wealthy classes demoralize and humble the poor masses.</p>
   <p>The Socialist Party, if the masses will vote solidly for its candidates, can also accomplish much on this dominion. It can carry through city, state, and national institutions where the sick and aged can have relief without being forced to beg for it. The Socialist Party can carry through such social laws, as in several European countries where the government gives the trade unions directly, specified sums for sick treasuries, old age pensions, and <pb facs="5423972_3_1541.jpg" n="2"/>etc. It can also carry through more public gymnasiums, swimming pools, educational institutions, hospitals, orphanages, and aged homes (where Jews will be able to get Jewish meals, speak the Jewish language, and have the opportunity to observe Judaism according to their own manner), etc.</p>
   <p>The Workmen's Circle is also a great beneficence to the Jewish masses, which help the sick. It even has a private hospital for the consumptives. Yet the resolution to organize relief institutions, which shall be under the control of the organized working class, is in place. And at present, not all workers belong to the trade union. A great number of Jewish workers and radicals are still not members of Workmen's Circle and have not elected any Socialist law makers.</p>
   <p>The question is only - what can the masses carry through alone, if anything? Can they control it under the present conditions? All the charity institutions were, to begin with, established by the poor Jewish masses. But after the institutions grew up, they were transferred into the hands of those who had more money to manage them.</p>
   <p>It was so with the orphan home, which is being controlled by a clique that does not care for their own people. It was so with the Hebrew Institute <pb facs="5423972_3_1542.jpg" n="3"/>which has, under the leadership of Jack Loeb, dispersed a Jewish mass meeting by police force. The Maimonides Hospital was at first being built with the pennies of the poor masses, but upon completion it fell into the claws of the ugly cheap politicians who have ruined and brought it to destruction.</p>
   <p>The only way to free the masses from these fiendish charity institutions is through the labor organizations. They are the only power that can stand against the charity trust which seeks to bring every charity institution under the control of the political leagues and "social working" cliques.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
