<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Cigar Makers on Strike for Higher Wages</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0975</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0975.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CIGAR MAKERS ON STRIKE FOR HIGHER WAGES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Five hundred Chicago cigar shops, employing about 3,500 workers, will be deserted tomorrow morning, as a result of the general strike which went into effect yesterday noon.</p>
   <p>The six local cigar makers unions took this step after the manufacturers refused to negotiate for a fifty per cent wage increase. At their joint meeting last Sunday, in East End Hall, Erie and Clark Streets, the workers decided to ask for this wage increase.</p>
   <p>Union leaders declared that the cigar makers are firm in their determination not to give up the fight until they gain a complete victory. As strong as the strike enthusiasm was yesterday, among all the workers it was even stronger in the ranks of the 15,000 Jewish cigar makers, the majority of whom belong to the Progressive Cigar Makers Union, Local 527.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0976.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In an interview with a reporter from the Courier, Mr. J. Bilov, president of Local 527, explained: "To the general public a raise of fifty per cent may seem too much for us to demand. The truth is that even with a fifty per cent increase, we still do not receive a really decent living wage. The cigar worker, up to the present time, has been more exploited than any other worker--and he has worked for a starvation wage.</p>
   <p>"Our average earning is twenty dollars a week. The increase we demand will simply mean an average of thirty dollars a week. who, therefore, can doubt the justice of our demands? Can a family man live on even thirty dollars a week these days, with the cost of living still rising?</p>
   <p>"We were ready to confer with the manufacturers, but when they refused a peaceful settlement, we had no alternative but to call a general strike."</p>
   <p>Two important mass meetings will be held tomorrow at two o'clock in the afternoon; one, at Netherwood's Hall, Marshfield and Taylor, and the other <pb facs="5423972_3_0977.jpg" n="3"/>at Colonial Hall, 20 West Randolph Street. A number of famous speakers will address these meetings. Beginning tomorrow, Colonial Hall will become the regular meeting place for all strikers, and also the headquarters of the strike committee.</p>
   <p>It is expected that at today's meeting, the Chicago Federation of Labor will certainly endorse the strike, and will help to win a victory [for the strikers].</p>
   <p>Among the important cigar manufacturers involved in the strike are the following: The Congress Cigar Company, Racine and Van Buren, manufacturers of La Palina cigars; Wengler and Mandel, Madison and Robey--Tom Palmer, Trophies and King Bee cigars; Ben Bey, Wells and Lake Streets--Ben Bey, Lord Bacon; Cohen Brothers, Market and Franklin Streets--St. Adpa; Fernbach, Indiana Avenue and Twenty-ninth Street--Cyrilla; Soloman, Madison and Clinton Streets--Lord Lester; and the E1 Joe Cigar Company, 1635 West Van Buren Street, which manufactures E1 Joe cigars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0978.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>National Strike Over Entire Country Possible</p>
   <p>The joint general strike committee, which is leading this fight, consists of representatives from the six following locals: 14,15, 217, 227, 383, and 527. Yesterday this committee arranged a series of meetings all over the city, and set up the strike machinery. We know that it is quite possible that Chicago's strike may lead to a general strike in the cigar industry throughout the entire country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
