<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Cloak Makers Strike Avoided - Tailors Strike Unavoidable</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CLOAK MAKERS STRIKE AVOIDED - TAILORS STRIKE UNAVOIDABLE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The danger of a general strike of the cloak makers has passed. The principle of arbitration has been victorious, and after a number of meetings held by prominent persons with representatives of the manufacturers and the union, both sides agreed to settle their differences through arbitration. The board of arbitration will consist of: a representative of the union, a representative of the manufacturers, and a neutral chairman. Both parties readily agreed upon the well known Jewish civic leader, Federal Judge Julian W. Mack, as chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1093.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The person, who was instrumental in bringing both quarreling parties together was Judge Harry M. Fisher. When the Jewish judge read the editorial in the Courier about the danger of a strike and the appeal to Chicago's prominent citizens, he immediately became active and did not rest until he influenced the manufacturers to sit at the same table with the representatives of the union and settle their differences in a peaceful manner.</p>
   <p>Yesterday evening at 6 o'clock, the Chicago Cloak and Suit Manufacturers' Association signed an agreement with locals 18, 44 and 81 of the Cloak Makers' Union as to the terms of arbitration, which are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Judge Julian W. Mack shall be the chairman of the Board of Arbitration and each side is to elect its representative not later than 5 o'clock today.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1094.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>2. The work in the shops shall not cease, until the Board of Arbitration shall render its just decision as to the demands of the Union.</p>
   <p>3. All the decisions of the Board of Arbitration shall be binding upon both parties and remain in force not less, than two years.</p>
   <p>The union at once chose Mr. William A. Thompson as its representative for the Board of Arbitration. Mr. Thompson formerly was the attorney for the United States Industrial Relations Committee. At 5 o'clock the manufacturers will announce the name of their representative and the board will begin its task Monday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1095.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Judge Mack at present is on his vacation at Mackinac Island, Michigan. Upon the telegraphic invitation of Judge Fisher he consented to accept the chairmanship of the Board of Arbitration, and for this purpose will come Monday morning to Chicago.</p>
   <p>The manufacturers of Milwaukee Avenue who do not belong to the association have so far remained behind. It is therefore possible that a strike may break out in their shops, which would be a calamity to the manufacturers. Rumors are circulating that Milwaukee Avenue is getting active, and it is expected that in a day or two, they also will consent to arbitration. Rumors have it that at their meeting yesterday evening they decided in favor of the principle of arbitration, but so far it is not known as yet, whether or not they will become affiliated with the association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1096.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. B. Schlesinger, president of the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, who has been in Chicago for the past eight days, has been working for the preparation of the general strike. This afternoon, Mr. Schlesinger in an interview with the representative of the Courier, made the following statement:</p>
   <p>"We do not want to strike. Our true aim has always been to settle all differences in a peaceful manner. But if the employers compel us, then we are prepared to fight with all our energy.</p>
   <p>"At the same time," Mr. Schlesinger added, "we are working on both fronts. We are preparing for peace, as well as for war, and if the employers will not consent to arbitration, then the workers will walk out on strike next Tuesday."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1097.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>When Mr. Schlesinger made this statement it was not known as yet what the answer of the manufacturers association would be, though he was hopeful, that the employers eventually would give in to the just demands of the union. Later in the evening, when the decision of the association became known, Mr. Schlesinger declared that he is well satisfied with the manufacturers intelligent handling of the entire situation.</p>
   <p>"Our international union," he added, "has always been for arbitration, and now we can hope that the peace in Chicago's cloak industry will be a lasting one."</p>
   <p>Thanks to the editorials of the Courier about the serious situation of the cloak makers, Judge Harry M. Fisher took the initiative in preventing the big strike in Chicago in which several thousands Jewish families would have <pb facs="5423972_3_1098.jpg" n="7"/>been involved. Judge Fisher at once conferred with the union, as well as with the manufacturers association, and although the union was willing to arbitrate from the first, the manufacturers hesitated about the matter. However, thanks to the earnest efforts of Judge Fisher it was finally possible to convince the latter that they have no right to reject arbitration, to which they have eventually consented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
