<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-23">December 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Co-Operative Workers Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-23">December 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CO-OPERATIVE WORKERS SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The weekly meeting of the board of directors of the Co-operative Workers Society, was held on December 17, The chairman was Friend Wabitzka.</p>
   <p>1. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved.</p>
   <p>2. The financial secretary reported fifteen applications for share holders. The applications were postponed until the monthly general membership meeting.</p>
   <p>3. The bookkeeper reported that the restaurant grossed $385.65 last month. The expenses were $221.37. The report was approved.</p>
   <p>4. The manager of the restaurant reported, that there was an additional income of $60.00 donated by the labor editor of the Daily World, Morris Siskind. He also reported that there was an increase in meat of one cent per pound, and the price of butter also increased. The report was accepted and the last clause was given over to the Administration Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. Friend Maryfield reported that the site for a new restaurant at 3450 W. 12th Street, is now being remodeled and will be completed within ten days. The work will amount to $300.00. The report was approved.</p>
   <p>6. The question of the management of the new restaurant was taken up and it was determined to engage a manager, an assistant manager, and a cashier. They shall be under the supervision of the administration committee, who will be appointed by the board of directors.</p>
   <p>7. It was determined to celebrate the opening of the new restaurant, Saturday, January 5, 1918, with a banquet.</p>
   <p>8. The matter of improving our activities was taken up and it was determined to engage an organizer for this purpose.</p>
   <p>9. The distributing committee was ordered to hasten the establishment of a grocery distributing station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
