<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">On the Field of Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Edward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE FIELD OF LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Edward</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It would be an extremely long account if we attempted to enumerate everything within the three-year agreement that the Union negotiated with the two boss Associations, "The Ready Made" and the "Special Orders." We will, therefore, need to limit ourselves to those points which are of greatest interest to us.</p>
   <p>1. A preferential union shop.</p>
   <p>When members of the Association need workmen, they must apply to the Union as long as the Union can supply union members.</p>
   <p>2. A Board of Arbitration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0239.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The establishment of a Trade Board and a Board of Arbitration to settle disputes.</p>
   <p>When a workman is discharged, his case must be brought before the Trade Board, which has the right to reinstate him.</p>
   <p>3. Complaints of workers.</p>
   <p>All grievances of workmen are taken up by the representatives of the Union and the immediate work superiors.</p>
   <p>4. Increase in wages.</p>
   <p>The problem of wage increase will be taken care of by the representatives of the Union and the employers. In case they <pb facs="5423972_3_0240.jpg" n="3"/>cannot reach an agreement, the question will be referred to arbitration.</p>
   <p>Increases will become effective June 1, 1919.</p>
   <p>5. A 44-hour week.</p>
   <p>Working hours should be limited to 44 hours a week: the first five days at 8 hours, and Saturday 4 hours. Work done after regular hours is to be designated as overtime and paid for as time and a half, to the weekly workers as well as to piece workers.</p>
   <p>6. Regarding strikes and lockouts.</p>
   <p>No strikes or lockouts to occur for the duration of the agreement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0241.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is almost twenty-three weeks since the fighting Progressive Cigar Makers Union Local 527 opened battle against the trust, by calling to strike five hundred workers of the La Preferencia Cigar Co. And still the courage of the workmen is not yet broken. It is certain that sooner or later the Union must and will conquer.</p>
   <p>Our certainty is based not simply on strength but definitely on indisputable facts which speak for themselves. These are as follows:</p>
   <p>First, the firm during all this time has been unable to secure more than eighteen scabs, and these know very little about the work.</p>
   <p>Second, about 200 of the strikers found work elsewhere. Those still unemployed are being aided in a true brotherly fashion by the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0242.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Third, the entire working movement also helps the brave strikers. It very generously gives financial aid unstintingly.</p>
   <p>Fourth, the Progressive is firmly resolved to continue the fight to a victorious end. We know from experience what a decision of this Union means.</p>
   <p>Today everyone says, "Do you not believe as we do that sooner or later the cigar makers will and must be victorious?"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
