<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-22">Aug. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Klafter Injunction Modified; Union Can Call Sympathy Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-22">Aug. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">KLAFTER INJUNCTION MODIFIED; UNION CAN CALL SYMPATHY STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a great deal of argument, that went on morning and afternoon, Judge Joseph David yesterday modified the injunction which he had issued several days ago against the strikers at the Philip Klafter Company, 137 South Market Street. Consequently the Dressmakers Union, Local 100, will be permitted to call sympathy strikes in the continual struggle of the workers of this concern, who have gone out on strike, demanding the same conditions that exist in most of the shops of this industry, whose owners recently concluded agreements with the Union.</p>
   <p>Attorneys Max Shulman and Meyer Abrams, representing the Union, argued the case, proving the constitutional right of workers to strike and picket the shop. Mr. Shulman quoted some similar cases heard before the Supreme Court. Analyzing the injunction, Judge David declared that although he had issued the injunction only on the ground, that the strikers are charged with a conspiracy to injure the <pb facs="5423972_3_0951.jpg" n="2"/>interests of the concern mentioned, which in the eyes of the law, appears as a boycott, nevertheless he recognizes the fact that in general the workers have the right to induce others to join the Union; to have their own shop committees; to dictate to the boss the working conditions, such as hours, wages, etc.; to call a strike; to induce others to go out on strike; and numerous other things, which rights the court granted, although the injunction in its modified form still remains in effect.</p>
   <p>Besides the question of sympathy strikes, Mr. Shulman was also successful in securing a modification in connection with picketing. According to this modification, the workers are permitted to parade in front of a shop, but are prohibited from carrying any signs or placards.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
