<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">In the Field of Workers</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FIELD OF WORKERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the United Jewish Federation, D. Alsansky of the Rain Coat Makers Union, resigned his post as financial secretary, and Henok of the Progressive Cigar Makers Union was elected in his place. Mr. Mazur of the Furriers Union was elected as organizer at a salary of five dollars a week.</p>
   <p>The United Jewish Federation received a communication from the New York Jewish federation criticizing the federation in this city for recognizing the Hebrew Actors Union. This commication was turned over to the executive board for investigation and to be acted upon accordingly.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Bakery Workers of the Northwest Side, who have determined to sever connections with local #239,have organized a local of their own.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0363.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are holding their regular meetings every Friday, and have elected Mr. H. Holtzman, as their temporary secretary.</p>
   <p>A committee of five, elected at the last meeting, has applied to the International before which body they presented their grievances and grounds for a charter for a new local, and although the International was in sympathy with the committee's report, the International could not grant the charter, on account of not desiring to get mixed up in the controversy. So, after receiving the report of the committee, the bakers have decided to lay the matter before the general executive board. They will not leave a stone unturned until they obtain their desired charter. It is unofficially reported that although the International has refused them a new charter, it had to refrain from complying with the committee's request mostly because they were afraid to mix too much in affairs of the locals. Among the Jewish bakers you can find many workers in the large bakeries on the North Side, who also are working in the bakeries of Rosen, Petikon and Himelstein.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
