<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">February 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Activity of the Jewish Socialist Singing Verein</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-02-22">February 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACTIVITY OF THE JEWISH SOCIALIST SINGING VEREIN</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great and feverish work is now being carried on in the Jewish Socialist Singing Verein. The work is spreading more and more in new dominions, and the Singing Verein will soon be transformed into a strong Jewish Socialist "culture center" in Chicago, where the various elements, in which Chicago is so plentiful, will find complete satisfaction and a wide field for activity in the socialist "culture center," and at the same time cling to the principles of the Socialist Party. This will call new strata and elements to life, who recognize the importance and necessity of cultural work, and unite and inspire them to activity, to influence the Jewish working masses for our general socialist ideals.</p>
   <p>The Singing Verein is increasing in membership at each meeting. The next month (from February 15 to March 15) is set aside as membership month and our members are trying their utmost to advance the cause.</p>
   <p>Everything possible is, at the same time, being done to bestow upon our members excellent opportunities, in order to develop their abilities and beautify the singing. Classes were organized for this purpose where notes are being taught thoroughly and systematically, by competent teachers, such <pb facs="5423972_3_1553.jpg" n="2"/>as Comrade Schaffer, the choir director, and assistant director, Dobrow.</p>
   <p>Solo Groups of the better singers were also organized, and those who possess greater musical ability will sing solos at the various undertakings of our radical organizations. The solo group is under the supervision of a special teacher, Alexander Nocurtin.</p>
   <p>In addition to this, lectures will be arranged on music, singing, and other cultural subjects, in Jewish and in English, by the best lecturers, such as the noted Morris Rosenfield, J. Millman, Solomon Gollub, and etc. The lectures will be made with musical accompaniment and at popular prices. This is one of our most important tasks - to spread more enlightenment and a truer conception of music to our members and others who are interested.</p>
   <p>But the finest and greatest thing that the singing society has already accomplished is the organizing of a Jewish Socialist orchestra. Chicago was in need of such an orchestra a long time ago. Nothing can be undertaken without a musical division.</p>
   <p>All these classes of the various parts are controlled by the entire Verein and anyone who desires instruction must become a member of the Verein at <pb facs="5423972_3_1554.jpg" n="3"/>large. Dues are only eighteen cents a week.</p>
   <p>The erection of a school for Jewish socialist and general literature and drama is being planned. The cultural work is contributed by many organizations in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
