<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-07">Jan. 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-07">Jan. 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Courier recently made public the fact that the multimillionaire and businessman who became a member of the Ku Klux Klan is none other than William Wrigley, the famous manufacturer of chewing gum. Wrigley is also the president of the National League baseball team, the Cubs, and is generally a sport fan. The recent provocative acts of this organization should have opened the eyes of Mr. Wrigley, who is a man of understanding and intelligence. By not resigning from the Klan, Mr. Wrigley has indicated that he is highly pleased with the poisonous campaign of race hatred and religious condemnation, which is particularly directed against the Jews.</p>
   <p>By admitting Wrigley as a member, the Ku Klux Klan caught a good cow to milk. From him they can obtain a large sum of money for their propaganda purposes, not only here in America, but also in Europe. The Ku Klux Klan is already spreading <pb facs="5423972_3_1410.jpg" n="2"/>its propaganda in Europe. Since most European countries are predominantly Catholic, the Klan will direct its wrath against the Jews. It is understood that this will lead to pogroms against European Jews who have very little protection. William Wrigley, the chewing gum manufacturer, who wants us to buy his gum, will help to promote this reactionary propaganda.</p>
   <p>Misfortune always befalls the Jew. No sooner does Henry Ford quiet down with his propaganda against Jews, than up springs a William Wrigley, who helps to continue it. Jews have no luck.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
