<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">Apr. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Second Examinations for Entrance into the Actors Union Will Be Given Soon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">Apr. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND EXAMINATIONS FOR ENTRANCE INTO THE ACTORS UNION WILL BE GIVEN SOON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of the Actors Union, the question was debated as to whether or not to re-examine new applicants who failed on their first examinations.</p>
   <p>The popular Jewish Actress, Helen Zelinska, who failed for the first time, has asked the union authorities in a letter to please give her another chance to take the examinations. She believes that the sentiment among most actors is that she should be admitted into the Actors Union.</p>
   <p>Miss Zelinska, therefore, asks the union for another chance. She also said that should she fail to make the grade this time, then she will know that the actors don't want her in their union, and that she'll never again burden them with examinations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0039.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The executive committee submitted her request to the union.</p>
   <p>Many speakers participated in the debate. One could tell from their speeches that the members are in favor of giving new examinations.</p>
   <p>There were various opinions on whether new examinations should be held right away or later in the season.</p>
   <p>However, Mr. Guskin, manager of the Actors Union, solved the problem by suggesting a compromise.</p>
   <p>Mr. Guskin spoke frankly and impressively, outlining the whole situation. He admitted the fact that the Jewish Press has antagonized the union and that the union did not deal fairly with some actors.</p>
   <p>Mr. Guskin said: "The union was not only unfair to its candidates, but it <pb facs="5423972_3_0040.jpg" n="3"/>was also unfair to itself." He added that many of the rejected members whom we failed to accept will be given another chance very soon.</p>
   <p>The union will feel then morally justified. Mr. Guskin, therefore, proposed that the week of June 15. should be set aside for those actors who failed [to pass] their first entrance examinations.</p>
   <p>This proposal was accepted by the union in order to get new members.</p>
   <p>Madame Fishon, the wife of the first organizer of the Jewish theaters in Russia, gave a very profound talk. She spoke in behalf of her daughter, Mrs. Arde, an actress, whose application was rejected by the union.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Fishon gave a very vivid and accurate account of the history of the Jewish Theater in Europe and in America. She related the hardships and struggles she went and is still going through for the sake of art and beauty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0041.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>She concluded her speech saying that since her family has sacrificed their happiness for the welfare of the Jewish stage, they deserve a little more consideration by the union than that which they were given.</p>
   <p>There were tears of sympathy in everybody's eyes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Guskin and the committee assured her that Mrs. Arde will be reccommended to take another examination.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
