<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-20">May 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Overestimating Things</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-20">May 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">OVERESTIMATING THINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Tribune, in its issue of last Saturday, discusses editorially the problem of Americanization and especially the problem of the Americanization of the Eastern European Jew and says: But Americanization implies for us a knowledge of American principles and institutions and a loyalty to them based on understanding and an intelligent conviction. It opines that many of the so-called Jewish radicals in this country are not loyal to American principles and institutions in spite of the fact that they might be ready to fight for America in times of war. The problem therefore is: How is it possible to Americanize these elements and to make them ex-radicals.</p>
   <p>If this be the problem with which America is confronted today, then Uncle Sam need not worry at all. The Jewish radicals are less numerous than the Tribune imagines and they are less influential than the Tribune imagines. We do <pb facs="5423972_3_1380.jpg" n="2"/>not want to underestimate matters but we must state once and for all that the number of the sort of Jewish radicals as described by the Tribune does not exceed a few thousand in the country, and they are men and women without any real influence and standing in the community. The average Jewish workingman is not a radical, unless the demand for a living wage and good working conditions be called radicalism. The Jewish middle classes surely are not animated by the spirit of radicalism and needless to say that our rich and wealthy classes are not radically inclined, and if these three classes are not radically minded, where are the Jewish radicals in this country of which the Tribune is so afraid?</p>
   <p>We do not deny that there are a number of Jewish radicals in America, but are there not native Americans of real Anglo-Saxon stock who are radicals, and extreme radicals, too? Are there not to be found in this country a number of Italian, French, Irish, and German radicals as well? Why single out the Jewish radical and represent him as a menace to America, and in addition create the impression that all, or most of the American Jews of Eastern European origin, are radicallyminded?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1381.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Tribune has a perfect right and a good right to wage a war against radicalism in America and it does wage such a war against radicalism. There is nothing to say against this policy of the Tribune. The vast majority of the Jewish papers in America whether printed in Yiddish or in English do the same thing because they, too, realize the danger of radicalism and are as bitterly opposed to it as is the Chicago Daily Tribune, but we consider it unfair to make out a case against three and a half million American Jews because there are a few thousand Jewish radicals in this country who have read themselves out of Judaism because they are as much opposed to Judaism as they are opposed to what we call today Americanism.</p>
   <p>The Tribune overestimates the number of Jewish radicals in this country and it also overestimates their influence.</p>
   <p>There always have been groups of radicals in America and there always [will] be groups of radicals in this country and in other countries. Can the Tribune point out a period in American history when the country was totally free of radicals? Can any historian point out a period in world's history when radicals <pb facs="5423972_3_1382.jpg" n="4"/>and radicalism were unknown? There will always be groups of dissatisfied and malcontents, and radical die-harders, because ours is not a very perfect world and it happens once in a while that men are crossed eyed intellectually and cannot see things in a normal way. It also happens once in a while that men cannot see that two and two make four, but these men are always a small and insignificant minority and they are to be found among all creeds and races. They are not a special Jewish Product. We contend that even if America were an absolute Eden from every point of view, there would still be radicals in this country who would try to improve upon that Eden. But all that has nothing to do with Judaism and it has less to do with American Judaism.</p>
   <p>We agree with the Tribune that Americanization is our common concern and that the public schools are not doing what they might to instruct our youth in the principles of Americanism, and as far as the Jewish community is concerned, we need not assure the Tribune that it, the Jewish community, is ready and willing to do its share and to contribute as much as possible toward the Americanization of our youth by the way of education. The Jewish community is doing it right <pb facs="5423972_3_1383.jpg" n="5"/>along and it is not boasting about it. The Jews are an old race with old traditions and they still have something of that antique grandeur....to do great things silently and in a dignified manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
