<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1908-08-28">August 28, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Development of the Trade Unions</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1908-08-28">August 28, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE TRADE UNIONS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Labor organizations, unions where workers organize with united powers in order to improve their conditions, to receive higher wages, shorter hours and more sanitary work-shops, better and fairer conditions from the bosses and foreman, is an inevitable result of the present social and industrial life.</p>
   <p>As long as business and industry have not yet been greatly developed, the workers were dispersed and scattered in small shops and small factories; they did not understand nor realize their common interests; many times they protested, agitated, but except for a few places, without a plan, without a system, without any organization, it was not a general systematic movement. Such outbursts of unknown dissatisfactions took place that unions organized wherever capitalism developed. Living conditions drove the workers to organize and with united strength they were able to force the capitalists to alleviate conditions. And, when the workers are now working shorter hours, are getting better wages and are living a more decent life than they did fifty or a hundred years back, it is due to the steady courageous struggle that the organized workers have been carrying on with the capitalists to protect the interests of the working class.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
