<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-02">July 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">3500 Workers Leave Their Shops Today at 10 A. M</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1019</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1019.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-02">July 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">3500 WORKERS LEAVE THEIR SHOPS TODAY AT 10 A. M</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today at 10 A. M. sharp the strike of Chicago's cloakmakers will begin. All of the 3,500 organized workers in the local cloakmaking industry will leave their respective shops at the summons of their union and will thus start the struggle for a living wage.</p>
   <p>A union explanation states that the workers are forced to take this last step because the series of conferences with the manufacturers resulted in nothing at all; the bosses stubbornly refuse to accept the demands for a living wage in the face of the present high cost of living.</p>
   <p>It was the hope of the union, during this time, to be able to avert the strike by exerting every means of arriving at a peaceful settlement. But <pb facs="5423972_3_1020.jpg" n="2"/>when mediation failed, nothing more remained but to display unity and strength which today leads right to a desertion of all Chicago cloak shops.</p>
   <p>At the conferences which began the previous week, President Benjamin Schlesinger and the representatives of the Local Cloak and Skirt Makers' Joint Board explained to the manufacturers the demands of the workers. The most important of these, identical with those won some time ago by the New York cloakmakers and with those existing throughout the country, are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Work by the week instead of piece work.</p>
   <p>2. Minimum wage scale for all branches of the i industry.</p>
   <p>3. A forty-four hour week.</p>
   <p>4. Time and one half for overtime.</p>
   <p>5. Pay for legal holidays.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1021.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus the negotiations and the dealings on both sides were begun. At Monday evening's conference it appeared that the strike was averted because the bosses, as stated in yesterday's Courier, had already conceded the forty-four hour week. But on the point of wages for every type of worker in the industry, it became apparent that the manufacturers steadily refused to give to certain classes of workers a sufficient subsistence wage. Instead they set one that failed to meet even the wages earned by cloakmakers at piece work. Representatives of the Union understood that simply acquiescing to a forty-four hour week meant nothing if the workmen do not receive a living wage.</p>
   <p>Many thought that this action was probably nothing more than a means of delay on the part of the bosses to weaken strike enthusiasm. But yesterday morning the representatives of the Union demonstratively left the conference, and thus the general strike began.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1022.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At seven in the evening all chairmen were assembled at Union headquarters for a special meeting. Word of the strike brought forth storms of enthusiasm which were strongest on Division Street where hundreds of cloakmakers waited impatiently to hear the news.</p>
   <p>Upon leaving the shops with the well-disciplined workmen, the chairmen received "red circulars" with instructions and the name of the hall to which they were to go.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
