<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-07">Oct. 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In the Labor World</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-07">Oct. 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE LABOR WORLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unemployment that has taken hold of the whole needle trades industry is also an important problem for Chicago's Amalgamated Clothing Workers. The unemployment in this industry is not entirely the result of the high prices which the clothing manufacturers have established due to abnormal conditions; there is also another more profound and more serious cause, says Mr. Sam Levin, manager of the Chicago Amalgamated.</p>
   <p>In the opinion of Mr. Levin, the scarcity of raw materials, artificially created through the closing of the mills several months ago, plays an important role in the unemployment problem.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Amalgamated is not as seriously affected by this unemployment as are other unions in the needle trades industry. It is true that the Amalgamated <pb facs="5423972_3_0684.jpg" n="2"/>members are not working normal hours and their earnings, naturally, are less, but the percentage of completely unemployed is negligible. The reason for this is the strong control of the Union over its members. The Union regulates the work so that it is divided equally among all.</p>
   <p>The Employment Bureau of the Amalgamated is performing a great service for its members by providing them with new jobs as soon as they lose their old ones, thus keeping the army of unemployed as small as possible. It is, therefore, in the interests of the unemployed members of the Amalgamated to take advantage of the Employment Bureau and not solicit each shop separately for employment. The old system of soliciting jobs was played out long ago, and [this is] especially [true] at a time of abnormal unemployment. Such solicitation makes the workers look cheap in the eyes of the manufacturers, who in the meantime obtain a little additional courage and begin to seek ways of taking advantage of the unemployment situation for their personal interests.</p>
   <p>This is the opinion of the leaders of the Amalgamated and the general membership <pb facs="5423972_3_0685.jpg" n="3"/>will know how to evaluate the opinion of their leaders.</p>
   <p>A unique strike is now being conducted by the Chicago Dressmakers Union, Local 100, a strike that will have a definite place in the history of the American labor movement.</p>
   <p>The unique aspect of this strike lies in the fact that the Union called the strike because the firm of Shatzburg and Kite of 308 Jackson Boulevard, which has employed only Negro workers, Union members, dismissed all of them from work. When the organizer of the Union, Julius Ginsburg, asked the officials of the firm for an explanation of the lockout, the officials declared that they had called the lockout simply because the workers were Negroes. They were not seeking a fight with the Union, they simply did not wish to employ Negro workers; they wanted white workers. Let the Union supply them with white labor, and the matter would be settled.</p>
   <p>The Dressmakers Union took up the problem immediately and decided to act as a <pb facs="5423972_3_0686.jpg" n="4"/>progressive right-thinking labor organization should: it refused with contempt the proposal of the firm to betray its colored members, and called a strike in the shop, which is now going on.</p>
   <p>The Negro problem came to the foreground in this Union in 1917, when the Union conducted a general strike. Negroes played a prominent part in the failure of this strike when they became scabs and took the jobs of the strikers.</p>
   <p>After the general strike, the Union realized that it must consider the colored workers very seriously. It then launched an intensive campaign to organize the colored workers, and succeeded to a certain extent. About two hundred Negroes are now members of the Dressmakers Union.</p>
   <p>Having solved one problem, the Union is now confronted with another: The manufacturers who used the colored workers to break the strike of the white workers do not care to employ them any longer, now that there is no strike, because they contend that the colored workers are not as competent and productive <pb facs="5423972_3_0687.jpg" n="5"/>as the white workers. Therefore, if there is to be a union, with a union wage scale, then the wage scale should be paid to white workers and not to Negroes.</p>
   <p>While the manufacturers, at every opportunity and for various reasons, are trying to dismiss the Negroes from their jobs, the Union is concentrating all its efforts upon providing them with new jobs as quickly as possible. Through the Employment Bureau of the Union, the colored workers are sent to jobs faster than the white workers. When the firm of Shatzburg and Kite, which has employed colored workers only, dismissed them from their jobs, the Union had no alternative but to declare a strike there and to protect the rights of its colored members.</p>
   <p>This honorable action on the part of the Dressmakers Union will certainly be commended by the entire labor movement, and the strike undoubtedly will occupy a special page in the history of the struggle of American Labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
