<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-02">Mar. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Rotten Eggs Used as a Weapon in the Dressmakers' Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-02">Mar. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ROTTEN EGGS USED AS A WEAPON IN THE DRESSMAKERS' STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dressmakers who have remained at work in the shops where a strike has been called,yesterday experienced the taste of rotten eggs. Yesterday, when the strikebreakers who work for the Ribak And Lonzis Dress Company, came out on the street, they were met with a shower of eggs that had been fresh at the time of George Washington. Most of the strikebreakers who did not object to working under the conditions dictated by the manufacturers, objected a lot to the smell of the eggs. Many of the girls returned to the shop to clean up their dresses.</p>
   <p>Many of the girls who picket the shops were arrested Friday and yesterday. The union bailed them out at once.</p>
   <p>A delegation of the manufactures told Mayor Dever yesterday that they want to negotiate directly with the strikers, rather than with Mr. Perlstein. The strikers refuse to consider this. The union has given up its fight against <pb facs="5423972_3_0808.jpg" n="2"/>Perlstein. Even his opponents declared yesterday that as far as the present strike is concerned, it is of no importance that the members of the union were against him before the strike. His strongest opponents, the left-wingers, are among the most active strikers.</p>
   <p>The right- and left-wing workers have united to win the strike, declared the union. Many of the expelled left-wing workers have been appointed to responsible strike positions.</p>
   <p>There will be a big demonstration of the pickets tomorrow morning, Monday, in the district of the shops.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
