<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">On the Field of Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">Retail Clothing Clerks Win a Strike in Twenty-Four Hours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE FIELD OF LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Retail Clothing Clerks Win a Strike in Twenty-Four Hours</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The retail clerks of Monteband's three clothing stores on the West Side went on strike last Thursday. The stores are members of the International Retailers Protective Association. They struck because their employer acted "smart" and refused to obey the rules of the union, which orders retail stores to close on Monday, Wednesday and Friday at 6 P.M. However he quickly realized that nowadays you cannot act "smart" with organized workers. And it took only twenty-four hours for the clothing salesmen to win the strike.</p>
   <p>In a conversation with Mr. I. Harris, an active member of the [Retail] Clerks Union, he asserted that this is not the first time that a struggle has been conducted against Mr. Monteband. Three years ago the union struck against this firm for three whole months, but eventually the union came out victorious. "These days, however", Mr. Harris said, "it is not necessary to strike for months <pb facs="5423972_3_1066.jpg" n="2"/>at a stretch in order to win better working conditions. Today things go, as they say, 'by steam'."</p>
   <p>When the officer of the Union was asked whether all the West Side gent's furnishing stores obey the rules of the union, he said that all except one close on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday at 6:00 P.M. This one, which is on Twelfth Street near Ashland Boulevard, stubbornly remains open late on these nights, and the salespeople are naturally compelled to work long hours. "However," Mr. Harris said, "this storekeeper will soon realize that union members cannot patronize stores where the salespeople are compelled to work long hours."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
