<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-03-27">March 27, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-03-27">March 27, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Great Victory of the Amalgamated. Wins the Kuppenheimer Shop. - The Fortress of The Association.</p>
   <p>The firm will reemploy all the strikers and will also pay them for the time they were on strike, and above all will recognize the shop committees.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated Union celebrated one of the greatest victories, in the history of this brave and aggressive union yesterday. The Amalgamated settled the strike, yesterday, that had lasted almost 3 weeks. Almost 1,200 Kuppenheimer tailors went back to work. The settlement read as follows: All strikers must be taken back to work. 2 - Shop committees must be recognized. 3 - The strikers must receive full pay for the time they were on strike. The Chicago Tailoring Co. employing about 600 tailors also signed an agreement yesterday and so did the firm of Dobi Rosenthal.</p>
   <p>It is reported that the Amalgamated is well on the way toward organizing the workers of the contracting firms of the South West Side. Our friends, Mayor Thompson's police, for no reason at all arrested about 60 pickets near the shop <pb facs="5423972_3_1049.jpg" n="2"/>of Ederheimer and Stein. Near Chas. Kaufman's shop, the police beat up the pickets, then arrested them. The strike at Cohn and Rissman is going on very lively and the workers are sure of a victory.</p>
   <p>The business agent of the Raincoat Makers Local 54, Mr. Greenspan, informs us that Nathan Alshanski was here, in Chicago, hunting for scabs for the Chicago Rubber Clothing Co. of Racine Wisconsin, where 200 raincoat makers are on strike. A Chicago strike breaking firm sent a truck full of scabs to Racine. The strikers attacked them and almost the whole town came to assist the strikers. Many fights with the police took place. There is a rumor that two scabs were shot.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
