<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-27">October 27, 1910</date><title level="a">A General Strike in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-10-27">October 27, 1910</date><title level="a">A GENERAL STRIKE IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The big tailor strike in Chicago has already affected over thirty clothing manufacturers, who are considered the biggest in the men's clothing trade such as Hart Schaffner &amp; Marxs, Kuppenheimer &amp; Company, Royal Tailors, International Tailors, County National Tailors, Hirsch Wickmire, Decker and Cohen, J. L. Taylor, Price &amp; Levy, Ederheimer &amp; Stein, Schonebrin, Rose and Company, Levin &amp; Company, Isendrath, Kling Bros., Kohn &amp; Rissman, Phillipson Schieff, Reliable Tailoring Company and so forth.</p>
   <p>The present strike will no doubt spread in Milwaukee also, for it was found that Chicago clothing is being manufactured in that city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1167.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Union recognition is the main point demanded and the tailoring workers are determined to carry on this fight to a finish until victory is assured.</p>
   <p>In the special order shops the worker seems to be contented with his lot as a worker, but he insists on the recognition of the Union. The strike in these special shops is supervised by Mr. Phillip Rosenstein, who stated to a Jewish Courier reporter, that from indications it looks very favorable for an early settlement in favor of the strikers. A few of the bosses already have made overtures and a speedy settlement is in sight. According to Mr. Karin's statement to a reporter of the Jewish Courier, "As president of District Council #6, I hope that all strike leaders will see to it that all non-union shops also will be closed by Saturday. In fact, I already have the assurance that all shops will be closed in due time."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1168.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The strike is growing and spreading mighty fast. An additional 2,000 workers joined the strikers yesterday, so it seems that the general strike is in full progress and victory is in sight. There are nearly 75,000 workers out on this general strike. A committee of 28 was selected to meet the representatives of Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx. At this meeting a communication in the form of compromise from that firm was read that they agree to all demands except recognition of the Union. Of course this proposition was flatly rejected by the committee, for that is the main contention of the workers. It is the recognition of the Union in which the workers are mostly interested at present, and with nothing short of a complete acceptance of the workers demands will the strike come to an end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
