<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-23">Feb. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dressmakers Win Strike; Agreement Signed in Two Hours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0837</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0837.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-23">Feb. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DRESSMAKERS WIN STRIKE; AGREEMENT SIGNED IN TWO HOURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at 10 A. M., all the dressmakers responded to the call of the Joint Board in Chicago and walked out on strike. Two hours later, all the workers in the shops belonging to the Dress Manufacturers' Association returned to work, having won their demands.</p>
   <p>One hour after all the dress factories had been emptied, four men met--Barney Shaffer, chairman of the Joint Board of all local unions, his attorney, Peter Sussman, who represented the union, Carl Sobel, president of the Dress Manufacturers' Association, and his lawyer, L. Bosky who represented the dress manufacturers--and the union agreement was signed. The workers in the shops that had signed the agreement, returned to work in the afternoon. A small number of dressmakers, whose bosses were too busy to sign the agreement, remained on strike.</p>
   <p>The union leaders are extremely pleased with the result of the strike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0838.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only did the workers in the organized shops stop their work at exactly ten o'clock, as had been decided by the Joint Board, but even the workers in nonunion shops put down their work and walked out on strike. In approximately twenty minutes, both halls, at 180 West Washington Street and on Ashland and Milwaukee Avenues, were filled with jubilant men and women. Every new group of men assumed a holiday spirit and many were grateful to the union officials for calling a strike on a day when the whole nation celebrates the birthday of a great revolutionist--George Washington.</p>
   <p>The quick settlement is a remarkable victory for the Joint Board, which called the strike upon its own responsibility. The new officers and business agents of the Joint Board, who work harmoniously in the interests of the workers of that trade, are to be congratulated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
