<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-15">July 15, 1913</date><title level="a">Workers Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-15">July 15, 1913</date><title level="a">WORKERS GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Garment Workers Aid Conference officially dissolved last Sunday morning, and a committee of seven have undertaken to call a meeting of delegates from trade unions in order to establish a United Hebrew Trades. This was also approved by the dissolved conference. In our opinion this was the one and only good proposal by the two months' old conference, viz. to dissolve and to call a meeting for the establishment of a United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The committee will appeal to the fifteen Jewish trade unions, through newspaper announcements and personal contacts, to elect delegates to the first organizational meeting, on Sunday morning, August 3, at 1125 Blue Island Avenue. It is the duty of each union which will hold meetings in the meantime, to consider this matter and elect delegates.</p>
   <p>It is for the benefit of the unions to have a United Hebrew Trades, because by uniting into one body, they will strengthen the already existing unions and also will organize new trades and unions. It will also help the Jewish unions which have technical disputes with their internationals, e.g. the Progressive Cigar Makers Union, the Independent Painters Union, the Independent Carpenters Union, etc. A united body will also take up the question of strike funds.</p>
   <p>A United Hebrew Trades in one of the most important labor institutions, and it <pb facs="5423972_3_0431.jpg" n="2"/>must receive full moral and financial support from the Jewish Trade Unions. A United Hebrew Trades can only be successful in its aims if it is loyal to its tasks and principles. The mission of a United Hebrew Trades is to do trade union work only. As a body, a United Hebrew Trades is a necessity now and always. The Jewish trade unions should, without any complaints, elect delegates to the first meeting. It is also worthy to remark that they should send the most able and loyal members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
