<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In Chicago's Jewish Unions</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN CHICAGO'S JEWISH UNIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fight in the millinery trade between the rank and file of the Capmakers Union and those of the United Hatters of North America, which has been going on for years, and has been harmful to the workers employed in this trade, has intensified in bitterness. How much harm has been done the millinery workers, as a result of the wrangling among the rank and file, can be seen from the present strike at the Eiger Millinery Factory, where two hundred girls walked out, demanding recognition of their union and a raise in wages. This strike, as well as other strikes in this trade, has aroused the hostility of the rank and file in both unions. Each one accuses the other of dishonesty.</p>
   <p>The United Hatters of North America accuses the Capmakers Union of permitting its members to work, while others are striking, and the Capmakers Union accuses the United Hatters of North America of declaring a strike against the Capmakers <pb facs="5423972_3_0933.jpg" n="2"/>Union and of permitting their membership to scab. Naturally, the officials of both unions deny each others accusations.</p>
   <p>If it were merely a question of whether the officials of one or the other union was right or wrong, then it wouldn't be worth the paper on which these lines are written. The issue at stake, however, does not concern the officials, but rather the membership at large of both unions, who really suffer from this conflict. Even if the accusations are absolute falsehoods, still they hurt the workers because they create misunderstandings among the rank and file. Furthermore, this encourages the manufacturers to carry on their fight against the workers because they hope to win, as a result of the lack of unity among the workers. But, if the accusations of the union officials are partly, or entirely true, and if the workers actually scab against one another, then an ugly and disgusting crime is being committed by the rank and file of this industry. The sooner this crime is eradicated, the quicker will the workers in this industry regain their strength--then their [economic] conditions will rapidly improve.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0934.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These crimes will cease only when the officials of both unions, who are so terribly antagonistic to one another, who cannot see the just claims of the other side, will place the dispute in the hands of impartial representatives of other unions, who will bend every effort to unite both organizations.</p>
   <p>The general membership of both unions is made up of honest workers; men and women who earn their living by hard work, and it is in their interests that both unions should come to a definite understanding, and, with united forces, should fight and strive for the improvement of their economic conditions. The loathsome situation in the millinery trade must stop and the rank and file must demand that this strife should cease at once.</p>
   <p>In the Amalgamated</p>
   <p>The unauthorized strike of the 800 cutters in some of the Hart, Schaffner and Marx factories was certainly not a happy incident, because it proved that even <pb facs="5423972_3_0935.jpg" n="4"/>in the Amalgamated, one of the strongest and most liberal unions in America, there are many members who do not understand the significance and importance of their organization. It is not a question of whether or not the demands of the cutters were just; they were bound to submit to the rules of the organization which has gained for them the satisfactory conditions which exist in the tailoring industry today.</p>
   <p>If the cutters had any demands to make, they should have brought them before their union, which is in a position to fight for those demands, that is, if they are just.</p>
   <p>But, the step taken by the cutters to fight for their demands on their own initiative, has broken the organization's discipline, one of the pillars upon which the organization rests. Without discipline, and sincere confidence and belief in one another, no organization can exist. Yet, notwithstanding the great mistake made by the cutters, there was no reason to neglect the matter, and, therefore, it sounded ridiculous, when so-called authorities in union <pb facs="5423972_3_0936.jpg" n="5"/>matters boasted that they had known of the existence of the strike, but in the interests of the union, had kept quiet on the subject.</p>
   <p>What kind of a secret was it? First of all, the 800 cutters and trimmers certainly knew about the strike; several thousand tailors knew about it as well. In the factory where the strike occurred, the secret was known to hundreds of workers, who, without a doubt, related the fact to their co-workers. If, in Chicago, there were several thousand Amalgamated members who were not aware of the strike, they certainly had the right to know about it. It harmed no one when the truth became known.</p>
   <p>Those who are afraid of telling the workers the truth, show what a narrow conception they have of the members of the Amalgamated. They also indicated how they misjudged the great organization which was successful in procuring for its members not only higher wages, to cover the high cost of living, but also a higher standard of living. If it was able to accomplish that, it certainly was in a position to settle a small dispute within its ranks. The general membership, <pb facs="5423972_3_0937.jpg" n="6"/>which was capable of creating such a large organization, certainly is able to understand how to handle such an incident. The healthy instinct of the rank and file will steadily lead them upon the right road. If it is possible to discuss and settle this incident in an earnest and intelligent manner, then it will strengthen the morale of the ranks of the Amalgamated, and will unite the membership in a more brotherly fashion. It will also increase the confidence of the rank and file in their organization, thus making the repetition of such an incident in the future, impossible.</p>
   <p>Among the Cigarmakers</p>
   <p>There is no encouraging news from the cigarmakers. It is no secret that the last strike conducted by the cigarmakers ended in a fiasco. The largest cigar manufacturers of Chicago have left the city, moving to smaller towns where the cigar trade is not organized and labor costs are cheaper.</p>
   <p>Of the three thousand members in the locals of the Chicago Cigarmakers Union <pb facs="5423972_3_0938.jpg" n="7"/>before the general strike, only two thousand remain. Of the nine hundred members of the Progressive Local 527, only 450 members in good standing remain, and of these, only 175 are employed.</p>
   <p>These facts were made known by Jacob Belove, president of Local 527, who said that although his report was pretty terrible, he did not want to keep it a secret. That these facts are known to the remaining Chicago manufacturers, is proved by the demands which they made this week upon the Cigarmakers Union to reduce the price of labor on the eight-and ten-cent cigars.</p>
   <p>From all indications, the Chicago cigar manufacturers have not as yet realized the true spirit of the cigarmakers, who have fought so heroically, and suffered in the struggle to improve their living conditions through the strength of their union. The cigar manufacturers are greatly mistaken if they think that the spirit of the cigarmakers has been broken, and that they [the manufacturers] will again initiate the old-time sweat-shop system.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0939.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>If the cigarmakers decide to turn down this demand, then they will be victorious. Otherwise, the remaining cigar manufacturers will also be forced to move out of Chicago, and the cigarmakers will then earn their living by manufacturing cigars themselves, or they will shift to other trades.</p>
   <p>The Cleaners and Dyers</p>
   <p>Credit must be given to the cleaners and dyers for their enormous sacrifice and fighting spirit. Though forced to call off their strike, after it had gone on for many months, the cleaners and dyers did not become discouraged. With deep earnestness and true loyalty, they continued to build and strengthen their organization, and now, they are ready once more to begin the fight, with fresh courage and renewed enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>It is expected that those disappointed members, who have left the ranks of the union, will return to its fold, and, with united effort, will renew the fight for the recognition of their union and for better economic conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
