<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-16">November 16, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting of Cloak Makers Condemns Communist Conspiracy to Confiscate Treasury and Call Members to Vote "No" Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-11-16">November 16, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING OF CLOAK MAKERS CONDEMNS COMMUNIST CONSPIRACY TO CONFISCATE TREASURY AND CALL MEMBERS TO VOTE "NO" TODAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Approximately four hundred cloak makers, rain coat makers, ladies tailors, and dress makers, last evening, in the Labor Lyceum, unanimously condemned the attempt of the Communist leaders to confiscate the Finance Department and abolish the office of Secretary-Treasurer.</p>
   <p>Philip Davia, chairman of Pressers, Local #18, and chairman of the meeting explained in a brief talk why the delegates of three local of the joint Board, had called this meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1322.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A list of speakers talked about the scheme of the Communists, who want to destroy the office of the Secretary-Treasurer, an act that is against the Constitution of the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union. They all pointed out by facts, that the Communists are lying when they try to convince the members that money will be saved if they permit the manager to have charge over the Finance department. All exclaimed that the manager cannot fill that office as Secretary-Treasurer.</p>
   <p>It also was pointed out that the Communist politicians printed the ballot in English only, in order that the Jewish member, who is accustomed to vote in Jewish, should not know how to vote.</p>
   <p>We the members of Locals #5, #18, #59, #81, #100 and #104, assembled at a mass-meeting to protest against the Administration of the Joint Board, and the manner in which it has tried to destroy the office of Secretary-Treasurer, which we consider as an important office in our Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1323.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whereas, the present Administration attempts to fool the members through false arguments, that they will save money by destroying the office, which will result in employing non-union members at wages, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, they are doing this for no other purpose than to oust the present Secretary-Treasurer, who does not agree with their policies and they have no one from their machine to fill this position, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, they refused to permit three locals to write a letter to the members about the referendum, in which to clarify the reasons why the office of the Secretary-Treasurer should not be destroyed, and the circular which they have distributed is an ugly document, which is an insult to all members and full of insinuation, that avoids the issue, and</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1324.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Whereas, the Joint Board delegates of these locals asked the Joint Board for permission to explain to the members why the Secretarial office should not be destroyed and that they were refused, therefore</p>
   <p>Be it Resolved, to protest against the false tactics of the Joint Board to force the leadership of one man upon the members.</p>
   <p>Be it also resolved, that it is the opinion of the membership to continue the office of Secretary-Treasurer and not to introduce any politics into the Finance Department of the Joint Board.</p>
   <p>The members are urged to vote "no" in the referendum to confiscate the Finance Department.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
