<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-01-20">January 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Workers Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-01-20">January 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week we gave a report of our tenth annual celebration of the Women's Trade Union League, our aim was to interest the women workers in organizational work and in order to gain this point we will be obliged to give a short summary of the women labor movement in general and of the women union activities that have occurred here of late.</p>
   <p>The installation of machinery made a great disturbance in industrial life and not only the men, but the women, were also forced to leave their shop and run from one factory to another to sell their labor power. Later, the more perfected machinery enabled the manufacturer to divide <pb facs="5423972_3_0393.jpg" n="2"/>the work among the men, women, and children, as the work with the aid of the machinery became so simple that children were able to do it as well as the men. The manufacturers realized the savings in employing children and women, so it was not long before the women in most cases took the places of men.</p>
   <p>The employers, realizing that the women can get along with less than the men, cut the women's wages to suit themselves.</p>
   <p>Naturally the women were not conscious of what harm they were doing to the men, circumstances forced them to take what they got; the more broad-minded male workers realized that.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0394.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The women were always good producers - the woman always worked, she plowed, planted, cut the wheat, milked the cows, churned the butter, ground the wheat, made the flour, baked the bread, raised her children, taught them as best she knew, she really was a queen in her own home.</p>
   <p>With the development of industry her activities gradually vanished. The cost of living rose. The husband's wages were not sufficient to meet the bills and in that way the women were forced to leave their house duties and go to work in the shops, factories, stores, and offices. Today we have a few million women working outside of their homes, and to protect this ever growing army of women workers, we organized the women's trade unions known as the Women's Trade Union League. Women's trade unions exist since about the middle of 1900. Women were even permitted as members of the male workers first union known as the Knights of Labor, which has developed into the great organization now called the American Federation of Labor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0395.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Women's Trade Union League helps organize women workers into unions and teaches them the principle of unionization and educates each new member on the relationship between education, work, and life.</p>
   <p>Her platform demands, organization of workers in trade unions, equal pay for equal work, an eight hour work day, a minimum wage scale, and equal rights for women. It helps strikers, and devotes its time and energy primarily in informing the world of the actual conditions existing in the different trades.</p>
   <p>As hard a task as it is, the Women's Trade Union League still tries to realize its program and is very successful. It has a membership of many thousand men and women who pay one dollar a year dues each, and besides a membership of many unions and clubs which sympathize with its program. Its goal is to help all men and women workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
