<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-10">Jan. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Chairman of Investigating Committee of Retail Clerks Union Assaulted at Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-10">Jan. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">CHAIRMAN OF INVESTIGATING COMMITTEE OF RETAIL CLERKS UNION ASSAULTED AT MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Max Bernstein, chairman of the investigating committee of the Retail Clerks Union, Local 195, was attacked and brutally beaten by a group of members Monday night, as he was leaving the meeting hall in the Ashland Auditorium. Bernstein, who now lies seriously injured at his home, 838 West Roosevelt Road, told the following story, in a weak voice, to a Courier reporter:</p>
   <p>Sometime ago, the United Hebrew Trades, at the request of the retail merchants and the members of the Clerks Union, brought charges against Harry Winick, president, and Leon Green, business agent; they demanded that a committee investigate the charge that $3,000 graft had been received by Winick and Green from members of the Retail Merchants Association, at the time that a new agreement with the clerks was signed. A committee of nine, with Mr. Bernstein as chairman, was appointed to <pb facs="5423972_3_0499.jpg" n="2"/>investigate, and after investigating the evidence the committee publicly rendered a decision that the charges against the officers were unfounded. Now it has been found that this report was issued with the stipulation that it recommend the resignation of the present officers of the Local. When this was put before a vote, the first part of the report was approved by the membership and the second part was tabled. Thereupon a special election meeting was immediately called and the same officers were reelected.</p>
   <p>With the aid of Mr. Bernstein and other members of the committee, who claim that they have been double-crossed, the United Hebrew Trades again seeks to investigate the charges of graft, according to the following plan:</p>
   <p>The Union shall elect a new committee of three, excluding the members of the previous committee of nine; the United Hebrew Trades shall appoint a committee of three, and both committees shall jointly select three impartial people for the investigation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0500.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the Union's last meeting, which was held Monday evening, this proposal was taken up and it was decided that the Union committee should include a member of the previous committee, viz., Mr. Cooper, and also, that the United Hebrew Trades' committee, which consists of A. Bisno, Hyman Schoolman, and Louis Shaffer, cannot be recognized because of the presence of Mr. Shaffer who is suspected of having close connections with the Retail Merchants Association.</p>
   <p>The friends of Mr. Green and Mr. Winick claim that the whole affair is a frame-up, manipulated by certain people who seek to make I. Harris, president, and Leon Hannock, business agent of the Retail Clerks Union, and that the principle involved is only a struggle for jobs.</p>
   <p>It is rumored in the ranks of the retail clerks that the whole matter will be turned over to the States Attorney.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
