<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-27">March 27, 1922</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-27">March 27, 1922</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference which was called by the United Hebrew trades, concerning the organizational campaign for the unorganized workers, was held yesterday at the Workmen's Circle Lyceum, where many Unions were represented by delegates and officers. Comrade Lerner, of the Jewish compositors, was appointed chairman.</p>
   <p>Morris Zeskind of the United Hebrew Trades Organization Committee, explained the purpose of the conference. He related the condition of the working class, enumerating the causes that weakened the strong unions and broke the small unions. He showed the necessity for all workers, organized or unorganized, to carry on intensive agitation, or organization among the Jewish working masses. Many representatives of unions partook in the discussions concerning this issue. Several criticized the present form of organization in the Unions, which hinders them in protecting the unions that are on strike, because their international unions are organized on the basis of craft unions. They proposed that the United Hebrew Trades carry on an educational-campaign, to the effect that the Unions of industries should not oppose each other, but cooperate solidly against the common enemy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was decided that an executive should be elected to draw up a plan on work that could be organized and that the plan be reported at the next meeting of the Conference, Sunday A.M., May 9, in Labor Lyceum.</p>
   <p>The following were appointed on the Organization Committee:</p>
   <p>Messrs. Cohen, Ladies' Tailors Union; Reinstein, Local 5, Cloakmakers; Millstein, Furriers' Union; Lerner, Jewish Compositors' Union; Lingender, Amalgamated Cigarmakers Union; Schusterman, City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle; Leon, Hannock, and Ziskind, United Hebrew Trades.</p>
   <p>The same committee was ordered to visit the unions not belonging to the United Hebrew Trades, and urge them to join and help the organizations in their work.</p>
   <p>The committee will also visit the locals of the United Hebrew Trades, whose delegates neglect their duty by being absent at the general meeting of the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
