<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-18">Nov. 18, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Workmen's Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-18">Nov. 18, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WORKMEN'S GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We call your attention to the appeal of the United Alliance, that we print here concerning the Philadelphia and St. Louis cloakmakers strike. Relief is an absolute immediate necessity; therefore, let each union and union person betake himself actively to this great work without losing a single opportunity to gather contributions.</p>
   <p>It is in order to warn everyone who wishes to donate for the above mentioned strikers, to give only to those who present credentials from the United Jewish Alliance since there are many "fakers" who are collecting money in the name of the strikers. No one knows what becomes of them. Please be careful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1125.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"To all Jewish workers and to the general public of Chicago!</p>
   <p>"Friends! For eight weeks now the cloakmakers of Philadelphia and St. Louis have been waging a bitter battle against their bosses for the right to be organized and for better living conditions. As in all clashes between capital and labor, in this case also the manufacturers have on their side the services of the police to split the heads of the strikers. Thus, in Philadelphia there have been three so victimized. The strikers have not lost their courage but stand steadfast by their demands for more bread in their homes, and less slavery in the factories. The strikers understand only too well that this is no mere local strike, that behind their bosses stand all the cloak manufacturers and all of the manufacturers associations of America. They wish to break the cloakmakers' union that has been established with so much effort and sacrifice and which, to the workman, is the only defender against turnover and slavery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1126.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Therefore, my friends! The results of this strike will determine whether Jewish workmen, through their unions, will be able to achieve a better standard of living for themselves and their families, or whether they shall again sink to their previous low level of misery and need. The strikers of these two cities are not merely striving for themselves, but for all Jewish workmen in America. For 18 long weeks have the cloakmakers themselves, through their international and local unions, carried the burden of the struggle. But now the time has come when all the Jewish workmen of all the other trades must come to their aid.</p>
   <p>"The United Jewish Alliance of Chicago appeals, therefore, to all Jewish workmen and the general public of Chicago: Help! Help these brave warriors who fight a battle that is ours too. Will we permit hunger to drive these men back into the factories and thus endanger the stand <pb facs="5423972_3_1127.jpg" n="4"/>of all Jewish unions? No! We must not permit this. Do what you can to secure immediate aid. Make collections in the shops, see that your organizations contribute to this cause.</p>
   <p>"Committees of the United Jewish Alliance will confer with all workmen and progressive organizations. Let every union, every workmen's organization, help with as much as possible.</p>
   <p>"Sunday, November 23, committees under the auspices of the alliance will make a house to house collection....</p>
   <p>"Friends; we hope that this appeal will find a warm response and that you will all aid.</p>
   <p>With friendly regards,</p>
   <p>The United Jewish Alliance of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
