<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-31">Jan. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Conversation with Mr. Mazur - President of the Jewish Federation:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-31">Jan. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A CONVERSATION WITH MR. MAZUR - PRESIDENT OF THE JEWISH FEDERATION:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Jewish workers can be organized only in Jewish unions that understand their psychology, language and mode of living," declared Mazur.</p>
   <p>On this foundation he built for the excellent future of the federation. He is very much inspired with this central body, and is convinced that in time, all the Jewish workers joining a union will have the same inspiration, for they will realize that the masses of Jewish workers, who came from abroad can under no circumstances be organized by non-Jewish unions, for they cannot adapt even themselves to the half-Americanized Jewish workers, and for just that reason the Jewish trades are so far from unionism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0371.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To organize Jewish workers requires particular abilities. The Jewish worker is to a certain extent more idealistic than the non-Jewish worker. You cannot attract him with that which attracts other workers. The Gentile leaders have so far proven themselves unqualified for this task. This, everyone can see by the tens of thousands of unorganized Jewish workers in Chicago, according to Mazur. In his opinion, we need separate Jewish unions and particularly a central body such as the United Jewish Federation to see that the work of the unions is carried on with a conscientious plan and order. Mr. Mazur-also pointed out that the Jewish unions cannot exist when they are separated from one another. They must all be connected, centralized and united, because only in that manner can they best carry on the organization work and improve the existence of each individual union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0372.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"There is the task that the federation undertakes. It establishes a united harmony among the various Jewish unions.</p>
   <p>"The carpenters interest themselves deeply in the work and existence of the tailors, cigarmakers, capmakers, etc. And this is brought about through, strenuous efforts and hard work. The federation is a young organization, but the work there is manifold,"Mazur said.</p>
   <p>"Before, every union tried to shift for itself, as for instance, the cloakmakers who thought that in organizing their industry, they didn't need the help of any one; likewise with the furriers, the bakers, and other Jewish unions. The work was limited, their locals were small, and <pb facs="5423972_3_0373.jpg" n="4"/>so were their prospects, and their opinions were limited and one sided. But when the work of the Jewish unions began developing they immediately felt the need of a strong central body to bind the unions together and see that one union helps the other proceed in its work. This, according to my opinion, is the most important work of the federation,"Mr. Mazur added.</p>
   <p>He also believes that as it progresses, the federation is more and more being liked by the unions and the workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0374.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This being brought about, in his opinion by the people realizing that the federation plays an important role in the life of Jewish workers. Mazur confirmed his statement with the case of the Jewish carpenters who were locked out of the federation because they had a dispute with the ladies straw hat operators' local. The Chicago Federation of Labor surely made a mistake in locking out the carpenters' local, but the most interesting thing was that the Jewish local brought their case to the federation where it found a warm welcome. The federation took up their fight, as it does the grievance of all other of its unions.</p>
   <p>The federation organized the Jewish bookbinders in Chicago - over 300 of them. The Gentile bookbinders' union has been in existence for many years, but it never occurred to them that the Jewish bookbinders were being <pb facs="5423972_3_0375.jpg" n="6"/>treated worse than they, getting smaller wages, working in the worst shops. Now they are organized in a local, and the federation is doing all in its power to have them taken into the International. The federation has also organized the laundry workers, as well as the boot and shoe repair workers, and a type setters' club, whose intention it is to see that the union work is made known and to see that all printing is done in union shops.</p>
   <p>The federation could make possible for the Jewish bakers that they would not have to work nights when man and nature sleeps. The federation will soon have to help the bakers with their new agreement.</p>
   <p>In the furriers' union in Chicago - a general strike is sure to take place this summer. Their International has already approved $25,000 for that purpose. The federation will have to help them as much as is in their power.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
