<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-09-27">September 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Socialist Alliance Celebrates the Fifth Anniversary</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-09-27">September 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH SOCIALIST ALLIANCE CELEBRATES THE FIFTH ANNIVERSARY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee of the Jewish Socialist Alliance of Chicago has completed all preparations to celebrate the fifth anniversary in an elaborate and interesting manner. Three undertakings will be carried out when the Socialists celebrate the fifth year of the Alliance's existence.</p>
   <p>Before giving any information concerning the celebration it is important to point out, briefly, one of the chief merits attained by the Alliance in the course of its existence.</p>
   <p>When the Alliance was established a movement developed which placed as its chief task the control of existing unions and the Workmen's Circle, and the destruction of the solidarity that prevailed within the ranks of the organized labor movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The new "Messiahs" come to the Jewish workers of America with an ineffable reputation of good, imported from Moscow, and they have undertaken to revolutionize America and socialize the labor movement according to the tune of the third "International."</p>
   <p>And in a short time the damage of the Communist tactics and the falseness of their interpretations was felt in the movement.</p>
   <p>It remained for the Jewish Socialist Alliance to take up the battle against the dangerous and false tactics of the Communist "Messiahs," and thanks to the organized Jewish Socialists work of the Communists was combated on all fronts. Their true status was exposed until many thousands of members in a majority of the unions and thousands of Workmen's Circle members were convinced, that all that the Communists had in store for the Jewish workers was words of praise from one side and curses and insults from the other.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1327.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Alliance was an organization that estimated the dangers of the Communist tactics and its methods. It started an educational campaign among most of the unions and Workmen's Circle members, and developed an opposition movement in the organization that carried on a fight against the Communistic adventure all along the line. Thanks to the actions of the Jewish Socialist Alliance and its organ, the "Waker", and its staff; it was successful in weakening the activities of the Communists in many unions and in the Workmen's Circle, so that by now many of the workers have learned the truth. The naive mislead followers of the Communists will soon sober up and also learn the truth that they are being mislead by Communistic methods and tactics.</p>
   <p>At this opportunity, when the Alliance will be five years old, the Jewish Socialists of Chicago, who realize the great importance of its existence for the labor movement, have joined in arranging a Fifth Jubilee where <pb facs="5423972_3_1328.jpg" n="4"/>they will distinguish themselves by demonstrating to the Jewish Socialists in the country, that the Chicago progressive workers are with the Alliance, and appreciate the work it has done in the interest of the unions and the Workmen's Circle.</p>
   <p>The program of the Fifth Jubilee celebration will be divided into three parts as follows: A special jubilee publication of the Waker; a banquet for the Socialists and representatives of the Jewish labor organizations; a theatrical performance for the many friends and sympathizers of the movement.</p>
   <p>The special Waker number will contain articles about the Chicago labor movement and the Jewish Socialist Alliance written by active workers of the party and our movement, and greetings from members of our Alliance and friendly organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1329.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The special number of the Chicago Waker will appear Saturday, October 16, when many thousands of copies will be distributed. It is important that all Socialist and labor organizations shall help, that the special number of the Jubilee Waker may be a success.</p>
   <p>The banquet will be given in Barron's Banquet Hall, Saturday night, October 16. The theater performance will take place Monday night, October 16, at Glickman's Palace Theater.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that large crowds will come to the theatrical performance when we celebrate the Fifth Anniversary of our Jewish Socialist Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
