<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-19">Oct. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Congressman Sabath</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-19">Oct. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CONGRESSMAN SABATH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the many Jewish candidates running for Congress, none is as popular as Congressman A. J. Sabath, who has successfully represented the Fifth Congressional District of Illinois in Washington for the past twelve years. None of the Jewish Congressmen can boast of having accomplished as much, or of having devoted as much time and energy to Jewish interests, as Congressman Sabath. The voters of the Fifth Congressional District will also testify that their congressman represented their interests skillfully and earnestly; there is no doubt but that they will again show their confidence in him by re-electing him on November 2.</p>
   <p>All who are interested in the work of the House of Representatives know that Congressman Sabath is a leading figure there. He is a member of the Immigration Committee and of the Foreign Relations Committee; as a member of these two <pb facs="5423972_3_1730.jpg" n="2"/>important committees of the House of Representatives, he is in a position to influence the immigration policy of Congress, as well as American relations with the Eastern European countries.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath is liked and respected by all of his colleagues in the House of Representatives, with the exception of a very small group--the opponents of a liberal immigration policy. The members of this group are either complete reactionaries or narrow-minded politicians; Congressman Sabath is their strongest and most dangerous opponent, and it is this group of antagonists to a liberal immigration policy that would like to see Congressman Sabath defeated, because when he is in Congress, he knows how to block some of their devious plans against a liberal immigration policy.</p>
   <p>We Jews are vitally interested in maintaining America's liberal immigration policy. Hundreds of thousands of Jews in Poland, Lithuania, Hungary, the Ukraine, and other parts of Eastern Europe, now have but one goal before them, one single hope--America. And as Congressman Sabath has always been an <pb facs="5423972_3_1731.jpg" n="3"/>outstanding and devoted leader of Jewish affairs, and has worked skillfully and successfully in behalf of Jewish interests, he is absolutely indispensable in Congress. He has the confidence of the leading statesmen of the Democratic party, and is also respected by his Republican colleagues in the House. As a member of Congress, he can and will do a good deal toward effecting a liberal immigration policy.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath is often characterized as our ambassador in Washington, because of all Jewish Congressmen, he is the only devoted and successful Jewish intermediary. Hundreds of Jewish matters--political, personal, immigration, etc.,--go through his hands each year. He never refuses anyone who makes a legitimate request of him. He is an advocate of justice for all, and because he is so well known and admired in all the governmental departments in Washington, he is also successful there to a great extent.</p>
   <p>We personally know of a great many cases of Jewish immigration which Congressman Sabath handled with great skill. He has earned the blessings and good wishes of <pb facs="5423972_3_1732.jpg" n="4"/>innumerable Jewish immigrants who, through his efforts, overcame their difficulties quickly and attained their goal.</p>
   <p>If a Jewish congressman ever honestly deserved the honorable title of a great public servant and advocate of justice, that congressman is A. J. Sabath.</p>
   <p>We are sure that Congressman Sabath will, for the seventh time, be re-elected by a large majority, because he enjoys the absolute confidence of his district and the confidence of all the Jews of Chicago. It is unnecessary to appeal to the constituents of the Fifth Congressional District in behalf of Mr. Sabath. Each vote received by the Congressman on November 2 will be a vote of thanks, and an expression of confidence and appreciation of the marvelous work which he has accomplished up until now. Yet it is very important that Congressman Sabath receive a vast majority of votes so that he may be inspired with increased enthusiasm and energy to work for the welfare of the country, as well as his district, and in behalf of the great Jewish problems.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1733.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We need Sabath in Congress again, and every Jewish voter of the Fifth Congressional District must vote for "our ambassador in Washington.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
