<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Field Work</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">FIELD WORK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Jewish Federation held a meeting last Sunday at the Federation office. The financial secretary rendered last year's report, which showed rapid progress in the last 12 months. Ten new unions with membership totalling several thousand, were installed last year.</p>
   <p>The secretary also informed the members of the different important activities of the Federation. There was not one question of any importance, which came up in the Jewish unions that the Federation did not sanction. In many cases the Federation was instrumental in establishing peace and harmony in the unions when necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He pointed out the scope of the work which the Federation had accomplished in the Jewish unions. He then emphasized the fact that the United Jewish Federation is a big power now, which has brought fair play and system into the work of the Jewish unions....</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected for the ensuing year: B. Mazur, of the Carpenters Union, president; Alshanski, of the Raincoat Makers Union, financial secretary; Mr. Lehrner, of the Hebrew Typographical Club, recording and corresponding secretary; and Mr. Weinstein, treasurer. It was determined that the financial secretary receive a salary of $5 a week for his services. All other officers of the organization are to furnish their services gratis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0367.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The delegates of the Hebrew Actors Union have requested the Federation to do something for them in reference to an opposing union which has been organized, and also using the name of Hebrew Actors Union. This competitive union has no charter and is using this name, to which it has no right according to the delegates' information; we understand that this opposing union is made up of amateurs, who were refused admittance into our union because they were not actors. The Federation has made faithful promises to get busy at once in handling this problem for the Hebrew Actors Union and seeing that our rights as a union are not infringed upon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
