<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Michael Rosenberg's Campaign</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1713</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1713.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">MICHAEL ROSENBERG'S CAMPAIGN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Michael Rosenberg, who is the Democratic nominee for the Sanitary Board, is undoubtedly the most popular Democratic candidate for that office. He has really had a whirlwind campaign because many of his friends have actively and vigorously participated in it. A campaign such as Mr. Rosenberg's was well worth making because it revealed his standing in the community. His successful campaign testifies to his popularity among all sections of the population. Mr. Rosenberg is held in high esteem by Jews and Gentiles alike, and all his friends pay tribute to his amiability, straightforwardness, and good nature. His friends express the hope that all the Chicago Jewish voters, as well as tens of thousands of non-Jews, will cast their votes for Mr. Michael Rosenberg, when they go to the polls on November 2.</p>
   <p>Mr. Michael Rosenberg has done a great deal for the community, and has proved <pb facs="5423972_3_1714.jpg" n="2"/>that he is an able and efficient man, and deserves the trust and respect of the community. Mr. Michael Rosenberg has a fine reputation among his business friends as a businessman. His political friends like him because of his straightforwardness and reliability; he had all the qualities that go to make up a good citizen and a good man. He passed his first political test as a delegate to the Constitutional Convention, and his political friends think that he deserves a promotion. We hope that the people of Chicago will promote him, and will place him in the office for which he is now running.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
