<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Havana-American Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0962</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0962.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">HAVANA-AMERICAN STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Way down in Tennessee That's where I'd like to go" (sic).</p>
   <p>This popular folk song, which those who attend vaudeville performances hear so often on the stage...was heard yesterday at the mass meeting of the striking cigarmakers, at the Colonial Hall, 20 West Randolph Street. In his address, Jacob Belove said that the Havana-American Trust, whose workers have been on strike for almost eight months, is preparing to move to Memphis, Tennessee, in order to "get away from the union".</p>
   <p>Mr. Belove pointed out that the union is well-acquainted with the map and knows where Tennessee is. In the meantime, this news increased the enthusiasm of the workers who realize that the future success of their organization depends upon the results of this strike.</p>
   <p>Sam Goldin, chairman of the general strike committee, said: "Twenty small <pb facs="5423972_3_0963.jpg" n="2"/>manufacturers have already signed with the union, and the outlook for a complete victory is promising. The manufacturers argue that this is simply a matter which concerns an agreement between the eastern and the local cigarmakers because the former have higher standards. The truth of the matter is, however, that last year they [the manufacturers] said the same thing, and still they realized that a peaceful solution was the healthiest one. At the present time, the union is sending a number of representatives to various middle western cities where strikes will soon be called to improve the conditions of the workmen there. About ninety-five thousand cigarmakers throughout the country are today fighting for better [working] conditions, and even more of them will, in the near future, join this strike, which is a life or death struggle."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
