<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-16">May 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What the Amalgamated Convention Has Accomplished - by Morris Ziskind</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-05-16">May 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What the Amalgamated Convention Has Accomplished - by Morris Ziskind</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the triumphal march of the thousands of Chicago tailors is over, the tunes of revolutionary-music are heard no more; the gardens of flowers with their sweet aroma are wilted, and the delegates from all over the country have their shops or their Unions. It is possible to glance over the work that was done at the Convention that closed last Saturday, and express an opinion as to the success of the Amalgamated as a labor-organization.</p>
   <p>Many of the visitors who witnessed what went on at the Convention wondered how it was possible for a young organization only eight years old to have such power, such life, so much courage, and so much spirit as one will find in very few labor-organizations in the country that are much older than the Amalgamated.</p>
   <p>Sitting at the Convention,one could see idealistic leaders and representatives striving to bring those ideals to reality, the whole delegation and all the leaders striving for a better world of freedom, where the workers will be able to live their own lives as the collective possessors of the things they, themselves, <pb facs="5423972_3_0546.jpg" n="2"/>produce. In this fundamental ideal they all believe. Despite their separation, and the diversity of the methods used to attain their aim, still they worship that one ideal which serves them as a guide in many of their undertakings.</p>
   <p>The leaders are very practical men and very idealistic. They go step by step, gaining a point at every move.</p>
   <p>One of the most important decisions of the Amalgamated Convention was to help rebuild Soviet Russia,by organizing a corporation to act as partners with the Russian Government, in clothing factories and weaving mills.</p>
   <p>This decision proves the relationship between the practical and the idealistic sides of the Amalgamated.</p>
   <p>From the idealistic viewpoint, all friends of Soviet Russia must admit that the decision to help Russia is only human, as Sidney Hillman said in his speech. The practical side is also clear to those who know the conditions in <pb facs="5423972_3_0547.jpg" n="3"/>Russia. The Russian Government is satisfied to give concessions to those who will invest capital, and the Amalgamated is secure in its undertaking, because the Soviet Russian Government displayed very much friendship toward the plan, out of respect for the Amalgamated, which helped Russia's hungry and needy so wholeheartedly, until now the Amalgamated Clothing Worker is the first organization to help Russia, not only with money to feed the hungry, but also with practical and constructive plans to encourage other progressive organizations to follow its good example; and, as we learned from a responsible source, Hillman is negotiating with one of the American labor-organizations a plan similar to this one which will be of great help to Soviet Russia.</p>
   <p>The second big step was decision for one Union for the entire needle-trade industry.</p>
   <p>The American labor-movement is far behind the progressive action of the united needle trades.</p>
   <p>The American labor-movement is especially backward in economic construction. The organizational forum of these unions is a survival of that which <pb facs="5423972_3_0548.jpg" n="4"/>prevailed in early days when production was very small.</p>
   <p>The needle trade is not organized as an industrial union.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated, at its Convention, approved the organization of the entire needle trade in one great industrial union. This is without a doubt the most practical step in the interests of all needle workers in the country.</p>
   <p>It is the hope of all who realize the necessity for such a step that in a period of a few years there will be one great powerful industrial union of all the needle trades, which will serve as an example for the entire American organized labor-movement.</p>
   <p>The General Executive Board of the Amalgamated has determined to have the officials of the Amalgamated take active interest in the conference to be held in December, to organize an independent political labor-party.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0549.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>One of the decisions which illustrated the practical dealing of the Amalgamated was, without a doubt, the decision not to join the Red Trade Union International of Moscow.</p>
   <p>The reason the Convention rejected this was mainly because it is not practical. The Resolution Committee declared that the Red Trade Union International was of no value or interest to the Amalgamated.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated weigh and consider every plan, every motion, every resolution, and see what possibilities there are to benefit its members. The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America know how to execute the practical policies adopted at the Convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
