<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-21">July 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In the Field of Labor</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-07-21">July 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FIELD OF LABOR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"As you sow, so shall you reap." For the last year the Chicago Cloak Makers, united in a joint board, were busily engaged in a systematic organizing campaign according to trade union principles. Now come the results - to reap what they have sown.</p>
   <p>They have undertaken to organize all of Chicago's cloak shops, and it seems as if their task will be accomplished in the near future. Especially is the joint board greatly interested in increasing the pay rate to a point, that would enable the cloak makers to make a living. For, as long as the bosses alone have the power to designate the rate of pay, <pb facs="5423972_3_1100.jpg" n="2"/>and as long as the workers have to depend upon the conscience of the manufacturers, who are the sole judges of their skill and fitness, then very little is left for the cloak makers. Under such conditions, they are unable to make a living.</p>
   <p>The union is determined that the worker should have his say when pay rates are established, and to accomplish this, proposes, that a representative from the union, together with the manufacturer should determine the rate of pay.</p>
   <p>In cloak manufacturing, the rate of pay plays a very big part. The ever-changing styles quite often double the hardship of cloak work. This is responsible for the change in the rates of pay for each <pb facs="5423972_3_1101.jpg" n="3"/>new style. It is, therefore imperative that the workers have their say, when pay rates are established.</p>
   <p>The union's tactic of calling strikes in individual shops, rather than a general strike in all shops has proven very successful. Last Friday the union called a strike in the shops of three manufacturers. They were: Glick and Company, Goldstein and Company, and Liberman and Company. Naturally this could be done only after the movement had been started, the workers organized, and their demands set forth.</p>
   <p>Liberman and Company changed their minds over night and settled their strike by yielding to all the demands of the workers. The other two are a little stubborn as yet, but will have to give in eventually to the solid and united front of the strikers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
