<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-09">Dec. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">From Workman's Ghetto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-09">Dec. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FROM WORKMAN'S GHETTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a rare occasion when workmen laud an employer, especially following a dispute, not to mention a recent strike which was quite an open battle with the boss. Even then, it is a long time before their demands are put into force.</p>
   <p>But it is different at Spector Bros., the well-known cigar manufacturers. As we have already written, the strike was won entirely in favor of the workers, and noteworthy of mention is the fact that the workers have now the best opinion and confidence in Mr. Barney Spector, owner of Spector Bros. Cigar Manufacturers. Perhaps because he is one of those exceptions who fulfilled everything he promised, and at that, much sooner than the agreement called for. His dealings are praiseworthy and should serve as an example for other manufacturers.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the strike, he complied with all the sanitary demands and also increased the prices on some cigars. Although he had two weeks time before paying the increase of one dollar on the thousand, fifty cents <pb facs="5423972_3_0401.jpg" n="2"/>immediately and fifty cents four weeks later, Mr. Barney Spector started the new order at once. This in itself is a rare good act, not only from the employer's point of view but also from the employee's viewpoint. And now, Spector Bros. shop is one of the best paying and most satisfactory in the trade.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, we have the stubbornness of the cigar manufacturers of Wall &amp; Komstock, where the Progressive Cigar Makers Union recently called a strike.</p>
   <p>One of the employers, Mr. Peter Wall, is a former anarchist, a person whose soul was seeped in Baccunin's and Kropotkin's teachings. Naturally, such a person must have an individuality that others had not the opportunity of attaining.</p>
   <p>The strike, therefore, has all of a stubborn nature, reaching the assumption of a battle for principle. The cigar makers union will not deviate from the demands set forth by the strikers, and the employers, under the influence of Anarchism, will not recognize discipline and control. They desire freedom <pb facs="5423972_3_0402.jpg" n="3"/>to rule, not to pay prices set by union men for this or the other cigar.</p>
   <p>The Cigar Maker's Union will not stop at obstacles, but will carry the strike to a finish. The union is strong enough to withstand the hardships of a strike for years and years. But, when we speak of strength between the two, we wonder whether the stronger be the union or Wall and Komstock. This we shall see presently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
