<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-10-22">Oct. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Tailors Promise to Help New Organization</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-10-22">Oct. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TAILORS PROMISE TO HELP NEW ORGANIZATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago tailors, over 4,000 of them, at a mass meeting last night at the West Side Auditorium, through a resolution unanimously adopted at the Nashville convention, promised moral and financial aid to the newly elected officers of the United Garment Workers' of America.</p>
   <p>The sentiment of the large audience present was in accordance with the reports and speeches of the delegates, who declared that this is not a new movement, that the old organization did not dissolve; it is the same movement, rejuvenated, with a new element of workers, representing the interests of the workers and not the interests of the manufacturers.</p>
   <p>Every speaker was tremendously applauded, especially those who in their speeches brought out in the open and condemned the traitorous work of that <pb facs="5423972_3_0377.jpg" n="2"/>clique of job hunters who through force seek to elect themselves as leaders of the great masses that despise them, and don't want them. These speeches were accepted with overwhelming acclaim.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pietro, the chairman, who declared the purpose of this meeting, introduced Mr. Sam Levin, president of the Chicago District Council, who was one of the delegates at the convention, and he had much to report. He proved how the majority of delegates, representing seventy-five per cent of the garment workers, were not admitted to the convention, but only those who made appeals to be admitted.</p>
   <p>"Do you know why we were not admitted?" he cried. "Because we represent you and not the manufacturers, because representing you, would hinder us from voting for Rickert and Company!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0378.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He went on to say that the delegates assembled elsewhere and held a real convention of the garment workers, and elected officers, that the workers chose as their leaders. At the conclusion he appealed for unity and solidarity, because only through unity can the work, neglected by this clique of job hunters, now be continued for the good of the thousands of garment workers throughout the land.</p>
   <p>After a few remarks from delegates Tabak, Schneid and others, the chairman introduced the president of the United Garment Workers of America -Mr. Sidney Hillman, who received a thunderous applause. Mr. Hillman analyzed the conditions of the garment industry, and pointed out that the new epoch in the movement will greatly improve the deplorable conditions of tens of thousands of tailors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0379.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Things could not continue in the old way any longer. The negligence of the so-called and self-crowned leaders of the tailors was a crime and a stop had to be made. They brought it upon themselves, an everlasting disgrace, by the low and dirty deals they made at the convention which brought about their defeat.</p>
   <p>A new spirit reigns in the garment trade, a national spirit which the masses have striven for, for years. The bad and corrupt is now rooted out and the true representatives lead and will continue leading the tailor masses to victory. To achieve this requires the general assistance and solidarity of all the garment workers.</p>
   <p>"Stand united behind your leaders; this will lead to better conditions in the trade, higher wages, shorter hours." These were the last words of President Hillman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0380.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>At the conclusion, the resolution which was unanimously adopted, was read. It is as follows:</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that we, members of Chicago locals, assembled at a mass meeting, express our satisfaction and approve heartily the transactions of the delegates who had in mind to protect our interests, and we promise to unanimously support in all cases, the newly elected officers."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
