<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-22">November 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Grocery Clerks Triumph</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-22">November 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH GROCERY CLERKS TRIUMPH</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish grocery clerks have determined to walk out on strike this morning at 8:30 o'clock, in every grocery store where the owner will not sign an agreement with the union.</p>
   <p>A conference was held two weeks ago between representatives of the union and the Employers' Association. The employers were represented by Mr. Mackowitz, president, Mr. Rothbaum, Mr. Block, Mr. Weiner. The grocery clerks were represented by Mr. Ethin, Mr. Harris, president of the United Hebrew Trades, Mr. Grass, business agent of the Retail Clerks' Union, and Mr. Yukelson of the Progressive Cigar Makers' Union. The union waited two weeks to hear from the employers. The business agent then called upon the president of the Employers' Association to inquire as to whether he had signed the agreement. He ordered the business agent to leave. The business agent immediately called a meeting of all grocery clerks to decide what action should be taken. The clerks discarded their work and responded to the call. All were satisfied to contribute what little money they had toward fighting for their justified demands. Several clerks reported that their employers are willing to sign the agreement. The workers demand a working week of sixty-six hours, a <pb facs="5423972_3_1078.jpg" n="2"/>two dollar raise and that the employers shall hire union help only.</p>
   <p>The employers rejected many demands of the workers and announced in the Courier, that they would like to appear before a body of arbitrators. The grocery clerks obtained the assurance from the officials of the United Hebrew Trades and the Retail Clerks' Protective Association that they will help them, morally and financially, in their fight. After adjourning the meeting, a committee contacted the bosses and asked them to sign the agreement. The following bosses signed the agreement: M. Weiner, H. Rothbaum, Mrs. Minnie Berstein, H. Markovitz, Isador Sol, H. Royack and H. Rosenthal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
