<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Workmen's Movement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE WORKMEN'S MOVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last week The Amalgamated Union Tailoring Workers celebrated a double victory in Chicago. The long drawn strike at Alfred, Decker, Cohen &amp; Company was settled when the firm agreed to recognize the shop committee and when it promised to organize the necessary organs for collective bargaining, i.e., to deal with the workers as a body through their chosen representatives, a principle which this firm defeated for many years.</p>
   <p>The strike, carried on with so much enthusiasm and solidarity, finally opened the eyes of the stubborn firm, forcing it to accept progressive measures and comply with the demands of the organized workers.</p>
   <p>General organizer Rosenbloom has contributed much to the success of this victory, just as he has done for other strikes occurring at this <pb facs="5423972_3_1042.jpg" n="2"/>time and having the same demands, namely: that the bosses stop discriminating against union workers and increase the standards of wages and working conditions.</p>
   <p>The strike won last week at Alfred, Decker, Cohen &amp; Company gained union recognition and an increase in wages of fifteen per cent. This double victory of the Amalgamated Union is a great and definite step forward for the organized tailor workers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>At the end of the week another firm acquiesced, the great firm of Kupenheimer, which so strenuously fought the union, thus making this victory an even greater accomplishment for the workers.</p>
   <p>These victories acquired within so short a time, have increased the already large prestige of the Amalgamated. New members are joining the union in such great numbers that it is hoped that soon the Amalgamated will be in a position to state that all trades under its auspices are 100 per cent organized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
