<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-24">Apr. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Only Without Stubbornness</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-24">Apr. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ONLY WITHOUT STUBBORNNESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bakers' strike is in the air in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Around the first of May the yearly agreement between the Jewish Bakers Union and their employers usually expires, and it is therefore in order that before a new agreement is signed, all kinds of hints and strike threats should begin to circulate. In this respect, this year is no exception. Conferences are being held now between both sides and before the differences are settled, those who circulate the rumors, do their work, shouting the word "strike" into the air.</p>
   <p>We are of the opinion that strikers, at any time,are merely the outgrowth of unreasonable stubbornness, which comes either from one side or the <pb facs="5423972_3_1073.jpg" n="2"/>other. When people with sense get together and talk things over, sincerely and openheartedly with the intention not to do any harm, and to be considerate of one another, then there can be no reason for a strike.</p>
   <p>This year, there is even less reason for it. The cost of living is high, and in many trades wages are being raised by the bosses on their own volition, as occurred not so long ago in the garment trade. There is no reason why the representatives of the union and the bosses should not have a friendly talk with the sincere understanding that both sides shall do what common sense and justice demand.</p>
   <p>A bakers' strike during the present period of the high cost of living and provision difficulties would add to the hardships of living, not only of the strikers and bosses, but also of thousands of families whose existence is hard enough as it is.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that if the negotiations between both sides could be <pb facs="5423972_3_1074.jpg" n="3"/>conducted without stubbornness, without trickery, but with an earnest desire to do what is right for each side, then there would be no strike.</p>
   <p>We understand that today there is to be a conference between the union and the bosses. Lets hope that a friendly settlement will be the outcome of this conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
