<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-30">May 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Union Victory at Marion Court Hebrew School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1025</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1025.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-30">May 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[UNION VICTORY AT MARION COURT HEBREW SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hebrew school on Marion Court has settled [the strike] with the union, granting the teachers all their demands. The victory at this school is of great importance, because only a couple of days ago Mr. Siegel, the principal of the school, declared that he would under no circumstances settle the strike with the union. Mr. Siegel is responsible for prolonging the strike. He is the one who "plays politics" in the synagogues. Everything he does "smacks of politics".</p>
   <p>He forgot, however, that he was dealing with a union. This mistake almost cost him his position; for if the strike had continued only a few hours more, there would have been no school in the building and no position for Mr. Siegel, since the teachers' union had decided to rent [space] in the Educational Alliance [building] for a Hebrew school. Now, the teachers blame him, while the parents are angry with him, because of the damage he has done with his "politics".</p>
   <p>At this time we would also like to explain to those who are interested in the strike, that the news [regarding the strike], which the [Daily Jewish] Courier <pb facs="5423972_3_1026.jpg" n="2"/>prints, is false. The Courier states that the written contract [with the school] obligated the teachers not to belong to the union and to abandon the trade-union council. While it is true that a proposed contract contained a section, to which the teachers were willing to agree, that no strike should be called during the year, this contract was not executed. Moreover, it did not contain a single word about the trade-union [council].</p>
   <p>The strike is still in progress at the following Hebrew schools: Talmud Torah Agudath ha-Kehillah on Hirsch Boulevard; Talmud Torah Anshe Sholom at Homan Avenue and Douglas Boulevard; and Talmud Torah Kehilath Jacob on Hamlin Avenue.</p>
   <p>The teachers request all parents, whose children attend the above-named schools, to communicate with Mr. [Saul] Prochovnick at 1904 South Albany Avenue, and inquire regarding the Talmud Torah the teachers are planning to open in the Lawndale district.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
