<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-01">September 1, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-01">September 1, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Butchers' Union Signs an Agreement with Bosses.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Butchers' Union, Local 596, whose agreement with the butcher bosses was concluded today, held a conference with the officers and representatives of the Butcher Bosses Association, Wednesday evening, and after a thorough discussion, the representatives of both parties agreed to the clauses of the agreement and promised to introduce the agreement to the members of both organizations. With the exception of a few clauses, the representatives of the Butcher Bosses Association agreed to sign the old contract, paying the same scale for all former employees and grant all the workers' demands.</p>
   <p>A new clause was adopted that permits those working one year to receive $30.00 a week instead of $25.00, as prevails now. After the elapse of one year a journey-man has the privilege to request an examination and if the Examination Committee attests that he is eligible, he is then entitled to higher wages or to the full scale of $41.00 a week. The bosses are also obligated to pay for Jewish holidays, for July 4, and Labor Day, and work is to be only until noon on all other holidays.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0114.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Concerning the question of being responsible for accidents in the butcher shops, it was determined to appoint a committee and draw a plan of insurance for the butcher bosses so that every boss will be insured and if an accident will occur, the worker should get paid from any butcher, regardless of how large or small the shop may be.</p>
   <p>At these transactions, the union was represented by: Sam Gordon, Max Weiss, Ely Krop, Barney Sachs, Sam Solotkin, and the business agent of Local 596.</p>
   <p>The Bosses Association was represented by: Joe Goldberg, president, Mr. Simon, secretary of the organization and other executive board members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
