<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-04-19">April 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Six Thousand Amalgamated Members Approve New Agreement with Employers</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-04-19">April 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">SIX THOUSAND AMALGAMATED MEMBERS APPROVE NEW AGREEMENT WITH EMPLOYERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than six thousand members of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers met, after work yesterday, in two separate halls and have unanimously approved the renewal of the agreement, with the clothing manufacturers for a period of three years.</p>
   <p>The first meeting which unanimously approved the agreement was held by the cutters in Temple Hall.</p>
   <p>Sidney Rissman, business agent of Local #61, gave a brief survey of the transactions with the manufacturers. He, then, introduced President Hillman who portrayed the policies of the Amalgamated, preserving the conditions of the industry at all times and struggling for better conditions whenever it confronts a favorable outlook.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0473.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>President Hillman clarified the position that the delegates tried their very best to obtain the demands that were set up. He read the changes that were adopted in the agreement.</p>
   <p>The manufacturers agreed to pay 3 per cent to the Unemployment Insurance Fund, in lieu of 1 1/2 per cent, as they have been paying for the past three years. (The workers will pay no more than they are paying now).</p>
   <p>Concerning the demand of a 40 hour-work-week, negotiations are pending and it will be seen to it that working hours are curtailed. The demand to raise wages in the under-paid section will be negotiated by the representatives of the Union and the manufacturers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0474.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After work, the coat, pants, and vest makers assembled in the Ashland Auditorium, where Sidney Hillman addressed the members of the Amalgamated on the achievements of their Union since it was first organized.</p>
   <p>The manufacturers recognized the importance of their demands.</p>
   <p>The agreement was approved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
