<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-10">Apr. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Tomorrow's Primary Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-10">Apr. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TOMORROW'S PRIMARY ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Even primary elections have their [own particular] fate. Sometimes a primary election in Chicago passes by as if it were an insignificant incident. The local political situation is not complicated, the public knows what is what, and is well acquainted with the leading personalities of the campaign. When the local political situation is clear, the public knows for whom to vote and the primary elections pass as though they were unimportant incidents. Every citizen goes to the polls, votes, and he is through. But it sometimes happens, as in tomorrow's primary elections, that the political situation is not clear because the parties are split up. The public is then in the dark; it does not know who is who and what is what. It hears from so many candidates, about so many parties, programs, slogans, and so on, that it is bewildered and it needs <pb facs="5423972_3_1679.jpg" n="2"/>a guiding hand to clarify and explain the parties and the personalities of the candidates.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, consider it our editorial duty to discuss tomorrow's primaries and to say a few words about the parties and the candidates, particularly about the Jewish candidates of the various parties.</p>
   <p>There are four parties active in the election campaign for tomorrow's primaries: the regular Democratic party, the rebel Democratic faction, the regular Republican party and the Republican faction led by Brundage and Crowe. All four parties have put up their candidates. Many independent candidates are also running.</p>
   <p>The Republican groups have a few Jews running on their ballot. Sol P. Roderick is running as candidate for Sanitary District Trustee, and Emanuel Eller, <pb facs="5423972_3_1680.jpg" n="3"/>Max Luster, and Benjamin Cohen are running for judges of the Municipal Court.</p>
   <p>Emanuel Eller is a young, capable lawyer who is well known among the local circles of Chicago. He is the son of Morris Eller, a member of the Sanitary Board.</p>
   <p>The regular Democratic party has six Jewish candidates upon its list, four of them running for judges. Of the four candidates for judges, one is a well-known and beloved figure in Jewish Chicago. We mean Judge Henry Horner of the Probate Court, who has distinguished himself as a judge by his capability, wisdom, honesty, and hard work. The other three candidates for Municipal Court judges are Samuel E. Weinshenker, Isidor Brown, and S. E. Pincus. The other two candidates of the regular Democratic party are Alderman Schwartz and Michael Rosenberg. Mr. Schwartz, as alderman of the Third Ward, distinguished himself by his ability and he became one of the leading and most influential <pb facs="5423972_3_1681.jpg" n="4"/>aldermen, although he is still a young man. The Democratic party recognized his capability and talent by running him as a candidate for the Board of Review. The other candidate, Michael Rosenberg, is the son of Rachmiel Rosenberg. Mr. Rosenberg, better known among his many friend as Mike Rosenberg, is one of the most popular young Jewish men in the community. He is an active civic worker. He, like his father, is a great philanthropist. He is active in almost all Jewish institutions, and is, in general, a good and likeable man. The leaders of the Democratic party are running him as a candidate for the Sanitary District. They know that he is very popular among the Jews and they hope that he will receive the Jewish vote.</p>
   <p>The rebel Democratic faction did not put up any Jewish candidates for important offices but instead, to satisfy a personal grude, put up rival candidates against Judge Horner, Michael Rosenberg, and Ulysses S. Schwartz for the Board of Review. Had the regular Democratic party dropped the candidacy of Judge Henry Horner, then the so-called rebel faction would not have put up its own <pb facs="5423972_3_1682.jpg" n="5"/>candidates and would have accepted and approved the general slate of the candidates of the regular Democratic party. This is important for the Jewish Democratic voters to know.</p>
   <p>It would be a crime to fail to elect a man like Judge Henry Horner, who, by his excellent conduct of his office, brought honor to it, to himself, and to the Jews of Chicago. It would not be right to fail to elect Michael Rosenberg, a capable, young Jewish nationalist, because certain politicians have a personal grudge against him. The regular Democratic party deserves credit for exhibiting character and courage in protecting the honor of men who won the esteem of the community by their public activity.</p>
   <p>This covers in full the list of the Jewish candidates of the various parties.</p>
   <p>Among the Jewish candidates there are important personalities, who merit our <pb facs="5423972_3_1683.jpg" n="6"/>respect. If there is any chance to elect them all, it becomes first of all the duty of all Jewish voters in Chicago to go tomorrow to the polls and vote. By not participating in the primary elections, they rob the Jewish candidates of the possibility of being elected at the regular elections. If the political parties see that the Jews do not participate in the primaries, they will not put up any Jewish candidates in the future.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, say to the Chicago Jews: do your duty tomorrow as citizens and as Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
