<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-18">Feb. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-18">Feb. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The citizens of Chicago will be asked to vote in the aldermanic primaries, which will take place Tuesday, February 27. Instead of thirty-five wards, there are now fifty wards, and instead of two aldermans, only one will be elected from each ward. The Jewish citizens, as well as the non-Jewish, are earnestly requested to participate in the elections, and help elect the best and most suitable men to the City Council.</p>
   <p>The Twenty-fourth Ward is one of the new wards and ninety-five per cent of its population is Jewish. Thus, it is a Jewish ward--the most beautiful Jewish district in America. The largest and most significant institutions of the Jewish Orthodoxy of Chicago are located in that ward. Most of the Orthodox synagogues can be found there. Hitherto, this district has not been represented in the City <pb facs="5423972_3_1670.jpg" n="2"/>Council by a Jew. We now have an opportunity to send a Jew from that ward to the City Council. And he should be Paul Rothenberg.</p>
   <p>The writer of these lines is wholeheartedly in favor of voting for Paul Rothenberg. Many individuals and organizations, whose memberships are made up of all classes of Jews, have agreed that the next City Council of our city shall have a majority of more capable members than the City Council has had for the past eight years. That is why they will vote for Paul Rothenberg.</p>
   <p>Paul Rothenberg is very popular in his ward and he has gained this popularity as a result of his willingness to serve all those who turn to him for help. He is influential in the higher political circles of our city, county, and state governments. He is also a brilliant orator. He is a considerate person, and has initiated some constructive community enterprises. He has decided to make an honorable record for himself, for the ward in which he lives, and for the city in general, if he is elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1671.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It grieves me, therefore, to see how some of his political opponents and toadies hired by his enemies seek to undermine his candidacy, not by discussing issues, not by comparing his ability and character, but by slander, lies, and cheap provocations. These are their campaign methods.</p>
   <p>They do not want Paul Rothenberg as alderman. They seek the office of alderman for themselves. As honest people, that is their privilege. But honest people do not throw stones and mud at political adversaries; honest people do not fabricate accusations, nor do they incite or provoke others. We hope that the Jewish masses will protest against such campaign methods on election day.</p>
   <p>His opponents are raising the question of the Mexican project, in which Paul Rothenberg played such a prominent role in the interests of our people. They deny the fact that President Obregon of Mexico offered Paul Rothenberg territory for Jewish colonization. They also deny the fact the the offer is still good. They claim that he wished to have Jews settle there "for his own financial purposes," and "that the Jewish people laughed at that". These libels ought to <pb facs="5423972_3_1672.jpg" n="4"/>bring jail sentences upon their framers. Here is the offer which has been publicly reproduced:</p>
   <p>"President of the Republic of Mexico, National Palace</p>
   <p>May 10, 1922</p>
   <p>"Mr. Paul Rothenberg,</p>
   <p>"1639 South Sawyer Avenue,</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Dear Brother: In reference to our conversation regarding the immigration of Russian Jews to Mexico, it gives me pleasure to inform you that the Government of which I have the honor to be President, would welcome this immigration. However, I deem it advisable to let you know that if the immigrants are to acquire real estate in the Republic of Mexico, they must become Mexican citizens. Also, the law provides that foreigners are prohibited from buying property within a distance of one hundred kilometers (eighty miles) parallel to the border, and fifty kilometers (forty miles) within distance of the ocean front.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1673.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"In the country, there are several million hectares which can be used for colonization purposes. A large portion of the land can be used for farming. You can rest assured that the immigrants whom I have designated, if they will accept the provisos that I have mentioned, and will abide by the laws of our constitution, concerning the acquisition of property, will enjoy the guarantees of security and protection which are given to all citizens of the Mexican republic.</p>
   <p>"I have taken up the matter with Senator Shleimer of Arizona in an interview which I had with him in our capital city. He is in a position to give you more details than it is possible to convey in a letter.</p>
   <p>"With my personal greetings, I am</p>
   <p>"Your devoted friend,</p>
   <p>Obregon."</p>
   <p>Paul Rothenberg asked Jewish leaders to sponsor this project, but none of them, <pb facs="5423972_3_1674.jpg" n="6"/>with the exception of Israel Zangwill made any inquiries about it. A person who speaks disparagingly of the territory does not know what he is talking about because no one has taken the trouble to investigate it. Rabbi Zelenko of El Paso, [Texas] is such a person. In his report, he speaks of second-hand information, and second-hand information is little better than ignorance or false information.</p>
   <p>Paul Rothenberg, together with a few intimate friends, went to Mexico, at his own expense, to investigate the land. They took with them a noted American engineer and a surveyor, who issued a detailed and favorable report. In the meantine, Paul Rothenberg has advised no one to settle there until the project has been legalized.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the project was not supported by the large Jewish organizations. But this fact, however, does not in the least minimize the good intentions and lofty ideals of Rothenberg in his attempt to find a home for the Jews of Eastern Europe. No decent or loyal Jew can have any complaints against Rothenberg, <pb facs="5423972_3_1675.jpg" n="7"/>especially since he did not ask anyone for financial support; at least he did not ask his political opponents.</p>
   <p>Paul Rothenberg wanted to accomplish something great, noble, and sacred for his people, but he was not successful. Although he failed he still towers above his opponents. The people are with Rothenberg and they will vote for him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
