<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-06-09">June 9, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a well attended meeting of members of the Jewish Socialist party branches in Liberty Club, the issue of keeping the party and the Socialist Federation from breaking into the left-movement, was discussed.</p>
   <p>The following Resolutions were adopted:</p>
   <p>It was declared, at the meeting, that the existence of the Left-Wing annihilates the activities of the Jewish Socialist branches in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Therefore, be it Resolved: That individual comrades or organizations that join or remain in the left wing, are automatically excluded from the Federation; although we recognize, at the same time, that all Comrades have a right to remain loyal to their Socialist principles and theories and are permitted to propagate them in the press or in the Party.</p>
   <p>Protests were made, at the Meeting, against the three Chicago delegates, who have abandoned the Federation's Convention in Boston, on account of not including the Left Wing in the Convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1507.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was resolved to urge the Committee of the Socialist Party branches to re-organize the branches that are unwilling to submit to these resolutions.</p>
   <p>It was resolved to urge the management of the Chicago"Forward" and the Central Committee of the Jewish Party branches to see it that the policy of the Federation and of the Party be published in the Forward.</p>
   <p>These resolutions will be introduced at the meeting tomorrow evening, in the Northwest Side Branch, and Wednesday-evening at Douglas Park of the West Side branches of the Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
