<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-04-28">April 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Youth in Chicago. Max Carson</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-04-28">April 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH YOUTH IN CHICAGO. Max Carson</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The intellectuals and radicals, who have boasted so much about the idealism and sacrifices of the Jewish youth in Russia, those, who guarded their revolutionary spirit so much, their struggle against despotic power, did they ever consider anything of our Jewish youth here in America? What is happening to it? How, and in what, does it spend its leisure time? Did it ever meditate upon life's ideals, and its spiritual and moral development?</p>
   <p>Few of them have, perhaps, considered the above, and others have written about it. Well, were they satisfied with the results at which they arrived? Certainly not. But did they do anything to help the poor Jewish youth? Unfortunately, we must say, that nothing has been done until now. When any intelligent Jew tears away from his daily mode of living; goes over to the Jewish community; considers the Jewish youth; and listens to its street discussions, a shock runs down his spine.</p>
   <p>The honest, intelligent person comes to the conclusion that the average young man and the average young woman is ignorant in Jewish, as well as in English, and a great number of them have no desire to know anything; never attended <pb facs="5423972_3_1536.jpg" n="2"/>any schools, and would rather go to a dance hall or a dancing school, where they have the opportunity to meet with their equals. Yet our radicals have done nothing to revive the Jewish youth. Besides the organizing of the Jewish Sunday School, they have done nothing for which the Jewish youth have cause to be thankful.</p>
   <p>The Poale Zion, however, saw this necessity. They took advantage of the opportunity for propaganda purposes, and began organizing, four years ago, Maccabees Clubs, which carry the same character almost, as childrens' schools. In addition to this, they have done good work in the educational field; yet they did not receive any response from the Jewish community. Their membership grew very slowly and had a small effect on the youth. Other radicals and socialists have quietly dreamt, awakening now and then to the alarms of a campaign or some other happening, and then have fallen asleep again. Everywhere, the Jewish youth began to awaken and revive. Young Jewish socialist organizations were beginning to organize throughout the entire country with the exception of Chicago. The Jewish youth of Chicago designed its style of living, namely, as working, eating, and drinking (if there is anything), and sleeping.</p>
   <p>A few years ago, a few foreign, intellectual socialists, deploring the condition of the Jewish youth in Chicago, determined to organize a Jewish youth <pb facs="5423972_3_1537.jpg" n="3"/>organization, whose main object should be to organize the entire Jewish youth interested in improving the lot of the working class, to establish a center for a pure intellectual, social intercourse, to establish methods for physical and chiefly, spiritual development, to spread the knowledge and principles of socialism through educational work, to refine the conception of literature, drama, etc., and to aid the Socialist Party in its propaganda and political work. They have established the first branch of the Jewish young socialists in Chicago on these principles.</p>
   <p>In spite of the opposition of many socialists, (who are against the Jewish movement), the first branch, nevertheless, sprouted, blossomed, and grew in the Jewish centers, drew the attention of the young Jewish element, spread the education of socialism and class struggle among those whom it otherwise would have been impossible to reach.</p>
   <p>It made such a stir in the Jewish community that the necessity to have more than one branch was soon felt. Without assistance of any older or more experienced group, they organized a second branch in Douglas Park District and a third on the North Side. All three branches have already succeeded in showing that they have earned the name and principles they bear. They have now a <pb facs="5423972_3_1538.jpg" n="4"/>membership of four-hundred. They conduct weekly debates, discussions, and lectures on miscellaneous current, scientific, social, and literary problems; hold classes, publish a monthly journal, "The Free Youth," help carry on campaigns, help radical organizations, make special affairs for the Daily World. They have recently organized a "City Central," that endeavors now, mainly to organize new branches in and around Chicago; to revive the "Youth Federation" and open new childrens' schools under their supervision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
