<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-07-04">July 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Capmakers Strike Settled</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-07-04">July 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CAPMAKERS STRIKE SETTLED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strike of the Chicago Capmakers Union ended yesterday. The strikers accepted the settlement recommended by the strike committee and Tuesday morning all the capmakers returned to work.</p>
   <p>The settlement with the Cap Manufacturers Association was as follows:</p>
   <p>The demand for a 40 hour week and a raise in pay was referred to the Board of Arbitration. The manufacturers will not give out any more work to contractors or corporation shops. All work must be made in their own union shops. The bosses cannot buy any ready made caps from other manufacturers without the consent of the union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0785.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The capmakers in this settlement have won the most important demand, that the work shall not be given out to outside shops. This is something against which the union protested for a long time without success. Now the union will make an attempt to annihilate all the corporation shops that ruin the trade and lower the standard of living of the Chicago Jewish Capmakers.</p>
   <p>The strike lasted three days, - during that time the union organized the workers of many shops. The trouble in the cap trade was that the bosses would give out a good deal of their work to sweat shop manufacturers, corporation shops and contractors, who work with their wives and children also their fathers and mothers; also uncles and grandfathers, all partners in the business, all working long hours, while the workers in the union shops were without work.</p>
   <p>Full confidence is placed in the Arbitration Committee that they will realize the necessity of a raise for the workers, and grant it to them so they can make a living the whole year around.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
