<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-12">Mar. 12, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Public Hearing on Dressmakers' Strike Tomorrow at City Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-12">Mar. 12, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC HEARING ON DRESSMAKERS' STRIKE TOMORROW AT CITY HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There will be a public hearing on the dressmakers' strike tomorrow afternoon, at two o'clock, at the City Hall building, in the office of the Public Welfare Department, under the chairmanship of Miss Mary McDowell. The hearing has been called by Mayor Dever at the request of a group of clergymen and reformers who have heard about the complaints of the pickets against the police, who are being accused of indirectly supporting the manufacturers.</p>
   <p>Invitations to attend the hearing were sent to both sides. Mr. Meyer Perlstein, leader of the strikers, was the first one to accept the invitation. It is believed that the bosses, although they have not yet accepted the invitation officially; will select their representatives by tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The workers are attaching a great deal of importance to tomorrow's conference. Besides the representatives of the dressmakers' Union, representatives of the Chicago Federation of Labor, which has helped to arrange the hearing, will <pb facs="5423972_3_0796.jpg" n="2"/>also be present, as well as representatives of civic organizations.</p>
   <p>Union headquarters announced yesterday that though the Union is certain that the strike has been won, it is, nevertheless, ready to accept arbitration, and that it will present its demands at the open hearing tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Twelve firms settled with the Union yesterday, granting all of its demands. Two pickets, Lillian Shapiro and Edith Abrahams, were arrested and held until the Union put up bail for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
