<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Forward</title>
      <date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>
      <title level="a">Chicago fur workers celebrate great victory Bosses grant all demands</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Forward</title>
     <date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>
     <title level="a">Chicago fur workers celebrate great victory Bosses grant all demands</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The furriers union yesterday recorded a great victory in its battle to keep up union conditions in the shops of the organized fur manufacturers.</p>
   <p>At a union meeting, yesterday, the settlement made by President Kaufman and the strike committee, with the representatives of the manufacturers association, was approved. The following conditions were agreed upon: The manufacturers are with drawing their demands; the minimum wage scale will not be reduced; the wages remain the same as per last year's agreement.</p>
   <p>The agreement with the fur workers union shall be binding until July 15, 1922, the beginning of the fur season. The strike breakers now employed must leave the shops where the union workers start working. The injuction cases against the union shall be withdrawn. The victory of the union was complete and greatly demonstrated the power of the union, in that the instigator of the battle against the union, for the manufacturers, was ignored, and was not permitted, to appear at the conference when the settlement was made.</p>
   <p>President Kaufman approved this settlement for the union. The workers are now going back to work after four weeks of striking. During the strike a rumor was <pb facs="5423972_3_0164.jpg" n="2"/>begun by the manufacturers that Kaufman, who was leading the strike and brought about the settlement, was leaving Chicago and that the strike would be lost. To this Kaufman replied, "The bosses were fooling themselves, I will leave Chicago only when the strike will end with victory for the union."</p>
   <p>"To day I can say that the statement I had made then is now a reality. I am leaving Chicago satisfied and happy that the workers are returning to work, victoriously, knowing their union conditions will not be tampered with until the beginning of next season."</p>
   <p>Tonight-a farewell evening will be given for President Kaufman. All members of the fur workers union local 45 will assemble at 180 W. Washington St., to bid farewell to their international President, before he leaves for New York after spending seven weeks in Chicago in the interests of the union. All members should come and say good bye to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
