<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-25">Sept. 25, 1905</date>, 1:4.
<title level="a">Ghetto Scene of Riot Mention of Witte by Adolf Kraus Causes an Uproar in a Synagogue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-09-25">Sept. 25, 1905</date>, 1:4.
<title level="a">GHETTO SCENE OF RIOT MENTION OF WITTE BY ADOLF KRAUS CAUSES AN UPROAR IN A SYNAGOGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the second time within a week the ghetto was in an uproar last night. Instead of money being the cause of the disorder, however it was the spirit of revolution, and in place of a bank as the center of activity there was a synagogue. A young Jewess, an exile from Russia, was the leader.</p>
   <p>Five hundred Russian Jews, men and women, who believe in revolutionary methods to right the wrongs of their brethren in the land of the czar, caused a riot at the Russian synagogue, Clinton and Judd streets, where Adolf Kraus was addressing a Jewish meeting. The tumult had to be quelled by the police, and ten men and women were arrested.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kraus had been talking some time and had begun to tell of his interview with Sergius Witte, at which he asked justice for the Jews through Mr. Witte's good offices.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1634.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Words Start Trouble</p>
   <p>"We may trust the word of Mr. Witte that he will do all in his power to ameliorate the sufferings of the Jews," Mr. Kraus was saying when suddenly a member of a Jewish revolutionary society sprang to his feet.</p>
   <p>"Do you trust a Russian politician," he shouted.</p>
   <p>Before Mr. Kraus had time to answer there was a roar from the men and women, most of them young and hot-headed, who belong to or sympathize with the local Jewish organizations which seek to foment revolution in Russia. Throughout Mr. Kraus' speech they had been controlling themselves with difficulty, being anxious in the extreme to show their disapproval of his trip to the East to see Witte, which they regarded as "spiritless bending of the knee to tyranny."</p>
   <p>Shouts Rend The Air</p>
   <p>The interruption gave them their chance. Five hundred men and women jumped up - some on chairs, some on each other. "Down with Witte" "Down with tyranny!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1635.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Down with the bureaucracy!" came the shouts. "Long live the revolution!"</p>
   <p>Some of Kr. Kraus' friends and officials of the synagogue sought to quell the tumult, but the Jewish revolution was not to be stopped. Miss Annie Feder, a Jewish exile from Russia, who has been imprisoned in Warsaw, became the Joan of Arc of the affair.</p>
   <p>"I protest against the action of Kraus in begging Witte for our rights," she cried, mounting a chair.</p>
   <p>Again the roar of the Jewish battle cry rang through the hall. In the excitement some man - declared by the revolutionists to be a believer in "cringing to the czar" - struck Miss Feder. That was the signal for pandemonium.</p>
   <p>Police Make Arrests</p>
   <p>Then somebody telephoned for the police. Somebody else locked the doors. The synagogue continued to be a maelstrom until the patrol wagons arrived, when ten revolutionists were arrested and the remainder dissuaded from further rioting by the sight <pb facs="5423972_3_1636.jpg" n="4"/>of drawn clubs.</p>
   <p>The prisoners, hailed as "martyrs" by the mob, were hustled into the patrols, followed by a cheering throng of men and women, who kept shouting life to revolution and death to autocracy, bureaucracy, Witte, and Nicholas. They were taken to the Maxwell Street station. Subsequently they were bailed out.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kraus, accompanied by Dr. Joseph Stolz and A. Sulenfreund, his secretary, meanwhile had made his exit from the synagogue amid hisses and had driven away. On looking over the battlefield for casualties it was found several men had suffered slight wounds of various kinds. A wrenched arm and black eye were the worst injuries reported. Miss Feder was not hurt.</p>
   <p>Special Meeting Held</p>
   <p>After the smoke of battle had cleared away the believers in a Russian revolution called a special meeting at Porgas Hall, Maxwell and Jefferson streets, which was attended by the men and women who do not think Mr. Kruas should have asked Witte for anything in the name of the Jewish people. A. Litman was the orator of the meeting, which was held at 7 o'clock, about an hour after the riot. The meeting passed some <pb facs="5423972_3_1637.jpg" n="5"/>seething resolutions, calling for the instant overturning of the czar, the grand dukes, and Mr. Witte.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kraus said last night:- "I had been invited to address the congregation on Jewish questions of the day and my remarks were in the nature of a sermon. I had spoken three-quarters of an hour, and in concluding I referred to the conference with Baron Witte and said I thought he would put forth his best endeavors in behalf of the Jews in Russia. A voice interrupted me with the declaration, 'You can't trust any of these Russian officeholders.'</p>
   <p>Regrests the Occurrence</p>
   <p>"The man who had interrupted me jumped up, and several young men in the rear joined in hooting and yelling. Members of the congregation, becoming enraged, tried to eject them and a general fist fight followed. I regret the occurrence for the sake of the congregation, the members of which had nothing to do with the interruption, as well as for the sake of the misguided young men and women who caused it. I feel no resentment toward them, but only regret at the consequences to them which must follow."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1638.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The persons booked at the station were: Hyman Nikter, Sophie Nikter, Sara Sammon, Sam Pass, Ed Schwartz and Abe Alpert. Four men and women arrested were allowed to go at the station, no charge being entered against them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
