<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-25">Apr. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditations of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I B 3 b (Italian)</item>
     <item>II E 3 (Italian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-25">Apr. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATIONS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Symphony Orchestra has frequently been proclaimed as the first in the land. Last year it went on an Eastern trip and visited New York, Boston, Philadelphia, and, if our memory serves us right, also Washington, and brought back golden opinions of its golden ensemble talents. In brief, everywhere it was acclaimed as a great orchestra. Now we Chicagoans, who have attended its concerts and have frequently thought that the expense of the company must be enormous, that each man in the orchestra was receiving at least his seven or ten thousand dollars a year, have the surprise of our lives, literally speaking, on reading the fact in our daily paper that there is danger that the whole company of artists may be dissolved because of their demand that their minimum weekly wage be raised from sixty dollars per week to sixty-seven fifty. There may be individual players in the orchestra who receive more but the low minimum wage does not suggest that any of them are receiving fabulous sums. The <pb facs="5423972_3_0082.jpg" n="2"/>director, Mr. Stock, undoubtedly receives a living wage--in all probability as much as all the members of his company put together. No one may quarrel with that. He is entitled to what he gets, but this is a peculiar world indeed, where a skilled musician of a famous orchestra receives a minimum salary of sixty dollars.</p>
   <p>Since we are on the subject of music, we may make some comments on a statement by Miss Martha Scott of Hull House. Miss Scott teaches music to classes totaling 125 boys each week. These are mostly Italians, according to her report, who come from homes where they are beaten if they do not earn enough from selling newspapers or shining shoes. These boys are easily disposed to take advantage of a situation to lighten their burdened lives and have an easy road to crime almost forced upon them by circumstances. Music gives them relief; music softens their tempers, made harsh by a drab life, and inspires them with an ideal that is a builder of character and aids them to cope with their problems, when they are young and when they grow older. Music for many reasons is certainly one of the most significant of the arts. It is the most popular in appeal. In view of these facts, does it not appear somewhat ludicrous that men of the undisputed <pb facs="5423972_3_0083.jpg" n="3"/>musical talent as the players of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra have to fight for a minimum wage of $67.50? The Civic Opera pays its participants on the stage in thousands, and opera is less instructive than symphonic music. America pays big sums also to its business executives, while it starves its artists. Yet American critics often marvel at the lack of native talent. The explanation is very often evident enough for those who want to see as much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
