<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-15">Jan. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Ku Klux Klan Murder Case in Louisiana</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-15">Jan. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE KU KLUX KLAN MURDER CASE IN LOUISIANA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The facts which have been disclosed regarding the case of the brutal double murder in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, prove very clearly that the Ku Klux Klan is a criminal organization which sanctions terrorist acts of the worst sort. It is high time that the Government took a decisive step against such a reactionary and treacherous clique. Naturally, not all the members of the Klan can be held directly responsible for the horrible acts of the Klan in Baton Rouge, but each one of them, whether in Louisiana or in Illinois, must bear the moral guilt of this act, because every Klan member, wherever he may be, is, according to his oath of allegiance to the Imperial Wizard, obligated to help and defend the Ku Klux Klan murderers of Baton Rouge, as well as other criminals of the Klan.</p>
   <p>There is only one method which can be used against such a criminal <pb facs="5423972_3_1408.jpg" n="2"/>organization as the Ku Klux Klan, viz., suppress it through the might of the law, before it is too late, i. e., before the law is suppressed by the Klan. Unfortunately, the Federal Government has hitherto refused to take a direct stand against the Ku Klux Klan on the technical ground that it [the Klan] falls within the jurisdiction of the State Government. The terror of Baton Rouge proves, however, that the Klan can paralyze the Government machinery. It also proves that what was done in one district, can be done on a larger scale throughout the entire country if measures are not taken in time against such acts of terrorism. Will the [Federal] Government act now?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
