<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-19">June 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">On the Field of Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Undeserved Attack on Ben Schlessinger</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0727</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0727.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-19">June 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE FIELD OF LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Undeserved Attack on Ben Schlessinger</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brother Benjamin Schlessinger, president of the International Ladies Garment Workers of America, is well beloved and greatly honored by all who know him. It was therefore with a feeling of pain and chagrin that the Jewish workers of the United States and Canada read the news that last week at the convention of the American Federation of Labor he was insulted by a delegate named Duffy, and hissed at by other delegates--all because he, Schlessinger, dared to act in accordance with his convictions as a loyal labor leader and a true patriot.</p>
   <p>The first time Mr. Schlessinger was attacked by this delegate who wanted to advertise himself as a patriot, was when Schlessinger protested against a statement made in the report of the American Labor Commission. This commission went to Europe to confer with organized labor in England and France <pb facs="5423972_3_0728.jpg" n="2"/>about founding an international federation of workers. In this report the commission expressed itself as being in favor of such a federation, but that from it politicians and theorists should be excluded--meaning the socialists. Mr. Schlessinger, as a socialist, protested against the commission's proposal.</p>
   <p>The second time he was attacked was when he asked in what light the delegates would consider his vote, when he votes in favor of the peace resolutions of the English and French workers.</p>
   <p>As has been stated, Mr. Schlessinger was attacked for his convictions, despite the fact that he represents an organization which has purchased hundreds of thousands of dollars worth of Liberty bonds, and has contributed huge sums of money for the Red Cross and other patriotic purposes. But all these denunciations did not perturb the president of the International Ladies Garment <pb facs="5423972_3_0729.jpg" n="3"/>Workers. He fought courageously at the convention for the interests of the worker. And it is to be hoped that he will conduct the organizational campaign of the Chicago ladies' waist makers and white goods workers, with similar courage. This organizational campaign was decided upon at the last convention of the International Ladies Garment Workers in Boston.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the fact that different opinions prevail among the delegates of the convention on certain questions, the convention of the A.F. of L. has already accomplished a great deal. Some very important resolutions have been passed; one demanding that the government refuse to carry on its railroads goods produced in factories employing children; another asking President Wilson either to pardon or to obtain a fair trial for Tom Mooney; a third, asking the government to levy a large tax on war-profits; demanding that the government take over the telegraph business if the companies do not concede the telegraphers' demand that they be given the right to organize; appointing special organizers to help the International in its organizational campaign <pb facs="5423972_3_0730.jpg" n="4"/>in Cleveland and Chicago. Other important resolutions are also being considered at the convention.</p>
   <p>Should the above-mentioned resolutions be fruitful, then the thirty-eighth convention of the American Federation of Labor will have accomplished important and praiseworthy work for the whole of American labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
