<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-02-07">Feb. 7, 1923</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-02-07">Feb. 7, 1923</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a special meeting of the United Hebrew Trades, a committee of three, consisting of Louis Schaeffer, manager of the Forward, Peter Sussman and Abraham Bizno, made known the verdict against Leon Green, business agent of the Retail Clerks Union.</p>
   <p>Comrade Schaeffer, represented the United Hebrew Trades in the committee that listened to the charges, read the decision, which reads as follows: that the charges, which were made by the officers of the Cook County Retail Merchants Association, that they have given Leon Green, in the presence of Harry Winik, president of local 195, three thousand dollars April 2, 1920, in Mr. Bryers office is true and the committee finds that Green is guilty and recommends that he should immediately be impeached from his office in the local, because he is not fit to be a representative of workers.</p>
   <p>The decision also reads that Harry Winik can be accused, because he knew of the negotiations, although it is not known definitely what part of the money he has taken.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0094.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The United Hebrew Trades have determined to see that the verdict shall be carried through and that Leon Green shall be removed from the labor movement.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bryer and Mr. Maremont made charges against Green and Winik; both testified that they have given the money to Green in the presence of Winik. The United Hebrew Trades became aware of the charges and compelled the Union to take up the case and make an investigation.</p>
   <p>Both, the United Hebrew Trades and a committee of the Union have chosen a committee of three from each side and the six appointed; Peter Sussman as chairman of the trial Committee and the United Hebrew Trades appointed Schaeffer and the Union Bizno as judge. These three acted as judges and they have given out and undersigned the verdict against Green.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
