<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-15">June 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Workmen's Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Edwards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-15">June 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WORKMEN'S INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Edwards</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That the Chicago Cloak Manufacturers were not feeling so happy yesterday and, together with their colleagues, the bosses of the local waist, dress, and skirt shops, walked back and forth troubled and worried, holding on tightly to their check books as if someone was going to take something away from them, is something for which we can scarcely blame them. As it is, it would have been sheer hypocrisy for them to remain indifferent to what was going on at the convention of the American Federation of Labor in Atlantic City, where they were mentioned and mentioned more than what is good for them. Yes, they know what it means when workmen discuss them in strong terms, and their fears were not unfounded either. The thing has really happened.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0225.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The convention accepted a resolution to aid the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union in its forthcoming fight to improve working conditions among the waist and cloak workers in Chicago. That the Federation of Labor means business is well known to all manufacturers, and so it is no wonder that the bosses paced back and forth yesterday, clutching their checkbooks in their hands, the very same checkbooks which have a habit of getting leaner when the workmen receive somewhat of an increase.</p>
   <p>The Jewish bakery workers must and will retain their hard-won positions. This is the unanimous opinion of the entire Jewish working movement in Chicago. If the recently ended many-month strike of non-Jewish bakery workers has instilled in Jewish Baker bosses the desire to reinstate night work, which about six weeks ago was again permanently abolished when Local 237 renewed <pb facs="5423972_3_0226.jpg" n="3"/>its agreement, the bosses will get no further than just desiring, because local Jewish bakery workers in their thirty-five years of union experience, have never learned the art of returning to discarded methods. Under no circumstances will they relinquish their present positions.</p>
   <p>Those who witnessed the Friday meeting of Local 237 could easily see how strongly determined the Jewish bakery workers were on the matter of not returning to night work, a matter which is at present definitely buried. It would be much healthier for the bosses to expel from their minds the queer and impossible thought of trying to regain that which the union holds so fast in its locked arms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
