<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-27">Mar. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Poverty and Crime</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-27">Mar. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POVERTY AND CRIME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A man does not commit a wrong unless the spirit of evil enters his mind. These are the words of the ancient Hebrew sages, in whose times the idea was entertained that sinners and criminals were possessed by evil spirits the very day they were born. We know better now; we know that evil thoughts don't enter people's heads before they commit crimes. Criminal traits are not born with the individual, even if the words of our sages are often confirmed by cases in which normal individuals commit crimes as the result of foolish thoughts entering their minds, crimes which they regret as soon as they get over their emotions.</p>
   <p>The judges before whom this type of criminal is brought, are always trying to find a justification for the crime. Here in America the lawyers have devised for this type of criminal a list of names, among which "dementia Americana" is the most popular. For such a criminal the unwritten law <pb facs="5423972_3_1596.jpg" n="2"/>is often sought, a law under which the crime is viewed from the standpoint of the ancient Hebrew sages.</p>
   <p>The attorneys for the defense of Madame Kaya, wife of the French finance minister, who murdered the editor of Figaro, seek a justification for this crime in the unwritten law, and it is quite possible that she will be acquitted, just as her sisters, involved in a murder in Chicago, were acquitted on the same grounds.</p>
   <p>A poor criminal, however, who is driven to crime through want and privation is often severily punished for a petty offense. It is in exceptional cases only that judges are swayed to the realization that the spirits of starvation and cold are stronger than those of envy and jealousy.</p>
   <p>In France, a murderer at one time confessed the slaying of a wealthy woman in the following words:</p>
   <p>"I am not guilty. Evil thoughts entered my mind. I saw gold on her and the <pb facs="5423972_3_1597.jpg" n="3"/>temptation was too strong. I did not know what I was doing. You may do whatever you wish with me." His words created such a stir of emotion as to touch the embittered hearts of the judges and closest relatives of the victim. All were convinced that evil spirits had entered the man and transformed him into a beast. He had remained thus possessed until the human spirit awakened again in him and it was then that he sensed the hideousness of his act.</p>
   <p>His was the case of an unemployed worker who in good times used to earn a living by the sweat of his brow. His ambition was to have sufficient strength to work in order to procure enough bread to eat, nothing else but bread, bread to gain strength to work. When the famished worker saw a wealthy lady wearing a golden chain, the gold, the metal that protects its owner from work and hunger, was stronger than he. They (the wealthy) don't have to toil, yet they have more than those who work hard, and are better safeguarded against hunger and cold. The glitter of the coveted metal had overwhelmed this poor man, and he felt nothing but one strong urge, <pb facs="5423972_3_1598.jpg" n="4"/>to have it, to possess it.</p>
   <p>As long as there exist the hungry and the well-fed, the rich and the poor, -- and apparently this will be the case for a long time to come, -- we shall not want in thieves, murderers, counterfeiters, arsonists, and others. The growth of labor unions and the higher development of the masses make the present-day worker realize that he is no longer to be tempted by the glitter of gold alone, not even when he is hungry. The time has come when a worker gets indignant when he realizes that the ones who work get less than those who idle. He no longer rebels against this protracted injustice with the evil thoughts of a criminal, but rather with the rational spirit of one who is certain of his final victory. He joins powerful groups and parties that will abolish the dishonest rule of money and restore the honest, natural rule of trade and commerce.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
