<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-26">November 26, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-11-26">November 26, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Locals 5 and 18 Accept Schlessinger's Recommendations.</p>
   <p>At Friday's meeting of the Joint Board, Locals 5 and 18 reported that they had determined to accept President Schlessinger's recommendations.</p>
   <p>That, shows that the situation of the Cloakmakers Union is almost straightened out. The question is, will they pass through the Joint Board? Perhaps the matters should have been discussed, but most of the time was spent on complaints and cases against business agents, the latter in some cases, being exaggerated, because of the coming election of the business agents. At any rate, after the manager of the Joint Board, Mr. Fogel, answered the complaints, those who had asked the questions admitted that he had been just. Much time was also spent in discussing the question of getting a larger hall for the Joint Board meetings, a claim being made that there must be more room so the shop chairmen could be present at the meetings. Delegate Novak said, "For economy's sake let us get along the best way we can for the time being. Let the shop chairmen come to <pb facs="5423972_3_0505.jpg" n="2"/>our meetings, and if we fail to accommodate all of them, then it will be time to discuss the question of renting a larger hall." This plan was accepted.</p>
   <p>At our next meeting, President Schlessinger's recommendations concerning the Joint Board will be taken up for discussion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
