<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-09-15">Sept. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Workers' Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-09-15">Sept. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS' GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish labor movement of Chicago is a movement sans soul, sans life, and sans will-power, the most insignificant one in comparison with the large, general labor movement of Chicago. The Jewish trades are the most poorly organized,comprising the smallest part, the most insignificant number among the large powerfully organized army of workers who carry on a struggle in the economic field for better conditions for both the present and future.</p>
   <p>Eighty per cent of the workers of the needle trades are unorganized and work under feudal conditions. There are trades that have not even begun organizational work. The Jewish trades that are already organized are so weak that the slightest wind can topple them. The United Hebrew <pb facs="5423972_3_0752.jpg" n="2"/>Trades, which was organized as a central body to help strengthen the organized trades and to organize the unorganized, is in poor shape today. Cultural conditions are just as bad as economic conditions among the Jewish workers - no lectures, no libraries, no centers for meetings.</p>
   <p>Why are the Jewish workers afflicted so? Where are our labor intelligentsia and labor leaders? They are not here....You will probably say, "That is a mistake, they are here!" You will find them in the "literary clubs," "dramatic clubs," at May 1, demonstrations, at picnics, in "Kabitzarnes" (a Kibitzing place), and at banquets; that is where our intelligentsia and labor leaders spend their time and energy. They are deaf to the groans of the thousands of Jewish workers who are being oppressed and <pb facs="5423972_3_0753.jpg" n="3"/>exploited in the factories and shops; they are blind to the poverty in the Jewish workers' districts. They are busy with philosophy, literature, and banquet-toasts, and there is no time for the daily struggles.</p>
   <p>The Jewish labor movement lacks vitality. The spirit, life, energy, and devotion to help construct a sound Jewish labor movement are missing.</p>
   <p>Winter will soon be setting in, and you will see a movement evolve among our intelligentsia to provide the Jewish "illiterate" masses with philosophy, literature and drama. No, my friends! The Jewish workers are, first of all, in need of bread, coal and rent. They want, above everything, to free themselves from sweat shops, from long hours and humiliation, and they can not feed and clothe their children with reviews on Hegel or Kant's philosophy, or on Sholom Ash's God of Revenge.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0754.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let us ask the respective unions that belong to the United Hebrew Trades, and which have appointed delegates (some two, others three,and four), "Why don't the appointed delegates attend the meetings of the United Hebrew Trades?" We can draw up a list of unions that are never represented at meetings, or if they are one is present when three or four should be.</p>
   <p>Do the delegates think that the United Hebrew Trades is like a countrymen's verein, and that they therefore do not have to attend meetings? The United Hebrew Trades, friends, is a responsible labor body embracing important pursuits. The presence of every delegate is a necessity - a duty. Should a delegate neglect his duties the union must, without fail, penalize him and appoint someone else as a delegate to the United Hebrew Trades.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
