<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-07">Feb. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Newly Elected Amalgamated Joint Board Holds its First Meeting</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Meyer Kaufman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-07">Feb. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">NEWLY ELECTED AMALGAMATED JOINT BOARD HOLDS ITS FIRST MEETING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Meyer Kaufman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Joint Board of the Amalgamated, which was recently elected, held its first meeting last week at the Amalgamated headquarters. Also present were the old delegates of the Joint Board.</p>
   <p>The credentials report noted that locals 6,38,39,61,144,152, and 270 were represented at the Joint Board by ten delegates from each local; local 269 was represented by 7 delegates, local 271 by 3 delegates, and local 272 by two delegates. The total number of delegates was eighty-six. The officials of the Joint Board will be elected at the next regular meeting of the Board.</p>
   <p>The meeting of the Joint Board was devoted chiefly to an interesting discussion <pb facs="5423972_3_0487.jpg" n="2"/>of various organizational problems: activities of the Amalgamated, conditions in the needle trades industry, greetings [received], the problem of help to the unemployed, and so on. The meeting was somewhat enlivened by the reports of business agents concerning an improvement in the various departments of the tailoring industry in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was reported that many shops have reopened, among them the shops of Leopold and Solomon, Dobby Rosenthal, Lilenthal and Sons, Leigendorf and Company, Fogel Brothers, and many other independent and association shops, which have been closed for many months. This report was accepted with enthusiasm by all the members of the Joint Board who now, on the basis of these reports, hope for a general improvement in the tailoring industry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
