<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-16">May 16, 1927</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-16">May 16, 1927</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The communist business agents of the Chicago Cloak Makers Joint Board are willing to sell out the Union and destroy the agreement, in order to get one of their communist "commissars" a job. That this is a fact is proved by the case that occurred last week in J. Coopersmith's shop, 115 S. Market Street.</p>
   <p>The left wing business agent, Harry Zeff, sent Dora Lifshiltz, leader among the communist girls of Local #100, to report for work at the above mentioned firm.</p>
   <p>The boss wanted to discharge her from her position, so Comrade Zeff entered the scene and made a deal with the boss to this effect: that Dora should remain on the job and, in return, the boss would allow her privileges are not permitted anyone else.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1297.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First of all, the business agent commanded the tailors to work until 5 o'clock on Saturday, a thing that is against the agreement with the Union. In accordance with the agreement 44 hours a week are permitted, Saturday until 2 o'clock. The contract expressly states that over time is not allowed.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday, the tailors worked four hours more than the agreement calls for. This alone, however, does not complete the story.</p>
   <p>The business agent agreed with the employer that Dora would not be the shop chairman and would keep her mouth closed about Union affairs. She was to remain silent in the midst of the horrible treatment of the workers as long as her job was safe. She immediately fulfilled this task by working over time, last Saturday, and sold all her communistic principles for a mess of pottage. The communist representatives of the local Cloak and Dress Makers' Union commit such acts, which are, to them, just and wonderful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
