<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-18">May 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Cigar Makers' Strike and How it Can Be Settled</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Pozner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0863</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0863.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-18">May 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CIGAR MAKERS' STRIKE AND HOW IT CAN BE SETTLED</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Pozner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past six weeks, a cigar makers' strike or lockout has been going on at Baron Brothers, 1911 West Van Buren Street, manufacturers of the High Sovereign cigars. Forty Jews, fathers of families, are taking part in the strike, which is being led by the Amalgamated Tobacco Workers.</p>
   <p>The company closed the shop during the first three weeks of the strike but then it adopted a new policy: it opened the shop and began to use strikebreakers. The Union had, meanwhile, also changed its policy. At the beginning of the strike it merely picketed the striking shop, but recently it began to issue propaganda concerning the strike, appealing for public sympathy.</p>
   <p>Both sides suffer from this method of struggle. The company suffers because <pb facs="5423972_3_0864.jpg" n="2"/>it hired strikebreakers who certainly cannot do the work as well as the old, experienced cigar makers. The reputation of their product will suffer because of that. Furthermore, many cigar smokers will, undoubtedly, stop smoking cigars that are made by strikebreakers. The strikers suffer because industrial conditions are bad, and it is not easy for a striker to go around idle, even though the Union is paying strike benefit.</p>
   <p>I visited both sides yesterday and found out how they felt about this prolonged struggle. The representative of the Cigar Makers' Union, Mr. Miller, told me that the dispute arose because Baron Brothers paid its workers two dollars less per thousand cigars than the other manufacturers. The Union had voluntarily agreed, about two months ago, to a cut in wages of two dollars per thousand cigars, from the other manufacturers, and Baron Brothers had also introduced the cut in their shop, although they were not, according to the declaration of the Union, entitled to it. Mr. Miller said that the strikers were ready to go on striking as long as it was necessary. Most of the strikers are employed, and those who have no jobs, receive strike benefits from the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0865.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The manufacturers, Baron Brothers, told me their version of the strike. They claim that they have always paid the wages decided upon by the Union. When the Union made the two dollar reduction in wages, they were notified about it and they introduced it in their shop. Now, they say, they have an adequate number of strikebreakers; they are operating at full force and do not seek any settlement.</p>
   <p>However, the facts, as I have shown, prove that both sides suffer in this strike, and there is no reason for the strike to continue. A settlement in this strike is entirely feasible. If both sides would come together, they would certainly arrive at some understanding. The cigar makers strike can be settled to the satisfaction of both parties who are stubborn, and do not want to propose a settlement committee to each other.</p>
   <p>I, therefore, propose that both parties should choose representatives to discuss a settlement. Any point upon which they cannot agree, should be left to the decision of the arbitrator, whose decision should be binding on both sides.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0866.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If they do not wish to have simply one arbitrator, they should leave the decision to a board of three arbitrators, one to be chosen by the company, one to be chosen by the Union, and the third to be chosen by agreement between the first two arbitrators. I am certain that a speedy settlement can be effected in that way. Gentlemen of both sides! Do you accept my proposition? Let me hear your answer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
