<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-06-07">June 7, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0759</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0759.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-06-07">June 7, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Worker's Ghetto.</p>
   <p>The organization of the Jewish Tailoring Trades. - New unions constantly being formed. - The latest demands of the Cloak Makers Union. - A mass-meeting of the cloak makers, skirt makers, finishers, and pressers.</p>
   <p>The last few years have shown remarkable progress in the organization of the various tailoring trades. Working conditions have been greatly improved but they are still not what they should be. Hours are long, prices still at the hunger level, are set by the bosses and the foremen.</p>
   <p>The United Garment Workers, being the only truly strong union, has now embarked on an organization campaign of organizing the unorganized, and aiding and guiding the smaller and weaker unions. They are out really to improve working conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0760.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Jewish Tailors! Are you satisfied with your present working conditions? Certainly not. Join a union and improve your working conditions. The following should be the program of all tailoring unions: The prices in every shop should be set by a shop committee in consultation with the boss and not by the boss himself. Prices for duplicate should be the same as that for stock. No work after 12 P. M. on Saturday. One full hour for lunch. Wages should be paid weekly. Extra pay for overtime work.</p>
   <p>The above were the latest demands of the Cloak Makers Union. We believe that these demands should be the demands of all workers in these trades. Such demands can only be realized through strong unions and consolidated action. The Fall season is approaching and the time is now ripe for action. But a united front is necessary to gain our ends.</p>
   <p>The mass meeting has been called by the Cloak Makers Union, Local 44, International <pb facs="5423972_3_0761.jpg" n="3"/>Garment Workers, and American Federation of Labor. Their Chicago office is at 1125 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>The foremost principle of all unions is to better the economic life of its members, by obtaining for them better working conditions, better pay, and shorter hours. We are convinced, fellow workers, that only through organization can we achieve the goal toward which we are striving, a more abundant life for ourselves and our families.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Shochet Ben Ha-Rav.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
