<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1916-10-13">October 13, 1916</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1916-10-13">October 13, 1916</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great tailor strike broke out in Chicago in 1910. It had more of the character of an outbreak, or a revolt, rather than a strike. Hardly any of the workers belonged to the union. No discussions were held regarding a strike. No vote was taken for a strike.</p>
   <p>A girl working in an open shop at Hart, Shaffner, and Marx, had an argument with the foreman who then discharged her. Nine other girls then ceased working, in sympathy with this seventeen year old girl. These ten girls were the cause of a strike of over 40,000 workers. As soon as this shop stopped working, the news started to travel from one shop to another and in a very short time, there was not a wheel turning in the tailoring industry in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was not an ordinary strike. It was a strike without money, without a thorough understanding, without pre-arranged plans and without leaders. The many different nationalities of strikers banded together. One thing they had all agreed upon, to demand recognition of the union and a closed shop. The reason for this was that for a period of time the manufacturers suppressed the union people and the workers felt that they cannot improve their <pb facs="5423972_3_1082.jpg" n="2"/>conditions until their union will be assured of a closed shop. Shorter hours, higher prices, decent conditions and authority in the shop - all this will be accomplished through bargaining collectively. In this strike, not only tailors participated, but in a short time the strikers won the active participation of Chicago's progressives. Ministers, rabbis, university professors, bankers, all joined in the work of the striking tailors - held speeches - raised funds - wrote articles in the daily papers - and encouraged the strikers in their great battle.</p>
   <p>At that time two manufacturers' associations were in existence, one of the ready-made clothing, the other for special order makers. The firm of Hart, Shaffner and Marx, who at that time employed 45,000 workers - did not belong to any of the associations. The United Garment Workers, who at that time also took in special order makers have sent their entire executive board, with their president, to Chicago, to try and take charge of the strike, but the strikers didn't have enough confidence in the leaders of the United Garment Workers. John Fitzpatrick, president of the Chicago Federation of Labor, who took a great deal of interest in the strike and Mrs. Raymund Robbins - had no confidence in the United Garment Workers, <pb facs="5423972_3_1083.jpg" n="3"/>so the strikers then carried on the strike independently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
