<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-04-18">April 18, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Conference Determines to Call a Hugh Protest Meeting against the Condemnation of Sacco and Vanzetti</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-04-18">April 18, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR CONFERENCE DETERMINES TO CALL A HUGH PROTEST MEETING AGAINST THE CONDEMNATION OF SACCO AND VANZETTI</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of the Jewish unions of the United Hebrew Trades, delegates of the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle, and of the Jewish Socialist Alliance, organized themselves to carry on the protest movement against the condemnation of Sacco and Vanzetti, and to demand that the Governor of Massachusetts should grant them their pardon.</p>
   <p>Comrade Leon Hannek, secretary of the United Hebrew Trades, opened the conference and declared that it was determined to call a conference for the purpose of organizing a protest movement among the Jewish masses, as well as uniting with the Chicago Federation of Labor. Comrade L. Benenson was elected chairman, and Comrade Morris Ziskind, secretary.</p>
   <p>After the election of officers, delegates of a few left branches of the Workmen's Circles, that do not belong to the City Central Committee of the W. C. demanded admission to the conference. Comrade Benenson related the decision of the United Hebrew Trades and informed them that the three bodies that constitute the conference will not have any relationship with the communists and in order to avoid hinderance will not drag this element into the protest <pb facs="5423972_3_1306.jpg" n="2"/>movement.</p>
   <p>The conference appointed an Executive Committee consisting of the following delegates: L. Hannek, H. Rufel, M. Ziskind, M. Israelson, Nachtigal, D. Silverstein, Braveman, M. Blumin, Bloomfield, and M. Rappaport.</p>
   <p>The conference decided to send letters to all affiliated organizations urging them to send protest resolutions to the Governor of Massachusetts. It was also resolved to send delegates - Blumin and Ziskind - to the Sacco Vanzetti Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
