<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-08-05">August 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Society and Industrial Workers</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0722</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0722.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-08-05">August 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY AND INDUSTRIAL WORKERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The trial of the industrial workers which has been continued for the past few months in Chicago is not far from its end. The plaintiff tried to prove that the defendants, member of the Industrial Workers of the World, are a detriment to the welfare of society. Their agitation and sabotage often strikes among unorganized workers, propagate the masses to animosity, and disturb the peace and order of society.</p>
   <p>Before Judge Landis, the plaintiff tried to confirm its statement with reading articles, letters, and general literature published by the I.W.W., but was unable to present personal witnesses to confirm the charges. The defendant was successful in obtaining witnesses who proved that the strikes caused by the Industrial Workers was not intended to propagate the masses against capital, nor to disturb the peace, but to exclusively improve the conditions of the workers, through shorter hours and better pay, and if anyone agitated or wrote against war, it was not with the intention to disturb the government in their plans for war, but that their principles are against war.</p>
   <p>The witnesses called by the defendants are of all classes. The accused appeared and declared their principles and theories to the judge and jury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0723.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If the government feels obligated to protect the nation for individualism, then why should not the individual be protected from society? If agitation and encouraging strikes is a crime in the eyes of the law, then whi is the manufacturer not forced to pay a living wage, establish shorter work-days, to consider the worker as a partner in the production? If one is arrested as a disturber of society, for insisting upon his natural rights, why not the other? If one is a criminal, for demanding bread and clothing for himself and his family, why shall not the one who robs the other of these things he needs to sustain his livelihood, not be considered a criminal?</p>
   <p>Capital and government are one, and the working class is completely a different part of society and when the worker wants to attain his natural rights, he must accomplish it on the economic field through unions and politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
