<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-29">May 29, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Communist Fakers of the Chicago Cloak Makers Joint Board Killed the Unemployment Insurance Fund, Friday Evening. They Gave the Employers a Gift Amounting to a Few Thousand Dollars a Year</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-05-29">May 29, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMMUNIST FAKERS OF THE CHICAGO CLOAK MAKERS JOINT BOARD KILLED THE UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE FUND, FRIDAY EVENING. THEY GAVE THE EMPLOYERS A GIFT AMOUNTING TO A FEW THOUSAND DOLLARS A YEAR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The agreement which the Joint Board made, two years ago, with the Cloak Manufacturers Association was that the employer must pay 1 1/2 cents for every dollar they pay out in wages and the workers agreed to pay 3/4 of a cent in order to receive $60 a month when unemployed.</p>
   <p>When the communists went into office and became busy with their communistic politics, to destroy the International, they forgot entirely that such a thing as an Unemployment Fund exists and did not collect anything from the employers for two seasons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1293.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When President Zigman was recently in Chicago, he inquired about the Unemployment Fund and found out that it is as good as killed, because the communists do not collect anything from the bosses.</p>
   <p>The communist clique foresaw trouble by neglecting their duty to take care of the fund, so they commenced to speak with the employers about the Unemployment Insurance Fund and pleaded that the slow season is already at hand and there is no money to pay insurance benefits. The wanted to evade the issue completely.</p>
   <p>The communist leaders have seen that they are in bad shape due to ignoring the agreement, so they compromised with the bosses to this effect: they reduced one-half of the employer's contributions; instead of the bosses paying 1 1/2 cents they will only pay 3/4 cent, i. e. instead of them paying $50,000 annually, they will only pay $25,000 a year now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1294.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From this sum a certain portion will go to the expense of management. The office will only have a balance of four or five thousand dollars to pay unemployment insurance to the six hundred cloak makers of Chicago, who are entitled to the benefits of the fund.</p>
   <p>The communists accepted this plan knowing that they have broken the agreement with the association and have killed the Unemployment Insurance Fund. The Communist manager, himself, reported at the Joint Board in the presence of President Zigman, Judge Horner, the arbitrator urged the employers to live up to the agreement by contributing toward the fund for the unemployed in order not to break the agreement.</p>
   <p>The communist leaders will certainly insist that they achieved a victory for the workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1295.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The truth is that the victory was accomplished two years ago, when the old administration signed the agreement and introduced the insurance fund.</p>
   <p>The cloak makers have fought in vain because the communists have annihilated everything.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
