<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-12-31">December 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Chicago Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-12-31">December 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE CHICAGO AMALGAMATED CLOTHING WORKERS UNION</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Morris Ziskind</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Amalgamated is supervised by the Joint Board, the central body of all locals. The Joint Board passes on certain policies and undertakings, then brings them before the membership to act upon. In the last year, the Joint Board supervised a few important undertakings, which show the great spirit of cooperation of the organized clothing workers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>THE AMALGAMATED TRUST AND SAVINGS BANK.</p>
   <p>One of the greatest and most important steps, was this bank - the only labor bank in Chicago. In the first six months, this bank had one-million-one hundred and thirty-thousand dollars in deposits. Mr. Redefer claims the bank has a three-hundred-thousand dollar capital and its surplus with the checking accounts amounts to a million and a half. The bank for its short existence has four-thousand depositors. It is hoped that in the near future, plans will be made to send money to Russia, and pay out there with American dollars.</p>
   <p>One of the most important additions of the Amalgamated was the installation of an employment bureau with its main office at 409 S. Halsted St. This <pb facs="5423972_3_0502.jpg" n="2"/>also has been accomplished in the last six months of 1922.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated came to the conclusion that it is necessary to have full control of the jobs and of the distribution of the workers in the shops. They were so successful that the bosses must contact the employment bureau. The worker must register in this employment bureau - and must not wait at the bureau office - according to the new system. When he is next in line on the registration list - and a call comes from a boss - he is notified by a card to go to work.</p>
   <p>RESPONSIBILITY OF THE WORKERS' WAGES AGAINST NON-UNION CONTRACTORS.</p>
   <p>The workers shall notify the union that they did not receive their wages on time. The contractor ran away with their pay - or that he went bankrupt. The manager will immediately notify the manufacturer that his contractor did not pay his help, and the manufacturer is responsible for the pay.</p>
   <p>THE CREDIT UNION TO HELP MEMBERS IN DISTRESS.</p>
   <p>A credit union installed by the Amalgamated is another important factor. Many of the members who have been out of employment for a long time have <pb facs="5423972_3_0503.jpg" n="3"/>been helped with money - that he paid back, with no interest, in small weekly payments during the time that he worked. The members appreciate the fact that the union is doing good for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
