<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-01-07">January 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Organization Meeting Calendar</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-01-07">January 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Organization Meeting Calendar</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City Central Committee of the Workers Ring is meeting tonight for the purpose of discussing several vital questions and problems of our organization. All delegates must be present, and all members are requested to attend this important meeting because of the vital campaign issues that are coming up for consideration.</p>
   <p>Douglas Park S. P. Branch Notice.</p>
   <p>A regular meeting of the Douglas Park S. P. Branch and a joint meeting of all party members of all branches in the 34th ward will be held tomorrow evening at 8 o'clock, at the Headquarters, 3225 W. 12th St. The regular meeting of the branch is for the purpose of electing officers. After the election of officers, the joint meeting of all party members will take place.</p>
   <p>N. W. Side, S. P. Branch, meets this evening at 204 W. Division St. Hon. K. Marmor will lecture on the three vital questions in the German Socialistic movements.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jewish Socialist Song and Orchestra Society will have their regular annual meeting tonight, Tuesday, at 8 P. M., at the Hebrew Institute. A report for the whole year of 1918 will be presented. Election of officers and many important problems will be discussed, which must be handled at this meeting. All members, old and new, must come without fail promptly at 8 P. M.</p>
   <p>A. Galichki, Secretary.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Dryfuss, German translator, Secretary of the S. P. will lecture this evening at 8 P. M., at the headquarters of the 13th Ward, 3058 W. 12th St. The subject of his lecture will be 'The Revolution in Europe.' Admission free.</p>
   <p>The Ladies Tailors Union, Local 104, will meet this evening, at 180 W. Washington St. Very important business will be transacted.</p>
   <p>The new branch of the Ladies Tailors Alteration Union, meets tomorrow evening, <pb facs="5423972_3_1526.jpg" n="3"/>at 1145 Blue Island Ave. One dollar joining fee is the charge. All workers in cloak stores are urged to join this union.</p>
   <p>Zionist members of Branch 7, will hold a special meeting on Saturday evening, at 8:30 and all members are requested to come on time. The Delegate will make his full report of the Zionist Convention in Philadelphia. Friends are cordially invited.</p>
   <p>H. Bandrin, Rec. Secretary.</p>
   <p>Tonight at 8 P. M., the Progressive Organization, will hold a conference for the purpose of electing delegates to the Workers Congress at 1129 Ashland Blvd. There is no question that all organizations will be interested in this meeting. Those who have not as yet, elected their delegates, may be instructed through their officers. There will be other questions and problems to come up for discussion at this conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
