<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-12">Oct. 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Vote and Jewish Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1738</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1738.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-12">Oct. 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH VOTE AND JEWISH INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The anti-Semitic accusations that the Jewish citizens do not vote at the elections as Americans but as Jews, and that they vote only from the standpoint of Jewish and not American interests, are absolutely false. Anyone can realize this from his own daily life. Jews vote as Democrats, Republicans, Socialists, etc., and not as nationalists, assimilators, Orthodox, or freethinkers. Contrary to the anti-Semitic opinion, there is no Jewish vote. When a Jew goes to the polls he goes as an American citizen, as an adherent of this or that American political party, not as a member of a Jewish party. There is no Jewish party in America. Jewish voters belong to various parties.</p>
   <p>While there is no Jewish vote in America, there are, however, Jewish interests, just as there are Irish or prohibition interests. In a country with a population of one hundred and ten million people, of whom many have immigrated from <pb facs="5423972_3_1739.jpg" n="2"/>various parts of the world, it would be impossible to avoid having groups that have their own interests, quite legitimate interests, which do not encroach on American interests. The Jews, as a group, have their own interests which not only do not violate American interests, but which, in the final analysis, are also American interests because they are the interests of humanity and justice.</p>
   <p>What are the interests of the Jews of America? They want to keep Uncle Sam always on the side of the persecuted and the oppressed; they want him to protest against injustice; against persecution and massacres of the Jews; they want him to open the gates of this country to the persecuted of Europe, who come here with the earnest intention of working and of becoming loyal citizens of this country. Like all other citizens of America, the American Jews have a right to demand that the President of the United States and his cabinet should be the defenders of justice and the guards of righteousness, and that they should take the part of the persecuted Jews of Europe, as well as of any other oppressed people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1740.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These Jewish interests can and must be supported by the Jewish voter, because they are also American interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
