<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-05">March 5, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-05">March 5, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great mass-meeting was held Friday, by the members of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers. Five-thousand members attended the 9th educational meeting. They were very eager to listen to a message from their International President, Sidney Hillman, about the twelve clauses which the manufacturers handed the Workers' representatives, in order to formulate a new agreement with the Amalgamated.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hillman sent a telegram, stating that he was unable to attend this meeting because of other business transactions.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hillman was replaced by Prof. Sam Levine at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Prof. Levine gave a summary of the conditions existing in the clothing industry propr to any contract or agreement issued to the Union of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers. "Three years ago", said Levine, "we assembled in this hall to ratify an agreement with the Amalgamated Clothing Workers. At that time the manufacturers did not sign the agreement because we fought, sacrificed and compelled them to recognize us. At that time we did not expect to attain our aim so soon.At that time we had no concerts, no lectures, no music; we strived for freedom and the right to enjoy life, and we attained that aim.</p>
   <p>"We established that no member is to be discharged from any shop without <pb facs="5423972_3_0621.jpg" n="2"/>a fair trial.</p>
   <p>"Times have changed. We used to struggle and exert all efforts to maintain some freedom in the Shops. Now, the bosses demand freedom in the Shops.</p>
   <p>"We acknowledge the value of these privileges, to protect the Workers, and the right to work.</p>
   <p>"At one time, we spoke of having the right to meet and discuss our conditions, but now our discussions are carried to such an extent, that the employers are pleading for their freedom of speech.</p>
   <p>"We are aware of the problems of the industrial world and we understand the present condition of the clothing industry, together with the depressing times of today, and will do everything possible to better these conditions. In comprehending everything, our object is to avoid any strikes; we want peace in the industry, and we trust that the clothing manufacturers will consider everything and will not bring about any collision.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0622.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The employers are speaking of 48 hours. We know what we have attained in less than 48-hours of work. If they mean what they said, and I hope not, then I will tell them that we know how to act in the future, as we did in the past.</p>
   <p>"We can produce enough clothes in shorter hours, and we need not lengthen the hours".</p>
   <p>Levine concluded his talk by urging the worker to strike against the Will of the bosses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
