<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-30">Aug. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">On the Field of Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Standard Wage for the Tailors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-30">Aug. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE FIELD OF LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Standard Wage For The Tailors</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the members of Local 197 of the Amalgamated, there is considerable activity at the present time with the end in view of establishing a standard wage scale. Instead of each shop having its own particular scale of wages, as exists at present, these workers are striving to establish, once and for all time, a standard rate of wages in each shop, in order to determine the rate that the different types of workers should be paid for the different types of work.</p>
   <p>The situation at present is this; during the big strike in the tailoring industry last September, the union closed an agreement with the independent manufacturers. Now the union wants to take advantage of the Fall season, which is very promising, and also wants to improve the condition of the workers who were forced to accept lower wages during the slack season.</p>
   <p>In the agreement between the union and the bosses there is a clause which <pb facs="5423972_3_0324.jpg" n="2"/>gives each party the right to revise the wages whenever an occasion warrants such action. Immediately after the strike, just as soon as production declined, the employers invoked this clause and demanded a reduction in wages, which the union was forced to accept. But now, when conditions have changed and business promises to be good, the thousands of workers, employed in about forty shops, want a little more money. Therefore, the union has resolved to establish a standard wage scale for all section work in order to standardize the rate of wages in all shops.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, Local 197 has elected a wage committee composed of representatives from each shop. This committee is now drawing up a standard scale which will regulate wages for the forthcoming season. Members of Local 197 will hold a meeting Tuesday evening, September 5, in the Amalgamated Hall, 409 South Halsted Street, where the wage committee will submit its report on the new standard [scale]. A report will also be given by the Executive Committee regarding the transactions carried on with other locals, as well as with the International President, Sidney Hillman, to consolidate all existing coat makers <pb facs="5423972_3_0325.jpg" n="3"/>locals into one union. Also the Joint Board will submit its report on the general condition of the industry and then a discussion will follow on the educational work to be carried on during the coming winter.</p>
   <p>Bakery Drivers No Longer Ask, But Demand</p>
   <p>The Jewish bakery drivers, who now work continuously seven days a week only because God has not, as yet, given us an eighth day, will no longer request some rest--they will, with justification, demand it.</p>
   <p>Organized into a union a few weeks ago, and united with the Brotherhood of Teamsters, the bakery drivers, at their last meeting, selected a committee to draw up their demands. A special meeting will be held this Friday evening in Orkin's Hall 811 Maxwell Street, where the workers will ratify these demands, which will then be presented to their bosses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0326.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the meantime the bakery drivers union is growing. New workers join at each meeting, because the workers now understand that only the union is in a position to improve their working conditions. It is very important that all bakery workers attend the next meeting of the union--to be held next Friday evening--so that they can pass on the demands [formulated by the committee].</p>
   <p>Power Of Mattress Makers Union</p>
   <p>The extent of power which the mattress makers union has over the bosses can be seen by the following incident which occurred a few days ago. A certain firm, Gordon and Chapman, of 1436 West 14th Place, was the first firm to take out an injunction against the Union last year, and was then given the name "union-baiting firm"; this firm has now shown great loyalty to the organization of this trade, recognizing the great power of the union. Recently, when this firm needed employees, it did not hire anyone at random, but, instead, turned to the president of the Union, [asking him] to supply the company with workers. The bosses have also promised to reduce the number of working hours <pb facs="5423972_3_0327.jpg" n="5"/>from sixty to fifty-five, with time and a half for overtime.</p>
   <p>This incident has naturally encouraged the workers who stood aloof. They now flock in great numbers into the union, and are beginning to revive a great and powerful organization which defends the interests of all the workers in this trade.</p>
   <p>Grocery Clerks Unite With Their International</p>
   <p>The new union of grocery clerks has now become part of the International [Retail] Clerks Union and will now carry on its activities to greater advantage. The formal alliance will take place Tuesday evening in the Liberty Club, 2420 West Twelfth Street. Among others, John Fitzpatrick, president of the Chicago Federation of Labor, will speak.</p>
   <p>In The Cloakmakers Camp</p>
   <p>The "button system" which was installed Monday gives the union complete control <pb facs="5423972_3_0328.jpg" n="6"/>over the members because the button, which will be distributed each month, is the only sign indicating that workers are not in arrears in dues. This has proved to be a very successful system.</p>
   <p>The cloakmakers are highly pleased with this innovation, which will completely abolish all pretexts of the bosses that they are unable to distinguish members from non-members. The button is now the "obvious" proof and no pretexts will work from now on.</p>
   <p>The union has now inaugurated another innovation. All complaints [against workers] that the business agents handle will be reported at the regular meeting so that the members shall be informed of all situations which occur. This will increase the attendance at the union [meeting]. Also the general work will be carried on with more liveliness than has been true previously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
