<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Workers' Ghetto</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-05-20">May 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS' GHETTO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cloak makers of Chicago who complained of the bad season, are very busy, not, however, with bundles of work but with a certain cloak manufacturer, Borenstein, of 1242 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Borenstein has undertaken, it seems, to teach the cloak makers union a lesson and show them who is the most powerful - he or the cloak makers.</p>
   <p>A strike was called out at the Borenstein cloak factory by the union local #44. So naturally that did not look very good to Borenstein. He stated openly that under no conditions would he comply with the demands of the cloak makers. The strikers on the other side held fast to their demands and saw to it that no scab worker, (strike breaker), should enter the Borenstein shop.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Borenstein, after being convinced that he could not break the union with ordinary methods, turned to the courts and managed to get an injunction against the leaders of the union and their pickets.</p>
   <p>This is a fact, which is rather remarkable. Mr. Borenstein found two workers who were strike breakers, who went so far as to tell the court on the witness stand, that union workers are persecuting them and on the strength of this testimony, the judge issued the looked-for injunction.</p>
   <p>A soab is the scum of the earth, a man who determines to be a scab, deserves to be excommunicated and driven out from any kind of social organization.</p>
   <p>The cloak makers, right at the present moment, must get well organized and exert their energy, do all that is in their power, to conquer this dangerous small manufacturer and place the union in a respectful clean position, by cleaning up the filth, which was wrongfully charged up against them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
