<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-11">Mar. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The General Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_1114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-11">Mar. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE GENERAL STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One hundred thousand workers have declared a general strike this week in Rome. We can easily understand that the strike did not emanate from some unsound reason, because it was not spontaneous. It did not come suddenly, but only after a lengthy deliberation of all strikers. Before calling the strike, they held large meetings, where the importance of a strike was expressed. Consequently, all conscientiously agreed to strike.</p>
   <p>The chief demand that the workers have put forth in this strike is that the hospitals should serve the interests of the working class. And this demand is a very important one, for it has recently been discovered that many diseases spring from different types of work. That is why the workers, more so than any other class in society, are apt to become sick, notwithstanding present working conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1115.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this reason are the workers so intensely interested in the hospital question. Yet, we know that not all hospitals are open to workers, unless they can afford the sum paid by the rich. The hospitals which were made especially for the poor are far from being perfect healing places. This is why such a demand is a just one.</p>
   <p>Rumors are, however, being spread to the effect that the strike was called mainly because the workers want to manifest their power. Even if these rumors were true, there is no reason why we should be angered at the Italian workers. No one will be angry at a boss for closing his factory due to poor business, which will result into a wholesale layoff of thousands of workers. We do not reckon with the thousands of lives that are thrown into the streets. Much less should we become indignant when thousands of workers peacefully cast aside their work, upon discovering that it would be advantageous to them. The worker has as much right to his life as has the manufacturer to his factory.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_1116.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Particularly, is the consciousness of the strike reflected by the orderly manner in which the workers conduct themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
