<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last Convention of the Leftists, they adopted resolutions which show their desire to become not only the political-organization, but also the economic organization of the Workers of America. The Leftists have no intention of creating their own economic organization built on an industrial foundation in accordance with the time. Instead, they are trying to capture the I.W.W., for at the convention they adopted a resolution recognizing the I.W.W., as the only labor-organization possessed of the correct organizational principle.</p>
   <p>About the political aspects of their program, there will be a great deal to say.</p>
   <p>Here will be discussed the good and bad sides of both their constitution and destructive economic policy.</p>
   <p>The left-wing is correct in demanding that the Socialist Party should declare themselves for industrialism, as the organizational method for the workers.</p>
   <p>Our Party, over a long period of years, has experimented with neutrality in this question,and the result is that the Party is accepted by neither side. On the one hand, the American Federation of Labor does not recognize us, and on the other hand, the I.W.W. does not want us, and industrialists are dissatisfied with the tactics of the Party. We did not concern ourselves with the problem, and so we remain outside of both organizations.</p>
   <p>The Socialist Party can no longer remain neutral. It must come to the public with a clear, unequivocal decision for industrial unionism. We do not <pb facs="5423972_3_0702.jpg" n="2"/>have to fear the Federation, because we have nothing to lose. The official group at the helm of the Federation can be no more detested than they are, and the rank and file in the Federation are ready for an intensive propaganda campaign for industrialism. Both inside and outside the Federation, industrialism is necessary, and already the leaders of the Federation are showing signs of anxiety as to methods to prevail upon the conservative member ship to accept industrialism as a form of organization in the struggle against the bosses. Therefore, the time has come when the Party must learn its lesson and fit itself into the new circumstances, in which the old form of craft unionism acts as a terrible hindrance to the economic class struggle. There is no middle way. Either we recognize our mistake and learn the lesson or we admit our failure as an influential force upon the laboring masses. We can be a force if we announce ourselves for this new manner and tactics of organization for the Workers of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0703.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On such basis every one must be a Leftist, if to be pro-industrialistic is to be a member of the left. But the endorsement of the I.W.W. is another problem. The I.W.W. is principally and fundamentally, against political action and a great deal of the I.W.W.'s propaganda and agitation is against the Socialist Party as a political organization. The literature, the speakers, the principles,and the preamble of the I.W.W. are living witnesses to their contention that political-action means reaction; that it means maintenance of Capitalism under the guise of Socialism. And yet some people who call themselves Socialists, are proposing that we endorse the I.W.W. as the Labor Organization and as the only Workmen's Union which Socialists should and must support.</p>
   <p>This proves the inconsistency of the Leftists who wish to recognize the I.W.W. As I said above, there is no longer any question of party neutrality in regard to industrial unionism. But if the Party, as a political body, should tread the path of the Leftists, who are pro-I.W.W., then the Party recognizes that Political action for the Workers means suicide. This would sign the <pb facs="5423972_3_0704.jpg" n="4"/>death sentence of Socialism as a Political Party. Some Socialists proclaim their socialism and their belief in political-action, and at the same time recognize an organization which fights against political action with the same weapon that it fights craft unionism.</p>
   <p>The logical conclusion is that these individuals are not socialists at all. They simply want to use our Party to further their own interests. No doubt, any Socialist who believes in political-action as the means of abetting the Workmen's struggle, will not be recognized by the I.W.W. Despite this, the socialist-party will have to declare itself in favor of industrial organization. The revolutionary activity which grows out of industrialism must have the endorsement of the labor-movement. The American Federation of Labor must be put on a basis of revolutionary industrialism. Some unions have been organized industrially, and others are being constantly formed.</p>
   <p>The Revolutionary industrialism is founded on the class-struggle, and not on the trade or industry. All workers must be considered eligible for the Industrial Workers' Organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0705.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The flag of a revolutionary industrial organization must be the symbol of the working-class; of the final deliverance of the proletariat from slavery.</p>
   <p>We must see to it that the workers' movement of America becomes such an organization.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every socialist-branch to make the socialist-party an inspiration to the Workmen's Organization of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
