<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-04">Aug. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From Workmen's Interests</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_3_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_3_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-04">Aug. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM WORKMEN'S INTERESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edwards</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The victory of the skirtmakers and dressmakers merited a floral celebration.</p>
   <p>The general strike of 1917 sowed the seeds of today's flowers. At that time, the courageous girl strikers fought until their strength gave out; they were struck and arrested, and they finally returned to the shops, defeated.</p>
   <p>After a great deal of effort and sacrifice, the first collective agreement with the manufacturers was signed today; it is really the best reward for a struggle that left an indelible impression upon Chicago.</p>
   <p>Yes, today those workers all have reason to be happy and to congratulate each other, as well as to receive the congratulations of organized labor. The dressmakers union, Local 100, has, however, not yet completed its task. Its <pb facs="5423972_3_0970.jpg" n="2"/>real duties will now begin.</p>
   <p>The old obstinate[manufacturers']association is dead today. In its place are two new manufacturers' associations, which signed the first arbitration agreement with the union. These associations, although they represent the majority of the firms in the dress and skirt industry, cannot speak in the name of all the manufacturers. A group of independent manufacturers and some blouse companies, most important of all, several obstinate manufacturers still remain aloof. They are blind and deaf to the realities of the modern era.</p>
   <p>Well, the independents are falling into line one by one. The waist manufacturers too are getting nearer and nearer to the union office, but are the obstinate ones? The union is planning to deal differently with them.</p>
   <p>A series of strikes against them are expected in the course of this week. The union will give these stubborn manufacturers who believe they can maintain their independence in the industry, no peace. It is important that the triumphant <pb facs="5423972_3_0971.jpg" n="3"/>skirt and dressmakers remember that their victory is not complete as long as there are independent shops in the industry.</p>
   <p>Of course, it is not a difficult battle, but some efforts must be made. This and the unity of organized labor, I believe, will force these firms to cease being stubborn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
