<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-07-27">July 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Costly Education in the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-07-27">July 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">COSTLY EDUCATION IN THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many people think that in spite of the very low pay received by our school teachers, and of the poor equipment in our schools, the upkeep of our elementary and secondary schools, and colleges is our greatest burden. Even people who are well informed share these false convictions. Not so long ago, a prominent university professor made the statement that the maintainance of State Universities will bankrupt some of the States. In the meantime what do the facts tell? What are school expenses in comparison with other items either public or private?</p>
   <p>In the year of 1918, the United States spent $762,259,154.00 for elementary and high schools; $20,414,689.00 for normal schools; for high schools, colleges, universities, technical schools and other institutions of learning public and private, $137,055,415.00. Altogether the United States, spent $919,729,258 for educational purposes in the year of 1918. In the last 50 years, that is from 1870 to 1920, expenses for all schools in the United States, public and private, amounted to $14,552,796,037, or more than fourteen and a half billion dollars. In the years preceding 1870, the cost did not exceed two billion dollars. For normal schools, the expenditure was $3,000,000,00 and a maximum of $150,000,000 for higher education. The total sum spent, in the United States to the year 1920, for educational purposes amounted to $16,645,000,000 or seventeen billion in round figures.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0052.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This sum covers completely the expenses for all schools, in the United States and includes buildings, lighting, heating, repairing, salaries of professors and teachers and the like. In the year of 1918, expenses for educational purposes, amounted to less than a $1,000,000,000. Statistics for the year of 1920 show that the sum of $22, 700,000,000 was spent for luxuires, which was 22 times more than that spent for education in the year of 1918, and six billion dollars more than for education during our whole history.</p>
   <p>Let us bring out some of these figures and compare them with those spent for education: The sum spent for jewelry is $600,000,000, or $100,000,000 more than all salaries paid to elementary and high school teachers in that year; it also exceeds all private funds and donations in 1918 for the upkeep of colleges and universities. For cigarettes alone we spent $800,000,000; almost as much as for public and private schooling. In the year of 1920, $1,310,000,000 went up in smoke for tobacco of all kinds, this was $3,000,000 more than the expenditures for all schools, in 1918; and five times more than the salaries of all professors and teachers for the year of 1918. If all users of tobacco would come to an agreement and instead of three cigars or cigarettes, would smoke only two, and set aside all the money saved in that way, for one year, and donate this amount to schools, salaries of professors and teachers would be increase to 120%</p>
   <p>The upkeep of our schools should not be a burden, because we spend much more for luxuries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
