<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 21,
<date when="1923-05-24">May 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of a New School in East Chicago, Indiana</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 21,
<date when="1923-05-24">May 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF A NEW SCHOOL IN EAST CHICAGO, INDIANA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tolling of church bells on Sunday, May 2, 1923, announced a great joy among the Poles in East Chicago, Indiana.</p>
   <p>They announced the dedication of a new school and a new Polish settlement in the adopted country. The bells were also greeting a great church dignitary, Bishop H. T. Allerding of Fort Wayne, Indiana, who came to East Chicago to dedicate a magnificent school building of St. Stanislaus parish. The school is equipped with all modern conveniences that no other Polish school has. The new school building is in reality an ornament to the little city of East Chicago, Indiana. The Felician Sisters are in charge of the school where more than 1,300 children attend. There are eight grades according to the laws and regulations of the State. Polish children after graduating from the eighth grade usually go to a high school but a majority of them attend a Catholic high school where on recommendation and demand of the present rector, the Polish language will be taught also. But let us return to our subject.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0239.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the wings of the new school building contains school rooms and there are twelve of them. Every school room is provided with most modern equipment and is well ventilated. In every school room there is a built-in book case which serves as a library for the class. Near every school room there is a cloak room.</p>
   <p>The second part of the building contains a large gymnasium hall which also serves as a dance hall. There are billiard halls, bowling alleys, and bath rooms. There is also a library. Besides these there are many club rooms and assembly halls. There is a big theatrical hall capable of holding 11,000 people. The stage is magnificent. On the balcony there is a modern fire-proof room which will be used as the operator's room during moving picture plays. In that room are installed two moving picture machines.</p>
   <p>The school building is 120 feet long and 133 feet wide and three stories high. Besides roomy and high basements, the building is the most imposing structure in this part of the State of Indiana.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0240.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The plans for this building were designed by a young Polish architect, Mr. S. Bednarski. He came to the United States with his parents when he was still young. He completed his elementary education in Kenosha, Wisconsin, but studied architecture and engineering in Valparaiso University at Valparaiso, Indiana. The building cost about $175,000.</p>
   <p>The dedication ceremony started at 3 P.M. with a procession headed by the ministrants carrying a cross; then little girls dressed in white, followed by church societies; then the pastor of the parish, surrounded by the clergy. The whole procession, united by beautifully colored ribbons and accompanied by the tinkling of little bells, playing and singing, lead the bishop to the church. From the church the procession proceeded to the new school building, object of the celebration. After the dedication of the building by Bishop Allerdury, Father J. Mecikowski, the assistant of Immaculate Conception Church of South Chicago, took the stand at the pulpit and delivered a beautiful speech to the people, praising them for their good work. He spoke about Polish schools and the education of children. The people listened very attentively, with bowed heads, as if they said, <pb facs="5423968_1_0241.jpg" n="4"/>"Lord, we are your children." Then Bishop Allerding spoke, praising the Polish people for building such a beautiful school; he thanked them for their generosity and sacrifice, encouraging them for future work.</p>
   <p>When the bishop entered the church, the parish choir sang Ecce Sacerdos Magnus (by Molitar). After returning to the church there was a benediction, during which the choir sang O Salutaris (by Wagner), and Tantum Ergo (by Rosewig). The celegration was concluded by "God Save Poland." The building was beautifully decorated by American and Polish flags.</p>
   <p>In the evening there was an entertainment in the new hall, with moving pictures, singing, music, and a play. The hall was crowded. The audience was honored by the presence of the bishop and clergy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
