<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-23">June 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Loyola University and the Study of the Polish Language</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-23">June 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">LOYOLA UNIVERSITY AND THE STUDY OF THE POLISH LANGUAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish independence was the beginning of a new life in the political and economic phase in Poland. The entire nation is looking forward with confidence to the day when it will be entirely independent and capable of handling its own affairs. This atmosphere is affecting the Polish element of the entire world. Here, in America, we are becoming more aware of our civic rights and duties, and seek positions of high office for our countrymen. In a short time we shall attain the standard of the foreign elements, who thus far forced us to remain in the background.</p>
   <p>The Polish people in America, especially those who adopted this country as their own, must remember that the United States is now in the process of thorough Americanization. There is keen competition between national groups who wish to impress other groups with their importance in the formation of this new nation. For example, much credit must be given the English, German and particularly the Jewish people who work hard to thoroughly familiarize every member of their race with the history of their past, so that they are able to explain and eulogize the merits of their own nation, while in contact with the one hundred percent Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, too, have undertaken this important duty by forming classes for the cultural development of the Polish language and history in various universities in the United States. The influx of the Polish element into this country is greater than every before; Polish students and professors are arriving in America in large numbers. We also note that American students and professors are going to Poland in similar proportions.</p>
   <p>It is with great honor and pride that we point to the introduction of the Polish language and history which is to become part of the curriculum at the Loyola University, under the guidance of priests of the Jesuit Order.</p>
   <p>This university is located at 28 North Franklin Street. The Jesuit Order has been founded by the Spanish solider and saint, Ignatius Loyola. For the convenience of all, the study period from 6 to 10 P.M. is devoted to Polish language and history. All pupils, who complete these new courses, will be given credit equal to that of any other subject.</p>
   <p>Since the study of foreign languages is required in all universities, it would be proper and fitting that Polish students select their native language in preference to German or French. Every Polish professional should zealously study the language and history of Poland, because it will be of much benefit to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
