<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 209,
<date when="1908-09-05">Sept. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Archbishop Ryan against Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 209,
<date when="1908-09-05">Sept. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ARCHBISHOP RYAN AGAINST PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On account of public schools we have a rich growth of weeds, lawlessness and socialism. Modernism has been condemned on account of its work, which will end in the ruin of the nation.</p>
   <p>This statement was made by Archbishop Ryan at the thirty-fourth annual convention of Catholic youth, which is being held in Philadelphia, Pa.</p>
   <p>The teaching of various subjects in schools is unnecessary, according to the viewpoint of the Archbishop, because only church and monastic teachings will bring salvation to the nation. Idle complaints of a bishop will not change matters any.</p>
   <p>Foreigners Should Be Taught.</p>
   <p>The nation, continued the Archbishop, which depends for its growth to a certain degree on immigration, takes upon itself a great responsibility if it allows children of the immigrants, who in the future will become the citizens of that country, to grow and be brought up without the realization that only one religion can bring happiness and salvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is our national fault, he further stated, that a third or sometimes fourth generation which were taught in our public schools have empty hearts. Such youth is like an uncultivated field full of weeds - lawless and socialistic - thereby ruining the moral welfare of the entire country.</p>
   <p>Let those who contributed toward the creation of such a system, or do not recognize God, love,or fear, take a good look at the characteristic signs of today's life; let them read the descriptions of every-day accidents, violations and abuses in different states; let them investigate the murders and crimes which disgrace the country, and they will be convinced of the very sad results.</p>
   <p>But the Archbishop has forgotten to add that in the most religious Catholic countries, there is the most ignorance, poverty, slavery and degradation, with crime flourishing as a result.</p>
   <p>As an example of such religious notions, the Archbishop should have mentioned Italy, Spain, Ireland and Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There will be no progress in this country as long as the new element will continue to fall into the clutches of the "black vultures" in "spiritual robes".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
