<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 194,
<date when="1926-08-19">Aug. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Selection of a School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 194,
<date when="1926-08-19">Aug. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE SELECTION OF A SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Even though August is still considered a summer month, yet, as soon as it arrives, clear-sighted people immediately begin to think of their autumn occupations. Farmers begin to think about their winter corn, and the residents of the city, whose main worry consists of family affairs, think about the selection of a school for their children. The solution of this problem is not a difficult one for people of wealth. In our station of life, however, the situation is not simple. We must select either a public or a parochial school. Our modest material means do not permit an alternative.</p>
   <p>Which of the two schools shall we select: public or parochial? The answer is: parochial, for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>We have no reason for criticizing the teachers of public schools. They <pb facs="5423968_1_0235.jpg" n="2"/>are doing their duty, which is the teaching of reading, writing, arithmetic and English, and this at no cost to the parents. Nevertheless, the program of a free school does not take into consideration either religion or the mother tongue of our children, subjects which are so near to our hearts.</p>
   <p>We are concerned about the religious training of our children, because (according to our convictions) we consider the knowledge of the principles of religion one of the most important factors of all teaching, because religion is the basis of all morals, without which a person cannot be happy either in this life or in eternity, and finally, that a person without religion and without morals is an undesirable individual in society, because he is dangerous. Hence, since the teaching of religion is not permitted in public schools, we are compelled to choose the parochial school which, with due regard to its founder, places religion in the first place of its program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0236.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We prefer the parochial school because it teaches our mother tongue and tells us about the deeds of those of our blood. We consider these teachings very important, because without them we are unable to rear our children in a manner to which we certainly are entitled. We take into consideration the fact that America also has a right to our children because they were born here and live here. We also have the privilege of enjoying the fruits of their labor and profit thereby, because they are of blood of our hearts and because that blood owes its life to our love, our work, our devotion. Degenerate children are abominable and do not know either how to regard or how to respect their parents. Such would surely be the result in a great measure if we would permit them to be brought up without the knowledge of our religious training, without the knowledge of our mother tongue. Experience with many children in the past has taught us this lesson.</p>
   <p>We do not in the least scorn public schools. However, as long as the American majority will not permit the considering of our religious <pb facs="5423968_1_0237.jpg" n="4"/>and family needs, so long we will feel duty bound to entrust our children to the guardianship of parochial schools, in spite of the weight which the school's tuition places upon us. Surely, no one can hold this against us.</p>
   <p>But a parochial school is not less American than a public school. To this claim every American will agree, having fresh in mind the decision of the United States Supreme Court in regard to parochial schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
