<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 33,
<date when="1917-08-15">August 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Resurrection Sisters' Academy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0258</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0258.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 33,
<date when="1917-08-15">August 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RESURRECTION SISTERS' ACADEMY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the few Polish institutions of learning for girls belongs the new Resurrection Sisters' Academy in Norwood Park, Illinois, built on an extensive and very beautiful land, near Chicago. This institution is exclusively for Polish girls whose aim is to be developed into prominent citizens, and managers of families with a soul Polish and religious throughout. This institution is conducted by the Sisters who, with devotion, are working for a national and social idea.</p>
   <p>The plan of study comprises an elementary course, high school course, and a business course. The elementary course is the same as that in any well organized parochial school of eight grades. The high school course is a four year course. During this time, besides subjects given in every public high school in the English language, they also teach in the Polish language, religion, dogmatics, ethics, history of the church, Polish history, <pb facs="5423968_1_0259.jpg" n="2"/>literature (acquainting the student with its masterpieces) and, at the same time, grammar and the science of style.</p>
   <p>We must mention here that besides the subjects mentioned above, they teach violin, piano, organ, voice, and also give instruction in drawing. Practical things, indispensable to the future housekeeper and mother, are not omitted.</p>
   <p>All kinds of games in the garden are contributing to the physical development of the girl students, and the walks in the meadows, fields, and nearby woods are not only healthy but supply material for natural studies which, when properly directed, teach love of nature.</p>
   <p>Whereas material means are often the obstacle against which some of the noble impulses of our fellow countrymen are shattered, in order to enable as many of our Polish girls as possible to obtain a higher education, the institution has tuition fees as moderate as possible, in spite of the high cost of living that we have at the present time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0260.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We do not doubt that many Polish families will hurry to place their daughters in this institution, so moderately priced and practical in all respects, where, besides knowledge, they also put great stress and effort on their rearing. It is high time that the Polish women took their rightful position in social life over here and to accomplish this there is only one way - good rearing and education.</p>
   <p>Whoever wishes more information can, either by letter, or personally, apply to the management: Resurrection Sisters' Academy, 5959 Talcott Avenue, Norwood Park, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
