<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-03-15">Mar. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Circle of Error</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-03-15">Mar. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE CIRCLE OF ERROR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It would be difficult for any one, even after a brief visit to Chicago to overlook the beautiful and expensive wearing apparel of our women.</p>
   <p>Well dressed women are native not only to the aristocratic sections of the city, but can also be seen in offices, stores, restaurants, factories, and everywhere. Not even during the present-day high cost of living, can modern woman do without her silks, woolens, velvets, bird of paradise hats, ostrich feathers, beads and laces. These to her are necessities. In order to satisfy this passion for finery, a woman is willing to sacrifice anything, even her freedom, and that is why our courts today are plagued with divorces.</p>
   <p>It is evident that most of our young Polish girls of teen age are also afflicted with this passion for fine clothes. The old saying, "Clothes do not make a person," does not appeal to our women.</p>
   <p>We must regretfully admit that our girls are being influenced by and are quickly <pb facs="5423968_1_0098.jpg" n="2"/>adopting the habits and customs of the American girls.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is our duty, as newspapermen, to bring this to the attention of our readers.</p>
   <p>The theory that a higher education is not necessary for a girl, is generally an accepted one. Girls, upon completing grammar school, usually apply for work at one of the many tailor shops and department stores.</p>
   <p>Most of these girls are really glad to go to work, because as working members of the family they enjoy greater freedom, more privileges, and most important of all, a weekly allowance to buy new dresses, hats, shoes, ice cream, and admission to the shows.</p>
   <p>In many cases the mothers are to blame for allowing their daughters to acquire this passion for spending and fine clothes by constantly reminding them of their appearance. Mothers always complain about lack of money whenever anyone suggests a higher education for their daughters, but they won't even utter a whimper when a new dress, hat, or shoes are suggested, saying that they will manage somehow or other.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But in a short time the spending exceeds the earnings. The daughter, now accustomed to all of these luxuries, simply demands them. It is too late now. She has no control over her desires, and she must have what she wants irrespective of where it comes from. Many of us are aware of the shameful conditions that exist in many factories and department stores, where the foremen, the floorwalkers, or even the managers, knowing the weaknesses of these girls, take full advantage of them.</p>
   <p>This passion for extravagance is leading these girls and women to destruction and will continue to do so until parents insist upon a higher education, through which their children can develop character and self-respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
