<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-02-20">Feb. 20, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Urge Study of Poland.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish-Americans to Ask Board to Order a School History.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-02-20">Feb. 20, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">URGE STUDY OF POLAND.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish-Americans To Ask Board To Order A School History.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prominent Polish-Americans of this city wish the study of the history of Poland to be made an important element in the historical studies in Chicago public schools and they are taking action to bring the matter to the attention of the Board of Education and to Superintendent Cooley.</p>
   <p>At a discussion held in Polish literary, professional, and educational circles, it is contended that the present troubles in Russia, which are making important facts in history, can not be fully understood, appreciated, or traced unless the history and woes of Poland and other countries which were seized by the Russian Government are studied. It is contended by the Polish people that a study of the history of their country will do much to overcome systematic attacks and falsehoods which are spread about Poles.</p>
   <p>It is urged that the Polish-American citizens who pay taxes to support the public schools are entitled to have the subject of history of Poland <pb facs="5423968_1_0144.jpg" n="2"/>included in the studies as the German-Americans have their native language taught and others have the history of England taught. An appeal will be made to Dr. Kuflewski and Dr. Chvatal, the Polish and Bohemian members of the Board of Education, and an individual appeal will be made to every member of the Board of Education to have the history of Poland taught.</p>
   <p>"At the present time, the school children have a hazy notion of the history of Poland or none at all," said Attorney Stanley Walkowiak last night. "The present developments in Russia and in Europe generally make the knowledge and understanding of the history, the people, and conditions of Eastern Europe, particularly of Poland, most important. Not only should the students know what Kosciusko and Pulaski did for the country, but they should also know what they did in Poland."</p>
   <p>At a conference last night at the Educational Club of the Polish young men of the Southwest Side, resolutions were passed seeking to have the history of Poland made a special study in the public schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
