<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1927-11-06">Nov. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Introspection</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1927-11-06">Nov. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">INTROSPECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Extracts:</p>
   <p>Years ago education was a kingdom accessible to only a few of the elect. Today it is a necessity; an indispensable tool in securing one's livelihood. A man with no education is a cripple, and a burden to himself and his community.</p>
   <p>Civilized nations of today rank education first in their duties towards their posterity.</p>
   <p>The magnificent development of the American school can be attributed to the real democratic equality, through which every man is given an equal chance in acquiring the best of education.</p>
   <p>The consciousness of that equality lives even among children, the best expression of which can be seen in a remark of an 8 year old Polish democrat, who said: "I am born in the United States, and some day I may <pb facs="5423968_1_0232.jpg" n="2"/>be the president of our country. But first I have to learn very, very much."</p>
   <p>It is true that the Polish population here constitutes one of the largest communities. But how many of our Polish children acquire a high school education, not speaking of the university?</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of our children, right after they graduate from the parochial school, have to work; even before their young bodies are grown enough to endure the labor, and their minds developed enough to comprehend the benefits of education.</p>
   <p>Who is to blame for it? The parents? Maybe. But where are those who stand at the head of our community? Where are the teachers of Polish schools, who foster our children and form their young minds and souls? Why is it that, after spending eight years in a parochial school, such a small percentage of our children display interest in further education, whereas any non-Polish teacher in a public school arouses in our boys and girls an ardent desire for knowledge?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0233.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is only one answer: Negligence on the part of those who are supposed to be our spiritual guides, and indifference of the parochial school teachers.</p>
   <p>It is high time to approach that vital problem with more concern.</p>
   <p>We should be aware of the responsibility that lies upon us in regard to that important question. Let us not forget that some day our young generation will call upon us to explain the reasons of depriving them of one of the greatest privileges of democracy, education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
