<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-13">May 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Golden Book</title><title level="a" type="sub">Members of the Polish National Alliance Give Generously for an Alliance's High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-13">May 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOLDEN BOOK</title><title level="a" type="sub">Members of the Polish National Alliance Give Generously For An Alliance's High School</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our request for contributions towards the founding of a high school sponsored by the Alliance did not go by unheeded. Through announcements in the papers, notices in lodges and churches, word of mouth, and other means, the cause of a high school for the Alliance was made known to the Polish people, among whom there exists the Polish spirit of the Alliance, hospitable and understanding, upon which depends our future and the future existence of our people in the United States. The betterment of our people can be made possible only through education. The donations came in freely and generously. The general funds of this foundation grow rapidly.</p>
   <p>In our native country, across the vast expanse of the Atlantic ocean, there exist government subsidized schools. Our countrymen have organized a powerful people's School Society, where no stone is left unturned if it tends to further brotherhood. No matter to what extent the support of education has reached, <pb facs="5423968_1_0133.jpg" n="2"/>the following example of aid to public schools is worthy of notice: In the homes of the Galicians, the sale of accumulated orange peels enlarges the school funds every month by several hundred crowns.</p>
   <p>Our own supporters in America must always bear in mind the importance of fostering education, that is, of supporting our own high school.</p>
   <p>We must point out the following examples: The Czechs, through their own educational system, awakened their slumbering nation; the Lithuanians, through the work of Father Ambrozewicz, are contributing towards a national home in Vilno, and trying to purchase the estate of Prince Radzillowski, called the Verky Estate, which is to be used for a national cause. It would be a fine thing if we could get our members to follow these examples and devote all or part of their spare time to further this cause.</p>
   <p>Listen to this, if the Lithuanians are giving their undivided support to the completion of their project, then why can't we do something to bring ours to realization? Those who smoke cigarettes, indulge in sumptuous meals, drink beer and whiskey, could abstain from them for a month; let them drop off for a month who like to treat their favored guests with the best, who go to theaters, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0134.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>with the money thus saved by doing without these things, the enjoyment of which is very short and small, a national building could be erected that even our children's children could be proud of in time to come.</p>
   <p>Our Polish-American circles do not lack the spirit of cooperation. If there were more supporters of the idea of a high school under the management of the P.N.A., its completion would be a fact within the near future. If the number of supporters grow among the various communities, and if every opportunity is used best to help this cause along, there will be no difficulty in raising the necessary funds.</p>
   <p>We wish to emphasize once more the importance of education among our people. Schools for our youth are of vital importance, for the future of our position in the United States depends on them. Remember, therefore, about the Alliance's High School Fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
