<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-03">March 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Culture at University of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-03">March 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CULTURE AT UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is the last and most important notice announcing the Polish Night on the University of Chicago Campus, at Mandel Hall, which will take place this evening at 7:30 P.M. The hall is decorated for the occasion with Polish flags and the stage is set to represent a typical Polish rural scene. Many Polish artists of prominence are to appear as honorary guests.</p>
   <p>The object of this occasion is to acquaint those who are not of Polish birth or descent, with the customs, traditions, and the cultural development of the country. The guests of honor, this evening, will be the members of the International Club. All other students pay a small admittance charge of 50, and strangers, $1.00. The entire proceeds of this night will be given to the Kosciuszko Foundation. This social gathering also offers the opportunity to meet many members of the faculty who are greatly interested in this event and have promised to be there. You, the Polish element in Chicago, are expected to attend in large numbers to inaugurate the first Polish - Night at the University of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0038.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish women in Chicago who possess national costumes are kindly requested to appear; this will give our guests an opportunity to familiarize themselves with these beautiful fashions. The best way to reach Mandel Hall: Use the Jackson Park Elevated Railroad to University Ave., then walk a short distance to 57th street. Let us support this affair en masse.</p>
   <p>Polish Academic Circle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
