<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-12">Jan. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Governor's Platform</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-12">Jan. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOVERNOR'S PLATFORM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With more than ordinary pleasure, we present a literal translation of the newly elected Governor's platform in today's Dziennik Chicagoski. It is the platform of the Governor of Illinois, John P. Altgeld, and it is so interesting, so well planned out, and at the same time so clearly written, that it can be read with the greatest interest from the first to the last word.</p>
   <p>The new Governor of our State will certainly not be a figurehead. We can see in his platform the plans of a deep thinker, who will not lack the energy to carry them out; they are plans aimed at necessary reforms which may bring about a new era in the history of Illinois. Let us look at some of the important points.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0168.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are most concerned in the first place with schools. The Democrats have been accused, perhaps rightly, of a desire to abolish the Edwards Law without bringing forth another school law to take its place. Altgeld states plainly that the unjust Edwards Law should be abolished and a new one, making education compulsory, substituted. Every child must go to school and, according to Altgeld, must learn the English language. But the government has no right to dictate which school a child shall attend; this problem concerns the parents or guardians. Only in a case where the parents are plainly negligent, the government may see to it that the child is not entirely deprived of schooling.</p>
   <p>Altgeld is a capable and deep-thinking lawyer. With what eloquence he takes the part of the poor man who finds no justice in the lower courts; how sharply he criticizes the misrule of the politicians! And again, how energetically he demands civil service reform, so as to enable the State to secure the services of only the most able men, however poor. And then, in defense of the working man, he proposes projects which, if brought into being, will improve immeasurably the workers' conditions <pb facs="5423968_1_0169.jpg" n="3"/>and protect them against injustice. Referring to prison labor, he insists that its products should in no case compete with the products of private industry. Finally, he proposes a fair and just plan of taxation.</p>
   <p>In this platform, we find no high-flown, stilted phrases; its thought is practical, its spirit just; it shows deep learning and a fixed determination. Moreover, it is characterized by sincerity and straightforwardness, so that in reading it we come to the conclusion that the promises Altgeld makes are not empty ones, and that he is determined to live up to them. We believe that he is bringing us, the citizens of Illinois, to the threshold of a new and greater era. A legislature sharing his views guarantees us that his plans will take effect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
