<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 37,
<date when="1917-09-12">September 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of the New Edifice of Holy Trinity High School.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 37,
<date when="1917-09-12">September 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF THE NEW EDIFICE OF HOLY TRINITY HIGH SCHOOL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Holy Trinity Parish, organized in 1873, has for the past twenty years had as its pastor Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, ardent secretary of three Catholic congresses. The parish is comprised of several thousand souls, and conducts an eight grade school. Brother Peter, of the Order of Holy Cross, a man of wide views, deep education, and completely given to the educational profession, became the director of the high school.</p>
   <p>Under his leadership the high school in a few years received recognition as a well conducted college and has acquired a well earned reputation of the educating of youth. Reverend Sztuczko, seeing the growth, decided to build a separate new building. He started the movement, which serves as a credit to the Polish architect Hipolit Hincz, and Polish professions. The construction was begun in 1916, in the form of a letter "D" fronting Cleaver street. It has a length of 165 feet and a depth of 125 feet; it has 35 class rooms of which each can accommodate 60 pupils, which means it can take care of 2,100 pupils. In the basement of the school is a hall with a beautiful stage, which can hold 1,500 persons. The entire building is centrally heated and <pb facs="5423968_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>is built of red-face brick, making a stately appearance. The entire cost of building comes to $250,000.</p>
   <p>The act of consecration was performed by several priests, the parochial committee, societies, foreign delegations, honored guests, and many thousands of the faithful crowd.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
