<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-19">Sept. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Regarding the Number of Polish Children in School]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-19">Sept. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[REGARDING THE NUMBER OF POLISH CHILDREN IN SCHOOL]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a recent edition of the Polish newspaper, Dziennik Zwiazkowy, a census of Chicago's school children was made public. According to this list, there were 94,432 Polish children in this city. They occupy third place on the list in proportion to the children of various nationalities. Some may be of the opinion that this is the actual number of children born of Polish parents, and that it is a satisfactory proportion of the 300,000 Poles in Chicago. We are not concerned here in indicating the proportionate percentage of adults to children. The Dziennik Zwiazkowy wishes only to inform those who may be satisfied with these figures that they (figures) are too small.</p>
   <p>There are more than 94,432 Polish children of minor age in Chicago. It is necessary to remember that this list referred only to those children who were <pb facs="5423968_1_0093.jpg" n="2"/>born in Europe, or whose parents were born abroad. There are a number of fathers of families here who were born on American soil. Their children were numbered among the American group, which number is placed at 248,102. A considerable number of these American children are of Polish descent, although their parents were born here. In addition to this, if we take the fact into consideration that many Poles--hence their children as well--were listed as either Russians, or Germans, because they originally came from that annexed part of Poland, then the number of our Polish children in Chicago could safely be placed at 125,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
