<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 25,
<date when="1912-06-19">June 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Report of Building Committee of the New St. Stanislaus College in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 25,
<date when="1912-06-19">June 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF BUILDING COMMITTEE OF THE NEW ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We receive the following correspondence: In the matter of building a new suitable structure for the Polish St. Stanislaus College in Chicago, and to raise this college to the position of a first class truly Polish and truly Catholic institution of learning, a citizens committee was formed in the year 1908 at Chicago, whose honorary president became His Excellency Rev. Bishop Paul P. Rhode, and the active president, Mr. John F. Smulski, president of the Polish bank in Chicago.</p>
   <p>With the aim of establishing the important work a charter was procured on Dec. 4, 1908, from the State Government at Springfield; Illinois, and collections have gotten under way first for the purchase of a suitable place for the college.</p>
   <p>In conformity with the requirements of modern schools, which require for higher schools not only lecture rooms but also a laboratory, library, reading room, a place for work and practice of physics and also healthy dormitories, the building committee has chosen as a most suitable location <pb facs="5423968_1_0279.jpg" n="2"/>for the college a spacious and beautiful ground in Avondale.</p>
   <p>This ground on Milwaukee Avenue has perfect communication with the main Polish sections and with the center of the city and extends at the south from West School Street north to Roscoe Street, occupying three blocks between these streets from North Harding Street to North Hamlin Street.</p>
   <p>The building committee purchased this ground for the sum of $44,000. Considering the size and location it is very moderately priced.</p>
   <p>To cover the purchase price, the treasury has received the lump sum of $16,373.43 realized from contributions and tag day's receipts.</p>
   <p>Above that many priests and citizens subscribed a quota of about $8,000 which can be collected in a short time.</p>
   <p>In this way, as initial payment on purchase of the ground for the new Polish college in Chicago, for the sum of $44,000 the committee had in ready cash $16,373.43, so that the rest of the sum, $27,626.57, had to be paid immediately by private loan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0280.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This loan amounting to $27,626.57 must be paid without delay in order to make it possible to draw a first mortgage loan, a considerably sum is necessary for the building of the structure, a loan on convenient amortized payments, in other words, a debt amortizing in a course of time.</p>
   <p>The plans for the new structure are already completed and according to these plans, there will rise a beautiful structure with all accommodations and bringing honor to all of the Poles.</p>
   <p>Having therefore acquired the ground, the plans completed and having already paid on the initial sum of the purchase price, $16,373.43, the building committee presents the indispensable necessity to pay off the balance, $27,626.57, in as short a time as possible, so that we can begin building.</p>
   <p>John F. Smulski, President.</p>
   <p>Rev. W. Zapala, C. R., Cashier and Secretary.</p>
   <p>Rev. John Kosinski, C. R.</p>
   <p>Rev. Francis Wojtalewicz.</p>
   <p>Rev. Andrew Spetz C. R.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
