<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-25">May 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Commerce and the Art of Buying</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-25">May 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">COMMERCE AND THE ART OF BUYING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today brings the opening of the fourth "White Eagle" Polish Buyers' Association Convention in Chicago. In this respect it would be appropriate to mention something about the art of buying, as this is of vital importance. Today, competition is very keen in the commercial field and therefore, it is very difficult to operate a commercial enterprise without knowing the finer points of business.</p>
   <p>In America there is the custom of asking people where they were born and what education they have had. Before a person is hired, and if the job is other than the pick and shovel kind, he or she must pass a scrupulous and rigorous examination, show citizenship papers, or present credentials showing that he or she is capable of filling the position offered.</p>
   <p>This same rule applies to business. Qualification is of utmost importance. The higher the qualifications, the better the opportunities for success. Industry has relied upon the specialization and advancement of the knowledge gathered in schools that have from early times grown to prominence and are rated with the best academies and universities. The world of commerce, in the past ten years, <pb facs="5423968_1_0128.jpg" n="2"/>has availed itself of techniques developed by technical and commercial universities.</p>
   <p>The Germans were the first to open the universities to commerce. They did not follow the examples of other countries, who offered courses both in the higher and lower institutions. They founded special academies to devote their time especially to this kind of work. They, in turn, devoted a life time's work to elevate German business to world prominence. Special branch buildings were devoted entirely to the study of purchasing. Therefore, Germany has become a specialist in this field and now holds the first position, setting an example for other countries taking less interest in commerce.</p>
   <p>In this respect the United States could not look at Europe while sharing a back seat. The University of Illinois was among the first to recognize the importance of educating American businessmen. It offered four-year courses leading to a degree. Both young and old were enrolled. Those that took advantage of these studies now hold prominent positions in business.</p>
   <p>Many other educational centers followed the example of the University of Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0129.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Today one can find courses in commerce in most every college.</p>
   <p>From these institutions many people derive benefits, including the Poles. However, the number is very small. Only about six out of every hundred. This number is so small that it is almost unworthy of mention. Polish business in the United States needs this training more than any other nationality if we are to get recognition among big business. There is also a lack of familiarity and friendship in this field.</p>
   <p>The Poles, outside of the grocers and a few other small enterprises, rarely take interest in the larger and broader fields of business. They are not even on the threshold of the business of the world. And whenever we come cross a Pole who has established a business or an industrial plant, we find that he is a person of high position and intelligence. Sometimes we meet a Polish buyer of rank; he too, is a distinguished individual. These are the persons who did not change their gloves but stuck to their business and through the years, through the school of experience and hard knocks, forged to the top. This kind of training, free from most of the excruciating experiences can be had in the colleges by anyone able <pb facs="5423968_1_0130.jpg" n="4"/>to afford it.</p>
   <p>The waste of the best years of one's life in America through lack of knowledge, is an irreparable loss. A course at a university prepares one with all the necessary theoretical information, enabling one to adjust himself rapidly in the business world, thereby saving time, money, and painful experiences. Besides, this training enables one to obtain a good paying position without the many preliminary years of struggle. In spite of this, Polish parents, including business men, have not as yet come to the realization of the importance of educational training. The doors to big business cannot be opened unless one has the training and ability.</p>
   <p>The opportunities offered to attend these universities are not taken advantage of by the Polish people of America. As an example, out of one million Poles only six attend the University of Illinois at Urbana. Out of 60,000 Japanese in the United States, seventeen students are found at Urbana. This is a three to one ratio. In proportion there should be at least 850 Polish students.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0131.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Therefore, these sessions of Polish Buyers, besides striving for unity in business, should also take steps to promote a better support, within their own circles, of the opportunities offered by the colleges. In this respect they would not only be outstanding, but would also help their own kind occupy a higher place in the business world. The greater the unity and sponsorship, the greater the enthusiasm there is going to be in Polish business circles and the better the opportunities available to all. This will enable the Polish buyer to gain a strong foothold in the world of business. Therefore, as in industry, in business this preparation and qualifications can be easily obtained through the proper channels of education. Nothing helps patriotism and honor better than the slogan, "Kind for kind." But if this is not followed by sound educational policies, organization, and unity, then Polish business in America will always be in the background.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
