<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IV. No. 25,
<date when="1900-06-20">June 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">"Polish Language in the Public Schools"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IV. No. 25,
<date when="1900-06-20">June 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">"Polish Language in the Public Schools"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The activities to remove teaching of the Polish language from Milwaukee, Buffalo, Chicago, and schools of other cities, brought about a new rebellious dispute. This time Chicago is trying to show what it can do.</p>
   <p>Certain organized groups among our people see that permitting the teaching of the Polish language and bringing it into the public schools, will mean the saving of our nationality. We have given this matter considerable time and are trying to show, that teaching of the Polish language in the public schools will gain us nothing, nor help us. We base our decision on good experience.</p>
   <p>Those that best know our parochial schools and children will admit how innate is our indifference and disinclination towards matters pertaining to our nationality.</p>
   <p>Our elders, but mostly our children, are ashamed of their descent; they <pb facs="5423968_1_0218.jpg" n="2"/>do not care to speak Polish and change their names to English not only in schools, on the streets, but to the police and in courts where they have to testify in case of any accident.</p>
   <p>All the subject matter put out by the schools awakens the interest in children about the Polish language, but to get the children to learn this, extraordinary toil, ability, and pedagogical knowledge is needed on the part of the teacher. Woe unto the teacher who lacks these qualities, for he will discourage the children and they shall learn nothing.</p>
   <p>In order for the teacher to do something about this matter he must devote his body and soul, must use strong measures and not an idle minute, because his work will be futile. We know what it is to be a teacher here; they have many a headache.</p>
   <p>We openly admit that our schools are not an example of ability, likewise the public schools. We claim that in our schools, the child will learn the <pb facs="5423968_1_0219.jpg" n="3"/>Polish language in two years, whereas in the public school it would take six years, because it is not compulsory.</p>
   <p>The advantage of the Polish language being taught in the public school shall repay us. One of the few advantages is that we will have teachers who shall have steady employment.</p>
   <p>So bringing this language into the public schools, it might affect the average Catholic. But if you are a strict Catholic and care about raising your child religiously, you should send him to a parochial school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
