<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1915-02-10">Feb. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Jubilee of St. Stanislaus' College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0270</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0270.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1915-02-10">Feb. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER JUBILEE OF ST. STANISLAUS' COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>St. Stanislaus College in Chicago has been for a quarter of a century and will always remain one of our principal and most valuable educational and national centers here in America. It was founded in the year 1890 by the never-to-be-forgotten Reverend Vincent Barzynski with the co-operation of the former head of the Order of Resurrectionist Fathers, the late Valerian Przewlocki. The institution was originally located in St. Stanislaus' parish in Chicago, in a little frame building at the corner of Noble and Bradley Streets. The first rector of the College was the late Reverend Joseph Halter, a priest ardently devoted to the cause of the school and its generous guardian and father. The second rector from the year 1892 to 1895, was the Reverend John Piechowski, who later on became the venerable pastor of St. Hedwig's Church in Chicago. The rector who followed Father Piechovlski was the Rev. John Kruszynski, who deserved well of the institution and was in charge of it from 1895 to 1906.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0271.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thereafter the late Reverend John Kosinski was named rector; he held office until 1909 when the present rector the Reverend Ladislaus Zapala, took charge.</p>
   <p>A residential college, that is a boarding school, was established in 1899, and at that time the college was removed from the old building in St. Stanislaus' parish to a new building on Division street, where it still remains. Here the residential college was established according to the system employed in the highest institutions of learning. From this time on the students could not only attend classes, but could also live in the college building and get full benefit of the gymnasium, the college library and other facilities; and most important of all, they remain under the supervision and guardianship of their superiors. We are assured by the testimonials of eminent pedagogues that the sleeping rooms, the class-rooms, and the study-rooms are arranged in exemplary fashion and have good ventilation; the fare is wholesome and plentiful. Besides the regular studies, gymnastics and physical training are compulsory and are systematically conducted. During the incumbency of the late Reverend John Kosinski the task of improving and developing the college was projected on a large scale. The Reverend Father Kosinski promoted it with zeal and efficiency, and it is no wonder that his industry has been crowned with success and has received general recognition.</p>
   <p>The College now has a permanent course of study and an improved school program which are equal to those of any English educational institution of the same rank.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0272.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thanks to the continual efforts and the conscientious labor of its directors, St. Stanislaus' College reached so high a level of quality and efficiency that His Excellency Archbishop Quigley named it among the best high schools in his extensive archdiocese. During these years the number of students has shown a notable increase, and our entire community desires to see the expansion of this useful institution of learning. Credit for his real and lasting service should be here accorded to the Reverend Father Kosinski. Chief among those who have recognized the fundamental importance of this institution is the first Polish bishop in America, His Excellency the Reverend Paul P. Rhode. One should mention here in passing that when the State of Illinois revised the statute which regulates the Charters of higher educational institutions, the late Father Kosinski recognized the importance of this measure and obtained for St. Stanislaus' College under the terms of the act all university privileges as to the course of study and the granting of academic credits.</p>
   <p>And finally, our College has gained recognition of its diplomas by the Gregorian University in Rome and also by the educational authorities of the State of New York. It is only proper to mention here the constant striving of the adminstration for improvement, and the study program and the management of the institution are steadily approaching perfection. A business course has been established and a laboratory has been installed. Collections of various sorts have been accumulated, and private rooms and cabinets have been built.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0273.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Today this Polish College in its equipment is inferior to no similar institution. Our school's program is expressed in outline as follows: "The duty of the school is to foster and systematically to develop in the younger generation the consciousness of national origins, thereby leading the mind, the heart, and the will in a national direction; and since the good qualities of our country are ardent love of the fatherland and devotion to it, the love of our elders and worship of the traditions of our fathers, therefore the exaltation and the magnification of these virtues are the prime constituents of national education. "The teaching of religion in the native tongue, a custom of which St. Stanislaus' College is a guardian and fervid defender, the teaching of the Polish language, full of charm in sound and construction, the teaching of literature with constant emphasis on the sacred idea of love of the fatherland, the teaching of Polish history, so rich in records of the deeds of our forefathers, the arrangement of national celebrations, the remembrance of illustrious historical places and events, the preservation of patriotic songs and of national customs and practices, and the reading of Polish literature, - here are the reading of Polish literature, - here are the elevating influences, the ways and means of inspiring patriotic emotions in youth.</p>
   <p>Having for its watchword service for God and the fatherland in the Catholic spirit, and likewise in a spirit sincerely filled with love for all that is Polish, this institution for the education of our Polish youth born here in a foreign land endeavors to instill in them attachment to our national traditions and affection for them and for our native history, - for everything that is of Polish origin!" The educational program of St. Stanislaus' College corresponds in it details to that of English institutions in general of equal rank in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
