<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-25">May 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Education and Commerce.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-25">May 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION AND COMMERCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today we witness the opening session of the 4th annual convention of the Polish Merchants Association, the White Eagle. Therefore it is appropriate at this time, to say something on the important subject of education and its effect on business. This is a very important matter, as we are forced by keen competition to elevate the scope of our education because it is impossible to carry on the affairs of a business establishment without the elementary and fundamental knowledge of business principles.</p>
   <p>Years ago the question of heredity, nationality or education meant but little in our quest for employment; today, however, whether we are laborers or office workers it takes on a different meaning, and in many instances education is becoming a strict requirement.</p>
   <p>In industry or commerce, men, proficient in a profession or a trade secure, in most cases, the better paying positions. It is essential that certain establishments have employees with specific knowledge. This practical training, for many years, could be obtained at the various technical colleges and universities; but the vital question confronting us today is the urgent need of a sound business education which can likewise be obtained in these institutions <pb facs="5423968_1_0125.jpg" n="2"/>of higher learning.</p>
   <p>We must, however, give due credit to the Germans of Chicago; through their untiring and united efforts the first commercial course was introduced in our educational system. It is, therefore, easy to understand why they hold first place in the business world today; and the undeniable fact remains, that education, plus special training, makes leadership possible and easier to achieve.</p>
   <p>The University of Illinois introduced a 4 year commercial course. The classes, in the beginning, were composed of merchants of all ages. These men, however, after graduating, became, and are today, leaders in their respective field of endeavour in the business world.</p>
   <p>We regret to say that the enrollment of students of Polish descent or origin, at this time, is very small and cite as an example the University of Illinois School of Commerce, where only 6 Poles, in a class totaling several hundred, are enrolled.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0126.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is a very small percentage which does not, and cannot, attract the attention of the public. Therefore, all Polish Merchants, individually and as a group, should encourage and propagate the program of higher higher education. Only then can we rest assured that our business enterprises and commerce in general will meet with success in the years to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
