<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[The Need For]Continuation Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[THE NEED FOR]CONTINUATION SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the initative of Edwin G. Cooley, principal of Continuation Schools, a group of prominent Polish leaders attended a special meeting on December 9. Those who attended the session at the bureau of Public Schools were as follows: Mmes M. Smietanka, Magdalene Milewska, Leokadja Zielinska, W. Kuflewska, L. Kadow, Irene Koralewska, P. Dyniewicz, Agnes Klawitter, H. Mazurkiewicz, P. Zdanowska, Bertha Fritsch, Mary Paczynska, K. S. Obarska, M. Sadowska, A. Podbielska, W. Chodzinska, Pearl Stranc, and Attorney F. P. Danisch.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this meeting was to set up plans for the proper care of children between the ages of fourteen and sixteen who are employed. This action has been taken because the new State law provides that children between the ages mentioned must attend an eight hour school session once a week in public schools.</p>
   <p>In the Continuation Schools now operating in Chicago over forty per cent of <pb facs="5423968_1_0049.jpg" n="2"/>the students are of Polish extraction. Because of this large number, it was deemed by the Polish leaders that it is the duty of our society to see that they are adequately taken care of. As it happens many times, there are employers who are against this law, and as a consequence, they do not pay the minors in their employ for the day at school. This Polish delegation is of the opinion that this kind of treatment on the part of employers must be stopped immediately.</p>
   <p>They also believe that the present number of Continuation Schools--three in number--is not sufficient to handle all the children that are employed, therefore, they urge the building of new schools to accommodate the increasing number of children that are being employed in industry.</p>
   <p>After a number of meetings arranged by the outstanding Polish people, it was decided to form a group. This was agreed upon. The Citizens Continuation School Committee was its outcome. Its aims are: to take interest in the present schools that offer training to children employed in industry between the ages of fourteen and sixteen, and to urge the building of such schools <pb facs="5423968_1_0050.jpg" n="3"/>throughout the State of Illinois in order that they may meet the ever-increasing number of children. These schools will in no way conflict with the parochial schools, for they will be primarily concerned with the employed children of the city.</p>
   <p>It was agreed to contact all clubs and groups of every nationality in the city to support this movement, after all it concerns every nationality in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>When this Society was organized, Mrs. Mary Smietanka was elected chairman, and F. P. Danisch was chosen secretary. Mmes Hedwig Smulska, president; P. Dyniewicz, secretary; W. Chodzinska, K. S. Obarska, M. Paczynska, M. Milewska, and L. Kadow, became members of the organizing committee.</p>
   <p>A general meeting will be held January 4, 1922 at 2 P. M. The organizing committee will convene on December 29 at the home of Mrs. Smulska. This meeting will be held during the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
