<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-11">Jan. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">System of Elective Subjects Introduced at Alliance College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-11">Jan. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SYSTEM OF ELECTIVE SUBJECTS INTRODUCED AT ALLIANCE COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance College has undergone a complete change in its academic system. Up to the present the grade system was used. This means that the pupils were classified, and entered into specified grades, not according to their knowledge of particular subjects, but according to their average mental development.</p>
   <p>This system was the cause of a great deal of dissatisfaction on the part of the students who did not want to or could not conform to the average standard of a given grade. On the other hand, students transferring to the college from American schools could not fit themselves into such a primitive and impractical system of education.</p>
   <p>There were also other difficulties to solve; for instance, the Polish boys who were born and brought up here in America very frequently had but a scanty knowledge of the Polish language. For these boys the grade system <pb facs="5423968_1_0264.jpg" n="2"/>was not only an inconvenience but, from a pedagogical standpoint, was very harmful. Let us suppose that a boy not knowing the Polish language and attending a local American school suddenly comes to the conclusion that he ought to learn the Polish language. He goes to the Alliance College, where he is enrolled in one of the upper grades on the basis of his knowledge of English subjects. Here the tragedy, if not actual comedy, begins. In the upper classes Polish literature and composition are taught, while this boy cannot even read Polish tolerably, not to mention orthography and grammar. The same thing happens with English subjects if the pupil does not happen to know English.</p>
   <p>The elective system does away with the disadvantages of the grade system. Besides this, it brings in such elements of pedagogical value that sooner or later this system will become universal. This system is based, in the first place, on a thorough understanding of the psychology of the adolescent, in the second, on the needs of a democratic people and the idea of specialization in modern society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0265.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know from the study of educational psychology that the mental development of one child differs greatly from that of another, that it possesses different qualities, has different interests and different aims. Each one of these minds represents a world in itself. Nevertheless the needs of a democratic society aim toward a certain mental level, a common ground, on which all the citizens of a given society can meet and work together toward the attainment of a mutual goal. On the other hand, the diversification of the needs of modern civilization and the progress of education constantly require more specialization in the chosen field, training for which must be begun practically in childhood.</p>
   <p>Therefore, pursuing the lines indicated by education and life, practical pedagogy has produced an elective system. I wish to describe briefly the application of this system at the Alliance College. For exacting minds there are science courses; for lively and practical minds, business and technical courses; for the undecided there is a general course. Besides this, these courses are so arranged that a student can make a change at <pb facs="5423968_1_0266.jpg" n="4"/>the very beginning, when he notices that he has made a mistake or when the need for such a change arises. Secondly, no student will be able to climb to the next rung of the ladder of education who has not been thoroughly prepared for it and who has not given proof that he is thoroughly familiar with the preceding steps and that he can lean back on them. That is why all promotions will be granted according to the subject, not from grade to grade. For example, a promotion in Latin will have no effect on a promotion in algebra or physics, and vice versa. In this way the student will be able to eliminate those subjects which do not conform to his ability, and should he fail through his own negligence he will see the justice of a system which punishes him only in the case in which he has been at fault. Thirdly, a certain number of academic subjects is absolutely required, others are elective. This characteristic trait of the system is the result of the need to give the pupils a social background on the one hand; on the other hand it answers the call of the people that the schools should give consideration to the future vocations and practical lives of future citizens. The fact that such subjects as Polish language and literature, English language <pb facs="5423968_1_0267.jpg" n="5"/>and literature, Polish and universal history, mathematics and one of the sciences are required of everyone, indicates that this system has taken into consideration the things on which a democratic society wants to base its activities, that is, a certain mental standard and common ground for its citizens. Each of these subjects creates a point of meeting and at the same time constitutes a tool for producing this mental equality required by a democratic society. Nevertheless a democratic society, although it requires certain co-operative efforts from its citizens, for its own good is not despotic and does not use up all the energy of these citizens. This restraint of society in regard to its members is reflected in the school system. We see that many subjects are elective, which means that the student can guide himself not only by the needs of society, but by the needs of his own mind and future vocation or profession as well.</p>
   <p>The choice of subjects is regulated in accordance with the purpose of the student. This purpose may be aimed at the distant or near future, it can be very practical or impractical. The purpose can even be the immediate <pb facs="5423968_1_0268.jpg" n="6"/>earning of a livelihood upon leaving school. All these purposes can be justified by various students; it is even the duty of the school to help the students attain these aims. That is why the Alliance College has adopted a school system which, by allowing the students to choose from among elective subjects, satisfies the various aims and desires of the students, which their mental, economic, and psychological differences indicate.</p>
   <p>This system will be especially beneficial to poor students, who not only will have the opportunity of obtaining an education, but will also be able to arrange their program of studies at the Alliance College in such a say that on leaving the College they will be able to earn a living while continuing their studies at American universities. This fact is of such great importance to poor students who are seeking an education that we wish it were as widely known as possible. With the inauguration of the present system at the Alliance College, no boy wanting to learn can complain against Polish society that it did not open the road to higher learning for him and help him along the way.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0269.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In conclusion I wish to state that the elective system which has been introduced into our Alliance school is, thanks to the above-mentioned pedagogic values, the kind of system that the members of the Alliance had the right to demand, namely, a system having a certain amount of elasticity so that it can satisfy all the requirements of life as well as those of education, at the same time that it prepares future citizens for their social life and responsibilities.</p>
   <p>(Signed) E. Dolewczynski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
