<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-08">Oct. 8, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Evening Schools]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-08">Oct. 8, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[EVENING SCHOOLS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The evening schools in Chicago will begin on Monday, October 10. Our fellow Poles should benefit from this opportunity. This pertains not only to the younger set, who should strive to complete their studies, but to the elders, as well, who wish to become adept in the use of the English language, which is so necessary in this country. We find from the reports issued by Mr. Roberts, Assistant Superintendent of Public Instruction in Chicago, that the increase of students in evening schools will be unusual this year; thus far 6,153 have enrolled, and it is anticipated that approximately 20,000 people will take courses in the evening schools. The greatest number of students have enrolled in Lane Technical High School, where 950 have applied for courses in manual arts.</p>
   <p>These schools will be opened for four days a week instead of five as has <pb facs="5423968_1_0083.jpg" n="2"/>been the practice heretofore. Evidently either lack of funds or the desire to economize plays a role here. Rumors have it that an evening school is to be opened at Holy Trinity Parish, where courses in the English language are to be given. The teachers here will be young Poles. Polish teachers will also be assigned to public schools where an adequate number of Poles desire to take courses. This depends upon our people themselves. The only thing necessary is good will on our part; the portals are open to those desiring knowledge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
