<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 21,
<date when="1921-05-26">May 26, 1921</date><title level="a">The Literary Test in Immigration Law</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_1_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_1_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 21,
<date when="1921-05-26">May 26, 1921</date><title level="a">THE LITERARY TEST IN IMMIGRATION LAW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The average social worker in this country has always insisted that the "foreigner" learn the American language. Methods verging upon enforcement of the daily use of the language by the "foreign element" have failed completely for obvious reasons. Some workers will have it, that only he who speaks English in this country is a good American. The immigration law provides for a literary test and well might this test be considered foolish, since many a European criminal was granted admission into this country on the strength of his being able to read and write very fluently, while the honest and efficient immigrant was denied admission because of his lack of such knowledge. Poverty and persecution prohibited (prevented) the honest and efficient immigrant from attending school even in his own country. He lived in hope that the new land would offer him opportunity, but his hopes were shattered and all noble ambition lost by an unreasonable literary test. A thorough understanding of the commandments of the Supreme Being, and the precepts of nature, should make up for the literary test. The illiterate immigrant practices the law of God and the precepts of nature while the literate European criminal practices forgery and makes the poor illiterate immigrant his prey. Which would you rather have in this country, the peace-loving, honest and ambitious but illiterate, immigrant or the literate European criminal?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
