<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-02-11">Feb. 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Less Words, and More Action</title><title level="a" type="sub">by V. Levkovich Editorial of the Rnzov--Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-02-11">Feb. 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">LESS WORDS, AND MORE ACTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by V. Levkovich Editorial of the Rnzov--Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the present time there is a great deal of talk and written discussion relative to the consolidation of the Russian colonies in the United States and Canada. All of these rumors and speeches would be good if the people considered this matter seriously. But, besides talking, they should also act for the benefit of unity. Join organizations and societies, and stimulate more activity within the organization; arise and help solve the problems concerning the condition of the colony.</p>
   <p>I happen to meet many colonists who are loquacious, and are always complaining that they are embarrassed and ashamed of the Russian colony; but they themselves, for some reason, are not at all interested in the movements within <pb facs="5423967_4_0605.jpg" n="2"/>the organizations. It is a pity that such people keep themselves aloof, and have the nerve to say that they are sick in spirit about the Russian colony, because it is not organized--because it is not progressive.</p>
   <p>Is it possible to believe in their sincerity? If they wish to see the Russian colony united, then they must take an active part in the matter, and not remain seated and wait for somebody else to do it.</p>
   <p>Unity is the most important question which stands before our nonpartisan organizations. Especially is this true now, at the time of such a terrible depression, when cold and starvation menace us. The majority of us are old colonists who have lived here over twenty years. To many of us, even when this [crisis of]unemployment is over, the doors of shops, mills and factories will be closed because of our age. Can one remain passive? Let's hope that unity will be accomplished soon, and that the colony will begin to improve the existing conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0606.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the duty of the members of Rnzov--Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) to strain all their efforts, to establish one mighty, great, Russian family here, across the ocean. It is necessary to stretch out, and, by every means, to introduce into our social life worthwhile projects in order to benefit ourselves.</p>
   <p>Think it over, dear reader; can you possibly hesitate when life itself pushes you toward unity? The Russian colony needs to be united, and it must succeed in that endeavor no matter what the cost.</p>
   <p>Two relatively similar organizations, the Rnzov and Roov, Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obschestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (The Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society) should stop their sparring, should compromise and achieve the agreed-upon goal for the benefit of the entire Russian colony. It is necessary to believe in a better future, and that belief will unite us.</p>
   <p>At the present time conventions are being held. The brotherhood branches should strive to formulate a resolution for the unification of all the Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_0607.jpg" n="4"/>organizations into one strong mutual aid organization. The Mutual Aid Society does not seek a political or religious goal; there is a great field for those who want to work for the benefit of the Russian colony. Think of and remember the needs of the broad masses of unorganized Russians.</p>
   <p>Let's hope that the hour is near when the Russian masses will be organized--if that goal is not sidetracked by various adventurers who pretend that they support the Russian cause, but in reality only injure us greatly. By all means, we must sever relations with such persons. We must take care of ourselves and of our future generation.</p>
   <p>We know that our ranks are growing thinner every year--the older members are retiring. The cursed rheumatism keeps many of us from working for our organizations as eagerly as before. Our youthful years pass imperceptibly but the colony remains silent and sleeps an eternal sleep. Our youth grow up and leave us because we have nothing to offer them, and thus to hold them near us. We do not have a national university, a Russian theater, hospital, farm, or even public hall with a decent library and reading room. These are the things <pb facs="5423967_4_0608.jpg" n="5"/>we should consider; we should not delay our movement toward unity, but should unite at once; the sooner we do it, the better it will be. All for this significant and invaluable cause!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
