<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-13">Dec. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Day of the Russian Child a Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-13">Dec. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE DAY OF THE RUSSIAN CHILD A SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago branch of the Russian Emigre Children's Aid Society held a social gathering and an entertainment for the benefit of the destitute Russian children who are refuges in foreign countries. The affair, which was called The Day of the Russian Child, was held October 21 at the Russian-American Club. The evening was a complete success, both financially and artistically.</p>
   <p>The Russian artists who answered the call in large numbers and disinterestedly contributed their talent to make the evening a success are chiefly responsible for the splendid outcome of the efforts of the committee in charge of arrangements. They offered a rich and extensive program of Russian music, songs, and dances. The public highly enjoyed the program; the entire audience was enthralled by its own native music, songs, and dances performed by native artists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0319.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following Russian artists contributed their time and talent to the affair without any remuneration whatsoever: <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Viniarskayd, Ukrainian singer; E. Vadimov, Russian baritone; <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Gedevanova, radio singer; A. Dobrokhotov, balalaika player; V. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>irova, dancer; P. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>aksakova, singer; P. Nelidov, opera baritone; Mrs. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ostovaya, accompanist.</p>
   <p>The committee that arranged the entertainment expresses its sincere thanks to the artists participating in the program, as well as to the following persons and institutions for their hearty co-operation in making the event a big success: the Right Reverend Leonti, the Right Reverend Timon, the Reverend S. Snegerov, the Russian newspaper <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>assviet, its publishers and editors, and to all persons who in any way assisted in arranging The Day of the Russian Child.</p>
   <p>The net proceeds from the affair, including admission tickets and bar <pb facs="5423967_4_0320.jpg" n="3"/>receipts, were $111.01. This money will be used to alleviate the sorrows and tribulations of Russian refugee children in many foreign countries.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Branch of</p>
   <p>the Russian Emigre Children's Aid Society</p>
   <p>I. F. Erin, chairman,</p>
   <p>A. D. Dobrokhotov, secretary.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Branch....Aid Society</p>
   <p>I. F. Erin, chairman,</p>
   <p><gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. D. Dot....., secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
