<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-09">Sept. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Fundamental Questions of Our American Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial of the R. I. M. A. S.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0593</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0593.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-09">Sept. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FUNDAMENTAL QUESTIONS OF OUR AMERICAN LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial of the R. I. M. A. S.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many Russian people in America consider political questions the basis of life in this country.</p>
   <p>Political questions are being solved by our Russian immigrants in various ways. Some of our people have been carried away by Bolshevism; others by socialism, and still others by monarchism and by Fascism. Each of these groups is convinced it is working for the good of the Russian laboring class in America. They do not realize that political activity paralyzes and distorts our everyday actualities, and prevents us from concentrating on the questions of everyday life in a foreign country.</p>
   <p>It is high time to limit our problems to realities, and to stop grouping ourselves according to different political views. We should now look for <pb facs="5423967_4_0594.jpg" n="2"/>a common ground.</p>
   <p>In this period of economic crises, political questions appear to be of the utmost importance. In reality, we should set before ourselves immeasurably deeper and more fundamental questions pertaining to our life in this country, and to the destiny of the Russians in America.</p>
   <p>The Russian cause in America must not be lost because of the pressure of politicians and internationalists. Nor should any Russian man find himself lost, like a sheep in a strange flock.</p>
   <p>It is only necessary that every one should exert himself to renounce for a time his political opinions, without, however, suppressing his Russian national consciousness; to analyze the effects of the long and painstaking work of Russian immigrants in America; to sum up the lost time and energy and health in our political activity, and then impartially ask himself this question: "What price have we paid for all this work, and who of <pb facs="5423967_4_0595.jpg" n="3"/>us has derived any benefit from it?"</p>
   <p>Then we shall see that the only good derived from this activity by Russian immigrants was frequent change of their political convictions. In other words, they have been changed by various political "priests" from Socialists to Bolsheviks, and from Bolsheviks to Communists.</p>
   <p>The most holy political tenet that the Russian immigrants so eagerly embraced was Communism. But here also they burned their fingers. The hypocritical Communist leaders lately have shown their shameless faces; their "principles of liberty" proved to be a subterfuge. Many more honest people who had been trapped into Communism, left the party. Some of them became Fascists, trying thus to "save their face" by embracing this new movement, like a drowning man grasping at a straw.</p>
   <p>But all this is a vain effort, a futile loss of time and energy. The working man cannot find salvation at the hands of the politician. All party work of <pb facs="5423967_4_0596.jpg" n="4"/>the politicians, in the past and now, has always been directed toward gaining power over the masses in order to exploit them.</p>
   <p>Taking all this into consideration, what real and fundamental question shall we say is facing all Russians in America? It is understood that the question now facing us is economic and spiritual. The political question should take the third place.</p>
   <p>All Russians should ask themselves: Is there spiritual unity among us? Is there peace and agreement among us? Do we preserve brotherly love in all our relations? Are we ready to stand by one another, and to extend a helping hand to our Russian brother in case of need? Do we possess the hope that the Russian name in America will reach the height attained by other national groups? Can our children receive a good bringing up, and a higher education, in order to become useful not only to themselves, but to the Russian nation and to the entire cultured world?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0597.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This should be our fundamental question and the mainspring of our activity here in a foreign land.</p>
   <p>Before entering political life, it is necessary first to prepare ourselves spiritually, and to strengthen ourselves economically. Only after solving these two fundamental questions can our people find the right political way--a way in which there will be no room for our present political adventurers.</p>
   <p>But to accomplish this we should organize ourselves into one great Russian family, into the organization of mutual aid. Then, on this foundation, we can build our well-being and our happiness, acquire our spiritual nourishment, and develop our general outlook.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
