<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-19">Feb. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[The USSR and War]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-19">Feb. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[THE USSR AND WAR]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pravda [Translator's note: Official organ of the Communist Party of Russia] prominently features an editorial concerning the "USSR in the international scene". In this editorial the Red newspaper attempts to justify the growth of Red militarism by [mention of] a new military danger which confronts "the only socialist country in the world."</p>
   <p>As reported at the Soviet Congress, the numerical strength of the Red Army, during the last four years, has been increased from six hundred thousand to nine hundred and forty thousand soldiers. The war budget for 1934 will total five billion roubles. [Translator's note: at the rate of exchange prevailing at the time this editorial was written, the rouble was worth fifty-one cents.] During the current year, the budget will increase to six and one-half billion roubles.</p>
   <p>In order to justify this immense expenditure for armaments, the Bolshevik <pb facs="5423967_4_1426.jpg" n="2"/>newspaper states or emphasizes those circumstances which are supposed to exist in every capitalist country. The Soviet government, in other words, claims that it is arming the country as a defense measure because the other countries are increasing their armaments. The Soviet government declares that the Soviet Union does not intend to use its military strength to attack any other country.</p>
   <p>The Newspaper states: "Imperialist Japan is carrying on an open war against China, openly declaring that its aims are the redivision of the world, which has already been divided. Fascist Germany is ready to follow imperialist Japan. The National Socialist party of Germany is spreading its beastly propaganda against all other nationalities, and attempts to mask this by its nonsensical 'theories' about the superiority of the German race.</p>
   <p>"The German National Socialist party is spreading the gospel of hatred toward other nations. It is depending [for support] upon other nations who wish to grab some territory in a world which is to be redivided or to be created in opposition to Soviet Russia. The danger of war has grown, and with it has grown <pb facs="5423967_4_1427.jpg" n="3"/>the danger of an assault on Soviet Russia.</p>
   <p>"For this reason, the [Communist] party and the government have worked without respite all these years to strengthen the defenses of the Soviet boundaries and to make them impregnable. During recent years fortified regions have been established with all the necessary military equipment on the Soviet Union's eastern and western frontiers. The numerical strength of the Red Army has been increased and the Red Fleet has grown tremendously, particularly, the submarine fleet. Artillery, tanks, and aviation equipment for the Red Army have been developed to a staggering proportion. This increase of the armed forces required an extra expenditure for defense."</p>
   <p>From all this we can see that Red militarism has grown tremendously, but the newspaper claims that all this is due to the inevitable attack which is pending against the Soviet Union from the capitalist countries.</p>
   <p>But, let us see, do not Japanese, German, Polish, English, and other militarists <pb facs="5423967_4_1428.jpg" n="4"/>tell us the same story when they increase their own military expenditures? Of course, they do. They also assert that their countries are in imminent danger of attack from other countries, and for that reason alone they have to arm their own countries.</p>
   <p>The difference between the militarists of capitalist countries and Bolshevik militarists is that the former do not consider it necessary to engage in hypocritical talk about world peace and disarmament, and the latter always talk about their own peaceful intentions. However, the facts show that the more Bolsheviks talk about peace, the more they appropriate for armaments. In this respect they have, in fact, surpassed all capitalist countries. No wonder, therefore, that nobody takes seriously their empty blabbering about world disarmament and peace. As the old adage says: "Men are known not by their words, but by their deeds".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
