<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-12-02">Dec. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Recognition and the Russian Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-12-02">Dec. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">RECOGNITION AND THE RUSSIAN ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some queer Russian fellow, who for twelve years was a member of one of the Russian organizations, after reading in the newspapers of the recognition of the Soviets by the United States Government, has suddenly decided that, since the American Government has recognized the Soviet regime, all the Russians in America should become Communists, and should also acknowledge the Soviet government. There may be more such undiscriminating fools among our number, whose ignorance can be exploited by dishonest politicians to their own and their families' harm. For this recognition complicates greatly the situation of the Russian immigrants in America, especially those who are not citizens of the United States.</p>
   <p>The recognition of the Soviets by the Washington Government is purely a political act, instituted for the purpose of establishing with the Soviet diplomatic and commercial relations, arrangements for the liquidation of debts, and means for the exchange of views pertaining to military matters. The recognition act not <pb facs="5423967_4_1486.jpg" n="2"/>only fails to favor the existing Communist system in Russia at the present time, but actually forbids the sponsoring of Communist propaganda by the Soviet government in the United States or in any of its possessions or territories.</p>
   <p>In connection with this, the Soviet Foreign Commissar Litvinoff has formulated and signed the following communication--a promise not to conduct propaganda:</p>
   <p>"Washington, November 16, 1933.</p>
   <p>"My Dear Mr. President:</p>
   <p>"I have the honor to inform you that, in connection with the establishment of diplomatic relations between our two governments, the fixed policy of the government of the Union of Socialist Soviet Republics will be:</p>
   <p>"1. Rigidly to observe the indisputable right of the United States to live its own life, according to its own laws and principles, and to refrain from any interference whatsoever in the internal affairs of the United States, its territories and possessions;</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1487.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"2. To restrain all persons in the service of the Soviet government, and all organizations under its direct or indirect control, including those organizations which receive from this government financial aid, from any open or secret activity which might in any way undermine the tranquillity, well-being, order, or safety of the United States or any part of its territory or possessions; and, in particular, from any act which might cause armed intervention on the part of the government," also to restrain such from the use of any propaganda having for its purpose the undermining of the integrity of the United States; and from attempts to change, by force, the political or social order of the United States, its territories or possessions.</p>
   <p>"3. Not to authorize or allow under its banner the formation, continuance, or activity in the United States of any organization or group aspiring to become the government of the United States, or threatening the integrity of the United States, its territories or possessions; or any activities of representatives of <pb facs="5423967_4_1488.jpg" n="4"/>the same. Also, not to form, organize subsidize, aid or authorize any military organizations or groups having for their goal an armed uprising against the United States, its territories or possessions; and not to sanction the recruiting of members for such organizations and groups.</p>
   <p>"4. Not to sanction the formation, training or occupancy on the soil of the United States or any of its territories or possessions of any organization or group which has for its aim the overthrow by force of the United States Government, or preparation for such action, or the use of force in bringing about social and political changes in any or in all parts of the United States, its territories or possessions; or sanction any activity toward these ends on the part of its representatives, chiefs or commanders.</p>
   <p>"I remain, my dear Mr. President,</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"Maxim Litvinoff,</p>
   <p>"People's Commissar for Foreign Affairs</p>
   <p>of the Union of Soviet Socialist</p>
   <p>Republics"</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1489.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Russian organizations in America, organized and conducting their activities according to American laws, are not in the least hurt or threatened by the recognition of the Soviets by the American Government. Our organizations have no obligations to the Soviet government, and, although they have Russian names they are legally American organizations, under the jurisdiction and proctection of American laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
