<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XI, 4601 N. Broadway, Russkoye Slovo,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"Fruit of Knowledge" (Club Znaniye)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XI, 4601 N. Broadway, Russkoye Slovo,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"FRUIT OF KNOWLEDGE" (CLUB ZNANIYE)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some months ago a new Russian Club was organized in Chicago, and was named KNOWLEDGE (ZNANIYE) its organizer being prelate and the psalm-chanter, Mr. R--ov.</p>
   <p>The fundamental reason or organizing this club was, apparently, the advantage for his holy little business-place, to which the little patriots flocked, and from whom the most honorable Fathers gathered wool.</p>
   <p>The choir for this church was picked from among the club members, who sang very beautifully hymns and songs for a remuneration of kisses, one a-piece, impressed on the forehead by the very Bishop himself.</p>
   <p>One day the little father betook himself with his mission to the nearby suburb Melrose Park, and took his club choir along, to whom it occurred to whip up <pb facs="5423967_4_1156.jpg" n="2"/>National patriotic feelings by singing "God save the Tsar."</p>
   <p>The listeners began to whistle and to hiss and the singers barely escaped a beating. The choir felt insulted and cleared out. There occurred a second incident, which was even more interesting. These progressive compatriots bethought themselves to give a concert in behalf of refugees, which affair began and ended in true Russian fashion, i. e., in a wholesale drunk--everybody prostrated, "soused," "stewed."</p>
   <p>The collection was large but no account was submitted, although more than a month has passed since the affair.</p>
   <p>One only wonders that our good countrymen, protected by the Russian clergy, singing hymns to the Tsar, should call itself a progressive club!</p>
   <p>Signed,</p>
   <p>Karantinov</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
