<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-07-16">July 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Running after Two Hares</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-07-16">July 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">RUNNING AFTER TWO HARES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Editorial concerning the efforts of the Soviet government to gain the recognition of the United States)</p>
   <p>The editorial points out that the Soviet government in its relations to the foreign powers, tries to follow two opposite courses at the same time. On one hand the Soviet government tries to gain the friendship of capitalistic states, on the other hand it carries on a revolutionary communistic propaganda through its secret agents and its secret organizations in the same countries. When the Soviet government tries to gain the recognition of some foreign power, it buys the cooperation of important capitalists and politicians by promising them concessions and other advantages in Russia. Thus both revolutionary Communists, foes of capitalism, and industrial and financial magnates and prominent politicians are seen to work together for the <pb facs="5423967_4_0681.jpg" n="2"/>cause of a Communist government. This strange alliance is especially prominent in the United States, where secret or camouflaged Communist organizations, and men like Senator Borah and the millionaire Harriman are making propaganda for the recognition of the Soviet government. The capture of the United States is very important for the Russian Bolshevist government, as it has lost its popularity in England; and such countries as France, Italy, and even Germany can do very little for Soviet Russia when it comes to financial help. It is very nice for a Russian commissar to go to France for a vacation in order to "restore his health." He can drink there very good champagne, but he would hardly be able to arrange a loan for Soviet Russia. Under such circumstances the Soviet rulers keep their eyes turned in the direction of the United States, where there is still plenty of money to be had.</p>
   <p>In spite of several declarations of the United States Government that <pb facs="5423967_4_0682.jpg" n="3"/>it would under no circumstances grant recognition to a Bolshevist government, the Soviet rulers do not despair and continue their efforts to break the resistance of the Washington government. They often use as their tools American tourists, some of whom during the summer visit Russia. Influential Americans, politicians, businessmen, journalists, etc., get from the Soviet rulers gorgeous receptions, are shown only the best of what is to be seen in Soviet Russia, get all kinds of promises, and are told how profitable it would be for the Americans to establish regular commercial relations with Russia. This, of course, could be achieved only if the United States would grant recognition to the Soviet government. Many of these tourists are fooled thus and make propaganda for such recognition when they return to America.</p>
   <p>The author of the editorial thought that these efforts of the Communist rulers of Russia who, while courting influential Americans, <pb facs="5423967_4_0683.jpg" n="4"/>at the same time are carrying on revolutionary propaganda in the United States, would hardly lead to success, since, as a Russian proverb says, "one who runs after two hares at the same time will not catch either of them."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
