<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Imbeciles</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Goroschenia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">IMBECILES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Goroschenia</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Whom the gods would destroy they first make mad." The last two issues of Novy Mir, the Communist daily newspaper in New York, devoted a great deal of space to the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. The articles were mostly about the supposed call issued by V. Ribak, the newly-acquired slave of Mr. Deviatkin [Translator's note: Deviatkin is a leader of the Russian Communists in Chicago].</p>
   <p>The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society seemingly keeps Deviatkin awake at night. This well-organized society obviously is particularly hateful to such people as Deviatkin.</p>
   <p>According to statistics there are seventy-four thousand Russians in Chicago. These Russian people have no attraction for Mr. Deviatkin and his clique. He pays no attention to them, but he is greatly disturbed by the existence <pb facs="5423967_4_0751.jpg" n="2"/>of the three thousand well-organized Russians who belong to the Russian Independent Society. Instead of doing something in the way of organizing new societies for those who so far have not joined any Social group, Deviatkin and his assistants are trying to destroy or disrupt the organization created by the efforts of other people. Why are they trying to do this? It is because Deviatkin's aim is to destroy every organization having nationalist leanings. This is the goal of all irresponsible free-lancers of Deviatkin's type. Deviatkin needs the Russians, but he can exploit them only when they are unorganized and helpless. They have already destroyed the Russian People's Mutual Aid Society of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. They seized control of this organization and stealthily joined it to the International Workers' Order [a mutual aid organization with very strong Communist leanings]. This mutual aid society was a strong Russian organization but, thanks to Deviatkin's efforts, it lost its Russian identity and surrendered its treasury to the manipulations of these international brigands, who are now in full control.</p>
   <p>Now the same clique is attempting to get control of the treasury of the Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_0752.jpg" n="3"/>Independent Mutual Aid Society. They are not interested in the well-being of seventy-four thousands Russians; indeed, they are very little concerned with what happens to the Society's members. They want only the Society's money, and are enraged because the officers of the organization stand guard over the treasury and refuse to let Deviatkin and his associates come near it. Others of the same calling as Deviatkin, Ribak and Nevsky, in their appeal to the members of the Society pretend that they want to explain the aims of the organization, but in doing so they deliberately distort the facts and spread misinformation.</p>
   <p>For the information of Mr. Ribak and his boss, we mention that the organization to which they refer in their appeal originally was called the "Russian Orthodox Society of St. George the Warrior," and its aims were: to propagate the Russian Orthodox religion in America; to build a Russian church; and to help those Russians who were in need by giving them financial aid.</p>
   <p>Our present society follows in the footsteps of the original organization, always acting hand in hand with the Russian people and adjusting itself to <pb facs="5423967_4_0753.jpg" n="4"/>the times. In 1925 we found it necessary to modify somewhat the aims of the organization. We revised our bylaws, and the purposes of the society were changed to conform to the wishes of the membership. In 1930 we introduced further changes and modifications, again in accordance with the desire of a majority of the members.</p>
   <p>It was only 27 years after he had joined our Society that Ribak, with the help of some "well-wishers" from Division Street, found it necessary to "elucidate" the aims of our organization to its members, but he very soon discovered that he had missed his own aim. It would be more proper for Mr. Deviatkin to join a Jewish society and not an Orthodox society which devotes its energies to propagation of the Russian religion.</p>
   <p>It may seem strange that a man, after being a member of the organization for twenty-three years, finally, after a lapse of so many years, all of a sudden discovers that the aims of our society still remain obscure to most of the members, and that this is not the organization he wishes to belong to. The entire Deviatkin camp consists of just such"progressive and conscientious <pb facs="5423967_4_0754.jpg" n="5"/>men". Only among the little-cultured and ill-informed can totally ignorant and irresponsible men like Deviatkin exist and prosper. Ribak seemingly felt ill at ease among our members; so he decided to try his luck with the members of the International Workers' Order.</p>
   <p>Well, the way out is clear and smooth. Let him feather another nest for Mr. Deviatkin. As far as we members of the rank and file of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society are concerned, we are happy and fortunate to belong to our own organization, which we control and which does not have to obey orders from Mr. Deviatkin's headquarters. The aims and tendencies of our society are subject to constant change; we progress and advance with the changing times. First it was the propagation of religion; now it is mutual brotherly aid in an organized way in accordance with the bylaws and not by voluntary donations. When a husband who is a member of our Society dies, the wife and children are now assured that they will receive substantial financial help, and in case of sickness of any member of the Society the society will pay the doctor bills. The new forms of insurance introduced this year, have put our society on a firm foundation, on a level with the <pb facs="5423967_4_0755.jpg" n="6"/>large American insurance companies. Later on, we contemplate acquiring a farm home for our aged members, and creating a strong organization of children of our members so that the young people will be able to lift the banner of our society still higher and enhance the prestige of the Russian name still more.</p>
   <p>All of these things, of course, are not needed by Deviatkin, for "those who were born to crawl cannot fly". All such aims and tendencies in our society are hateful to Deviatkin and his kind, for they despise all that is Russian. But Deviatkin knows what he is doing, whereas Mr. Ribak and those Russians who are with him do not know. Enlightenment and more enlightenment is needed by the Russian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
