<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Our Problems</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROBLEMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beginnings of the Russian group in America have not yet been investigated and recorded, either for our own use or for the use of future generations. In the past, no one had undertaken this arduous and important task, for the obvious reason that we lacked properly qualified, well-trained men. Our group in this country consisted almost exclusively of former peasants, simple and unlearned. Now, however, such work could be undertaken, since we now have in our midst a number of trained, well-educated people, who find themselves in America as a result of recent political upheavals in Russia.</p>
   <p>This work could best be accomplished through the collective effort of all Russian societies, political groups, business and labor organizations, and Russian religious orders, in all parts of the United States. A history of the Russian immigrants in America would serve as a guide and an inspiration to us and to our young generation, which soon must take our places as leaders of our group in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0562.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We might do many things for our sons and daughters to enable them to carry on our work more efficiently, but we cannot do them as long as we remain divided among ourselves, as long as we do not act as one group united in one great purpose. As a national group, we are disunited, we are dissipated into many small factions. Because of this fact, the Russian group represents a very insignificant and unimportant quantity in the general background of American life and American activities.</p>
   <p>The only activity of our group worthy of mention is that of mutual aid insurance. But even our mutual aid societies could do a much greater and more extensive work were it not for the lack of understanding and the unabating disagreements among our wrangling factions. Another cause of the lean business of our mutual aid societies has been the unemployment situation and the general economic depression, which has affected not only the Russian group, but all other national groups as well, and which has stifled the economic life of the entire country.</p>
   <p>With the coming of fall, we should begin a new group life. Every Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_0563.jpg" n="3"/>having the good of his people at heart should shake off his weakness and his inertia. Activity should be his watchword. "Through common action to a common goal" should be our slogan. More faith in our own powers and greater striving for the better things in life should be our motto. The ways and means will be found as a matter of course. Sooner or later, the all-Russian convention must be called. This convention should work out a plan of unified action for all Russian groups or factions, regardless of their petty opinions and orientations. The convention, among other things, may decide the question of compiling a record, a history of the Russian immigrants in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
