<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-23">March 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Conference on the Defense of Immigrants</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-23">March 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE ON THE DEFENSE OF IMMIGRANTS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the conference on the defense of Russian workmen immigrants took place on March 14 of the current year. Delegates from the following schools and organizations were present:</p>
   <p>From the Women's Progressive Society, two delegates; from the Fullerton School, 1; from the Wicker Park School, 2; from the Russian Workmen's Mutual Aid Society, 3; from the International Committee for the Defense of Workmen, 2; from the Cooperative Restaurant, 1; from the House of the Workman, 1.</p>
   <p>As the other organizations did not send their delegates, and the problem of the defense of Russian workmen is a very important one, the meeting elected a committee consisting of three persons and entrusted to this <pb facs="5423967_4_1306.jpg" n="2"/>committee the task of calling another conference on April 4 of the current year at the quarters of the House of the Workman.</p>
   <p>The committee begs insistently all Russian labor organizations without exception to pay serious attention to this important problem and to the threatening danger of exclusion laws concerning immigrants which are being discussed now by the legislature. All organizations and schools should send their delegates to this conference in order that they may deliberate together and decide what measures we should take for our self-defense.</p>
   <p>Workmen of various nationalities have already called their conferences of defense. And it is time for us Russian workmen to raise our voice. You should elect without fail delegates from your organizations and send them to the conference of all Russian labor organizations of the city of Chicago and suburbs, which is going to take place (do not <pb facs="5423967_4_1307.jpg" n="3"/>forget that) on April 4, at 10 A. M. at the quarters of the House of the Workman, 1902 W. Division Street.</p>
   <p>For the Committee of the Conference,</p>
   <p>V. Stefanov, Secretary.</p>
   <p>(Note: - This conference was called at the initiative of the Bolsheviki. In reality it was attended only by delegates of Bolshevist organizations and of schools controlled by the Bolsheviki. N. K.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
