<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1929-11-23">Nov. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Entertainment by the Brotherhood of St. George</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1929-11-23">Nov. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ENTERTAINMENT BY THE BROTHERHOOD OF ST. GEORGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, November 17, a very successful entertainment was given by the 1st branch of the R. P. O. S. (Russian People's Orthodox Society) or, in other words, the Brotherhood of St. George.</p>
   <p>The program of the evening, although really too prolonged because of the great variety of numbers on it, was very good, and would have been excellent, if the organizers had been more careful in selecting an orchestra which would be able to accompany the actors, singers, dancers, and others.</p>
   <p>The gay comedy in one act, "Poor Teddy," was successfully performed by the amateurs, E. Wagner, P. Gribova, K. Bremer and M. Zhekhovich. Certainly the best of them was E. Wagner, who already has earned the reputation of a talented actor, and has no competitors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1089.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the concert program a very interesting number was the appearance of the family Ergolsky, who at present are in Chicago having obtained engagements on the American stage. M. S. Ergolskaia, Alexander Ergolsky, and later the ballerina, Alexandra Lashkova with her partner, were the attraction of the evening.</p>
   <p>The public welcomed heartily the popular singers, Mrs. P. M. Maksakova, and Mrs. S. I. Shukhvostova, who appeared in another part of the program.</p>
   <p>It is our pleasant duty to point out that for the vocal number, "The Beggars at the Walls of the Church," Mr. A. V. Meyerson, artist of our colony, painted the special scenery which strongly impressed the public by its effective coloring.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1090.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the rest of the program, we must mention the appearance of the satiric humorist, P. Gursky, and the instrumental trio, Chernishev and Co.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. I. Nedzelnitsky, physician of R. P. O. S., appeared on the stage as master of ceremonies and interpreter of various numbers.</p>
   <p>The hall was crowded, there was a shortage of admission tickets, sandwiches and refreshments, and naturally also of stewards. The noise and smoke in the hall, the disorderly conduct of the mischievous youths did not give the public any opportunity to hear what was occurring on the stage.</p>
   <p>For this reason, the artistic success of the evening was noticed only by a minority, in contrast to the financial success which was seen by all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1091.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is rumored that it was the first financially successful evening of the current season in the colony. Many guests came from Gary, Indiana, and Detroit, Michigan; there were many intellectual persons present.</p>
   <p>The dance continued past midnight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
