<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Injustice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> INJUSTICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Bar Association contends that there is a dearth of laws in the United States.</p>
   <p>Yet, the United States has more laws than any country in the world, and if laws are more frequently broken here than in any other country, the reason for it may be found in the constant making of new laws, which is assuming here the proportions of an epidemic.</p>
   <p>One cannot move without clashing with an old law or new one. Were it not for the fact that many of them have grown so old that they are forgotten and have become deed letters, thinking persons would find life impossible.</p>
   <p>So we here are suffering, not from scarcity of laws, but rather from an abundance of them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0490.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The unusual growth of crime in America may be caused <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> by individuals who are emulating those exemplary citizens, who are supported by their capital and by their political appointees. The lower social stratum will always learn the ways of the upper social stratum. One will amass millions by plundering; the other will be content with a mere street robbery. The former fights the government; the latter only his boss. Here an officer of the law shamelessly breaks his pledge. There some wretched poor man follows in the footsteps of the officer. Swindling keeps spreading and becomes popular because we are surrounded by swindlers, who exploit us and demoralize us. Even the average citizen evades the law because it proves to be an instrument of injustice.</p>
   <p>If the masses want to protect themselves from the unhappy consequences of strikes, they must see to it that there is a fair deal for the working class. Laborers are the support of society, they are entitled to a decent share in life which, in all decency, should have been accorded to them by now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
