<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the city of Chicago.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. L. G. Percy)</title> No. 2,
<date when="1927-09-24">September 24, 1927</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the city of Chicago.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. L. G. Percy)</title> No. 2,
<date when="1927-09-24">September 24, 1927</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The assembly was called to order at 10:10 P. M. at the quarters of the YMCA, 1621 W. Division street, S. G. Prokopov being chairman and Dr. L. G. Pertsov-Kaluzhin secretary.</p>
   <p>The following persons were present:K. L. Kotsyubinsky, treasurer of the Center, and the members: V. I. Pustovoytov, V. V. Kotov, N. K. Kutnyuk, Mrs. Y. M. Prokopov, Mrs. S. D. Perkopov, R. Biryukov and P. P. Moretsky.</p>
   <p>The order of the business of the day is read and accepted unanimously. The first item is "concerning the yearly entertainment." The secretary makes a report. He holds that in the past our entertainments were not quite successful. Therefore, he recommends to arrange in the nearest future, on November 19, instead of the usual entertainment, a "Tolstoyan <pb facs="5423967_4_0213.jpg" n="2"/>evening," and on January 7, 1928, an "evening in memory of Sergey Yesenin. And in the future, if our organization gets stronger, and the number of members will increase, we may also give a yearly entertainment.</p>
   <p>Pustovoytov, Prokopov, Kotsyubinsky and Kotov participate in the discussion. Dr. Pertsov's motion to organize the two literary evenings mentioned before is carried unanimously.</p>
   <p>Concerning item 2, about the monthly dues, after the question had been put to the vote twice, the following resolution is carried by a majority vote: "Men must pay (in accordance with the by-laws) 50 cents a month; ladies, 25 cents a month." The monthly dues must be paid without fail in advance. It is proposed to members to start paying right away the dues for the coming month of October. The clause of the by-laws stating that a "person who did not pay any dues during two months is considered to have automatically ceased to be a member of the organization" should be enforced without fail.</p>
   <p>Concerning item 3 "about the admission of non-members to business meetings <pb facs="5423967_4_0214.jpg" n="3"/>and the right procedure in nominating new candidates for membership," several members express their opinions, and after that the following resolution is carried by a majority vote: "Non-members are admitted to business meetings of the Center when invited by some full-fledged member of the organization. Persons nominated by someone as candidates for membership are made members according to the existing clauses of the by-laws of the Russian Center." Mr. R. Birukov, a new candidate for membership in the Russian Center, nominated by Mr. Kotsyubinsky and Dr. Pertsov-Kaluzhin, is elected a member unanimously.</p>
   <p>Item 4 of the order of the business of the day, concerning "an appeal to the colony signed by the chairman Mr. S. G. Prokopov" is accepted unanimously. Mr. Kotov and Mr. Pustovoitov are elected members of the committee entrusted with the working out of the text of the above mentioned appeal.</p>
   <p>As to item 5 "concerning the negotiations with the ROOV, N. Y.," it is resolved to entrust the secretary with writing a letter pointing out <pb facs="5423967_4_0215.jpg" n="4"/>that "no benefit society has been organized as yet in connection with the Russian Center. When such a society is organized we shall take up the matter of the proposal made by the New York society and may join it and become a branch of that society."</p>
   <p>Out of the items summed up under the common title of "Current business," only the following were discussed as it was getting late:</p>
   <p>(a) "On what days of the week should the business meetings be held?" Resolved: to have these meetings on every first and third Friday of every month at 7:30 P. M. No special notices will be sent; the members will be notified through the press.</p>
   <p>(b) Concerning Rev. Zheltonaga's lecture. Resolved: there will be a charge for the lecture. Three persons are elected to take care of the work connected with this lecture: Mr. K. Kotsyubinsky, treasurer of the Center will sell the tickets at the entrance to the hall; Mr. R. Birukov will tear off the stubs from the tickets at the door and show <pb facs="5423967_4_0216.jpg" n="5"/>the people in, and Mr. P. P. Meretsky will be the controller. It is also resolved by a majority vote that the charge for the lecture will be twenty-five cents, and that a paid advertisement will be published in the newspapers.</p>
   <p>The meeting is adjourned at 11:25 P. M. The next meeting will be held on Friday, October 7, 1927, at 7:30 P. M. in the same place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
