<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Percy</title>, 2559 W. Division Street.
<title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago.</title> No. 3,
<date when="1927-10-07">October 7, 1927</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Percy</title>, 2559 W. Division Street.
<title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago.</title> No. 3,
<date when="1927-10-07">October 7, 1927</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was called to order at 8:10 P.M., at the quarters of the YMCA, 1621 W. Division street. S. C. Prokopov was chairman, and Dr. L. G. Pertsov-Kaluzhin secretary.</p>
   <p>The following persons were present; K. L. Kotsyubinsky, treasurer of the Center, and the members: P.R. Birukov, N. K. Kutnyuk, Mrs. S. D. Pertsov; also the following non-members: Mr. Sedlovsky, Mr. Maslov, Mr. Zatsariny, and Mr. Kruge. The order of the business of the day is read and approved unanimously. The secretary makes a report concerning item 1, "About the further work of the organization and the relations with the press." He points out under what unfavorable conditions the Center has to do its work, when every time that some short notice about a lecture or a meeting has to be published in the newspaper one has <pb facs="5423967_4_0210.jpg" n="2"/>almost to beg for it three times. As to requesting the paper to publish some information concerning the cultural work of the organization and its various activities - it is a useless task; all such information is simply thrown into the waste paper basket. Mr. Kotsyubinsky, Mr. Maslov, Mr. Birukov and a few others express their opinions about this matter. Resolved: once more two delegates (Mr. Birukov and Mr. Pustovoytov) must be sent to the office of the newspaper in order to find out what causes such an inimical attitude. After that new candidates for membership are nominated, and these nominations are approved unanimously. Thus the following persons have become members of the Russian Center: Mr. Maslov, Mr. Zatzariny and Mr. Sedlovsky (recommended by the secretary), and Mr. Kruge (recommended by Mr. Pustovoytov). The next items of the order of the business of the day cause such a heated discussion between Dr. Pertsov and Mr. Kotsyubinsky on one side and Mr. Prokopov on the other that the assembly has no chance to come to any definite conclusion about the matter. Almost everybody present participates in this discussion. The following resolution is carried unanimously: because <pb facs="5423967_4_0211.jpg" n="3"/>of the late hour and the small number of members present the discussion of these matters must be postponed till the next general assembly, which is to be held in the the same place on Friday, October 21, exactly at 7:30 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
