<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-11-05">Nov. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Boundaries of Russia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-11-05">Nov. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOUNDARIES OF RUSSIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The official agent of Soviet Russia in Canada, Mr. Yazykov, published a few days ago a communication in which he announces that, in accordance with the declarations of amnesty in 1921, 1922 and 1923, many of those who participated in the military organizations of Kolchak, Denikin, Wrangel, Petlura and Yulenich return at present to Russia. These who took part in the rising of Kronstadt and in anti-soviet formations in white Russian in 1918, 1919 and 1920, etc., can also be repatriated.</p>
   <p>"Those who have been amnestied, so we are told in the above mentioned communication, will be transported to the U. S. S. R., either in groups or individually, as they will find more desirable."</p>
   <p>All persons who are affected by the amnesty will be able to sail <pb facs="5423967_4_1601.jpg" n="2"/>without any obstacles from Canada to Russia during the period from Nov. 7, 1924 to June 7, 1925.</p>
   <p>This communication does not mention at all the Russians residing in the United States.</p>
   <p>We have here only comparatively few participators of military anti-soviet organizations, risings and riots. But there are some former political emigrants and hundreds of thousands of Russian workmen and farmers.</p>
   <p>For persons belonging to these classes who want to go to Russia the boundaries of that country are almost closed.</p>
   <p>They cannot go to Russia "as they please - either in groups or as individuals."</p>
   <p>They have to join communes. They have to pay large sums of money as <pb facs="5423967_4_1602.jpg" n="3"/>otherwise they are not accepted as members in any of these communes. They have to spend much time in trying to get permits for entering Russia.</p>
   <p>They are not guilty of anything, but are treated as such.</p>
   <p>They are not able to return to their own native country.</p>
   <p>No explanations of this state of affairs given by the Soviet government can be considered as satisfactory excuses.</p>
   <p>Every one of these Russian emigrants should have the unconditional right to return to his native country. But as a fact at present we are deprived of this right.</p>
   <p>Being deprived of it constitutes the greatest injustice. And by perpetrating <pb facs="5423967_4_1603.jpg" n="4"/>this injustice the Soviet government is committing one of its gravest mistakes. This mistake gives rise to a justifiable discontent both among those who foster anti-soviet feelings and among those who are friends of the Soviet regime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
