<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-06-12">June 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">West Trust and Savings Bank Thanks the Russian Colony of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0629</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0629.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-06-12">June 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">WEST TRUST AND SAVINGS BANK THANKS THE RUSSIAN COLONY OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A quarter of a century ago, Russian immigrants who came to Chicago settled in the district of Halsted Street and Roosevelt Road; which was then the center of aliens of various nationalities. Arriving to a new country, unknown to them, without the knowledge of the English language, our immigrants naturally desired to become clients of those establishments where they could use their native language. Some crooked individuals took advantage of the confidences bestowed upon them by the Russian colonists, and have deceived them most unmercifully. The situation was radically changed after the establishment of a bank in "Russian Chicago," which became the bank of all the Russian immigrants.</p>
   <p>The West Side Trust and Savings Bank was established a quarter of a century ago by large financial interests connected with the Chicago Stock Yards. From the day of its opening, this bank became an institution where the hard earned savings of the Russian immigrant and many Russian organizations were deposited; where the Russian colonists went in order to get some good advice; or to send money to the old country; or purchase steamship tickets, etc. During the past twenty-five years this bank stood to guard the interests of its depositors, among <pb facs="5423967_4_0630.jpg" n="2"/>whom were thousands of Russians.</p>
   <p>The Russian colony which was concentrated in one locality had, during the past few years "scattered" all over the city and still the Russians continue to consider the West Side Trust and Savings Bank as their "own" bank. The Russian clients of this bank come from many different places; Pullman, Argo, Gary, Cicero, etc. Those in Chicago reside mostly in the vicinity of Humboldt, Douglas, and Brighton Parks.</p>
   <p>The staff of the bank thanks the Russian colony for the confidence and assures that it is always ready to render any service to its Russian clients and to safeguard their interests as it has been done for the past twenty-five years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
