<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.1"/>
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item><item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="unk" reason="[blank]"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="unk" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From 1910 to 1912 he was instructor at the Corps of Cadets of the name of the Emperor <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the II in St. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <p>In 1912 he joined the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Section of the Imperial Military Academy in St. Petersburg and, having completed his studies there, he graduated from the academy in 1914.</p>
   <p>During the years 1918 and 1913 he attended the practical courses in astronomy and high geodesy at the Noverossiysky University in Odessa.</p>
   <p>General Usefovich's service record stands as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Scholar of Artillery School</cell>
     <cell>1902</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Second lieutenant of artillery</cell>
     <cell>1902</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>First lientenant</cell>
     <cell>1905</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Second captain</cell>
     <cell>1909</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Captain</cell>
     <cell>1915</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>("with the right of seniority from 1913 for excellent service rendered in encouaters with the enemy.")</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1716.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Professor of tactics and topography at the military school in Vilno</cell>
     <cell>1915</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lieutenant-colonel, Tifle's Military School</cell>
     <cell>1918</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Colonel</cell>
     <cell>1918</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Major-General, retired</cell>
     <cell>1920</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>General Usefovich participated in the following campaigns:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1. Russe-Japanese war - in the defense of Port Arthur (field and coast artillery)</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2. World War, on Austrian frontier (on duty as an officer of the General Staff</cell>
     <cell>1914-15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3. Anti-Bolshevik war (South Russia) in General Denikin's army</cell>
     <cell>1918-20</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>General Usefovich has received on various occasion the following decorations:</p>
   <p>I. Crosses:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1. St. Vladimir's 4th class with swords and bands</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2. St. Anne's 3rd class with swords and bands</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1717.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>3. St. Stanislaus 2nd class with cwords and bands</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4. St. Anne's 2nd class with swords</cell>
     <cell>1915</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>5. St. Stanislans 2nd class with swords</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6. St. Anne's 4th class on the sword for "bravery."</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>7. Cross (iron) for Port Arthur defense.</cell>
     <cell>1904</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>II. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1. For Port Arthur defense (silver)</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2. Red Cross nedal for Russo-Japanese war (silver).</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3. Parechial schools' medal (silver)</cell>
     <cell>1909</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4. 300th Jubilee of the Romanoff dynasty (bronze)</cell>
     <cell>1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>5. For the Great War mobilization (bronze)</cell>
     <cell>1914</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6. French medal for Port Arthur defense (gold)</cell>
     <cell>1914</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>and several other insignias from many military corporations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1718.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>General Usefovich came to Chicago in 1923. In the beginning he had to do some odd jobs which were not at all appropriate for a man of his education and abilities. But in 1924 he was invited to work with the world renowned Rand McNally Company (printers specializing in maps), 538 S. Clark street. Soon he was able to occupy a responsible position in the department of cartography of this firm.</p>
   <p>In 1931 General Usefovich obtained a United States Civil Service government position having passed brilliantly his examination, ranking second among the candidates. About two years he has been serving in the Geodetic Division of the Department of Commerce. At present the general holds a responsible position in the United States Ship-Building Department. He has not only become an American citizen, but also a true American patriot. He is a member of five American military patriotic organizations. The organization of the Foreign War Veterans extended to him its invitation to visit its last convention in Annapolis, Md., in the quality of an honorary guest. At this convention he made a speech on behalf of the Russian war veterans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1719.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>General Usefovich was the first among foreign generals to be allowed not only to become a full-fledged member of the above mentioned military patriotic organization, but also to wear the American military uniform. He is the author of several monographs on <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> subjects both in the Russian and in the English languages.</p>
   <p>While residing in Chicago the general has been lecturing very frequently both for the Russian and for the Americans. He has also been an active member of several Russian social and philanthropic organizations in Chicago. He also acted as counsel to the Russian Center of the City of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
