<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-28">Mar. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Recommendations Concerning the Immigration Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1281</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1281.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-28">Mar. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">RECOMMENDATIONS CONCERNING THE IMMIGRATION QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last June, the Secretary of Labor, Miss Frances Perkins, formed a special committee of fifty persons well acquainted with our social problems in general, and the immigration problems in particular, and gave it the task of investigating conditions existing among recent immigrants in this country, with a view toward possible improvements and reforms in our immigration law.</p>
   <p>A few days ago, this committee ended its work and presented to Miss Perkins about eighty new recommendations, the more important of which are given below.</p>
   <p>The committee is of the opinion that, at the present time, when there are millions of unemployed in this country, there can be no talk of opening our doors to new immigrants from foreign countries, or of increasing our present immigration quota.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1282.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But, at the same time, the committee recommended that certain immigration regulations be changed. It suggested that our present immigration law should be changed so that it would not prevent the union of families, of husbands with wives, and of children with parents. At the present time, there are many cases where one member of a family, living in the United States, cannot be joined by other members living in a foreign country, because of the restrictions in our immigration law.</p>
   <p>The committee also favors the retention of the right of asylum for all refugees forced to leave their countries on account of religious, racial, or political persecution. In its recommendations, the committee mentions the fact that the right of asylum has been one of the oldest and most cherished of American traditions since the days of the first pilgrims, who left England because of religious persecution. It is understood, the committee added in its report, that such refugees should not take part in any activities directed against the social system existing in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1283.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Reporting on the question of deportation of immigrants who have violated the immigration law of this country, the committee recommends some necessary changes in the present immigration statute. In the opinion of this committee, the government agencies should concentrate their attention on the deportations of immigrant criminals and those who abuse American hospitality. Those who, in the future, illegally enter the United States should also be deported, the committee suggests.</p>
   <p>Those illegal entrants who have resided in this country for at least five years, who appear to be honest, and who have not committed any crime, should receive an opportunity to legalize their residence here, and even to become American citizens. This recommendation was made by the committee in view of the fact that many such persons, since their arrival, have established their homes and their families here and have maintained a good reputation, but who nevertheless face deportation for illegal entry. In cases of deportation, their wives and children become public charges.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1284.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The committee is also against the deportation of those persons who have lived here since childhood, but who have failed to obtain their citizenship papers; under the present law, such persons are liable to deportation as undesirable aliens.</p>
   <p>Thus it is seen that the committee has presented to the Secretary of Labor very important recommendations directed to softening and modifying the existing harsh immigration laws. It is impossible to predict whether, and to what extent, these recommendations may affect the proposed modification of the immigration law. But we can be certain that at least some of these recommendations will be enacted into law. There are now before the Congress several bills providing for "easing the pressure" on immigrants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
