<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title><date when="1923-11-26">Nov. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"Too Many Organizations."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0883</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0883.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title><date when="1923-11-26">Nov. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">"TOO MANY ORGANIZATIONS."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the section of our paper called "The Free Tribune" we publish a letter from Mr. Pavlov in which he complains about the excessively large number of Russian organizations which have cropped up in Chicago. He finds that many of these organizations are entirely unnecessary, "useless," and proposed that the readers of his article would express their opinion about this matter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pavlov is not the only one who raises this question. He is not alone to voice his discontent with the fact that "entirely too many organizations" have been formed in our midst. Our editorial staff gets many letters from our readers containing the same complaints.</p>
   <p>Like Mr. Pavlov the writers of these letters commit the mistakes of thinking that this large number of organizations is harmful for the common cultural <pb facs="5423967_4_0884.jpg" n="2"/>and educational work carried on in the colony, and that there exists many useless organizations.</p>
   <p>The great number of organizations does not interfere at all with this common work.</p>
   <p>Many persons wrongly believe that clubs which have the purpose of arranging evening entertainments, or opening classes of singing and music are useless. Such clubs are also necessary, and it is not right to call them "useless institutions."</p>
   <p>The trouble is not that there are so many organizations; it lies in this, that many of our organizations do not want to cooperate with each other. The trouble is that there is no consciousness of unity among the various organizations; they do not want to come closer to each other.</p>
   <p>Sometimes similar organizations, pursuing the same purpose, act quite <pb facs="5423967_4_0885.jpg" n="3"/>independently of each other, without taking each other into consideration at all, relying only on one's own forces, while it would have been much more efficient and expedient to combine the forces of several organizations.</p>
   <p>Very often also two organizations pursuing similar purposes are inimical to each other. Still more often it happens that there arises a very strange competition between two organizations: one of them tries to outdo the other in some kind of activity.</p>
   <p>In all such cases the force represented by such similar organizations is split; if they would work together they could achieve much better results; working separately they achieve very little.</p>
   <p>We could illustrate our statement by many examples. For example, why should not several organizations--especially if they are of a similar character--join hands in collecting money for those suffering from famine or for other <pb facs="5423967_4_0886.jpg" n="4"/>similar purposes? Why should not such societies arrange lectures or entertainment together? What could prevent them from uniting in order to organize by their concerted efforts a large library which could be used by the whole Russian colony? Why should they not combine in order to found some kind of common refuge--a place where members of all the Russian organizations could meet and where these organizations could arrange by their concerted efforts various entertainments?</p>
   <p>It is not the great number of organizations that does harm to the common work of Russian people; nor is it harmful that side by side with other organizations we have also organizations which are wrongly considered to be useless. What harms us is the fact that there is no feeling of unity among the various organizations, it is their enmity towards each other, the scattering of their efforts.</p>
   <p>We should welcome the arising of new organizations. But at the same time we should appeal to the colony for greater unification and cooperation. Only under such conditions will our work for the common cause be done successfully.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
