<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-08">Feb. 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Results of Bolshevik Recognition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-08">Feb. 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">RESULTS OF BOLSHEVIK RECOGNITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bolsheviks' hopes of receiving credits and loans from the United States have not been justified. It is generally known that the Bolsheviks expected to outsmart the Americans by their Jesuit politics. But after her experience in extending loans to European countries during the World War, the United States began to consider carefully each new application for money submitted by the Kremlin dictators.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the Republicans are engaged in a strong campaign aimed at breaking off diplomatic relations with the Bolsheviks altogether. Appropriations totaling one million dollars for erection of an embassy building in Moscow caused serious disagreements among Washington legislators. While it is not yet clear what the outcome of this controversy will be, it is possible that the money necessary for the building will be withheld because of the number opposed to such a step.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is important to notice that the Russian radicals in America stood for Bolshevik recognition. They assumed that, by recognition of the Bolshevik dictators, all the horrors of the Bolshevik recgime would be revealed to America. They reasoned that the doors of Bolshevism would be thrown open after recognition, and that Americans could thus see the abuses and outrages of Bolshevism with their own eyes.</p>
   <p>However, their expectations have not been justified. Bolsheviks still continue to carry on their destructive propaganda in America. Bolshevism in Russia still exists as before with all its previous outrages and abuses, such as shooting, exile, and concentration camps. The economic poverty continues to grow.</p>
   <p>The "gigantic" construction program of which Bolsheviks so frequently boast has not brought any improvement to the Russian people. Factory goods and food products do not belong to the producers; they are in the possession of Bolshevik idlers and bureaucrats. The Russian workers and peasants find <pb facs="5423967_4_1445.jpg" n="3"/>themselves in the position of slaves, and their voices are stifled by Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>The Bolshevik regime has been recognized by all of the great powers, but this has not improved the condition of the Russian people. Recognition of Bolshevism, by other powers, only emboldens its bloody dictatorship. If recognition served to weaken the Bolshevik regime and its stranglehold on the Russian people, the Bolshevik leaders would never strive for recognition by such fascist leaders as Hitler and Mussolini.</p>
   <p>By supporting certain aims set forth by Bolshevism it is impossible not to advance Bolshevik objectives in their entirety. Those who support Bolshevik recognition by America, or by other countries, pour water on the Bolshevik mill. If the fight against Bolshevism is to go on it should be waged on all fronts. The Bolshevik system should not be recognized because it is based on fraud, violence, hypocrisy and ruthless exploitation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
