<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. I. Shevchuk</title>, Russian Evangelical Preacher.
      <date when="1937">1937</date>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. I. Shevchuk</title>, Russian Evangelical Preacher.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I interviewed Rev. Shevchuk at his home, 2317 Cambridge Avenue, on June 9, 1937.</p>
   <p>The first question I asked Rev. Shevchuk was what was the origin of the Evangelical movement among the Russians in Chicago. Was it started by Russian preachers or by Americans? His answer was that the movement here in Chicago was a direct offspring of the Evangelical movement in Russia.</p>
   <p>In Russia the Evangelical Christian movement was started in the second half of the 19th century, when the English Evangelist, Lord Redstock, visited Russia. During his visit to St. Petersburg, he converted to his religious views several noted Russians, among them Ivan Stepanovich Prokhanov, who became the most prominent preacher of the Evangelical faith in Russia.</p>
   <p>Soon after the year 1900 there came to Chicago from Russia several <pb facs="5423967_4_1004.jpg" n="2"/>Evangelists who started to preach the Evangelical faith among the Chicago Russians. Among these Evangelits were Krotov, who was the first to spread this teaching; another was Kyusev, a Bulgarian. Krotov started to preach in 1909. In 1912 a community of Russian Evangelical Christians was organized in Chicago, and Kyusev was its first preacher. The young community had no chapel of its own and was renting quarters on Halsted near 17th Street.</p>
   <p>In the beginning the community numbered only 15 members, but it has been gradually growing, and at present there are 106 members and over 80 young people who are prospective members.</p>
   <p>The members were not quite satisfied with Kyusev's preaching as he could not speak Russian very well and held some views which were not quite in accord with the views of the other members. Because of these dissensions some persons left the community, but joined it again when Schubert, a young <pb facs="5423967_4_1005.jpg" n="3"/>Russian, took over the office of preacher. Schubert held this office from 1914 to 1917. His successor was Marusich, a Baptist. He preached only about one year and was succeeded by Yaroshevich who held the office of preacher till 1920. In that year came to Chicago Ivan Ivanovich Johnson (changed from a Russian name) who was born in Russian in a family of Evangelical Christians. He was invited to preach and held the office of preacher till 1928, when he left for New York.</p>
   <p>Rev. Johnson was succeeded by Rev. Shevchuk, who still holds the office of preachers.</p>
   <p>From the very beginning the Russian Evangelical community in Chicago has been assisted by the American Church of the Disciples of Christ, which holds religious views almost identical to those of the Russian Evangelical Christians. The preacher of the latter was partly supported by the Church of the Disciples. This church also bought in 1920 for the Russians a church situated at 2127 Crystal St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1006.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>However, this harmonious cooperation of Russians and Americans did not last long. Some dissensions arose in connection with the teaching of Russian children in the Sunday Bible classes: The Americans insisted that the teacher should be appointed by them, whereas the Russians wanted to have a teacher of their own, independent of the Church of the Disciples. Moreover, the Americans wanted to connect the Sunday classes for children with some "social work," i. e., with entertainments of various kinds: games, theatrical performances, etc. The Russian Evangelical Christians, being somewhat puritanical in their views, were against such innovations, which they considered to be out of harmony with the teachings of the Gospel.</p>
   <p>As a result of these dissensions, the Russians decided to become quite independent of the Church of the Disciples. They bought the church building at 2127 Crystal Street from the Americans for $13,000, out of which sum they have already paid in installments about $10,000. The preacher is supported at present only by the Russians.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1007.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The preacher is elected by the congregation. As most of the members of the church are workmen who earn little money, they are unable to pay to the preacher a fixed salary. The preacher gets sometimes about $40 a month, sometimes less; in exceptional cases even as little as $10. Under these the circumstances the preacher has to earn more money by doing some work. The present preacher, Rev. Shevchuk, owns the house in which he is living and gets a small income from renting out apartments.</p>
   <p>Most of the members of the community work at such trades as matress-making, distribution of milk for dairy companies, making of furniture, etc.</p>
   <p>In connection with the church there are bible study classes: for adults (in Russian) on Sundays; for children (in English) at the same time. The children and young people are subdivided into seven groups according to their ages. Each group is taught by different teachers. Some of these teachers are young Russians, members of the church, and some are American young people, students from the Moody Bible Institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1008.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The community does not publish at present any literature of its own in Russian. The Rev. Johnson published a Russian magazine in New York, and later in Chicago. Since Rev. Johnson went back to New York nothing has been published in Chicago. After the Rev. Johnson, Mr. Prokhanov edited the magazine.</p>
   <p>At present all the Russian literature of the Evangelical Christians is being published in Berlin, Germany. The Russian magazine is entitled Yevangelskaya Vyera (The Faith of the Gospel), and is being published by the General Russian Slavonic Union of Evangelical Christians. The editor is Rev. W. L. Jack. The address of the editorial office is: Redaktion Der Evangeliums Glaube, Eisackstr. 14, Berlin-Schoneberg, Germania.</p>
   <p>Dimitri Stranden, Translator.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
