<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Minutes in Possession of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization</title>, 1902 W. Division St., Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Minutes in Possession of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization</title>, 1902 W. Division St., Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A resolution concerning the necessity of international relief to Russian refugees in the Far East was passed on Aug. 25, 1937, at a meeting of leading Chicago Russian immigrants, and an appeal was made to the Government of the United States of America to take the initiative in this under taking.</p>
   <p>Resolution</p>
   <p>The assembly of American citizens of Russian descent, gathered on August 25th, 1937, on the premises of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization, 1902 W. Division tree. After accepting the greetings of the Right-Reverend Leonty, Bishop of Chicago and Minneapolis, who had expressed his complete sympathy with the purposes of the meeting and had begged Dr. L. G. Pertsov to transmit his greetings to those assembled; and after hearing the reports of the leaders of large social Russian-American organizations of the city of Chicago: I. F. Erin, N. S. Gribov, E. P. Kopernik and N. F. as well as the speech of former secretary of the Ministry of Marine of the Provisional Russian government, V. I. Lebedev, resolved to appeal by wire to the government of the United <pb facs="5423967_4_0444.jpg" n="2"/>States in the person of the Hon. Cordell Hull, secretary of State, to include into the lists of those being evacuated, the Russian women and children in the Far East; to issue visas for all those desiring to leave the Far East, and to start an international campaign in order to promote this cause.</p>
   <p>The assembly, instructed the specially a apointed temporary committee, to ask the cooperation of the Russian and American press and social American and Russian organizations.</p>
   <p>The assembly calls the attention of all Russian social organizations in America to the necessity of acting quickly and resolutely in this matter.</p>
   <p>The text of the appeal to the government of the United States, adopted by the meeting was as follows:</p>
   <p>Hon. Cordell Hull, Secretary of State,</p>
   <p>Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>Hon. Secretary of State:</p>
   <p>American citizens of Russian descent, as represented by leaders of large social Russian-American organizations of the city of Chicago, call your <pb facs="5423967_4_0445.jpg" n="3"/>attention to the terrible conditions in which Russian refugees and emigrants find themselves in the Far East, being deprived of any assistance or protection.</p>
   <p>The citizens assembled beg to request the government of the United States in your person to take the initiative of organizing relief on an international scale to these people, who desire to remain neutral in the China-Japaneese war.</p>
   <p>The citizens assembled for the occasion appeal to the government of the United States in your person to include the Russian women and children in the number of those being transferred to the Philippino Islands and other near-by points on the Pacific.</p>
   <p>They also request you for the permission to vize their passports for this purpose, particularly for those, who are deprived either of Russian or Chinese citizenship.</p>
   <p>The citizens assembled rest assured that the sympathizing United States will not remain deaf to the sufferings of innocent women and children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0446.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Accept, Mr. Secretary of State, the assurances of our perfect loyalty.</p>
   <p>Right Reverend Leonty, bishop of Chicago and Minneapolis; G. V. Voevodsky; A. U. Pikiel; Zinovia Leschuk; I. V. Osipik; I. V. Erin; N. S. Gribov; Dr. L. G. Pertsov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
