<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">How Should Our Orientation Be? by D. L. Orlovsky.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">HOW SHOULD OUR ORIENTATION BE? BY D. L. ORLOVSKY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our life in America is closely connected with our peasant brothers in Russia, or as they call it the Union of the Soviet Socialistic Republics. The link that binds us is our common peasant interests. Everything that is going on over there, good or bad, is deeply interesting to all of us, since we greeted in the past the revolution against tsarism and its military, clergy and civil opritchniks, (henchmen of the Tsar), and expected that with the victory of the revloution the three headed dragon would pass into the domain of history, and instead of it the covenant idea of freedom and equality will triumph. In the six years since that time and now the people of the former Russian Empire who suffered so much, have survived many revolutions and counter-revolutions. During that period of time we have heard and read many undescribable horrors about our country on one hand and many attractive things on the other. Some exaggerate and others lie. Who is to be believed. Who is right? Who is guilty of the horrible experiences of the weary people? One thing is clear; it is an axiom that he, who is strong, in power and a conqueror, is also right, because conquerors <pb facs="5423967_4_1616.jpg" n="2"/>are not judged, but misfortune is with temporary conquerors! There is hardly a more beautiful monent in the whole of human history than the Great February Revolution of 1917. Greatness without bloodshed, unspeakable joy of a world fond of liberty incarnated in those happy days; the high ideals of the best fighters for the liberation of millions of people, who are deprived of their rights from bondage. All the people of new Russia felt like brothers, were kissing each other, and were weeping from joy. The world war was a terrible inheritance of the Revolutionary Russia. While the new revolutionary government was clearing up the inherited tsaristic horrors, international was and chaos--the bolsheviks--took advantage of the revolutionary freedom and confusion, and skillfully using all kind of pass-words, suggested to the army they leave the lines and enjoy the hard-won liberty, etc. The results, were the disbandment of the Revolutionary Constituent Assembly with the aid of bayonets, the bolshevistic regime, the Brest-Litovsk farce or the concluding of peace, the horrible Chrezvichayka, the general exile and destroying of the people and intellectuals, whose ideas were opposed to the ideas of the bolsheviks; idiotic money experiments, the resolute <pb facs="5423967_4_1617.jpg" n="3"/>abolition of the freedom of press, speech and meeting. Exciting the criminal civil war, which if not for the Ukrainian Atuman, Machno, would have signalized the restoration of Tsarism in Russia, the most horrible famine in the history of the human race exile to Siberia and the far Siberian swamps, executions of upright revolutionaries who gave away everything for the fight for the liberty of the people, and many other traps, which were arranged by the bolshevistic powers against the will of the great majority of the whole population. This are the indisputable merits of the bolshevistic or the communistic powers.</p>
   <p>There was a time when, if we could not agree, at least we could reconcile ourselves to supporting the Soviet regime during the monarchial counterrevolutionary period of Kolchak, Dienikin, Yudenich and Wrangel. 'Help us to defeat the tsarist generals who are attempting to reestablish the Tsar', cried the bolshevistic leaders,'and we will begin to live again a free brotherly life'. The bolsheviks at that time had not yet succeeded in showing their teeth to the people and the people, preferring the lesser <pb facs="5423967_4_1618.jpg" n="4"/>evil, absolutely destroyed all the counter-revolutionary plots of the tsaristic generals.</p>
   <p>The bolsheviks triumphed and forgot about the people, in the same manner as the Russian Tsars in the past. The communistic clique had felt themselves to be the masters of the situation. The salt of Russian and Ukrainian soil--the peasants were plundered, worn out, in a very unscrupulous manner deceived and deprived even of the sacred right to decide their own affairs; they were almost deprived of the right to vote. And all for the sake of a few unwanted newly arrived rulers. One should be insane to believe in the good intentions and soundness of the bolshevistic powers.</p>
   <p>Russia moaned three hundred years under the Tartar yoke. But what a comparison; the Mongols at least did not pretend to be liberators; they did not lie. The bolsheviks had, seemingly, given to all nationalities, national freedom on the basis of the Union of the Republics, but from Moscow was sent a decree 'to hold and not let it go'. The red army and its commanders are trembling for their life, silently and dejectedly are obeying the orders <pb facs="5423967_4_1619.jpg" n="5"/>from the Kremlin. But, will that be always the way?. The iron discipline! Where is the secret of power? Is there even one family in Bolshevist territory which did not suffer, or did not lose some of their relatives as victims of the bolshevistic fury? Who, if not the bolsheviks, are exciting the anger of the people toward themselves, driving the people to despair and into a state of submission even to the monarchical regime which is emerging again in Russia? We should not protest against the recognition of the Soviet power by other countries, as we did not demand in the past the cessation of relations with the tsartic power by other countries. On the contrary, relations with the outside world together with a certain pressure exercised by the love of liberty, can either bring the bolsheviks to their senses, or else against their will they will have to face the same fate which befell the Tsarist regime of blessed memory.</p>
   <p>By some means or other we must wait the cessation of the inquisition of the people and our native country. It is impossible to stand it any more and be silent. The cup of patience is too over-filled. We peasants, <pb facs="5423967_4_1620.jpg" n="6"/>more than the rest, perished under the pressure of one tyrant for another. We must make them feel that we are a class which gives all and gets nothing but insults, oppression and jests.</p>
   <p>We, who demand land, enlightenment and liberty peasants, but we are peasants of the past. We are persons, able to sacrifice, to fight and do everything, but do not force upon us your services with your bayonets. We have among us teachers, artists, actors, physicians and professors, and if that is not sufficient, then we are ready to invite more, not as leaders and dictators, but as hired workers.</p>
   <p>And realize, that we are strange to your desires and attempts to abuse anything or anyone. We must live humanely and once and for all erase the injustice done to us. Out of the way! The peasant, who broke the chains of slavery is coming! Our way as peasants is to earn our place as free human beings in our country. Our native country, entangled by the bolsheviks, is praying for mercy; it is waiting for the moment when it will be able to say to the newconers, the enslavers: Hands off!</p>
   <p>D. D. Orlovsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
