<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-20">July 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Students in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-07-20">July 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN STUDENTS IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the coming month of May, one year will have elapsed since the preliminary work of organizing and uniting the Russian students of the Chicago colleges.</p>
   <p>The first work of this kind had been done successfully with the assistance of Mr. Bowers, the secretary of the YMCA, by the Russian student S. A. P. who came to Chicago from the West.</p>
   <p>In August and September, 1924, four other Russian students joined the initial group of organizers. Together they formed an initiatory group and with the assistance of several Russian professors, organized the National Russian Christian Students' Society in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The by-laws of this society were carefully elaborated after the pattern of the Russian students' organizations of America, Europe and China.</p>
   <p>The object of the Students' Society is to provide Russian students with <pb facs="5423967_4_0978.jpg" n="2"/>means to complete their college education, to create a fund which would enable the Russian students to receive a higher education with as little suffering as possible and to provide mutual aid and mutual moral support; also prepare for Russia of the future, valuable workers and specialists who love their country.</p>
   <p>The first board of the Students' Society had difficult work to do. The society tried its strength, and proved that its members were efficient workers. In all justice, it must be said that during the eight months of its existence, it has done considerable inner work and has achieved a successful debut on the arena of Chicago life.</p>
   <p>The chorus and the band of balalaika players organized by the students have made several successful appearances on the stage. The most prominent and clamorous success was achieved on the occasion of two private entertainments given at the apartments of local American millionaires. Very successful also, was the performance at the Casino, where the orchestra and the chorus were invited to play and sing for a remuneration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0979.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In June, we witnessed a clamorous and well-deserved ovation to the students' balalaika orchestra, at the Trianon Ballroom.</p>
   <p>During the same period of time, about 35 evening entertainments were given on Saturdays and Sundays; also two popular lectures by Professor Yusefovich and Professor Braghin. A picnic with the participation of the chorus and orchestra has been arranged.</p>
   <p>At first, the society does not produce the impression of a "well-spring," but the well-spring is there right in the center, in the Board of Directors. During the short period of eight months, and under unfavorable conditions, the members of the board must be at the university in the daytime and then work during the night to solve a very difficult problem. The results have been good.</p>
   <p>There are 42 full fledged members in the society, and about 100 persons who <pb facs="5423967_4_0980.jpg" n="4"/>are in sympathy with it. Everybody did his share during the first year when the society was being organized. The young leaders are slowly but firmly leading the society in the path of progress.</p>
   <p>Every week the membership is increasing. From time to time some new student emerges or is dug up, another, a third, and they join the common family of Russian students.</p>
   <p>It is evident that this healthy group of young college students will speedily grow stronger, will stand firmly on its feet, and will help many of its members to join the family of American students.</p>
   <p>A Student from Kiev.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
