<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-30">Aug. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Foundations of the All-Russian Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0953</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0953.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-30">Aug. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOUNDATIONS OF THE ALL-RUSSIAN CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As every man has a right to live, so has every Russian a right, and duty even, to express his thoughts about the proposed all-Russian convention. We have had many conventions before. We had class conventions, church conventions, party conventions, district conventions, union conventions, and mutual aid conventions. But we have had no all-Russian, national convention. We need such a convention at this moment; it may enable us to fulfill our moral duty to crucified Russia.</p>
   <p>I fully agree with the statement printed in this newspaper that there are ten fundamental questions to be decided by the forthcoming convention. If we are to realize such questions as appealing to the entire world, and are to ask the United States Government and the League of Nations for intervention, we should plan the work on a nationalistic basis. Even our internationalists announced in issue thirty-three of Novyi Mir [the Russian Communist <pb facs="5423967_4_0954.jpg" n="2"/>newspaper] that they had sent a resolution, in the name of the Russian National Mutual Aid Society, to President Roosevelt and to Governor Miller of Alabama, in connection with the Scottsboro case.</p>
   <p>How sad and painful it is that an intelligent Russian like A. G. Alexuff looks upon the future convention from the point of view of a class struggle. How much longer will the Russians continue this class struggle? For sixteen years now the Bolsheviks have been conducting the class war in Russia. At the beginning we celebrated this war, thinking it was in the interest of the Russian people. But when they started to destroy the Russian peasantry, the economic foundation of the country, we began to think. But many of us awoke only when these international sharks had brought the country to general famine, to epidemic diseases and to cannibalism.</p>
   <p>These long rows of maytyrs of our homeland should quicken every Russian heart <pb facs="5423967_4_0955.jpg" n="3"/>in foreign lands, and should bring to understanding all adherents of the class war. The beastly experimentations of the Bolsheviks force us to organize on a national basis and to stop all class struggle. However, we should not mix our Russian nationalism with fascism. Fascism represents a political party, and Russia does not need more party dictatorships. Russia is waiting for the awakening of our all-Russian consciousness, our unity, and the day when all strata of our society--peasants, workers, artisans, doctors and editors, priests and teachers--will find a common language and understanding in the proposition of aiding the people of Russia, dying of hunger, and of bringing about the resurrection of Russia.</p>
   <p>The Russian colony in America has already seen through the Bolshevik lies. All Russian people living abroad want to be organized on a national basis, but the leaders are still delaying the action by lack of activity in the right direction. One faction wants the return of the Czar to Russia; another wants the dictator; and still another wants to continue the class war in Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0956.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>By reading many answers to the articles written by Mr. Kondratieff it can be seen that all Russians are proud of their nationality, and everyone is filled with sacrificial love for their country and its people. Therefore, my friends, express your opinion as to what kind of convention we need and what we should do.</p>
   <p>It is true that there have been dunces and blockheads who helped to change the word "Russia" to the letters "U.S.S.R." With the help of our own hands they now annihilate not only the well-to-do class, but all that is national. Try to offend the national feeling of the Gorman, or the Frenchman, or the Pole, and you will see how he will rise in defense of his national honor. But with us, if somebody spits into the depths of our soul or wounds us to the quick, we won't even rise to make any objection.</p>
   <p>It is possible that Mr. Kondratieff, by writing his sharp criticisms of the <pb facs="5423967_4_0957.jpg" n="5"/>Russian colony, wants to find out whether we shall be able to stand our ground in the future, and whether we can be reborn and strengthened in our national spirit as a great nation with a great culture.</p>
   <p>Welcome the national convention of all Russian people in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
