<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Dr. J. D. Hassin</title>, 30 N. Michigan Avenue, Chairman of the Chicago Council, Soviet Russia Medical Relief Committee (now extinct)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Dr. J. D. Hassin</title>, 30 N. Michigan Avenue, Chairman of the Chicago Council, Soviet Russia Medical Relief Committee (now extinct)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the turbulent years of 1920 and 1921, an organization on Soviet Russia Medical Relief was organized in Chicago under the chairmanship of Dr. J. B. Hassin. The purposes of that organization, according to Dr. Hassin, were medical relief for the suffering Russians.</p>
   <p>Medicines, physicians supplies, dental supplies, books, and clothing were sent from Chicago,as well as other places in America, to Soviet Russia.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. B. Hassin stated that in 1921 an epidemic of malaria and typhus was taking hold among the natives of Soviet Russia, and lacking in medical supplies they appealed to their brothers living in America for help in combating these diseases.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0451.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Doctor Hassin states also that many branches in their committee were established, and active work and help extended through the following sub-committees: hospital and drug supplies, serological products, sanatorium supplies, surgical instruments, dental supplies, etc. A microscope was also provided for Professor Lindberg, who is at present a professor of medicine in the University of Smolensk.</p>
   <p>Although the material resources of the above organization were limited, they sent a thousand dollars' worth of quinine to fight the typhus and malaria.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. B. Hassin, a graduate of the University of Kazan (class of 1897), practiced medicine in the city of Yeniseisk, Siberia, from 1897 to 1901. From there he left for Vienna and Berlin for further study in his chosen profession. In 1902 he left for America and in September of the same year he settled in Chicago, where he has been residing ever since.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0452.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1918 he was enlisted by the Johns Hopkins University as a medical officer with the American Expeditionary Forces in Siberia.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hassin is a well known medical authority in the city of Chicago, and takes and active part in the affairs of the Russian colony of that city. His offices are located at 30 N. Michigan Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
