<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. G. L. Percy, 2557 W. Division St.</title>
      <title level="a">Aims and Purposes of the Society 'Russian Center'</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. G. L. Percy, 2557 W. Division St.</title>
     <title level="a">AIMS AND PURPOSES OF THE SOCIETY 'RUSSIAN CENTER'</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the secretary of the society 'Russian Center' is getting many inquiries about the aims of this organization, we give below some extracts from the constitution of this society, which was accepted at the organizing meeting of the Russian Center in Chicago, held on April 3, 1925, at the House of Enlightenment, 1080 W. 14th Street.</p>
   <p>Clause 1. The Russian Center of the city of Chicago has for its aim the unification of all Russians of the city of Chicago without distinction of their political sympathies.</p>
   <p>The following things belong to the circle of activities of the center:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0238.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(a) Active cultural and educational work among the wide masses of the Russian colony of the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>(b) The organization of an employment bureau, of an information and legal section and of a mutual credit association for the relief of needy full fledged members of the society.</p>
   <p>(c) An intimate contact in its activities with those Russian-American organizations which pursue aims identical with those of this society.</p>
   <p>Clause 2. The Russian Center, being a non-political organization, decidedly excludes any politics, and does not pursue in this respect any aims having to do either with Russia, or with the United States, or with any other country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0239.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Clause 4. Any person who wants to become a member of the Center presents an application to the committee with a recommendation of one of the members of the society (such application can also be made verbally).</p>
   <p>The candidate is considered to be elected if he gets a simple majority of votes of the general assembly.</p>
   <p>Clause 8. The monthly dues are 50 cents for men, and 25 cents for women. The initiation fee is $1. The fees and dues have to be paid in advance.</p>
   <p>Complete information about the Russian Center can be had from the secretary of the Center, either by calling on him or through the mail. Address: Russian Center 2001 W. Division St., Telephones: Brunswick 3399, Armitage 5801.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
