<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-06">Mar. 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">"Letter of Comrade Maxim Gorky"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Mark Stepnoy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet, (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-06">Mar. 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">"LETTER OF COMRADE MAXIM GORKY"</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Mark Stepnoy</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The executive committee of Rnov (Russian Mutual Aid Society) has published a handbill entitled "Letter of Comrade Maxim Gorky to the Chicago Anti-Military Congress". One of these handbills is before me now. In it Maxim Gorky, among other things, writes:</p>
   <p>"Capitalists of Europe, America and Japan are preparing very assiduously for a new world war. This means that new millions of workers and peasants will be annihilated, millions of tons of metal will be used for the destruction of millions of people, and hundreds of prosperous and peaceful cities will be destroyed. Executors of the criminal capitalist will, the leaders of fascism, affirm their belief that centuries of warfare will accompany the future history of nations. This affirmation hardly expresses a sincere sentiment or conviction, for, as we well know, it is prompted by the lackeys' habit of adopting even the bosses' villainy."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1408.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That which was stated by Gorky regarding the capitalists is equally true of the Bolsheviks. Of course, Gorky, while remaining a faithful servant to his masters, does not mention the Bolshevik crimes, of which there are many; these have been legalized by government decrees and official proclamations.</p>
   <p>Millions of men under the Bolshevik regime are working for the benefit of a few thousand high Bolshevik dignitaries and thousands of functionaries who are running the government, industry, and trade. The working people of the U. S. S. R. work for the enrichment of a coterie of Soviet bureaucrats, to help them strengthen their rule over the Russian people, for their amusement. The working people in the U. S. S. R., just as in the capitalist countries, are deprived of most of that which they produce.</p>
   <p>Gorky writes about the accomplishments of the "Socialist State," which has,as its ultimate aim, "the liberation of the working class throughout the world." What hypocrisy! Are the workers of Russia free? Do they enjoy the civil liberties of a free press, free assembly, unrestricted movement, etc.?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
