<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-11-19">Nov. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Organizing a Russian United Relief Committee in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-11-19">Nov. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZING A RUSSIAN UNITED RELIEF COMMITTEE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, November 15, on the initiative of the Russian American Citizens' Club, a meeting of the representatives of all Russian organization in Chicago and vicinity was called for the purpose of creating a Russian United Relief Committee in Chicago,</p>
   <p>In spite of the haste with which the meeting was called ( invitations were sent only three days in advance) the meeting was attended by representatives of seven Russian organizations.</p>
   <p>There were represented: the Russian-American Citizens' Club with a delegation of five persons who were at the same time the organization committee; The Independent Mutual Aid Society, with four representatives; the "Knowledge" Society, with two delegates; the Union of Russian Officers, with two delegates; The Russian Children's School of Gary, Ind., with two delegates; the Transfiguration Society, with one delegate; and the "Sadko" Club, with one delegate. Organizations, such as the Holy Trinity Brotherhood on Leavitt St. and others, informed the Committee that they were busy organizing <pb facs="5423967_4_0340.jpg" n="2"/>benefit entertainments and were unable to send their delegates to this meeting. However, they were entirely in accord with the idea to create a Committee. They promised to send delegates to the next meeting and join in the Committee's efforts. It showed that the appeal to the colony to create immediately a Russian Relief Committee met with a hearty response on the part of the Russian immigrants, and this makes us hope for a bright future.</p>
   <p>Delegates were instructed by their organizations to restrict their activity only to matters pertaining to relief work. The delegates first listened to a report of the organization Committee, and after that to the report of the State Committee which had given relief to the needy, had worked out a program of activity for the future, and had elected a provisional committee of five for preparatory work and for convening the next meeting. The delegates decided to restrict the work of the United Committee strictly to the relief of the needy and unemployed.</p>
   <p>The provisional Committee was instructed to make one more appeal to the Russian colony to send delegates to the Committee and to work out a detailed plan for the United Committee. The meeting lasted four hours and was very successful. All participants at the meeting seriously considered the problem <pb facs="5423967_4_0341.jpg" n="3"/>of relief, except two representatives from one radical organization who all through the meeting strove to divert attention of the delegates from the matters of relief to those of politics.</p>
   <p>After the meeting the provisional committee was offered services for collecting money, food and clothes for the needy. One of the clubs furnished its own hall and musical talent free of charge for a concert program for the benefit of the needy, and recommended donations of provisions for the refreshments. All this to be arranged by this Club under control of the Relief Committee, the entire proceeds to be used for the benefit of those in need. One of the delegates offered to donate goods worth several thousand dollars for the relief of needy Russians.</p>
   <p>The Committee was organized so as to act on two fronts: 1) to work in cooperation with the State Committee in order to get from the latter relief for the Russian unemployed, as is done by other nationalities, and 2) to work independently among the Russians and all contributions to be distributed directly among the Russian unemployed.</p>
   <p>Thus the first meeting gave extremely good results. It laid down a good <pb facs="5423967_4_0342.jpg" n="4"/>basis for future work.</p>
   <p>I like to believe that in these hard times the Russians shall live up to the sacred principle: "All for one and one for all." It is necessary to achieve a close union on the field of mutual aid and by united efforts to help those Russians who suffer from unemployment.</p>
   <p>The conference was attended by the representatives of the Russian press.</p>
   <p>J. F. Erin</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
