<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Antsiferov, V. <title level="a">"Znanie Society"</title>, <title>Moskva</title>,
<date when="1929-12">Dec. 1929</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Antsiferov, V. <title level="a">"Znanie Society"</title>, <title>Moskva (Monthly)</title>,
<date when="1929-12">Dec. 1929</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Znanie" Society (50th Branch of the Russian Amalgamated Society for Mutual Aid in America) was founded in the fall of the year 1928, and it has succeeded, over a period of more than a year, to accomplish great creative work. At the present moment, this is without exaggeration, the most spirited and combating organization in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is impossible to present in a few short statements (the editorial staff, to our regret, allows so little space in the "colony" section.) an adequate statement of the genuinely great cultural work, which has been accomplished by this small organization, in such a short period of time.</p>
   <p>I will mention, while it is still fresh in my memory, the staging of the play "Days' of our Life," by L. Andreev, presented in December of this year, by the artists of the "Petrushka" club; and the first concert of the recently organized choir of the "Znanie" Society which took place on December 7, 1929.</p>
   <p>According to the statements of the local press and in the opinion of the public, the presentation of "Days of our Life" in Chicago was a great success and <pb facs="5423967_4_0036.jpg" n="2"/>the concert given by the choir was a real treat.</p>
   <p>Our talented V. V. Shumkov, the director of the choir in close cooperation with the singers and leaders, succeeded in attracting to the performance the "flower of the colony." In fact there was not enough room to accommodate the patrons.</p>
   <p>There are not enough words to express my admiration for the great progress made, in a short time, by the string orchestra (which participated in the concert) under the able leadership of Al. W. Meyerson (a professional engineer and at the same time a musician, artist, actor and lecturer) who with a small number of musicians,succeeded in creating a fine orchestra.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
