<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. Lobanov</title>, Holy Trinity Cathedral,
<date when="1937-04-30">Apr. 30, 1937</date><title level="a">Biography</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dimitri Strandon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. Lobanov</title>, Holy Trinity Cathedral,
<date when="1937-04-30">Apr. 30, 1937</date><title level="a">BIOGRAPHY</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dimitri Strandon</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alexander Vasilievich Lobanov was born in October, 1835, in Moscow. His father was an official of one of the departments of the state administration; his mother was the daughter of a priest. He received his education first in a theological seminary, and later in a military school in Hazan, from which he graduated with the grade of lieutenant. He served in the army before the revolution and was promoted to the rank of captain.</p>
   <p>He went to France with the Russian troops which were sent there during the World War. In 1919 he left for the Siberian front and served there under admiral Kolchak. When <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> army was defeated, he went east to Harbin.</p>
   <p>In 1923 he left for America and came to Seattle, and thence to Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1646.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Chicago he has been employed successively by the Western Electric Company, by the International Karvester Company, by the Crane Company and by the Y. M. C. A.</p>
   <p>As Mr. Lobanov used to attend regularly the services of the Russian Holy Trinity Cathedral he became acquainted with the then bishop Theophilus who, having learned that Mr. Lobanov had made his studies in a theological seminary, advised him to apply for a deacon's office in one of the Russian churches.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lobanov was ordained in 1927 and held for some time the office of second deacon. In 1930 he was appointed regular deacon of the Troitsky Cathedral and at the same time promoted to the rank of archdeacon. "protodiakon).</p>
   <p>Rev. Lobanov has been also teaching in 192<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and 1929 in two Russian schools; in the Douglas Park School and in the Fullerton Street School.</p>
   <p>Since 1932 he has held the office of secretary of the council of the diocese of Chicago, and since 1934, than of secretary of the Society for the Relief to the Children of Russian Immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1647.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is a collaborator of the Chicago Russian daily Rassviet, of the Chicago weekly Russkoye Obozreniye (Russian Review), of the newspaper Rossiya, (Russia), published in New York; and of the newspaper Sviet (Light), published in Wilkesbarre. He has been contributing to these publications articles on public life and on Christian apologetics.</p>
   <p>D. Strandon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
