<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-01">July 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal for Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-01">July 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL FOR AID</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several days ago, I was released from the Federal penitentiary in Leavenworth, Kansas, where I spent twelve years. For what crime? Homicide, robbery, rape? No. During the World War, I fought as an American soldier in France and in Belgium. I had not volunteered for the army. I had been drafted when I lived in the state of Michigan. I was sent to France against my will. When the war ended on the western front and the Versailles Treaty was signed, the government of the late President Wilson sent an armed expedition consisting of twenty-five thousand men to Siberia to fight the Bolsheviks. I was in that expedition.</p>
   <p>While still in France, our regiment and several others with a large number of foreign-born soldiers received one morning an order to be ready for a long journey. We thought we were going back to America. Instead, we were sent first to Vladivostok and then to Archangel to fight the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0302.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Because I was a Russian, and because of my general conceptions and principles, and also out of respect for my personal honor and my conscience, I could not kill my own people, especially at the time of the revolution when they were fighting for their liberty. Besides, I loved my people, and will continue to love them as long as I live.</p>
   <p>I refused to fight and thus committed a military crime. I was courtmartialed by the military court of the American General Staff and sentenced for sixteen years to the Federal penitentiary in Leavenworth. I was released after spending over twelve years in prison.</p>
   <p>In 1931 and 1932, I appealed for aid to the International Labor Defense Society in New York. Knowing that this "humanitarian organization" (on paper only) collects tens of thousands of dollars annually for the defense of military and political prisoners, I hoped to receive a few dollars for <pb facs="5423967_4_0303.jpg" n="3"/>tobacco and cigarettes. But the "comrades" from the International Labor Defense sent me a reply stating that theirs is a "purely political activity" and that all their money had been spent on the Scottsboro case so conspicuosly publicized over the entire country, and which, by the way, was not a political but a common crimminal case.</p>
   <p>My present need is for material or financial assistance. I left my military prison a week ago almost without a penny. On leaving the penitentiary, I received a suit of cheap clothes, a railroad ticket to Chicago, and five dollars in cash, all a government dole. I have already spent the five dollars, and now I do not know where my next meal will come from.</p>
   <p>I have been promised work in a tailor shop in New York City. The prison warden refused to issue a railroad ticket to New York. The bus fare from Chicago to New York costs ten dollars. I haven't got the money to pay <pb facs="5423967_4_0304.jpg" n="4"/>for the trip.</p>
   <p>Through the courtesy of Rassviet, I appeal to all good people of Chicago, to all Russian workers, and to Russian organizations, to collect a few dollars by small contributions and thus enable me to get to New York, where a job is awaiting me at the Rogers Peet Men's Clothing Company. I do not want to appeal again for aid to the International Labor Defense Society. This organization collects huge sums of money from poor workers, but the money is usually spent on things having nothing in common with the primary aims of this organization as they are presented to the general public.</p>
   <p>Russian people of Chicago, I stretch out my hands to you and ask you to help me. I have explained to you my prolonged suffering and my present difficult situation. Help me with whatever little you can. I promise you I will return everything as soon as I get back on my feet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0305.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Alex Sazonoff,</p>
   <p>c/o Rassviet,</p>
   <p>1722 West Chicago Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
