<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-24">March 24, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Russian People's Independent Society</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-03-24">March 24, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE RUSSIAN PEOPLE'S INDEPENDENT SOCIETY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first session of the Russian People's Independent Society took place last Sunday at the quarters of the People's Independent School, 917 N. Wood Street.</p>
   <p>The session was called to order by the president of the society, Vladimir Sabinsky.</p>
   <p>First of all a roll call of all the delegates was taken; after that the report for the six months from July 1, 1925, to December 31, 1925, was read.</p>
   <p>As no one of the delegates had any remarks to make about the report <pb facs="5423967_4_0086.jpg" n="2"/>the state of the treasury was declared to be entirely satisfactory.</p>
   <p>In connection with this the committee on audit declared that the books of the society were in good order.</p>
   <p>Next the election of the chairman pro tem. of the convention took place. The following persons were nominated. Alexander Pasuk, Ivan Dzidz, A. Sinkevich. A Pasuk got 24 votes, Ivan Dzidz, 21 votes, and A. Sinkevich, 3 votes.</p>
   <p>Alexander Pasuk, who had got the majority of votes, remained chairman of the convention; Ivan Dzidz was elected vice-chairman.</p>
   <p>Maria Karsh and Dmitri Vorobey were nominated candidates for the office of secretary. Maria Korsh got 28 votes, D. Vorbey, 16.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0087.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Maria Korsh remained ... secretary of the convention; Dmitri Vorobey became the assistant secretary.</p>
   <p>Alexander Pasuk, chairman pro tem, and Maria Korsh, secretary pro tem, occupied the places reserved for them.</p>
   <p>Maria Korsh read the minutes of the last convention, and all the delegates unanimously approved these minutes.</p>
   <p>The next item of the order of the business was the election of the committee for the next year.</p>
   <p>The former president of the society, Vladimir Sabinsky, was re-elected for the next year; his assistant, Nikifor Shlyapa, was also re-elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0088.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The former secretary, Yakov Dzayko, and his assistant, Ivan Kulik, were also re-elected.</p>
   <p>The former treasurer, Alexander Pasuk, and his assistant, Semyon Yakimovich, were re-elected.</p>
   <p>Nikolai Kucherepa was elected member of the trust. The following persons were elected members of the Supreme Committee: Vladimir Dedovich, Teodor Ustich, Mark Goroshchenya.</p>
   <p>The following were elected members of the committee on audit: Ivan Dzidz, Teodor Kaze, Josif Sleznik, Adam Breghin, Stefan Timoshuk, Pavel Kovalevich, Vasiley Grimechuk.</p>
   <p>Juvenile Department. - Teodor Ustich remains senior agent for the insurance of children. Daniel Breghin is appointed agent for the South Side; Faddey Grisevich, for Argo, and Semyon Fedorovsky, for the <pb facs="5423967_4_0089.jpg" n="5"/>Krestitelsky Brotherhood.</p>
   <p>The question concerning the member of the society, Ivan Putilov, who had been sick for a long time, was raised.</p>
   <p>The delegates to the convention decided to donate $100 from the treasury of the society for the relief of this member and his family.</p>
   <p>The date of the second session of the convention will be announced in the newspaper Russkii Viestnik.</p>
   <p>The Secretary of the Convention.</p>
   <p>Maria Korsh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
