<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. I, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">Izvestiya of the Society for Aid to Political Exiles and Prisoners in Russia</title> No. 2, Chicago, Illinois,
<date when="1916-07">July 1916</date>.
<title level="a" type="sub">To the Readers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. I, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">IZVESTIYA OF THE SOCIETY FOR AID TO POLITICAL EXILES AND PRISONERS IN RUSSIA</title> No. 2, Chicago, Illinois,
<date when="1916-07">July 1916</date>.
<title level="a" type="sub">To THE READERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are again compelled to call upon you not to forget our society, the aim of which is to aid the victims of the Russian revolution.</p>
   <p>Despite the bloody war that the tsarist government had to carry on on several fronts, and regardless of all the misery and destruction that the war brought to Russia, the government does not remove its attention for one moment from its old enemies, the revolutionists, and a struggle with them is carried on as of old.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As of old, chains of revolutionists are clanking; as of old, the prisons are overflowing; as of old, culprits are herded and exiled into isolated corners of Siberia, and last but not least, the political trials in Russia do not cease.</p>
   <p>As of old, the prison wardens, the judges and executors of order are hard at work. Everything is influenced by the war; all are involved in the war, but the war has not diverted the attention of the Russian government from the fighters for freedom, from the fighters for the future of our fatherland.</p>
   <p>The newspapers that are sent from Russia are painting a very sad picture of our comrades in the far off fatherland.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the prices on edibles are mounting; there is a real scarcity of living quarters and the necessaries of life. The prisoners and exiled are in dire need as never before.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0429.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>You, comrades, who have escaped the persecutions of the Russian government; you who are far away from the hell of European war should undertake to aid the persecuted.</p>
   <p>All those who are bound by spiritual ties to their fatherland; all those in whom the principles for which we have struggled are not extinguished should answer the call of our society.</p>
   <p>Join our society, bring in your friends.</p>
   <p>Do not neglect any work. The payment of membership dues will buy food for the hungry. A word of encouragement for those within the prison walls is a new source of energy for the struggle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
