<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-03-09">March 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the White Russians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0684</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0684.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-03-09">March 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE WHITE RUSSIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, March the 6th, a large meeting of White Russians took place and answered to the call of the White Russian National Union of the state of Illinois to protest against the violence committed against the White Russians on the borders of Poland and the western part of the White Russian territory. At the meeting the following persons made speeches explaining the events in their native land: Mr. I. M. Romanovich, a member of the committee of the White Russian National Union; Mr. Anton Zmagar; the leader of the meeting, Mr. J. Voronko, and a representative of the Ukrainians, Dr. Smuck.</p>
   <p>The audience listened to the orators with great attention and with expressions of consent. At the end of the meeting the following resolution of the White Russian National Union was accepted unanimously:</p>
   <p>"The White Russian residents of Chicago and suburbs, who have attended <pb facs="5423967_4_0685.jpg" n="2"/>a meeting called by the White Russian National Union of the state of Illinois, and listened to the last events in the western part of White Russia, - the arrests of Rak-Michailovsky, Tarashkevich, Voloshin, Melty and Golovach, deputies of the Seim (diet); the destroying of the White Russian educational and economic organizations; the revolting acts of violence against the White Russian population, which were systematically committed by the Polish government, - decided to protest emphatically: (1) Against the evil infraction by the Polish government of their obligation, concerning the rights of the national minorities of Poland, which was signed in Versailles in the year of 1919; (2) Against the continual persecution of White Russians in Poland; (3) Against the undeserved arrests of White Russian deputies of the Polish Seim; (4) Against the arrests of hundreds of White Russian workers. The White Russian of the city of Chicago and suburbs appeal to the American democratic people, which was first to raise his voice for the restoration of the Polish republic. We <pb facs="5423967_4_0686.jpg" n="3"/>mean the well known proclamation of the President W. Wilson. We make an ardent appeal to the people of the United States to use their influence and help to free the White Russian population from the Polish yoke. The committee of the White Russian National Union: I. Voronko, A. Zmagar, I. Rudionok, I. Romanovich, L. Anton, V. Trofimovich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
