<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Problems of the American Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">PROBLEMS OF THE AMERICAN SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The most effective method of creating the spirit of unity in this country is not by suppressing the national minorities, but by instilling in the new citizens a sense of cultural self-respect," James Marshall, who recently was appointed member of the New York School Committee, declared the other day.</p>
   <p>In his speech, delivered before the Association of Adult Education, Mr. Marshall stated that, in his opinion, one of the chief tasks of the American schools is to fight the prejudices and antagonisms of the old American generations directed against the newcomers to this country.</p>
   <p>"The schools," said he, "must constantly stress the point that we are all immigrants, even the Sons and Daughters of the American Revolution. In this connection it is also important to point out not only the great services rendered <pb facs="5423967_4_0503.jpg" n="2"/>to this country by such individuals as Carl Schurz or Michael Pupin, but the contributions to the well-being of the country made by the immigrant mass. Several thousands of English settlers sacrificed their lives during the period of the American Revolution in order to free this country from the control of kings and aristocracy. Of course we must respect and esteem those who fought and died during that period of American history. But how about the tens of thousands of people who often are given the abusive epithets of 'Greaser,' 'Polak,' etc. These people are those who sacrifice their lives in mines, in building railroads across the continent, in digging tunnels under rivers, in toil on cotton plantations, in building skyscrapers. Without them, to be sure, without waves of immigrants, not only from Northern, but from Southern and Eastern Europe, from Africa, from Central and South America, the major part of our country still would remain a wilderness. Acquaint each national group with the achievements of other national groups in this country. Let our schools show our country as a kaleidoscope of races, religions and cultures."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0504.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Familiarity with the parents' language is a powerful weapon for raising the cultural level among the second generation, Mr. Marshall declared.</p>
   <p>"I wish," said he, "that our schools might stimulate interest in German, Italian, Russian, Spanish, Jewish, Polish and other cultures represented in our population by various racial and national groups. In our schools we teach the German, French, Italian, and Spanish languages. In two or three schools we teach even Hebrew. Languages of other peoples also should be included in the programs of our high schools, and their study not made obligatory in order to demonstrate that our schools recognize equality in cultural values contributed by all races and nations. Children of immigrants, by studying the languages of their fathers, would acquire a greater respect for their cultural heritage. This would constitute a step toward breaking down the chauvinism which is present both in the American-born population and among the national groups."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
