<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Memorandum on Russian Organizations in Chicago</title> prepared for Foreign Language Project by Mark Khinoy, Jewish Daily Forward, New York,
<date when="1937-06-01">June 1, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Memorandum on Russian Organizations in Chicago prepared for Foreign Language Project by Mark Khinoy, Jewish Daily Forward, New York</title>,
<date when="1937-06-01">June 1, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>".... On our arrival in Chicago we found quite a large colony of Russian emigrants. Some of them hailed from the provinces of Russia--Letts, Lithuanians, Esthonians and Finns, some from Poland and western provinces of the Russian Empire--Poles, Jews and Ruthenians, some from southern Russia and Ukrainia. Very few, if any, came from the purely Russian (Great Russian) districts. The Russians proper in this multitude of Russian subjects were almost exclusively from the guberniya (states) of Minsk, Grodno, Vilna and Volyn. It should be noted that these four districts of old Russia did not possess municipal self-government (zemstvo) which by that time had already established a network of public schools in the agrarian districts of the thirty-four zemstvo guberniyas. And since the four guberniya mentioned above were non-industrial in character, the native sons they sent to this country were culturally backward, a great number of them illiterate. Economically most of the Russians in Chicago were unskilled laborers with a low standard of living, sometimes ten or fifteen men living in one"community-hourse". Their social life outside of the Church was almost nonexistent. The only active educational and cultural factors of the Russian community of that period were the Russian branches of the Socialist Party and the <pb facs="5423967_4_1228.jpg" n="2"/>non-political organizations influenced by them. Their lectures, meetings, free libraries and schools contributed both to the cultural betterment of the Russian colony as Russians and workers, and to the Americanization process of the immigrants."</p>
   <p>Article prepared in English.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
