<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title><date when="1923-07-17">7/17/23</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Gompers and Russia.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0693</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0693.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title><date when="1923-07-17">7/17/23</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Gompers and Russia.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. S. Gompers, the aged leader of the American Federation of Labor, still opposes the recognition of the Soviet government by America and the resumption of commercial relations with Russia.</p>
   <p>He struggles energetically, trying to put through his view of this matter in the American Federation of Labor, and defending these views also outside the Federation.</p>
   <p>He has been struggling hard for a long time. Whenever there is an opportunity he comes forward with a bitter criticism of the activities of the Soviet government, and would especially denounce any leanings of the American government towards resuming commercial relations with Russia.</p>
   <p>And Mr. Gompers does this in spite of the fact that members and prominent leaders of the American Federation of Labor have been demanding for a long time the recognition of Russia and the restoration of friendly <pb facs="5423967_4_0694.jpg" n="2"/>relation with it. The same demands have been made by some senators and congressmen and by many heads of commercial firms.</p>
   <p>The chief arguments used by Gompers are as follows: the absence in Russia of complete freedom of the press and of organizing unions, leagues, etc.</p>
   <p>In a letter addressed to the senators, King and Ladd, who have left recently for Russia, Mr. Gompers declares that before demanding the recognition of the Soviet government, the senators should inquire about the following matters:</p>
   <p>Is it true that freedom of the press does not exist in Russia? Are the workers allowed to join professional unions and to organize unions without interference on the part of the government?</p>
   <p>Mr. Gompers asks further: are the members of the Soviet government also members of the Third Internationale, and is the government of Russia ready to acknowledge the debts of the old regime to foreign countries?</p>
   <p>Let us admit that there is no complete freedom of the press nor a <pb facs="5423967_4_0695.jpg" n="3"/>sufficient freedom of organizing unions.</p>
   <p>But did these things exist in Russia under the autocratic regime? At that time Mr. Gompers did not demand these things to be granted to the Russians. The freedom of the press and of organizing labor unions is suppressed in Italy, in Poland, in Roumania, in Hungary.</p>
   <p>America recognizes the governments of these countries, and Mr. Gompers does not demand that in these countries freedom of the press and of labor organizations should be instituted.</p>
   <p>It is strange also that a leader of workers should demand from Russia the payment of debts incurred by the Tsar's government. What makes him so concerned about the interests of the French, English and other bankers?</p>
   <p>The leader of the American Federation of Labor is not just towards Russia. In the case of Russia his justice becomes rather severe.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile both in Russia and in America there are voiced continually demands for the restoration of friendly relations between these <pb facs="5423967_4_0696.jpg" n="4"/>two countries. Existing conditions have been demanding this already for a long time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
