<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Korob, <title level="a">"Two Clubs,"</title> <title>Moskva (Monthly)</title>,
<date when="1930-10">October, 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0855</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0855.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Korob, <title level="a">"Two Clubs,"</title> <title>Moskva (Monthly)</title>,
<date when="1930-10">October, 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There exist in Chicago, two Russian Clubs; the Russian-American (Cultural-Educational) Club, and the Russian-American Citizen Club. The former, "Russak" has opened evening classes in general-educational and technical study. Its headquarters, offices and hall are located at 1902 W. Division St. Evening classes are held at 1838 W. Division St. The Club has arranged an extensive program of cultural and educational work for the entire winter season. The first lecture will be delivered by Prof. S. Garner, who recently arrived from Russia.</p>
   <p>On the opening day Russak celebrated the event by giving a concert and ball, which broke all attendance records.</p>
   <p>The Krat, (Russian-American Citizens' Club) somewhat deviates towards political interests. November, and the time for general elections being near, the Club intends to intensify its campaign for.......</p>
   <p>Both Mrs. Mac Cormick and the former senator Lewis aspire for a seat in the <pb facs="5423967_4_0856.jpg" n="2"/>Senate and if the Krat Club will not help, they are likely as not to be unsuccessful.</p>
   <p>The Krat Club will announce its further activities after November 4th. In the meantime it celebrated its opening day on October 18. Present, were representatives from political parties, who had come to realize, that without the assistance of the Russians, they will fail to elect their candidates.</p>
   <p>Despite the fact, that Krat recruits its members from Wood Street organization, the most democratic in the Russian colony, and equally as good as J. F. Erin and his "Znanie" the most important role was assumed by the cream of the Officers Union.</p>
   <p>In the Russak Club (Russian-American) the democratic element predominates with its compact mass of progressive intelligentsia as its vanguard.</p>
   <p>There is a persistent rumor that the two organizations will amalgamate after the 4th of November; that is "Krat" (Russian American Citizens' Club) will end its historical mission and will realize that it can travel together with the "Russak". God-speed.</p>
   <p>Korob.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
