<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Minutes of the Meetings of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago</title>
      <title level="a">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Pertsov, 2559 W. Division)</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">No. 1</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Minutes of the Meetings of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago</title>
     <title level="a">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Pertsov, 2559 W. Division)</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">No. 1</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Minutes of the meeting of the members of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago and of persons intending to become members of this society.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order on Sunday, September 12, 1926, at 12 A. M., at the quarters of the Y. M. C. A. on Division street. D. K. Morozov was presiding and Dr. L. G. Pertsov (Kaluzhin) was the secretary.</p>
   <p>The following persons attended this meeting: D. K. Moroz, V. V. Kotov, S. D. Gladyshchuk, Dr. L. G. Pertsov (Kaluzhin), N. I. Kutnyuk, Z. I. Philipchik, K. L. Kotsyubinsky, L. V. Vinogradov, and S. G. Prokopov.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0232.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The order of the business of the day proposed by the chairman of the Center is accepted unanimously. The chairman made a speech concerning the activities of the Center during the eriod from the time of its organization in April 1925 to the month of August 1926. He pointed out that, though the committee of the Center had made some blunders, still the active members of the Center had derived from the work done by them a feeling of moral satisfaction.</p>
   <p>The question about the paying of their debts to the Center by the old members gave rise to lively debates. Morozov and Prokopov maintained that all old debts should be paid. Vinogradov, Kotov and Dr. Pertsov opposed this view, giving appropriate reasons. By a majority vote it was resolved to leave the matter of paying the debts to the discretion of the old members of the society.</p>
   <p>It was decided that all persons who were attending this meeting would become automatically members of the reorganized Russian Center, <pb facs="5423967_4_0233.jpg" n="3"/>and that (in accordance with the laws of the society) such persons should pay monthly dues of 30 cents, beginning with the 1st of September 1926.</p>
   <p>L. V. Vinogradov moves that no initiation for of one dollar (as demanded by the by-laws of the society) should be collected from new members during the month of September and October of the current year, in order to attract more members into the society. This motion is accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>After that new elections of the members of the committee took place. The following persons were elected by a majority of votes:</p>
   <p>S. G. Prokopov, Chairman</p>
   <p>D. K. Moroz, Vice-Chairman</p>
   <p>K. L. Kotsyubinsky, Treasurer</p>
   <p>L. V. Vinogradov, Secretary</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0234.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Pertsov and Mr. Vinogradov move that some entertainment be organized right away in order to attract new members into the organization. It is resolved that not later than in October a concert and ball should be arranged. This would be most convenient because Dr. Pertsov had proposed to procure from the Bohemians a large and interesting Russian film. The following persons are elected members of the theatrical committee: S. Gladyshchuk, V. V. Kotov, and Dr. L. G. Pertsov.</p>
   <p>The old committee is enjoined to turn over without any delay all the business to the new one. In order that this should be effected it is resolved that a joint meeting of both committees should be held on Wednesday, September 15, at 7:30 P. M., in Mr. D. K. Morozov's apartment.</p>
   <p>The clause of the by-laws, declaring that any member who has not paid <pb facs="5423967_4_0235.jpg" n="5"/>his dues for two months without explaining this by serious reasons is by this very fact automatically excluded from the organization is reasserted.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pertsov communicates that the Bohemian organizations propose that the Center would participate in the festivity which they are going to give in the end of this year's October in commemoration of the anniversary of the independence of the Republic of Czecho-Slovakia. They also propose that a delegate be elected by the Russian colony to represent it at this festivity. he meeting resolves to postpone the discussion of this proposal until the next general assembly.</p>
   <p>It is resolved to propose to all those present to make all possible efforts trying to enlist into the organization active members of the colony in order that the common work would be expanded and strengthened.</p>
   <p>The meeting is adjourned at 2:30 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
