<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-01">Feb. 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Youths' Congress of Roov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-01">Feb. 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">YOUTHS' CONGRESS OF ROOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow in New York, the Fourth Congress of Roov's Youths will open its sessions. This congress has great significance not only for Roov (The Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society of America), but for the entire Russian colony in the United States.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows that present day youth represents the future builders of social life. Therefore, it is not surprising that all dictators, all governments, and all political parties pay the greatest attention to their youth. Each country endeavors to rear its young in a desirable way so that each generation may pursue its course and build a social life according to the community pattern.</p>
   <p>The same thing is observed in the United States where the population is composed of many nationalities. Here, foreigners' children are reared in American <pb facs="5423967_4_1213.jpg" n="2"/>ways, on one hand, and in the ways of their nationality and their parents, on the other.</p>
   <p>This is revealed by the fact that almost all national groups in the United States have their own youth organizations, schools and various other institutions.</p>
   <p>Until lately, the Russian colony was the only foreign group that offered practically nothing for its younger generation. There were no organizations, no schools for the children, and no periodicals in the Russian language for the growing generation to read.</p>
   <p>There was a time when many Russians, because of their ignorance, did not identify themselves as Russians. For that very reason there was no Russian youth of whom mention could be made. The Russian youth was absorbed among the youth of other nationalities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1214.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When Roov appeared on the scene, this situation was changed. This organization understood that besides organizing parents it is necessary to organize their children. Without youths' participation it is impossible to carry on the work of social advancement. Unless thinning ranks of parents are augmented by the growing generation, this activity will be eliminated in the course of time.</p>
   <p>In this respect Roov has achieved good results. At present there are many Russian youth organizations in the eastern part of the United States. The membership of these organizations is growing rapidly despite the crisis and widespread unemployment. From this we must conclude that Russian youth is not lost. It is only necessary to approach the young Russians in a proper manner and instill the desire to do for the common cause what their parents had been doing. Then Russian youth will recognize its place in the world, and will actively participate in all social work.</p>
   <p>The Chicago society of Rnzov (The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) also strives to aid Russian youth. They have been fairly successful, although their <pb facs="5423967_4_1215.jpg" n="4"/>accomplishments do not compare with the results achieved by Roov. We entertain the hope, however, that very soon this society will also have large youth organizations and clubs.</p>
   <p>It would be quite laudable if these two societies would attempt to organize Russian youth in cities where there are no branches of these organizations.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we extend our greetings to the Fourth Congress of Roov and we hope it is successful in solving all of the important problems confronting it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
