<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-12-08">December 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Maximov's Funeral</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-12-08">December 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR MAXIMOV'S FUNERAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On December 6, 1928, at the University Chapel, the funeral service of the former eminent professor of the Military Medical Academy and lately of the University of Chicago, A. A. Maximov, took place. The funeral service was performed by the clergy of the Holy Trinity Cathedral. The Archimandrite M. Mulyar and the Archpriest A. Vyacheslavov were officiating, being assisted by the priest of the St. Mikhail Parish and the Archpriest N. Sokolov. The famous Kedrov Quartet sang marvelously. The church was overcrowded; there were more than 1,000 persons present. Among them were the former students of the late professor, and all the staff of the Medical Faculty with the president, Woodrow, at the head.</p>
   <p>The following well known members of the Russian colony also attended the funeral: Engineer I. M. Bregovsky, with his wife; Dr. M. I. Von Friesen; Dr. A. G. Gabrilyants; Dr. R. F. Koch; Dr. L. G. Pertsov; engineer A. A. Zakharov; Prince M. A. Obolensky, with his wife; Dr. S. A. Novakovsky; V. V. Kottov; V. M. Slavogorodsky; the former <pb facs="5423967_4_1691.jpg" n="2"/>consul, Volkov; E. V. Lutnitsky, and many others.</p>
   <p>The coffin was carried by the professors of the university in their full uniform. Near the coffin, according to the American custom, stood two guards of honor: two students, a man and a woman, on each side. President Woodrow of the University of Chicago made a splendid speech in which he explained how great a scientist the late professor, Maximov, has been. The Archpriest, A. Vyacheslavov, made a short speech in Russia. Professor Maximov was buried in the Woodlawn cemetery. Sad, with their heads bowed, the hundreds of people who knew him went home. They could hardly believe that the professor had left them forever.</p>
   <p>The death of Professor Maximov was a great loss to the medical science and to all those who knew and loved him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
