<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Professor M. A. Sherbinin</title>, of the Evangelical Christians, by Dimitri Stranden,
<date when="1937-05-19">May 19, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Evangelical Christians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Professor M. A. Sherbinin</title>, of the Evangelical Christians, by Dimitri Stranden,
<date when="1937-05-19">May 19, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN EVANGELICAL CHRISTIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Sherbinin has been a resident of Chicago since 1917 and during this period he has done much for the spreading of the teachings of Evangelical Christianity among the Russians in Chicago. He is not a narrow-minded follower of any particular sect. He sympathizes with all efforts to revive the true Christian spirit of piety and brotherhood wherever such sincere efforts are being made. Evangelizing activities among the Chicago Russians, however, have been carried on chiefly by Evangelical Christians, Baptists and some other so-called "sectarians."</p>
   <p>Professor Sherbinin said that the Evangelical Christians were the first to organize in Chicago a Christian community independent of the Russian Orthodox Church. In the beginning there was no dissension between the Evangelical Christians and those who had accepted the teachings of the Baptists; they all gathered, prayed and worked together. But later the Baptists, who attached more importance to the ceremony of baptism, decided to organize a church of their own, and established their quarters near Douglas Park. Their preacher was Mr. Prigodich, but about two years ago he left for New York, and Mr. Siberyakov ( a corruption of the name Sibiryakov) is occupying his place at present, and they hold their services and meetings at Ogden Ave. near Washtenaw.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
