<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-19">Dec. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Still Concerning the Russian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-19">Dec. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">STILL CONCERNING THE RUSSIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Rassviet of December 7, my letter "Concerning Russian Newspapers" was printed. Rassviet printed a long editorial referring to it. The editor said, "S. Zhukov unfortunately did not point out to readers the reasons for the existence of such conditions in the Russian colony."</p>
   <p>I think that evil conditions in the Russian colony were caused by the Russian Mutual Aid Organizations, such as Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society), Russkoe Narodnoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian People's Mutual Aid Society), Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) and several Brotherhoods in the United States of America.</p>
   <p>These societies were made up mostly of Russian peasants and laborers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Greedy politicians joined these societies in order to control the membership in the way they desired. These politicians, with the aid of the press, led the disorganization of the Colony.</p>
   <p>All of these organizations endorse the same principle--mutual aid and enlightenment, and therefore should walk arm in arm aiding each other. But instead they revile and accuse each other of every sort of crime.</p>
   <p>This is entirely the fault of politicians. If these politicians did not exist, the four organizations could be united into one unit, and then we would be recognized as are other national groups, but at the present time nobody recognizes us. Therefore it is necessary to work for the unification of all societies into one big and strong mutual aid organization.</p>
   <p>Previously, vilification and slander did not exist as it does now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0622.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Occasionally there were little political discussions--but nothing compared to what we are seeing at present.</p>
   <p>Look at the four Russian newspapers and you will see the abuse they direct at each other. We sometimes blush for the press and for our people. One attacks the other because the latter does not join the organization which the former prefers. The fault is in the press because it prints the vicious correspondence. The newspaper should [rather] discuss progress in science.</p>
   <p>I will relate here a few examples. In the past summer in the state of Connecticut, a picnic was held by the RNOV (Russian People's Mutual Aid Society) in Waterbury, and a speaker was sent from New York to deliver a speech of about twenty minutes in length. Ten minutes of the speech he devoted to praising RNOV, and in the remaining time criticized Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society). What was the result? He incited one against the other.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0623.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Later I asked him why he did such a thing. He stated that he was paid ten dollars and instructed to do so. This person was a teacher in Ansonia. He stole a couple of hundreds of dollars from several people and fifty dollars from the organization and returned to New York.</p>
   <p>There you are, that is the kind of teacher we have at present.</p>
   <p>All of the three mutual aid organizations engage in struggle among themselves. Which one of them can one believe? Which can one join, which deserves our sympathy? These questions often puzzle the colonists. Where is the truth? Where to go? Many remain aloof from organizations. But there is still a hope that there are Russians who will point out where the truth is, and where the lie exists, and will direct our people to mutual aid, and progress in science. And the sooner they do it, the better off the Russian people will be.</p>
   <p>S. Zhukov.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: Original letter of Zhukov under II B 2 d (1). Further discussion under III A.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
