<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-29">Apr. 29, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Washington Conference Will Discuss the Problem of Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-29">Apr. 29, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON CONFERENCE WILL DISCUSS THE PROBLEM OF IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On May 2, in Washington, in the Hotel Washington, a conference will assemble which will deal with problems of immigration. Its main purpose is to shed light on the present conditions under which foreigners live in the United States. For the first time in many months, after an intense campaign of propaganda directed against foreigners, the American public will get the answers to many questions and false accusations heaped on aliens. This conference, called on the initiative of the Foreign Language Information Service, will also make an attempt to uncover the causes and point our the sources of the malicious attacks against foreigners which have already led to proposals to deport all persons not citizens, to deprive them of the right to be employed on public works, and to introduce for them a special kind of passport system.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1238.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"One should not be surprised that at a time when it is most difficult to satisfy the needs even of citizens foreigners become the objects of discrimination and [the subjects] of heated arguments," recently declared Reed Louis, director of the Foreign Language Information Service. "On the one hand the most serious charges are preferred against them; on the other hand these accusations are made in violation of all justice and of American tradition. Then where is the truth in this problem? What should be our attitude toward immigrants, those who are not citizens, in the light of our own traditions and of our own needs? The task of the conference, therefore, will be to deliberate on these questions and to give answers to them. When in our attempt to make of foreigners the scapegoats for our own shortcomings and social and economic faults the most fantastic figures and 'proofs' are advanced, it is time to present to the public opinion of the country the real facts."</p>
   <p>One of the key speakers at the conference will be John G. Vinnant, former Governor of the State of New Hampshire and at present the head of <pb facs="5423967_4_1239.jpg" n="3"/>the Council on Social Security. He in his talk will deal with foreigners receiving material assistance. A professor of the Catholic university in Washington, Monsignor John A. Ryan, will speak on "Whether Foreigners Have a Right to Work". Justin Miller, chairman of the advisory committee of the Department of Justice, will deal in his talk with criminalism among foreigners, and Thorston Sellin, professor of sociology in the University of Pennsylvania, will speak on "Criminalism in the Second Generation". Among other speakers are the write Will Irwin, a professor of Harvard University, E. A. Hutton, and a Journalist, Morris Hindus. This last speaker will present the "immigrant problem" in the light of American history and from the point of view of the foreigners themselves.</p>
   <p>All sessions of the conference will be open to the public. After the reports have been made, discussions will take place. The participation of a large number of editors and publishers of foreign-language newspapers is expected. Representatives of many large public institutions have been invited to attend the conference. The American press will <pb facs="5423967_4_1240.jpg" n="4"/>also have a large representation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
