<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-05-13">May 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Bolsheviks Remind Themselves of Pushkin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-05-13">May 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">BOLSHEVIKS REMIND THEMSELVES OF PUSHKIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is rumored that the Russian Bolsheviks in Chicago have suddenly reminded themselves of Pushkin and are already busy preparing to honor the memory of this great Russian poet. This, of course, may be true, for even the Soviet government has decided to honor the memory of the greatest Russian man of letters of all times. Formerly the Soviet rulers were violently insane and did not recognize greatness in anybody but Karl Marx, but now they have become saner, and the Russian-American communists are following their superiors' sensible example, except, as always, some few individuals.</p>
   <p>If they wish to honor the memory of the great Russian genius, I should like to ask them why they are not willing to celebrate together with the rest of the Russian colony in Chicago. There is all the more reason for their <pb facs="5423967_4_0900.jpg" n="2"/>doing so because they have not [among them] anybody capable of presenting Pushkin properly to the workers of the Russian colony through his works. In this case they should really think of forming that "united front" of which they dream on other occasions less appropriate and less opportune.</p>
   <p>In Chicago we already see functioning the so-called Pushkin Memorial Committee, which represents all the cultured people of the Russian colony. The activity of this committee should be supported by all the Russian people, since the committee is nonpartisan in every way and will gladly accept help from any group of Russians, irrespective of their political convictions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
