<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 North Broadway, Unidentified Newspaper clipping. Date not given.
<title level="a">From New York to Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 North Broadway, Unidentified Newspaper clipping. Date not given.
<title level="a">FROM NEW YORK TO CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greetings to you, 'City of Gigantic shoulders, Nations' loader, flesher of the world'. To you, Blue Lake Michigan, to you - resplendent parks of the city of Chicago, of museums, libraries, spacious streets, and of grey, massive capacious structures.</p>
   <p>Greetings to you, - dear monuments of Goethe, and of Lincoln; to softly, speeding tram-cars; air-lines, and tranquil, unperturbed multitudes of the street; and to you, halting, Russian colony, - and to you, dear, dear friends....</p>
   <p>My greetings to you I send from turbulent, ever-agitated New York. I turned disloyal to you for a while, and have forgotten you temporarily.</p>
   <p>I became infatuated with the feverish, nervous bustle of this city's street crowd; what a light and luring step hers is. I am lured by myriads of bright-sparkling evening fires; by tops of giant sky-scrapers; by monstrous bridges of legendary enormity; by inviting buildings, monuments; and by the singular music of this city, which is stirring, soothing, joyous, and wistful. I am carried away here by contrasts that are heart-rending, and soul-prostrating; mad, luxury living, <pb facs="5423967_4_1737.jpg" n="2"/>side-by-side with destitution in this amazing city; congestion with spaciousness; matchless lustre with dusk from indigence; joyous smiles, with a depressing sleekness; elegance, with vulgarity.</p>
   <p>And I am carried away by certain spots so reminiscent of Europe...</p>
   <p>At no time in your capaciousness, Chicago, have the shadows of Europe appeared so artistic and so bright.</p>
   <p>Here, in this life-seething, nerve-quivering, giant city, I ramble for hours in the streets to look at buildings, show windows, monuments; the ease of the speeding crowds, all so reminiscent of Paris, London and Stockholm.</p>
   <p>At moments I feel drawn to your vastness, to your parks, your flower-beds, and your exquisite beaches of Lake and Sea Michigan, your streets abounding with trees. I simply long for you, as the city which became my own.</p>
   <p>Here, it is at times stifling, crowded. The streets are narrow, the houses are of many stories. It is sad to see pale-faced tots playing on the side-walks of narrow <pb facs="5423967_4_1738.jpg" n="3"/>business streets... It is depressing to meet everywhere, faces exhausted from work and worry.</p>
   <p>But then, there is more music here, and the masses are more sensitive, closer, more books, theatres, museums, paintings. And more of a throbbing, seething life. Then, swing is broader, broader and deeper are the people's demands on life in this city. There is more searching here for the ways of life, a greater avidity for life; there is more reflecting and a tragic-joyous, insight here. A more bold and audacious city, and a brighter struggle for the luminous and the beautiful.</p>
   <p>Ah, what an amazing, alluring, and agonizing city this is. A city in which people are grains of sand. A city of infernally hot and madly speeding subways. A city, whose workingmen, fight tragically for a better life for all, and whose bankers are in control almost of the entire world. A city of artists and of store-keepers. Of palatial homes and sardine-packed, barrack-like tenements. A city of the world's dreamers, and a center of most shameless corruption and exploitation. A city avidly hearing Chaliapin, and roaring with beastly hilarity and baseness at boxing-tussels. A city of pale-looking children and red-cheeked, plump, trades-women. A city with the statue of Liberty and 'an Island of Tears' in it. A city, which is a most <pb facs="5423967_4_1739.jpg" n="4"/>hospitable asylum for all, who are persecuted, yet also of intrigues and of cruelty.</p>
   <p>On the day when my infatuation with this city will end, and I shall tire of her beauty and her ugliness, of her allurements and her repulsiveness, take me then, take me back to you, Chicago, city mine.</p>
   <p>Signed-</p>
   <p>Alexander Zemetchinsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
