<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-07-14">July 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian-American Democratic League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0777</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0777.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-07-14">July 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League was organized six months ago by Mr. V. Kishun. Its aim is to unite, on political, social and cultural grounds, all Russians in Chicago who are American citizens and who believe in American democratic principles. The league is primarily interested in securing due political recognition in the State of Illinois, so as to be on an equal footing with other national groups in Chicago. The league maintains close co-operation with the Polish, Czechoslovak, Jugoslav and Ukrainian groups in Chicago through the Russian branch of the All-Slavonic Union of America.</p>
   <p>The recognition of the Russian-American Democratic League by American political circles will play an important part in the future development of our group and in its unification, as by it we will receive the right to nominate Russian candidates for various public offices. This fact alone will open a new field of opportunities for those of our young people who are interested in politics. As a result of this, our younger generation will become directly interested in supporting and developing Russian organizations. It will be to their own interest <pb facs="5423967_4_0778.jpg" n="2"/>to work for the union of all Russians, to build and support the Russian schools, and to uphold Russian culture and Russian consciousness among the younger Russian-American generation. The future political career of any of our young aspirants to public office will depend entirely upon how well our group is organized and how strong it is--in other words, in how big an army of voters we are able to put in the field, following the example of those experienced politicians, the Irish-Americans, and other national groups.</p>
   <p>Besides its political activities, the Russian-American Democratic League is striving with all its means to bring free aid and service to the Russian people of Chicago in such matters as citizenship and legal aid, and in interceding on their behalf in public institutions. How successful this work has been can be seen from the following summary: from January 1 to July 1 of this year 700 persons called at the office of the league on different matters; 271 people asked for help in finding employment; 111 in connection with property taxes; 39 who overpaid personal property taxes; 87 for legal aid in the courts; 4 for illegal arrest; 14 for first citizenship papers; 36 for second citizenship <pb facs="5423967_4_0779.jpg" n="3"/>papers; 9 for information on immigration questions; 12 for driving ordinance violations; 94 on real-estate mortgage loans. More than sixty per cent of these cases were successfully settled.</p>
   <p>During its six-months' existence the league has opened fourteen new branches in fourteen different wards in Chicago, also branches in Cicero and Argo, Illinois. These branches have a total of 685 members. The most successful branch is in Ward 25 in Douglas Park. It has 175 adult members, men and women, and a youth circle consisting of 60 young boys and girls.</p>
   <p>Each branch is an autonomous organization, and is governed by a committee of seven members, who are elected at the annual meeting by a secret vote of all members of the branch. The committees of all the branches, as a body, compose the council of directors of the central organization, and act as its governing board. This governing board elects an executive committee from among its members, so that each branch has one of its members in this central executive committee. The present central executive committee is composed of the following persons: V. Kishun, P. Paliniak, I. Erin, A. Kopernik, N. Vishnievsky, D. Sleznik, J. Sikovsky, V. Olesiuk, I. Sambor, P. Rozdielsky, R. Homko, S. Aarin, <pb facs="5423967_4_0780.jpg" n="4"/>T. Tureyko, N. Novin, A. Shakula, B. Zhuk, J. Chopko, V. Cheslavsky, K. Tanashchuk and C. Artemenko.</p>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League appeals to all Russian-Americans who have second or first citizenship papers to join this organization, and thus contribute their support to the new, sound undertaking of our group. Those members of the league who have only their first citizenship papers are entitled to vote only on the advisory committee. The membership dues are twenty-five cents a month or one dollar a year.</p>
   <p>On all matters concerning the league, and for information on all other questions, apply during the day to Mr. V. Kishun, 155 N. Clark Street, room 1420, and in the evenings to the Russian-American Democratic Club, 1902 West Division Street. On the South Side, apply to either Peter Kaliniak or P. Rozdielsky of the Carpatho-Ruthenian Citizens' Club, 2744 West 51st Street.</p>
   <p>The Central Committee</p>
   <p>Russian-American Democratic League</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
