<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-06-01">May 31 &amp; June 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Interviewing P. N. Milukov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-06-01">May 31 &amp; June 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">INTERVIEWING P. N. MILUKOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I was in Russia, in 1917, just eleven years ago, that I met last time Pavel Nikolayevich Milukov, that eminent Russian historian and outstanding politician of our time. At that time Petrograd was swept by the wave of the first demonstration of protest against the celebrated diplomatic note sent by him in April to the Allies.</p>
   <p>Today I met him again in that blessed city of Chicago, that American Babylon. Of course, Pavel Nikolayevich looks old, but, in spite of that, just as in the stormy days of the revolution of 1917, he is sprightly in his gait, and his flowing, elegant speech sounds calm and powerful.</p>
   <p>I had so many questions to ask him that I did not know how to begin.</p>
   <p>Just a few hours before I came some American journalists had visited Prof. Milukov. In the morning he had spoken downtown to an American audience. Even a young man might have been tired.</p>
   <p>So, out of a score of questions which I had jotted down beforchand, I selected <pb facs="5423967_4_1567.jpg" n="2"/>a few which, in my opinion, should be of greater interest to our public, and started to interview Pavel Nikolayevich without much ado.</p>
   <p>"What should we do in America in order to further the welfare of our native country?"</p>
   <p>Pavel Nikolayevich smiles:</p>
   <p>"First of all, you should spread correct information concerning Russia. Next, you should not forget Russia and the Russian language; you should watch all that is happening in Russia. It is also important for you to be in close contact with those Russian colonies in foreign countries which are nearer to Russia; for example, with the Russian colony in Paris, which is the largest in Europe.</p>
   <p>"You should also learn here in order to return to your native country with a certain store of acquired knowledge. And there are many things in America which are worth learning, and of course, the opportunities of acquiring useful</p>
   <p>knowledge are greater than in Europe."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1568.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>My next question I formulated thus:</p>
   <p>"What Russian groups existing abroad can unite in the struggle for a better future for Russia?"</p>
   <p>"The republican-democratic current," answered Pavel Nikolayevich, "can be amalgamated only with other republican groups. Our attitude towards such other groups as still adhere to the standpoint of an old ideology is a negative one. It is important for us to be united not only on a negative basis, regarding merely the enemy against whom we are concluding an alliance, but also on a positive basis, considering what objects we pursue by our struggle.</p>
   <p>"The first of such republican-democratic amalgamations is being planned right now in the United States, in New York. It is possible that in other large centers in America there will also be realized a similar unification of kindred political currents."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1569.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Tell me please, Pavel Nikolayevich, what you think about the activities of so called 'activists' abroad?"</p>
   <p>"The concept of 'activism' is a very definite one. In a certain sense we Russians who are living abroad, are all activists. True, some circles among Russian emigrants hold for some reason that activism is their monopoly, and manifest their activist attitude by taking to terrorism, which we do not approve. Terrorism does not find any response in Russia at present. Acts of terrorism are often imputed to foreigners or to white guards, and thus result only in strengthening the power of the Soviet government. We do not conclude any alliances with activists of that kind."</p>
   <p>"Do you remember," I asked Prof. Milukov, "how a comparatively short time ago there was much talk in the press and among emigrants as to the possibility of the appearance of a kind of Bonaparte in Russia? I wish we could acquaint the Russian colony with your opinion concerning this question."</p>
   <p>"A Bonaparte is needed in order that Bonapartism could exist; and there is no <pb facs="5423967_4_1570.jpg" n="5"/>Bonaparte in Russia. A Bonaparte usually arises as a result of some military campaign. The red army does not plan any campaign; its commanders keep very quiet. There are no appropriate conditions for the appearance of a dictator. A need of a strong power is felt in the country. Such a power will evidently arise in some way or other. It is possible that this power will be a strong one; but only such a power will last, as will be consistent with the principles of democracy."</p>
   <p>"Do you think that the restoration of monarchy in Russia is possible?"</p>
   <p>"Monarchy in Russia is absolutely impossible."</p>
   <p>Incidentally I mentioned the movement in favor of placing on the throne the Grand Duke Cyril, referring to it as to "a strong movement"; but Pavel Nikolayevich made a remark to the effect that this group of monarchists is small, and that the movement isn't grounded in any really existing conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1571.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>I next touched on the sore spot of the quarrel dividing our clergy into two inimical camps, disputing about the rightful succession of metropolitans.</p>
   <p>I shall explain briefly Prof. Milukov's views concerning this important question.</p>
   <p>"The right of succession," said the professor, "is in the hands of the metropolitan Evloghiy in Paris, and of the metropolitan Platon in America; consequently Bishop Teofil (Theophilus) is the rightful head of the Chicago bishopric. The synod sitting in Karlowitz can hardly act in a serious way. It is too deeply steeped in politics. It is a political church. It has been condemned by the patriarch and is a self-appointed pretender to ecclesiastical authority. Its only hope lies in the restoration of monarchy."</p>
   <p>As to questions which concern our Russian colony and have only recently aroused in it vehement discussions, I broached the subject of the "closing of the frontiers" of Soviet Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1572.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"Why is it that the Bolsheviki, who let all kinds of foreigners and bourgeois enter Russia, do not allow the old Russian emigrants (who have resided in America some fifteen or twenty years) to return to their native country? And when can we hope the frontiers of the U. S. S. R. to be opened to Russians?"</p>
   <p>This is the answer which Pavel Nikolayevich gave me:</p>
   <p>"The U. S. S. R. regards all Russians who stay abroad as its enemies. They are bourgeois, and the crime of which they are guilty is that they are not Communists. Sometimes, however, the Bolsheviki admit into the confines of Soviet Russia some specialists. But on the whole they are loath to let people in, and admit only such persons as are required by them."</p>
   <p>"When will the frontiers of Russia be opened?"</p>
   <p>"The frontiers will be opened either if the Soviet Government undergoes a change or if it is removed."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1573.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Now, here is a purely local question, one that is, so to say, a question of the hour among Chicago Russians:</p>
   <p>"Can a religiously minded person be a radical?"</p>
   <p>"Political views have nothing to do with religion. An atheist can be a conservative, and, on the other hand, a religiously minded person can hold progressive views in politics. Right now, in Paris, there is a dispute going on concerning this question among the Socialist-Revolutionaries. There they formulate this question thus:</p>
   <p>"Can one be a Socialist-Revolutionary and at the same time a Christian (belonging to the Orthodox Church)?"</p>
   <p>Pavel Nikolayevich was evidently tired, and, not wishing to impose on his kindness, I hastily asked him a question which is of interest to many readers and friends of our newspaper.</p>
   <p>I mean the question as to anarchists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1574.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Pavel Nikolayevich pointed out that at the time when the third State Duma was holding its sessions (1908 to 1909) there existed in Russia an incipient anarchist movement, but it did not develop into anything that could be regarded as a more or less powerful factor in Russian political life. During the revolution and after the victory various enemies of the Bolsheviki used the name of anarchists in order to conceal their real aims.</p>
   <p>We talked about anarchism in general and its best representatives. I happened to mention the name of Kropotkin, who is greatly respected in our colony.</p>
   <p>"Kropotkin," said Professor Milukov, "is the gentlest and most lovable of men; and anarchy, generally speaking, is a term expressing the utmost limit which can be reached by society in its evolution. It is, if I may say so, the music of the future, and perfect freedom in the present. This is why anarchism is the highest existing current of thought."</p>
   <p>I take my leave of Pavel Nikolayevich. He is very glad to learn that there is <pb facs="5423967_4_1575.jpg" n="10"/>in existence in Chicago a daily Russian newspaper, created and supported by the labor and efforts of some of the more intelligent among the Russian workmen, scattered in various nooks of the United States and of Canada. He listens with great attention to what I have to say about our attitude to various problems, and promises to try to be helpful to us in any possible way when he returns to Europe. One wishes one could stay longer in the comfortable room occupied by Pavel Nikolayevich at the hotel, and visit in thought, at least for a minute, our own dear St. Petersburg, where Pavel Nikolayevich has passed a large part of his life; but it is time to relieve him of my presence.</p>
   <p>Lev Pertsov.</p>
   <p>Hotel Del Prado</p>
   <p>May 29, 1928.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
