<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-10">Feb. 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">In Defense of Russia's Being Armed</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Krupinov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-10">Feb. 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENSE OF RUSSIA'S BEING ARMED</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Krupinov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some people write in their articles that the military budget of Soviet Russia exceeds that of all the bourgeois countries, that this is something unprecedented in the history of the Russian people, that the red rulers, disregarding the fact that their own people are starving, increase their military strength and continue to arm to the teeth, trying to save their own hides.</p>
   <p>I do not agree with such statements, but I grant that they are arming the country to the teeth. But why do they do it, and for whom?</p>
   <p>The Russian people do it for the sake of self-defense, for they have lived through the worst calamities that human beings have ever experienced, and many things have become clear to them. They know how difficult it was to <pb facs="5423967_4_1363.jpg" n="2"/>fight against the better-armed enemy. Russian soldiers had heavy hearts when they had to wait behind the front lines for their comrades to be killed so that they could grab their rifles.</p>
   <p>Even General Cheslavsky in his war memoirs writes that "we answered the enemy's gunfire sparingly, for we were short of shells".</p>
   <p>Now the Russian people are developing their mines and building plants and factories. They have begun to consider now to create a strong force so as to be able to defend themselves, and in order to defend themselves the Russian people need a powerful army, equipped with the latest weapons of war. All this requires money, and this is the reason why such a military budget is needed for defense.</p>
   <p>If the Russian people were in the unfortunate position of China, the Japanese, one may say with certainty, would invade Russia as they have invaded China.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1364.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As far as we are concerned in America, we do not pay any Russian taxes, nor do we shoulder any military expense, and in regard to the Russian people in their native land I say that they are well able to take care of themselves and to carry the burden of military defense. They have been able to widen their confines and to defend them against all odds through centuries of history, and of course they will not permit their country to become the victim of conquest and to be made the colony of some other stranger country. They have begun to develop mines and to construct factories and mills; they have built a powerful air fleet, the might of which is known and feared all over the world, and at present the Russian people vigilantly keep guard over their own immense land and decide their own destinies.</p>
   <p>But when the [idea of] brotherhood of men is realized, they will gladly stretch their hands to other peoples in sign of friendship, and then no military budgets will be necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
