<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Pushkin Committee Is Being Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE PUSHKIN COMMITTEE IS BEING ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second conference of persons undertaking the organization of the Pushkin Committee took place last Friday. The following were present at the conference: Bishop Leontie, D. Stranden, N. Novin, E. Moravsky, P. Lagunov, A. Lutnitzky, I. Erin, Dr. Nedzelnitzky, Reverend Lobanov, Reverend Antziferov, Reverend Dzeltonoga, A. Bernov, V. Tcheslavsky, Dr. Tchadovitch, and A. Dobrokhotov.</p>
   <p>Bishop Leontie made a full report of the preparatory work which has already been accomplished in connection with the proposed new organization. It was decided to call a meeting of the representatives of all Russian organizations, clubs, churches, and other groups. These representatives of the entire Russian colony in Chicago will form the proposed Pushkin Committee. The conference decided to divide the Pushkin Committee into the following sections: the lecture section, the school section, the publicity section, the publishing section, the art and drama section, the financial section, and the administration section.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0742.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The conference expressed the desire that all Russian organizations in Chicago and vicinity send their representatives to the meeting scheduled to take place July 26. The conference was of the opinion that the proposed Pushkin Committee will be successful in its work only if it represents the entire Russian colony in Chicago, and not some small section of it. The members of the conference agreed that the Pushkin Committee should be conceived as broadly and as democratically as was the committee on The Day of Russian Culture celebration, held in Chicago some time ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
