<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-09">Mar. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Fraternal Society RNzOV</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-09">Mar. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FRATERNAL SOCIETY RNzOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently, on the page devoted to the affairs of RNzOV [Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society], there appeared an article written by A. F. Bernov, an indefatigable civic worker and a very active member of our organization. This article might have been a sad one, had it not been for one single ray of hope which ran through the entire article--the idea of the need of unity in order to help one another.</p>
   <p>From his personal experience and mainly from observing people around him, A. F. Bernov has come to the conclusion that men who take no interest in public affairs and limit their activity by their personal lives, are, essentially, unhappy people and their lives in most cases end in disappointments. They die as lonely and forgotten men, as useless creatures for whom nobody cares. Their remains are accompanied to the cemetery by the paid man, the lonesome undertaker. And this sole "mourner" hurriedly covers their coffins with dirt <pb facs="5423967_4_0523.jpg" n="2"/>and rides posthaste back home to pick up "new business".</p>
   <p>The question arises: what has the man lived for, if during all of his life, no one has shed a tear nor given a sigh for him? Such a man should not have been born at all.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviks proclaimed to the world "the dictatorship of the proletariat," as if there were something new in that. The "dictatorship of the proletariat" means that "we are the rulers of the country, the force is in our hands, and, therefore, all good things in life shall belong to us; let others die as long as we can enjoy ourselves". And what happened? First, the Russian intellectuals died out--the people who were less adapted to the struggle; following them, the Russian bourgeoisie disappeared. And what about our proletariat, our workers and peasants? Don't millions of them die from hunger even now, at the end of the fourth five-year period of the dictatorship of the proletariat (sic)?</p>
   <p>And this is only physical suffering. What about the mental suffering of the <pb facs="5423967_4_0524.jpg" n="3"/>Russian people? Are they happy? All tourists notice that the Russia of today is a very sad country, that one very seldom hears a song, that there are no smiles on people's faces, and that invigorating and hilarious laughter has disappeared from the face of the Russian land.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviks have killed the soul of the Russian people, have imposed their egocentric ideas upon the people, despite the historic fact that the Russian people have always fought for the freedom and independence of small, oppressed peoples and died so that others might be happy.</p>
   <p>The Russian soldier always astonished the world by his bravery, by his vigor. He measured the Carpathian mountains, the lofty peaks of the Caucasus, while sacrificing his own life for brothers who were unknown to him. Even while they were in want and endured hardships, the Russian people never lost their sense of the enjoyment of life and laughter. They created the songs that enchant the world, the music that reveals the deep compassionate Russian soul, for within the Russian spirit burns the perpetual flame of truth, which from <pb facs="5423967_4_0525.jpg" n="4"/>time immemorial has inspired the oppressed and downtrodden people of the earth with high hopes and ardent faith.</p>
   <p>Haven't the Slavonic peoples of the Balkan countries, the Carpatho-Russians, and others preserved their national identity and their languages only because they believed fervently in the integrity of the Russian people and knew that sooner or later, the legendary Russian soldier, would come and liberate them from slavery and oppression.</p>
   <p>That is why the name of Russia is blessed by all the small nations of the Caucasus, Transcaucasia, Central Asia, and other regions. The Russian people have sacrificed on behalf of all their weak and unknown brothers. The communists want to change the very essence of the Russian soul, to impose on it the idea of egotism, the idea of "everyone for himself".</p>
   <p>The Independents (the members of RNzOV) are not concerned only with themselves. In the persons of their best representatives, in the persons of their most <pb facs="5423967_4_0526.jpg" n="5"/>advanced and active members, they want to serve others, to work for the benefit of the whole Russian colony in America.</p>
   <p>"Here, in a strange land, we in particular should help one another, should unite into one fraternal family," says Bernov in his article. United and strong around RNzOV, we shall remain strong; we shall do more good and we shall be able to help those of our brothers who need our help the most. While doing this we will all be happier and our lives will be fuller and more enjoyable. Though our path may be thorny at times and our cross heavy to bear, yet the end of our earthly journey will be happier. When we lie dying, we will smile when others weep at our death...</p>
   <p>We should all be united. Among the Independents, there are many devoted individuals who are always ready to perform a good deed, to serve the people's cause. It is the duty of every Russian to help them, to inspire them with courage, to give them spiritual support. For his own good, every Russian should join the ranks of RNzOV, should join this fraternal organization and <pb facs="5423967_4_0527.jpg" n="6"/>do his share for the good of his own people in a strange country, America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
