<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1926-08-27">August 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A Live Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0643</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0643.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1926-08-27">August 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A LIVE WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The author of this article relates how he passed a Sunday in the midst of a very interesting society in the far northwest part of Chicago. In a beautiful and dry place where six or seven years ago there was only a desert and prairies, now, as by magic, there appeared a new and clean district of twenty or thirty blocks. Not so long ago here in the district of Wellington Park appeared our Russian home owners who deserted the filthy and suffocating places of the South Side and of Maxwell Street, the early nests of the Russian-Jewish colonization. A simple reason attracted the Russian people to the new place. Comparatively inexpensive lots, fresh air, and convenient transportation made this place ideal. Today we have many Russian homes in that district, homes that are clean, cheerful and new. Last Sunday there was a gathering of our colonists in the home of an old settler, Peter Babylo. It was the first meeting of its kind in that district; a meeting called for <pb facs="5423967_4_0644.jpg" n="2"/>for the purpose of forming a school committee with the aim of opening a school for Russian children. A temporary committee was elected, which decided to lay a foundation for a permanent school committee that would open a school dedicated to the memory of I. A. Krylov. It was also decided to organize a children's chorus and orchestra. Every decision was made without any opposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
