<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-13">Feb. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Bolshevik Agents Among the Dukhobors</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-13">Feb. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">BOLSHEVIK AGENTS AMONG THE DUKHOBORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During recent weeks Rassviet has received many letters from the Dukhobors in Canada, revealing the Bolshevik danger. According to these letters, the peace and tranquillity of the Dukhobors are now endangered by intensive Red propaganda conducted within the settlement by the Soviet agents and provocateurs hiding behind the guise of true friends of the order.</p>
   <p>As a result of this propaganda, a most serious situation arose among the members of the colony. There had been disagreements and even disorders among the Dukhobors in the past, but they were, so to speak, of a family character and were easily settled, as the Dukhobors are traditional lovers of peace and Christian life, which characteristics they inherited from their Dukhobor ancestors in Russia. Now, however, the situation has become worse, for some of the members of the settlement have become infected with the Bolshevik poison, with the result that they now renounce the fundamental <pb facs="5423967_4_1077.jpg" n="2"/>principles of their order and their heretofore noble conduct, and begin to hate their brothers with unrestrained hate, as though they were their worst enemies. These lamentable conditions in the Dukhobor colonies in Canada are the direct outcome of the insidious, underground work of the Soviet agents, whose goal is the destruction of the Dukhobor colonies. These criminal Bolshevik elements work both secretly and openly among the groups and among the individuals of the Dukhobor community. They do not allow anything to keep them from sowing the seeds of hate, enmity and internal strife among the members of the Dukhobor settlements. They want to set brother against brother, children against parents. They are well paid for their criminal work. They are also supplied with sufficient funds for writing and publishing propaganda literature for the use of the Dukhobors. For instance, they publish and distribute, free, among the colony, but especially among the Dukhobor youth, the periodical The Signal. Besides, they flood the settlements with pamphlets, leaflets and appeals of all kinds.</p>
   <p>Very many of the Dukhobors are constant readers and subscribers of Rassviet, the only publication which honestly and disinterestedly defends their interests <pb facs="5423967_4_1078.jpg" n="3"/>and guards them against all dangers. For this reason the Bolshevik agents also fight our newspaper. They say to the Dukhobors that Rassviet is edited and published by monarchists, White Guards, and former capitalists, all enemies of the working people. We know that the overwhelming majority of the Dukhobor people know well the real purpose of these provocative lies-- to make it easier for the Soviet agents to get the Dukhobors into the Bolshevik trap. There are a few simple, credulous and stupid members of the Dukhobor community, however, who put their blind trust in these wolves in sheep's clothing, ignorant of the fact that they are being led into an abyss of great misfortune. They do not seem to realize that the principles of the Bolsheviks can no more be joined with those of the Dukhobors than fire can be joined with water. Any member of the colony who accepts Bolshevism as his dogma ceases not only to be a Dukhobor but to be an honest man, and becomes a mere animal. The Bolshevik sympathizers among the Dukhobors do not seem to notice the fact that the same Bolsheviks are cruelly persecuting their brothers in Russia, often punishing them with death, only because they want to lead a Christian life and not be the slaves of the Soviet government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1079.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All the foregoing facts deserve the closest attention on the part of all Dukhobors who are interested in the welfare of their several communities. Now is the time to prevent the downfall and destruction of the magnificent work accomplished by your order during the last several score years. The Bolshevik contamination should be uprooted and destroyed at its source. The Dukhobors should drive from their midst all the agents sent there by the Soviets, with all their propaganda literature. Then they should forget about their differences and work together hand in hand, as is fitting and becoming to true brothers of the Dukhobor cult, for the betterment of their future and for the glory of their high ideals.</p>
   <p>Rassviet has always been and always will be the true friend of the Dukhobors, and will continue to extend aid of every kind to meet the needs of the Dukhobor colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
