<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Russky Golos, date unknown)
<title level="a">Russian Independent Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Russky Golos, date unknown)
<title level="a">RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This organization was organized only about eight months ago, and one marvels at its speedy growth. During this time its membership has grown to over six hundred, and has accomplished very much for progressive development.</p>
   <p>The members of the society elect one of the membership to officiate at church services, and the affairs of the society are looked after by a committee of twelve chosen from among the parishioners.</p>
   <p>The educational work is advancing rapidly and satisfactorily, as a result of the school sponsored by the society, which functions regularly, and has forty students in its Chicago branch, whereas the branch in Argo, a Chicago suburb, has sixty students. During these eight months the <pb facs="5423967_4_0148.jpg" n="2"/>society gave several plays, also several literary-musical evenings with very interesting programs; the profits from these affairs are entirely for the school of this society.</p>
   <p>The most interesting part of the educational work by this society is the attendance of lectures every Sunday, on different topics. Sometimes the lecture is on health, hygiene, or history of Russia, etc., all in popular form, so that the audience, which is frequently quite large, proves by its questions that it is genuinely interested in the subjects of the lectures.</p>
   <p>The local church of St. George enjoys a wide popularity. Not merely the official Russian clergy, but also the progressive-radical elements of the local colony take part in its activities; some of whose representatives help considerably to advance the society by their own efforts and cooperation.</p>
   <p>These progressive elements acknowledge the great usefulness of the <pb facs="5423967_4_0149.jpg" n="3"/>organization because of its comprehensive educational program; and still they see it as yet only a church.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, those who are for the 'Georgians' are of the opinion that this organization is destined to play a decisive part in the life of the Russian colony, not alone in Chicago but in America generally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
