<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-26">July 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Intelligentsia Versus the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-26">July 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE INTELLIGENTSIA VERSUS THE RUSSIAN CONSOLIDATED MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society, whose plan of activities ostensibly embraces all Russians living in America, irrespective of their social backgrounds or their educational qualifications, has actually succeeded in drawing into its fold only a very insignificant number of Russian people in America who belong to the educated class, the so-called intelligentsia.</p>
   <p>The Russian intelligentsia in this country lives its own separate life, has its own interests, and holds itself aloof from the common Russian people, as though afraid of the closer contact with their less educated fellow countrymen.</p>
   <p>One of the activities of the Russian benefit organizations in America is the <pb facs="5423967_4_0737.jpg" n="2"/>cultural and educational work among our people. This type of work is most suitable for our educated men and women who are well acquainted with various branches of science, art, literature, history, etc. Russian literature, especially, has always exerted a profound influence upon the peasants of prerevolutionary Russia. Russian authors and other intellectuals, many of whom were of peasant stock, were very much interested, at that time, in the work of uplifting the common people. They were the true intelligentsia.</p>
   <p>The word "intelligentsia" does not imply, as many think,class distinction or political affiliation. The name "intelligentsia" we usually give to the educated,mentally developed part of society or a nation.</p>
   <p>Here in America our intelligentsia has isolated itself from the common people. After the terrible years of persecution and annihilation suffered at the hands of the Bolshevik revolution, the Russian intelligentsia became more cautious, <pb facs="5423967_4_0738.jpg" n="3"/>more suspicious, and more removed from the common people than it was before the revolution, the revolution which had been long in preparation by the same intelligentsia, and which later became the property of the Bolsheviks and was used as a tool for their own aggrandizement and for the destruction of the intelligentsia. All these misfortunes made the Russian intelligentsia what it is now. But such a state of affairs is not normal and should not be tolerated any longer. The entire attitude of the Russian intelligentsia in the United States to the Russian common people in this country should be changed.</p>
   <p>The Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society is a monpolitical organization. Anyone may become a member of this organization who complies with its rules and regulations and refrains from any political or religious activity within the organization. For these reasons it would seem natural to suppose that the intelligentsia would willingly and gladly join such an organization, and work together hand-in-hand with former peasants and workers. Actually, however, we <pb facs="5423967_4_0739.jpg" n="4"/>see that only a very small number of Russian intelligentsia have joined the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society or any other organization composed of former Russian peasants.</p>
   <p>At least one of the important reasons why our intelligentsia habitually shun our people's organizations is the fact that some of the leaders of these organizations are incorrigible demagogues who indulge, whenever and wherever possible, in their anti-intelligentsia propaganda. These pseudo-intellectuals, without formal training, but having acquired a spattering of oratory, are trying to denounce and bespatter the intelligentsia by calling them the intellectual self-seekers who should keep away from the peasants' organizations. Such an attitude on the part of some of our leaders is not only cruel and unjust to our intelligentsia, but it is harmful to the Russian cause in America.</p>
   <p>The question of the Russian intelligentsia in this country versus the Russian organizations should be answered once and for all by drawing the intelligentsia <pb facs="5423967_4_0740.jpg" n="5"/>into our ranks. The whole Russian group in America would derive great benefits from this union of the intelligentsia and the common people, with both groups the sons and daughters of one country--Russia.</p>
   <p>This problem should be included among the matters to be discussed and decided at the forthcoming convention of the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society, and should also be discussed at the conventions of other Russian organizations in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
