<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
            <date when="1923-10-11">10/11/23</date>.
<title level="a">The New Russian Emigrants.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1731</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1731.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia, (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>,
<date when="1923-10-11">10/11/23</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW RUSSIAN EMIGRANTS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last years there have come to the chief centers of America, to New York and Chicago, many new Russian emigrants.</p>
   <p>Formerly, there used to come from Russia to these cities mostly farmers and workers seeking employment, and a small percentage of persons who had been persecuted in Russia because of their political and religious views.</p>
   <p>At present, another class of people is coming; ex-officers, former officials, artists, persons belonging to the liberal professions and students.</p>
   <p>The majority of these people come not directly from Russia, but from those countries to which they had fled during the revolution and the civil war.</p>
   <p>Among these persons there are many former members of the nobility, who could not be reconciled with the new regime and who dream of revolutions and plots.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1732.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are also many such as have broken with everything that is going on the other shore of the ocean. These people have lost faith in the possibility of new revolutions. They have passed through all kinds of hardships during their travels across Europe, have suffered much, have experienced a kind of rebirth and have come to this country seeking only a peaceful life and work.</p>
   <p>There are also many persons of plebeian origin, persons who have come to foreign countries accidentally; they did not participate in any civil wars; they have occupied a neutral position and have fled from Russia, having been scared by the thunder of the revolution.</p>
   <p>Among all this mass of new emigrants there are many people who can be very useful to the Russian-American colony.</p>
   <p>Among them there are teachers, physicians, engineers, artists.</p>
   <p>Till now, the Russian colony has been poor in representatives of the intelligentsia. There was felt a distinct lack of such persons; and the colony is still feeling this lack.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1733.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Russian colony must take advantage of the presence in its midst of such educated and intelligent emigrants. Among them there are undoubtedly many who are willing to use the hours of leisure for rendering service to their countrymen.</p>
   <p>These new emigrants have come to this country, being yet full of energy and desiring to work.</p>
   <p>The presence of the best among them is already being felt in some cities as they are participating in the public life.</p>
   <p>Let us help such persons to establish themselves here, in America, and let us try to put to good use their experience and their knowledge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
