<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Approaching Debate</title><title level="a" type="sub">by L. K--ov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE APPROACHING DEBATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by L. K--ov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who from among the Russians in Chicago does not remember numerous challenges issued by the Chicago Communists to various organizations or even to individuals? When such challenges were not accepted the Communists boasted that everybody was afraid to debate the issues with them, for they alone knew the truth.</p>
   <p>Some courageous people, however, picked up their challenge, and thus Branch 18 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society will debate the burning problems with representatives of the Russian National Mutual Aid Society, Branch 35 of which is dominated by Bolsheviks. The committees appointed by both sides to make the necessary arrangements had their first meeting on March 10. The meeting took place in the Bolshevik hall on Division Street.</p>
   <p>The question of how to divide the proceeds, if there is any money left after <pb facs="5423967_4_0744.jpg" n="2"/>the expenses had been covered, proved to be the most difficult one to adjust. The representatives of the Branch 18 proposed that the money thus left over be equally divided between the debating sides. The Bolshevik side did not agree to this proposal. Their representatives insisted that the excess money should be donated to the committee which was organized for the purpose of helping victims of the German Nazis, or be sent to the Committee for Mooney's Defense in California. Representatives of Branch 18 rejected these proposals on the ground that both of these organizations are Bolshevik-controlled, and that the committees use the money collected by them not for helping people but for Bolshevik propaganda purposes. Branch 18 of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society says that its members do not need the money, and if the proceeds are divided they will turn over their share to the schools for Russian children which are maintained by their society. Their members declare that the debate is being arranged not with the aim of making money but for the purpose of enlightening the Russian people in Chicago on the conditions under which the people live in Russia. For this reason the controversy as to who shall get the rabbit which has not even been killed seems quite absurd.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0745.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Two whole hours were taken up in the discussion and finally, after all attempts at agreement had failed, committee members from both sides decided to close the meeting and renew the deliberations next Sunday, March 17, at 10 o'clock in the morning. At this point, a motion was made to send all the money left above expenses to Tom Mooney direct and not through the Defense Committee. To every spectator's surprise the motion was seconded and approved by the committee on arrangements.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
