<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the opinion of Mr. Moravsky the present Russian colony consists mostly of naturalized Russian-American citizens and is a permanent settlement in Chicago. Mr. Moravsky doubts very much whether any number of them would want to return to their native land if given the opportunity. It is very interesting to note, Mr. Moravsky thinks, that the Russian Colony in Chicago of today is a mixture of different Slavic nationalities and is not pure Russian. He gives the following reason: Most of the Russians who came to Chicago prior to the revolution of 1917 were single males who emigrated to the United States in search of better living conditions. Very few women came to the shores of America in years gone by. Most of those newcomers after settling in Chicago, with the oncoming of the revolution of 1917 have found it very difficult to return to Russia, and made up their minds to remain here as permanent citizens. A majority have been naturalized.</p>
   <p>Inter-marriages have played a big part in the life of the Russian in Chicago. Not finding his own nationality of the opposite sex, he was forced to inter-marry with other Slavic nationalities such as: Poles, Bohemians, Rumanians, Czecho-Slavakians, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
