<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novoye Russkoye Slovo</title>, New York,
<date when="1937-08-31">Aug. 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Committee for Relief to Russians in Far East</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novoye Russkoye Slovo</title>, New York,
<date when="1937-08-31">Aug. 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITTEE FOR RELIEF TO RUSSIANS IN FAR EAST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Telegram to Cordell <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ull; Bishop Leonty</p>
   <p>and others Join Committee; Call upon</p>
   <p>All Russians in America; Letter</p>
   <p>from Chicago to Novoye Russkoye Slovo</p>
   <p>The Chicago Russian colony finally has taken up the task of helping their compatriots in the Far East.</p>
   <p>In spite of the hot weather, a great crowd came to the hall of the Russian-American Citizens Organization, where people continued to arrive even after the meeting was over.</p>
   <p>The Meeting was presided by N. S. Gribov, who opened it with greetings</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>from Right Reverend <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Bishop of Chicago and Minneapolis. Dr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> G. Pertsov was delegated by the Bishop to act on his behalf and express is desire to participate in the movement to help the Russians in the Far East. After Doctor Pertsov, the floor was taken by a representative of St. Trinity Brotherhood, who called upon all present to help the Russians in the Far East.</p>
   <p>The chairman read a letter from Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Russian Citizens Organization of Pittsburg, Pa. In <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>etter the Pittsburg organization paid due respect to the initiative taken by "the highly honored Chicago colony," calling upon all other Russian <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> follow this good example, and expressing the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that all Russian-American citizen organizations will act hand in hand in this matter, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to convene together.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The floor as <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <p>The speaker dwelt <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> on the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> organization headed by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> chief, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, by the Bureau on Immigrant's Affairs, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> General <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, and by the Fascist party under Rodzaevsky. He also spoke <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> carried on in 1936 by the Russian immigrants against the outrages of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> organization, which had put itself at the service of the Japanese. The striking feature <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> speech was its appeal to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> conscience, Russians solidarity, and to compassion towards others, particularly towards those who need our brotherly help. He pointed put that Russians in the United States enjoy more freedom live more comfortably and are better fed than in any other country. He said, "At this very time, when you enjoy life, free of care, thousands of</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0270.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>our compatri<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ts are living in fear of shells bursting over their <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, amidst <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and callapsing <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>nes and under the incessant rattling of machine-gun fire and rifle volleys. They do not know what will happen the next hour the next <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>inute, the next moment. They are deprived of everything, shelter, food, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>rotection."</p>
   <p>The speaker reminded his listeners of the fact that they were lucky to be in Chicago instead of in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> "for," he said, "you night have been in their places, too. Your children, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ives, and parents would have been waiting for a miracle to happen in the form of aid that would never come. Just think what a terrible thing it is to be for<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>otten in the fires of burning cities, without shelter, your child dying in your arms, seeing privileged parents take their children with loving care aboard a ship to safety, all before your eyes. What a feeling of despondency when the little ones ask why they are not taken also to safety, when you have</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0271.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>to tell them that it is because "we are Russians"!</p>
   <p>Lebedev's speech was interrupted <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and then by applause, but at this point a roar arose from the audience. He continued, "In the souls of our victimized children the word 'Russian' sounds like a curse.</p>
   <p>"And since nobody but ourselves can help the children and women in Shanghai, let us go to their rescue, it is only through the cement of Russian solidarity at a time such as this, that we will be able to revive public sentiment, save the Russian name, and fulfill our duty towards Russia and humanity."</p>
   <p>Mr. Lebedev's speech produced a strong impression, an impression further driven home by the next speaker, Mr. I. F. Erin, secretary of the Russian-American Citizens Organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0272.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Erin motioned that a telegram be sent to Secretary of State Cordell Hull. The motion was carried unanimously.</p>
   <p>After a short recess, during which dollar bills were showered on the chair-man's table to cover administrative expenses of the movement to aid the Russians in the Far East, the meeting went on to name a committee, the members of which are Attorney A.J. Pikiel, president of the Russian-American Citizens Organization; J.F. Erin, a member of the Board of R.I.M.A.S: J. V. Osipik, chairman of the Third Branch of R.I.M.A.S: Mrs. Zenovia Leshchuk, chairman of the meeting; N.S. Gribov, and Dr. L.G. Pertsov.</p>
   <p>V.I, Lebedev excused himself from serving in the committee, stating that he was here on a visit and had to leave Chicago in a few days. He promised, however, his full cooperation in Europe and in other Russian centers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0273.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Those assembled expressed a desire to have <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ishop Leonty as honorary chairman and Col. George Voevodsky, a prominent worker among Americans, as honorary member.</p>
   <p>Appeal to the Organizations</p>
   <p>A resolution having been adopted that the Committee send an appeal to all public organizations in America and to all individuals willing to cooperate in this noble cause, the Novoye Russkoye Slovo was happy to do its part in conveying this appeal to all its readers.</p>
   <p>All desiring to cooperate in or render financial aid to the movement to aid the Russians in the Far East, are requested to communicate with the secretary of the committee, Dr. L. G. Pertsov (L.G.Percy, M.D.), 25 East Washington St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0274.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The desire was expressed to include the question <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> helping the Russians in the Far East in the agenda of the next annual convention of two of the largest Russian organizations in America, the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society and the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, in order that those organizations, as well as others in sympathy with this cause send petitions to the Government of the United States.</p>
   <p>A resolution to appeal to large America organizations, such as the YMCA, was <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Delegates were appointed to deliver copies of the resolutions and telegrams to the American press. A telegram, signed by the members of the newly elected committee and by <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Leonty and Col. George Voevodsky, to the Secretary of State Cordell Hull.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0275.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Church Services</p>
   <p>Religious people suggested that churches held special services on Sundays, so that they night pray to God to protect the Russians in the Far East.</p>
   <p>The task that Fate has thrown on the lap of the Chicago Russian colony is a heavy one, and we sincerely hope it will be chared in common by all Russian colonies in America.</p>
   <p>A provisional committee of representatives from other cities would eventually give rise to an organization including all the Russian colonies in America.</p>
   <p>It is quite understood that all documents in connection with the movement were forwarded by the committee to the League of Nations and to Nansen's Office, as well as to all Russian friendly organizations in Europe.</p>
   <p>L. Pertsov</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
