<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-08-06">August 6, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">What Can Excursions Give Us?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-08-06">August 6, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT CAN EXCURSIONS GIVE US?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On July 21, 1929, the Society "Knowledge" arranged an excursion to a model farm. The excursionists spent at the farm five hours. During that time a special guide given by the farm showed them the machines, the whole household, and the agricultural implements. The work of the machines was demonstrated to the excursionists.</p>
   <p>They were also shown the kitchen, the dining room, the laundry and some other rooms where some girls demonstrated to them some machinery and gave them detailed explanations and also willingly answered all their questions.</p>
   <p>The excursionists were also shown model poultry coops and pens and buildings for cattle.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0869.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All these buildings are erected according to the newest patterns, and improved methods are used for raising and feeding of the cattle and poultry. The work of the electrical motors was also demonstrated: how they unload the hay from the wagon racks into the lofts, and how the stalks of corn are cut into small pieces and then pressed, giving a very good feed for the cattle. On this farm one can see the best patters of agricultural machines and implements given to us by the technique of the 20th century. The next excursion will be to the Natural Science Museum, and will be managed by Mrs. N. A. Birsky. Thus the Russians of Chicago will have a good opportunity to become well acquainted with this museum. The excursion committee has resolved to ask Mrs. N. A. Birsky to give a lecture on the subject, on August 22, 1929, at 1902 W. Division Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
