<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-05-14">May 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Independents Throw Nikolaiuk Out</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-05-14">May 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENTS THROW NIKOLAIUK OUT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Chadovich was chairman of the convention of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, RNzOV, which opened last Saturday and ended Sunday evening. Mr. Sabinsky and Mr. Gapanovich were elected to the presidium. The convention was very successful and accomplished what it had set out to do. Mr. A. Pasiuk was elected president in place of Mr. Volos, the incumbent, who had resigned from the position after declining to accept renomination. Mr. N. Kozak was elected permanent secretary, and Messrs. Dziayko, Volodkin, Suatikova, Bernov, Erin, Volos, Vdovich, Zhogalsky, Parada, Yushko, Sabinsky, and Piatnitza were chosen to be directors.</p>
   <p>There was one unpleasant incident, particularly for the Bolsheviks. The convention of RNOV [Translator's note: Russian People's Mutual Aid Society], which had just closed its sessions in New York, had sent its delegate to the <pb facs="5423967_4_0940.jpg" n="2"/>convention in the person of Mr. Nikolaiuk, a member of the Central Committee. Mr. Nikolaiuk was to greet RNzOV's delegates and to tie a knot of "closer friendship" with the members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, and to establish over them the dictatorship of Deviatkin and his clique.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nikolaiuk received a very chilly reception from the delegates. The convention unanimously refused to honor his credentials and rejected his request to have the floor in order to explain his position. When the uninvited delegate protested, he was bodily thrown out of the auditorium by the doormen.</p>
   <p>"We want no such guest delegates," shouted the delegates.</p>
   <p>A detailed account of the proceedings of the convention will be given in the succeeding issues of Rassviet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0941.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: RNOV is a mutual aid society with strong Bolshevik leanings. For a number of years, it has attempted, by boring from within, to capture control of RNzOV, an organization similar in character but very strongly opposed to Bolshevism.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
