<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-02-14">Feb. 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Fiftieth Anniversary of F. M. Dostoyevsky's Death</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-02-14">Feb. 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF F. M. DOSTOYEVSKY'S DEATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Feb. 10th was the fiftieth anniversary of the death of F. M. Dostoyevsky, one of the greatest, world renowned Russian writers. In Soviet Russia they probably did not bring this fact to the attention of the people, since the ruling party has not entered Dostoyevsky's name on the list of the celebrated proletarian writers; and the Russian cultural circles are forbidden to mention this day, because in Russia free speech and free praise does not exist.</p>
   <p>But in the Russian colonies abroad, this day will now pass unnoticed. Lectures and soirees in memory of Dostoyevsky are given in many European and American cities; because every Russian knows that at the present time, neither in Russia nor in other countries, are to be found such writers as Dostoyevsky. He occupied a place equal to that of Tolstoy, not only in Russian literature, but in the literature of the world. The difference between Tolstoy and Dostoyevsky was only in that Tolstoy paved more attention to the purely literary and artistic aspect of his books, while Dostoyevsky was more concerned with the secret workings of the human soul.</p>
   <p>Tolstoy is a great master of words, while Dostoyevsky is one of the greatest psychologists. Dostoyevsky does not belong either to the reactionaries or to the revolutionists, as these terms are usually understood. Yet he was inimical <pb facs="5423967_4_0919.jpg" n="2"/>to the Czar's autocracy and was sentenced to death, as one who belonged to Petrashevsky's socialist circle and found guilty of having read a letter written to Gogol by Byelinsky, at a meeting of this circle. (Note: A letter in which the celebrated Russian critic Byelinsky violently attacked Gogol's reactionary views. D.S.) Capital punishment was, however, commuted in the case of Dostoyevsky to penal servitude. He lived on an island among inveterate criminals; but even in such degraded beings, he discovered a human soul.</p>
   <p>His book, "The House of the Dead", convinced us that among the so-called "criminals" are to be found some honest and noble persons who had become criminals only because they lived under a corrupt social order. Dostoyevsky did not side with the ruling classes; nor did he sympathize with the "idle torturers of the serfs"; but he did side with the insulted and humiliated.</p>
   <p>All his best books, such as "Crime and Punishment", "The Brothers Karamazov", "The Humiliated and Insulted", and others, were dedicated to the suffering of these people. In his writings, he severely lashed the rich landowners who dispised and mal-treated the serfs enslaved by them. He likewise denounced all other tyrants and oppressors of the Russian people</p>
   <p>At the same time, he was unmercifully attacked by revolutionists who wished to overthrow ore evil in order to put in its place another, substituting a new <pb facs="5423967_4_0920.jpg" n="3"/>social order based on violence, for the old one.</p>
   <p>Such revolutionists were vividly described by Dostoyevsky in his "The Possessed" This novel proved to be prophetic. In this novel, Dostoyevsky foresaw the appearance of bolshevism, and his characters very closely resemble contemporary Russian Bolsheviks who desired to enforce "liberty" on the Russian people by decree, imitating Dostoyevsky's "Grand Inqusistor and "Shigalev".</p>
   <p>Dostoyovsky was one of the greatest lovers of freedom, not only in spiritual, but in social life also. For this reason, he said, "Voluntary evil is better than compulsory good. Voluntary restriction of freedom is better than compulsory freedom, and voluntary hell is better than compulsory paradise."</p>
   <p>Holding such views, he did not respect the revolutionists who wished to "liberate" mankind by violent methods, driving the people into the "socialist paradise" with clubs and whips, as is done now by the Bolsheviki.</p>
   <p>Dostoyevsky was the greatest scrutinizer of human souls. His books are studied by writers, psychologists, and jurists, who wish to learn more about the soul of man. Therefore, it is no wonder that overywhere on any best book" list occur the titles of Dostoyevsky's books.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0921.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dostoyevsky was one of the greatest Russian writers, and an unsurpassed judge of Russian souls and Russian types, and herein lie his power and lofty grandeur.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
