<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>The Russian-American Educational Association its Objects, Program of Activities and Policy</title>
      <title level="a">Leaflet published</title>
      <date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>
      <title level="a" type="sub">Chicago, Ill.</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN EDUCATIONAL ASSOCIATION ITS OBJECTS, PROGRAM OF ACTIVITIES AND POLICY</title>
     <title level="a">Leaflet published</title>
     <date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>
     <title level="a" type="sub">Chicago, Ill.</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The objects of the Russian-American Educational Association are:</p>
   <p>1. To promote friendly relations, mutual confidence, good will and understanding between Russia and America.</p>
   <p>2. To render Russia practical aid and cooperation in the great work of rehabilitation and reconstruction in which she is engaged at the present time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0407.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To attain these objects the Russian-American Educational Association has set before itself and will endeavor to carry out the following program of activities:</p>
   <p>1. To provide the means and opportunities for Russians in America who desire to return to Russia to acquire the necessary training and proficiency in some special line of work to be applied later for the benefit of Russia.</p>
   <p>2. To assist Russians in America who have acquired the necessary training and proficiency in some special line of work to return to Russia and help them to get employment there in the line of work for which they are best qualified.</p>
   <p>3. To provide all Russians in America with the means and opportunities to acquire a general education in the English language, history of America <pb facs="5423967_4_0408.jpg" n="3"/>and other subjects that would help them get acquainted with this country, its language, history, laws, institutions, conditions, possibilities, and aspirations.</p>
   <p>4. To establish connections and centers of activity and influence among the Russians who have returned to Russia from America to promote the objects of the Association.</p>
   <p>5. To provide facilities and opportunities for Russians who go abroad to take up some special study or acquire proficiency in some special line of work, to induce them to come to this country for the above mentioned purposes.</p>
   <p>6. To provide facilities and opportunities for Americans to travel in Russia, study conditions there, and get acquainted with the country and its <pb facs="5423967_4_0409.jpg" n="4"/>people and assist the Russians in some direction as far as this country is concerned.</p>
   <p>7. To establish special commissions in both countries to gather the necessary date and information and to carry on special research work to promote the objects of the Association.</p>
   <p>8. To carry on a systematic general publicity and educational work to further and promote the objects of the Association.</p>
   <p>The Russian-American Educational Association is a strictly non-political, educational organization.</p>
   <p>The Russian-American Educational Association includes within the scope of its activities and interests Russia and America and invites and <pb facs="5423967_4_0410.jpg" n="5"/>shall welcome within its membership citizens of both countries who endorse and pledge themselves to aid in furthering and promote the objects of the Association.</p>
   <p>All who desire to get further information regarding the Association are asked to apply for it at the following places:</p>
   <p>Club of the Society "Enlightenment"</p>
   <p>1115 N. Robey St.</p>
   <p>The Russian Club "Znanie"</p>
   <p>731 W. 18th St.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Preparatory School</p>
   <p>3317 W. 12th St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0411.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Dr. Moses Sahud,</p>
   <p>President</p>
   <p>Ivan Erin,</p>
   <p>Vice-President</p>
   <p>Nicholas Klekner,</p>
   <p>Treasurer</p>
   <p>Julius Wulbert,</p>
   <p>Secretary and Organizer</p>
   <p>Note: - This Association was in existence for about two years. N. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
