<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>
      <date when="1923-07-21">7/21/23</date>
      <title level="a">Why Are People Not Permitted to Enter Russia?</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>
     <date when="1923-07-21">7/21/23</date>
     <title level="a">WHY ARE PEOPLE NOT PERMITTED TO ENTER RUSSIA?</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL)</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the two last weeks there have been published in our paper declarations of the Society of Technical Aid to Soviet Russia and of the empowered delegate of the Commissariat of Foreign Affairs about the closing of the Russian border to single individuals. Only organized groups are allowed to go to Russia. Single individuals have to get special permits.</p>
   <p>We do not agree with the protests against such restrictions-protests made without sufficient reasons by the enemies of Soviet Russia. We understand that all this is done in order to prevent accidents that may happen to single individuals, and all kinds of hardships with which such persons are liable to meet. We understand that it is difficult at present for a person who has been living abroad to live in Russia, and that only organized groups which have provided themselves with machinery can get a decent living there. We understand also that the government apprehends that harmful elements--white guards--may enter Russia.</p>
   <p>But, all the same, we do not agree with this non-admittance of single individuals <pb facs="5423967_4_1310.jpg" n="2"/>to Russia.</p>
   <p>Only persons who are definitely known to be harmful elements--such as white guards and persons who are conducting an agitation harmful to the interests of Soviet Russia--should not be allowed to enter the confines of Russia.</p>
   <p>Everybody else should be granted the perfect freedom to return to his native country.</p>
   <p>The workman, the farmer or the educated man who yearns to go back to Russia and is not afraid of hardships cannot do any harm to Russia. On the contrary, such persons can be only useful.</p>
   <p>We hold that every Russian citizen has the full and inalienable right to return to his native country.</p>
   <p>According to our firm conviction the Soviet government commits a grave mistake by not allowing single individuals to return to Russia.</p>
   <p>The Russian American Colony must demand that its members should get permits to return <pb facs="5423967_4_1311.jpg" n="3"/>to Russia without meeting with all kinds of obstacles.</p>
   <p>We had to meet enough obstacles under the Tsar's regime. It is about time now to remove these obstacles. We must request that. We must demand it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
