<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1922-11-20">Nov. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Fighting Famine</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Russian Section Dsr)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-11-20">Nov. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FIGHTING FAMINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Russian Section DSR)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comrades! Russian immigrants!</p>
   <p>There are millions of Russian orphans -- 600,000 in Povoloszhye, 400,000 in the Ukraine. They are in urgent need of immediate assistance.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of emaciated little hands are stretched out to us from across the ocean, from the distant, yet dear homeland of ours.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of little eyes turn to us with childish prayers for help.</p>
   <p>"Khly-e-bush-ka (breadie)," beg these unfortunate children.</p>
   <p>Can we, the well-fed, well-dressed and in good shoes, remain indifferent <pb facs="5423967_4_0387.jpg" n="2"/>to this heart-rendin cry from the children of our unforgettable comrades who fell in an unselfish strife for the future happiness of mankind?</p>
   <p>Shall we refuse bread to the orphaned Russian children, our children? The maintenance per child in the homes which we are now building in Russia will amount to two dollars per month. The initial equipment, with clothing, underwear, books and sundries, amount to $5 per child. Thus for the adoption of one child it is necessary to make the initial payments of $7, with subsequent payments of $2 monthly.</p>
   <p>In this wise, each one of you, comrades, by paying two dollars per month will save the life of one orphan, providing regularly food and shelter for the child.</p>
   <p>Do not take upon your conscience, comrades, the perishing of these unfortunate to Russian orphans. Fill out the enclosed blank, and together <pb facs="5423967_4_0388.jpg" n="3"/>with your contribution send it to the following address:</p>
   <p>Russian Section DSR: I, the undersigned, with the object of adopting.... orphans.... in Soviet Russia, am contributing the sum here enclosed, and am, besides, obligating myself to contribute monthly towards their support.....dollars.</p>
   <p>Then follows name, street address, city and state of donor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
