<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title level="a">Origin and History of the Russian Seventh-Day Adventist Church in Chicago (In Manuscript)</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">By S. G. Burley</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title level="a">ORIGIN AND HISTORY OF THE RUSSIAN SEVENTH-DAY ADVENTIST CHURCH IN CHICAGO (IN MANUSCRIPT)</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">By S. G. Burley</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the summer of 1917, the writer had opportunity to speak in the Russian Baptist Church whose pastor was the son of Mrs. Fannie Lesesky, a present member of the Russian Seventh-day Adventist Church. It was through this contact that an interest was started. A little more than one year later the Bureau of Home Missions arranged with the North Dakota and the Illinois Conferences to give Brother Burley an opportunity to start a Russian effort in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>By hard work and much prayer in two years a church was organized in this large city of Chicago. We must give credit to the Russian Department of Broadview College in helping to conduct evangelistic endeavor among the Russian speaking people. Mr. A.G. Yakovenko and Miss Anna Evanenko, two students of the above mentioned department rendered efficient service during 1919 in this work. Credit is also due to the Illinois Conference for moral and financial support <pb facs="5423967_4_1152.jpg" n="2"/>of this effort, for it was through the help of this Conference that Miss Evanenko became a Bible worker during 1920, the year this church was organized.</p>
   <p>Through the friendship of Mr. Yakovenko with Mr. Artimenko and Alex Samarchuk's family - both Sabbath keepers from Russia,- there was opened the opportunity for Reverend Burley to labour with them and win them to become members of the church, and through them to win others.</p>
   <p>At the close of another evangelistic endeavor, June 19, 1920, the church was organized by A. J. Clark, the president of the Chicago Conference, and the writer. The charter members numbered twenty-six. Mrs. Sam Krevoshen, nee Rosa Sitch, and Mrs. Anton Baybarz, nee Anna Evanenko as Bible and Christian workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1153.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As a means of strengthening this organization, the following religious education was carried on in the church:- primary, junior, and senior Sabbath-school classes were conducted, young people's endeavor, under the name of Missionary Volunteers, and a men's Bible class. The church continued to grow from year to year spiritually and financially.</p>
   <p>In December, 1922, Reverend Burley left for Europe. The good work went on with Bro. Koliadko as a Bible worker and Bro. Yakovenko of Broadview as one of the leaders. It was during this time that six new members were added to the church, and seven more by letter. In the fall of 1929 the depression came and compelled sixteen members to leave Chicago, two to Canada, one to New York, and thirteen to Virginia. The sudden change from prosperity to depression made itself felt in the small company of eleven who were left in Chicago. The writer, then returned from Europe, and connected with Broadview College, was again asked to take charge of this little company. With his divided duties, teaching in the College, and translating for the Pacific <pb facs="5423967_4_1154.jpg" n="4"/>Press Publishing Company in Brookfield, it was impossible to give full time to the pastoral work. But with help of the Russian students, as much as they could with their heavy school program, this small church has lived through these five years of hard times and come out victorious. Most of the young people and children have been saved to this church.</p>
   <p>Three persons of varied experiences have also been brought into the church fellowship, Brother Torlik who is eighty-six years old, and who was a charter member of the Russian Catholic Cathedral here in Chicago; Bro. Dvoinan (deceased) who used to be interested in Socialism and Communism; and Sister Harvey who was brought up in this faith from her youth, but who left it very young, and was found through Sister Bonderchuk in her Harvest Ingathering work, and joined the church. Before leaving the charge of this church in October, 1935, we received into church fellowship Mrs. Zdanovitch and Mrs. Chipel. In the same month 1935, the charge was taken by Reverend George Hmelevsky, who is pastor of the church at the present time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
