<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-02-11">Feb. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Around the Colony. a Discussion of Russia</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-02-11">Feb. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">AROUND THE COLONY. A DISCUSSION OF RUSSIA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of the recognition of Russia is being earnestly discussed at present in America.</p>
   <p>Much attention is given to this question in the newspapers and the magazines. It is being discussed also at meetings of various organizations. and these meetings attract large crowds.</p>
   <p>Some express the view that Russia should be recognized without any delay, and that friendly relations with our native country should be restored. Others oppose this view.</p>
   <p>For us, Russian emigrants living in America, this question is particularly interesting.</p>
   <p>With the exception of a small group of fanatical persons holding <pb facs="5423967_4_0688.jpg" n="2"/>ultra-conservative views, we all, both those who are violent enemies of the Communists, and those who are friends of the Soviet regime, desire that Russia should be recognized as soon as possible. The resumption of diplomatic relations with Russia will undoubtedly have a beneficent influence on its economic life and on the life of many Russian emigrants residing in America.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, at the Olympic Theatre, the Chicago Forum arranges a discussion of the following theme: "Should Russia be recognized?"</p>
   <p>The first speaker will be the well known American journalist, Captain Paxon Hibben. He will speak in favor of the recognition of Russia. The Chicago Forum is trying to find a worthy opponent for this speaker.</p>
   <p>Captain Hibben is very well acquainted with Russia and the situation in that country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0689.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Under the tsarist regime Captain Hibben was a member of the diplomatic corps of the Embassy of the United States in Russia. From 1914 to 1917 he was a war correspondent of several newspapers and magazines. During the last five years of his stay in Russia, he was a representative of President Hoover's Relief Administration in Russia.</p>
   <p>His report about Russia should be very interesting and instructive.</p>
   <p>A. Zemetchensky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
