<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-16">July 16, 1924</date>
<title level="a">With the Church People</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(At the Convention of the Chicago Russian Brotherhoods of Mutual Aid)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-07-16">July 16, 1924</date>
<title level="a">WITH THE CHURCH PEOPLE</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(At the Convention of the Chicago Russian Brotherhoods of Mutual Aid)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On July, 1924, there took place the opening of the Convention of the Russian Brotherhoods of Mutual Aid in Chicago and suburbs.</p>
   <p>Many times I have had the opportunity of being present at various meetings, sessions and conventions held in Chicago by Russians.</p>
   <p>I have witnessed many times how Russians got so excited that, without giving a chance to an opponent to elucidate thoroughly his view, they would seize chairs and almost start fighting.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday I got for the first time complete satisfaction from having attended for about two hours the Convention of the members of the Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0116.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What ideal silence, what remarkable order!</p>
   <p>One can safely say that Mr. Putilov, who was the chairman at that meeting, could preside without disgracing the Russians, in any parliament or Soviet of deputies.</p>
   <p>Considerate treatment of each other, politeness and truly brotherly relations between the delegates such was the spirit that reigned at this meeting.</p>
   <p>And you have to take into consideration that more than one hundred persons were present at this convention. The figures of women delegates from Argo, from the South Side Brotherhood, etc., showed like a few bright spots in the crowd of men.</p>
   <p>The women delegates, just like any of the other delegates, were <pb facs="5423967_4_0117.jpg" n="3"/>given the chance to express their views. The audience was listening to them just as attentively as to the other speakers; in certain cases, for instance, when the question of increasing the monthly dues was discussed, the voice of the women even prevailed over that of their opponents, and the majority of the delegates agreed with the views expressed by the women.</p>
   <p>One of the characteristic features of the Mutual Aid Brotherhoods connected with the churches is the way in which the voting is done when a decision concerning some motion has to be arrived at. Even before the hands have been raised and counted one feels what decision will be taken - which motion will be accepted and which will be rejected.</p>
   <p>One would wish that our home-made party talkers and various other chatterers would visit at least one of the meetings of the Mutual Aid Brotherhoods where they could learn how to conduct a meeting decently <pb facs="5423967_4_0118.jpg" n="4"/>and how to talk and act politely.</p>
   <p>And yet at "their" meetings these chatterers revile the members of the brotherhoods, call them "church-goers"; and our smart party men put into this word some disparaging meaning: a "church-goer" means with them one who is not "conscious" - a kind of inferior being.</p>
   <p>Fellow workers, how grievously you are mistaken!</p>
   <p>I have observed closely several times all the delegates who had come to the convention.</p>
   <p>They are more than conscious.</p>
   <p>They realize religiously what great work they have come to do; they <pb facs="5423967_4_0119.jpg" n="5"/>ponder beforehand every word they are going to say, and only after having thoroughly considered everything they come to some well grounded decision.</p>
   <p>You don't hear any shouting, any untoward exclamations.</p>
   <p>All honor is due to those church people, to those hundreds of Russian peasants and workmen who, having settled on alien, American soil, have not forgotten anything pertaining to their native country, and, have at the same time learned many good things from the Americans.</p>
   <p>May the Lord grant you success in the labors you have undertaken.</p>
   <p>Art. Veselovsky</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
