<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-25">June 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to Those Who Return from Soviet Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-25">June 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THOSE WHO RETURN FROM SOVIET RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A successful struggle against the dishonest and intentionally falsified information supplied by the communists regarding the conditions prevailing at present in Soviet Russia, can be waged only in two ways.</p>
   <p>The first way is by careful study of the Soviet press and extraction from it of all authoritative statements, by gathering the factual information presented therein and giving it a wide publicity. One must note with full satisfaction that the Russian and foreign press more and more often resorts to this source, and more and more carefully studies the data supplied by the Soviet papers.</p>
   <p>The second source is more important, and it promises to widen as time goes on. This is the information and data supplied by the foreign communists, and persons of Soviet sympathies who lived and worked in Soviet Russia. The truthful stories told by these people, which are crammed with facts, <pb facs="5423967_4_1373.jpg" n="2"/>present a very vivid picture of the life in Soviet Russia, and they are convincing to the numerous workers' circles which still believe the information concocted in the secret centers of the Communist party in Russia and abroad.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the informative news supplied by those who return from the U. S. S. R. appears only from time to time, and this exceptionally valuable material remains almost unknown to the masses of the working people.</p>
   <p>A few months ago Rassviet printed information to the effect that in Detroit and Chicago an organization is being formed of those who came back from Russia. Since then the news has not been confirmed; it would be very regrettable if the valuable idea has been dropped.</p>
   <p>At present my American friends tell me that among American communists and specialists who have worked in the U. S. S. R. the idea of forming an organization is growing, and they intend to supply truthful information <pb facs="5423967_4_1374.jpg" n="3"/>about the conditions in our native land. If the idea is carried through the newspapers and magazines will be furnished with valuable information at regular intervals.</p>
   <p>At present I request the initiators of such organization, and all those who came back from the U. S. S. R., to get in touch with me by mail and I will supply them with all the necessary information.</p>
   <p>All correspondence will be kept confidential. All names will be withheld from publication. All mail should be addressed to me personally.</p>
   <p>F. Mansvetov</p>
   <p>529 West 186th St.</p>
   <p>New York City, N. Y.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
