<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-17">Jan. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Russian People</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Minin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-17">Jan. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE RUSSIAN PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Minin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers! The hour has struck when we must regain our senses; when we must remember, and look back; when we must analyze the events which occurred in our native country, and among ourselves in America. You were Russians, you lived in Russia, in your own country, in your own home, amid the fields and forests, among your own people. And now you are scattered all over the world, as relics of the past, deceived, broken up, separated.</p>
   <p>Your country is in chains, in slavery. She is a prisoner of war in the hands of a band of usurpers, of bandits, of men strange to you in spirit, with whom you, as Russians, have nothing in common. It is true that quite frequently you find yourselves lacking (through no fault of your own), the knowledge required to distinguish between your enemies and your friends. You lag behind your own people and are ready to follow many charlatans, who will flatter <pb facs="5423967_4_1460.jpg" n="2"/>you cunningly. You place your confidence in them, and they lead you into a blind alley of hatred and enmity. And you hate; you don't fight your enemies, but your friends, just because you misunderstand each other.</p>
   <p>More than seventeen years have passed since Russia began to groan under a terrible oppression. You see and hear the tortures and lamentations of your own country, but you do not see clearly those who torment your people, even though you are among them.</p>
   <p>Shake off the despoilers who attack you; unite with your own brothers. Consolidate your ranks so that you can repel your enemy; regain your country and redeem yourselves in the eyes of your motherland. Restore the independence and freedom of all her sons and daughters, of all the men and women who, at present, are enduring slavery on the collective farms, in the lumber camps, in Siberia, where they are digging canals although they are half-starved, scantily dressed, and overworked.</p>
   <p>Let everyone of us, realizing the misery, aware of the enemy and his crimes, <pb facs="5423967_4_1461.jpg" n="3"/>take upon himself the obligation of devoting all of his strength, skill and spare time to awakening the minds of those who still grope in ignorance, and do not understand deceit; who find themselves influenced by the internationalists, the bolshiviks.</p>
   <p>During this period, it is a crime to sit with folded arms, blind and passive, and permit this crucifixion of our mother, our native land, and all her peoples.</p>
   <p>Over there, everything has been thrown underfoot and has been trampled into mud. And by whom? By a comparatively small clique of international bandits in whom you placed your trust, whom you believed when they pretended that they were your saviors, that they would lead you from darkness into light, that they would make your life abundant and free amid your native fields and forests.</p>
   <p>To remain silent, not to rise in defense of your brothers, your freedom, is to become the accomplices of the perpetrators of violence. By now it must be clear to everybody that we have been deceived, that the noose has been tied <pb facs="5423967_4_1462.jpg" n="4"/>around our neck, and that we are gradually being strangled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
