<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-25">July 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Holy Trinity Parish Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-25">July 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HOLY TRINITY PARISH HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Holy Trinity parish on Leavitt Street held its semiannual meeting Sunday, July 21. The parish executive committee, headed by F. Mikhailovsky, presented the financial report on the activities of the parish during the last six months. Then the cemetery committee offered its report, and other reports followed. All the reports, which had been previously approved by the control committee, were received and accepted by the assembly. Mr. Mikhailovsky, the administrator of the parish, presented his report on the expenditures incurred in the repair of the roof of the parish house, the construction of a new railing around the altar in the church, and the repair of the wooden fence around the parish property. The assembly expressed their thanks to Mr. Mikhailovsky, to the executive committee, and to other committees for their honest and disinterested work in behalf of the parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1051.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The question of enlarging the parish house evoked a lively discussion. It was argued that a larger space in the parish house is needed for the use of the children of the parishioners. A special committee was chosen to study this problem in detail and to make its report at the next, i. e. the annual, meeting.</p>
   <p>The former parish watchman, one Fietchuk, who was dismissed by the executive committee to cut down expenses during the Summer months, has presented the executive committee, through his attorney, with a written complaint demanding the payment of six hundred dollars in back salary, which, according to the complaint, had been withheld by the executive committee. A section of the minutes of the 1933 annual meeting was read in which it was stated that the watchman's salary should be reduced from fifty to twenty-five dollars a month. The meeting decided to institute no action on the complaint. It was resolved to administer an open reproof to Fietchuk for his unprincipled action. The whole scheme was branded as the shameful work of the enemies <pb facs="5423967_4_1052.jpg" n="3"/>conspiring against the parish, for it was they who induced Fietchuk to file the complaint.</p>
   <p>As a result of a suggestion made by the chairman, a collection was taken which netted about twenty dollars. The money will be used to pay for the iron lattice work around the altar of the Holy Trinity Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
