<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-03">Apr. 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Russian-American Democratic League.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-03">Apr. 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC LEAGUE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the absence of the chairman of the Russian-American Democratic League, Mr. V. Kishun, the annual meeting on March 12, 1935, was called to order by I. F. Erin, the vice-chairman. Mr. Erin immediately explained the reasons for Mr. Kishun's absence. In his explanation he said that Mr. Kishun, despite repeated requests by the executive committee to issue a call for the annual meeting for electing new officers, flatly rejected such proposals.</p>
   <p>After such refusals Mr. Kishun was forewarned by the same committee that if he, in his capacity as a chairman, did not issue a call for the meeting, the committee itself would call the meeting on its own initiative. To this warning Mr. Kishun gave no heed.</p>
   <p>But when the executive committee scheduled the annual meeting for March 12, of which action Mr. Kishun was advised by a registered letter and through publication of a notice in the newspaper, Mr. Kishun began to intimidate members over the telephone, and also to threaten members of the executive <pb facs="5423967_4_0747.jpg" n="2"/>committee with dire consequences if they dared to attend the scheduled meeting. Mr. Erin was told by Kishun that he (Kishun) had already hired bums to beat up the vice-chairman. He (Kishun) also threatened the newspaper Rassviet because the paper dared to print the notice without his consent.</p>
   <p>After Erin's report, Mr. Olesiuk was elected chairman of the meeting. Mr. Olesiuk immediately threw the floor open for discussion.</p>
   <p>Speakers were Messrs. Kometsky, Erin, Koper, Nik, Olesiuk, Stankovich, and others. All men spoke favorably of the League's past activity and the usefulness of its continuance. Some speakers suggested extension of the League's activity and enlargement of its Scope.</p>
   <p>The speakers condemned Mr. Kishun's conduct toward members of the League.</p>
   <p>The discussion over, the members selected a new chairman of the League and <pb facs="5423967_4_0748.jpg" n="3"/>new members for the executive committee. In closed balloting for the chairmanship Mr. Kometsky received 24 votes; Bernov, 6 votes; V. Kishun, 1 vote. B. Bernov and S. Karpin were elected vice chairmen. Mr. Beruk was elected secretary and Mr. G. Sambor, assistant secretary.</p>
   <p>During the meeting it was decided to expel Mr. Kishun from membership in the League. Thirty-eight members of various ward organizations attended the meeting.</p>
   <p>The new administration of the League declared that it would divest itself of all responsibility for the conduct of the former chairman of the League, Mr. V. Kishun.</p>
   <p>V. Olesiuk, chairman of the meeting</p>
   <p>M. Koretsky, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
