<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Owned by Dr. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">Statement of I. I. Laveter, of the Socialist Viestnik, 1369 S. California Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Owned by Dr. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">STATEMENT OF I. I. LAVETER, OF THE SOCIALIST VIESTNIK, 1369 S. CALIFORNIA AVENUE, CHICAGO, ILL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist Viestnik has a good many readers. As a representative of this paper I know the majority of its subscribers. I am sure that all of them would be interested in meeting each other and exchanging opinions, and at the same time helping the Socialist Viestnik and the Socialist captives of the Bolshevist regime. We, who live here in more or less satisfactory conditions, did not do a thing, with the exception of four or five comrades who had sent a few thousand marks to ease at least a little the horrible conditions of our comrade fighters against false Communism and real Socialism. Our duty is to help and show them that not all of the Russian emigrants are infected with the Bolshevist disease. I will hope that you will answer this call and will bring your share for the worthy cause. We will meet at the picnic of the Socialist Party at Riverview Park on June 18, at the Lithuanian <pb facs="5423967_4_0436.jpg" n="2"/>section. Ask there for Comrade Grigaytin, the editor of the Lithuanian Social-Democratic paper Naujienos. Try to come and register your protest against the Communist dictatorship over the proletarians. Invite your friends and acquaintances. With greetings,</p>
   <p>I. I. Laveter</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
