<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            Anonymous - 
"<title level="a">Biography of Mr. A. V. Meyerson</title>
<title>Moskva</title>,
    <date when="1930-06">June 1930</date>, p. 10.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>Anonymous - 
"<title level="a">Biography of Mr. A. V. Meyerson</title>
<title>Moscva, (Monthly)</title>,
    <date when="1930-06">June 1930</date>, p. 10.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alexander Vladimirovich Meyerson was born in June 1892, in the city of Astrakhan. Having graduated with honors from the first high school of this city, he entered the Department of Mechanics of the Warsaw Polytechnic Institute, and at the same time attended the classes of the Gatchina School of Aviation.</p>
   <p>Later he went to Baku where he worked for several years in the oil industry. He started as a common laborer, but after some time was entrusted with the position of assistant to the chief engineer. However, he was not satisfied with having attained this responsible position and contemplated becoming a sailor and joining the navy. After graduating as third in rank from a school for naval cadets, Mr. Meyerson was commissioned to serve as an officer on one of the destroyers belonging to a squadron which was cruising in the Black Sea.</p>
   <p>The nerve-racking life on a destroyer in war time, the hardships and dangers of war, and a tragic event in his personal life did not crush Mr. Meyerson's spirit. He continued as an officer of the navy until the time of the occupation of the Crimea by the German and Austrian troops. Later he managed to reach Kiev and served under Hatman, first as a member of the aviation administration, and later as assistant chief of the general staff of the navy. When Kiev fell and was occupied by the troops of Petlara, Mr. Meyerson left for the <pb facs="5423967_4_1681.jpg" n="2"/>southern part of the Crimea where he held various offices, ultimately becoming the head of the administration of the port of Kerch. He held this office until the Crimea had to be evacuated. Sailing from Kerch in his own small schooner, Mr. Meyerson reached Constantinople. There he led a precarious existence, often suffering from hunger, and finally was able to leave for Yugoslavia. Having reached that country, he was forced to work there first as a painter, and later as a teacher, official, public man, exporter and professor.</p>
   <p>Ultimately, Mr. Meyerson came to America. Here he had again to work as a laborer, using the pick and spade, and also to work in various factories. At the same time, he studied at an American university and received two diplomas. He traveled across the United States in an automobile and led again an adventurous life, enduring many hardships, He then came to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Meyerson has already resided three years in Chicago; and during this time he has done much for the Russian colony, working for his favorite idea, the unification of Russian immigrants and their elevation to that position in this country to which they are entitled.</p>
   <p>His lectures and articles, and his work in various organizations have been noticed both by Russians and by Americans. At present, Mr. Meyerson is working intently on his two books which will probably be published in the autumn. He is also a <pb facs="5423967_4_1682.jpg" n="3"/>collaborator on several American and Russian magazines. But in spirit, he is always with our Russian colony, and he devotes all his leisure to work done for the benefit of that colony.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
