<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-05-21">May 21, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Unnecessary Enmity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-05-21">May 21, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">UNNECESSARY ENMITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago there appeared on the pages of the Chicago Tribune an article specially devoted to the consideration of the fact that among the various groups of immigrants there are many cases when some nationality is conducting a campaign against some other nationality.</p>
   <p>And this is true. Germans abuse the French, and Frenchmen, in their turn, pour abuse in their papers on the Germans.</p>
   <p>The Greeks revile the Turks, and the Turks treat the Greeks the same way.</p>
   <p>The Russian newspapers pour abuse on the Poles and the Roumanians, and the Polish and Roumanian papers answer by abusing the Russians. The "red" papers abuse the "whites" who, in turn, say nasty things about the "reds."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All European nations are ready to jump at each other's throats; the immigrants bring with them from Europe their national prejudice and their hatred towards other nationalities and continue to foster them here.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune has expressed the opinion that this should not happen in America, as all nationalities have equal rights here, and so, says this paper, there is no reason for fostering this enmity here.</p>
   <p>It can be easily understood why the Tribune says that; it is an American paper, and it would like that all foreigners would forget their native countries as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Still there is also much truth in what the Tribune has to say about <pb facs="5423967_4_0368.jpg" n="3"/>this matter; it is true that here in America there is no sense in keeping up the enmity between nationalities.</p>
   <p>The Russian papers write often about the bad treatment which the Russians get in Poland and Roumania.</p>
   <p>It is impossible to avoid entirely writing about these things for in these countries are living our brothers, and we cannot be indifferent to their fate; and if the Poles and Roumanians who have seized certain regions act unjustly and cruelly, oppress the population, we naturally cannot praise them for doing this.</p>
   <p>But this is the worst part of it: When we here in America abuse Poland or the Roumanians, the Russians living in Poland and Bessarabia do not get any benefit from our writings.</p>
   <p>What they need is not our abuse, but help.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0369.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We Russians living here should collect money for Russian institutions in Poland, for schools, orphanages and newspapers.</p>
   <p>It would not be so difficult to collect here a few hundred dollars, and it would be a great help for the Russians living in Poland.</p>
   <p>Such help would be a very useful thing indeed. But if all our help consists only in words, if we only abuse those who treat badly our countrymen, and if we do not give them any substantial help at the same time, what benefit do they get from that?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
