<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Help the Disabled Veterans!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HELP THE DISABLED VETERANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago, I received the following letter from the Union of Disabled Russian Veterans Abroad:</p>
   <p>"Dear Father Basil: The Union of Disabled Russian Veterans Abroad again appeals to you in behalf of the unfortunate disabled Russian World War veterans living outside of Russia. This appeal is part of the drive for funds now going on in connection with the tenth annual Disabled Russian Veterans Day.</p>
   <p>"In times of heartbreaking sufferings sent down by fate upon the Russian people in Russia and, in particular, upon the disabled Russian veterans living beyond the Russian border, all Russians living in foreign coutries have shown on frequent occasions their magnanimous spirit in bringing aid to their less fortunate brothers, thus softening their privations and mitigating their misery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Today, in these times of severe economic crisis in almost every country of the world, the situation of all disabled Russian veterans is extremely difficult. They cannot expect aid from anyone except their own countrymen. Therefore, we again call on Russian people to show their sympathy for, and their generosity to, their suffering countrymen. It is our duty to repay our debt to those who did not stint their sacrifices in defense of our common mother country--Russia. Contribute whatever you can and appeal to others to make contributions."</p>
   <p>It is clear from the foregoing letter that the disabled Russian World War veterans are experiencing great economic difficulties, not to mention spiritual suffering which must also be unbearable. They are doomed to a wretched existence which may be mitigated only through our aid.</p>
   <p>Especially we Russians living in America could and should organize to collect substantial aid for those who fought for our common country, Russia, and were <pb facs="5423967_4_0299.jpg" n="3"/>crippled as a result of the war.</p>
   <p>In many cities of the United States, such as New York, San Francisco, Seattle, and Detroit, there are Russian societies especially devoted to the cause of aiding disabled Russian veterans living in foreign countries. In Chicago, however, no such organization has been formed. The Russian people of Chicago and vicinity should not lag behind in this humanitarian work. They, too, should organize a society dedicated to alleviating the need and sorrow of the disabled Russian World War veterans.</p>
   <p>For the purpose of organizing in Chicago an aid society for disabled Russian veterans, a meeting is being called for July 3, at 8 P. M., at the Russian-American Democratic Club, 1902 West Division Street, Chicago. Every Russian man and woman in whose breast beats a noble Russian heart is invited to this meeting. Those who will not be able to attend the meeting, but who desire to help the needy disabled veterans, will be kind enough to mail their <pb facs="5423967_4_0300.jpg" n="4"/>contributions to the fully authorized honorary member of the Union of Disabled Russian Veterans Abroad: The Reverend Basil Anziferov, 1834 North Kedzie Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>As the contributions come in, they will be immediately and fully reported in the local Russian newspapers, so that every contributor may be thanked publicly for his warm heart, and for his understanding of the urgent needs and bitter sorrows of the disabled Russian veterans now living in many foreign countries who are members of the Union of Disabled Russian Veterans Abroad.</p>
   <p>The Reverend B. Anziferov,</p>
   <p>honorary member of the</p>
   <p>Union of Disabled Russian Veterans Abroad.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
