<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-02-14">February 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-02-14">February 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mikhail <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> among the Americans called Michael Berg, is at the present time in China and calls himself Jacob Borodin. Mikhail Gruzonberg was a person with little <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> In America he did not experience much suffering and need. While at the Valparaiso <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> did not distinguish himself in any way. Coming to Chicago he tried the field of teaching. He opened a school of English and turned it later to a preparatory school, which, nevertheless, was not recognized. When Russia was struck by the revolution, Gruzenberg agitated against Bolshevik impudence, cursed, called them bandits and usurpers, and other sweet names. But the reader should not believe much in his sincerity.</p>
   <p>Gruzenberg was aggravated that he could not benefit from the situation, but when he realized how the Bolsheviks had overpowered the Russian people, he changed his tactics and through certain tricks became an official of the Foreign Office in Moscow. Here be found ground to <pb facs="5423967_4_1696.jpg" n="2"/>distinguish himself in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Bolshevism.</p>
   <p>And this was just in his line. The bolsheviks value such individuals and offered <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to conduct their intrigues among the Chinese Cantonese revolutionists. It is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that during the time <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> decleard himself to be the Societ representative Borodin in China, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the commandant of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> ordered that the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the Bolshevik agitators be shut.</p>
   <p>Then what? <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> God! Our former Chicagocan <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> betook himself again to Chicago, where his friends were trying to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to the Americans, calling him a "spets" (specialist), but not a Bolshevik or Communist. There you are! A Bolshevik official agent in China, and not a Bolshevik. The Russian colony of Chicago well remembers how Gruzenberg tried to make advances to the mission of Kerensky's government, which was greeted by the Russian colony of Chicago at the Auditorium. Everybody remembers well how this intriguer, with the assistance of his friends at the <pb facs="5423967_4_1697.jpg" n="3"/>meeting, succeeded in getting the role of president of the committee of the meeting and even of censor of the speeches of orators who greeted the mission. Flirting with Her msky's mission and America, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> tried not to permit the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to be too bad in their speeches; he did not want to allow even the presence of the local Bolsheviks at this solemn meeting, proof of how much of a rabid anti-Bolshevik <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> was is a shown by the fact that during the greeting of Kerensky's mission, he interrupted the orators who mentioned the free revolutionary government of Russia. Probably the Chicago Bolsheviks do not know what to make of this sudden turn from a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to a rabid Bolshevik. For some people (according to the American expression) "business is business." Therefore, reader, dismiss all year former ideas that the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who is making such a noise in China is the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Borodin or is a member of that family. It is generally the way at the Bolshevik camp to assume good Russian names in order to make oneself appear more important and to take advantage of the situation. In short, the Borodin in China is nobody else but our Chicagoan resident of the West Side, Michael <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>; <pb facs="5423967_4_1698.jpg" n="4"/>his empty school is still there, maintained on the money of the Russian peasants. peasants.</p>
   <p>One does not have to be a prophet to foretell that in the near future we shall see some of the good friends of Gruzenberg - Borodin appear on the Bolshevik horizon.</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
