<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-23">Feb. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Victory or Defeat?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-23">Feb. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY OR DEFEAT?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The other day, one of the news agencies reported that the bolsheviks celebrated another victory. This time the victory was won on the so-called "cultural front"--thus, the implacable and fiercest foe of Marxism-Leninism was laid low...religion was overwhelmed.</p>
   <p>If we are to believe assertions of some of the leading bolsheviks, religion in the USSR at present is in a state of complete collapse, and for that reason the magazine Bezbozhnik instead of its usual weekly publication will appear now once a month. (Translator's note: Bezbozhnik (Godless) is a leading anti-religious periodical published by the League of Godless). Some of the bolsheviks regard religion as being entirely dead; and, for the same reason, consider further existence of magazines as unnecessary, for it would be wasted effort to preach atheism among non-believers. Vice-chairman of the League, Mr. Lukashevsky, claims that during the last ten years such a severe blow has been dealt to religion that even the existence of the <pb facs="5423967_4_1422.jpg" n="2"/>League becomes. superfluous. He also declared that at present the common-run bolshevik propaganda against religion has been discontinued, and that the half-dead and half-alive institution is being dealt with not by forceful means, but by "scientific exposure of religious fallacies". The number of non-believers in the USSR, according to Lukashevsky, has grown so tremendously that the country in the nearest future will be left without a single church. As far as Bezbozhnik is concerned, its circulation during the last few months dropped by eighty thousand copies, which may lead to the total suspension of the publication. People who do not believe[in religion]consider the reading of the magazine unnecessary. Further on Lukashevsky pointed out the great success of the anti-religious stage presentation of the play called "Spanish Priest", and cited a case of a Russian priest who left his church with the declaration that "truly, religion is an opiate for the people".</p>
   <p>From all these statements one may conclude that in the course of the last seventeen years, Russia has been converted from a religious country into <pb facs="5423967_4_1423.jpg" n="3"/>a country of non-believers, of outright atheists. If this is so, there is no further need for creating new, or maintaining old, anti-religious organizations to publish magazines and spread anti-religious propaganda. This would seem to be quite logical. If the religion is dead, there is no sense in fighting a corpse. On the other hand, bolshevik utterances seem to be extremely incongruous. If we are to agree with their reasoning about religion, then, at present, there is no need for any kind of bolshevik propaganda in the USSR, for, according to their own statements, the entire population of the country, with few exceptions, is Marxism-minded and supports the Bolshevik party in its every undertaking, while worshipping its beloved and great genius-leader Stalin. But the bolsheviks do not do this; on the contrary, despite the complete victory of Marxism-Stalinism in the USSR, instead of reducing their output of propaganda they are increasing it. They do not abandon their bloody dictatorship, but reinforce it.</p>
   <p>This only goes to show that the population, far from being Marxist-minded, is manifesting an ever growing dissatisfaction with the bolshevik chain-gang regime. Probably the situation is the same in the matter of religion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1424.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In all probability, the bolsheviks have suffered an utter defeat on this front instead of gaining a victory, and for that reason they decided to discontinue any further struggle against religion. It is not because the soviet papers reported increasing activity among church followers in different localities and total inactivity among the godless elements, for in many places such elements [godless]are non-existent. During the Christmas holidays, according to the reports of American correspondents, the churches everywhere were jammed with people. In view of all this, we are constrained to think that all bolsheviks' claims regarding the total collapse of religion in Russia do not correspond with the facts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
