<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Fathers and Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FATHERS AND CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Generally, members of Russian colonies in America, and particularly in Chicago, can be divided into two categories: the organized and the unorganized. The colony can further be divided into several political, religious, and cultural affiliations. It is commonly assumed that the organized elements represent the vanguard of the Russian colony, its creative and cultural force. This is true in principle: the organized are always stronger and culturally more advanced than the unorganized. But this is true only when the members of the organization are really cultured and energetic men or women, pursuing desirable goals.</p>
   <p>This cannot be said about all Russian organizations. Some of them, for instance, belong to the Bolshevik group. The majority of the members of such organizations are illiterate, uncultured people. They do not have minds of their own, and they need guidance from someone else, as though they were blind men. But, as their guides are generally adventurers, it is obvious <pb facs="5423967_4_0510.jpg" n="2"/>that such organizations cannot create anything that is worth while.</p>
   <p>There are also purely religious organizations which are not interested in any of the Social problems. These cannot be a force in the social life of the Russian community.</p>
   <p>Along with all this, there are many really cultured people who are unorganized, and they represent a real social factor, much more important than many of the organizations.</p>
   <p>During recent years, cultured Russians, both organized and unorganized have paid a great deal of attention to the Russian youth. They take various steps in order to acquaint this youth with Russian organizations, or to create separate organizations for young people. This, of course, is a very important task, but, unfortunately, it is not particularly fruitful. Failure in such an effort makes many intellectuals despair, and they declare that American street life spoils the children, that the Russian youth is not interested in anything that is Russian, and, therefore, it cannot be interested <pb facs="5423967_4_0511.jpg" n="3"/>in the activities of any Russian organization.</p>
   <p>We cannot agree, however, with such reasoning. If the Russian youth is not interested in Russian culture or in what their parents are doing, it is the fault of the parents. To awaken an interest in the children in Russian culture and in the activity of the Russian organizations, it is necessary for parents to be good examples to their offspring, to demonstrate the value that there is to be found in Russian culture.</p>
   <p>For example: How can one awaken a child's interest in Russian culture or the Russian language when the parents themselves speak very poor Russian and are not at all interested in Russian culture? There are no Russian books or newspapers in their homes; they never attend the lectures and concerts of the best Russian artists. And how can parents develop in their children any interest in the Russian organizations when, on meeting one another, they immediately begin to argue about politics--with very little understanding? These arguments very often lead to squabbles and quarrels.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0512.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All this, instead of attracting children to the Russian organizations, repels them from all that bears the imprint of being Russian.</p>
   <p>The root of the evil, therefore, lies not in the apathy of Russian children, but in their parents who are bad examples to their offspring, and who are Russian only in words, but not in deeds. For this reason, organizers of the Russian youth should remember that their work will not be fruitful until and unless parents themselves mend their ways and become Russians not only in words, but also in deeds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
