<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">March 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Telegram of the Council of Labor and Defense</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">March 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TELEGRAM OF THE COUNCIL OF LABOR AND DEFENSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sovieta Truda i Oborony, Moscow, February, 1923.</p>
   <p>To the Central Office of the O. T. P. S. R. (Obshchestvo Tekhnicheskoy Pomoshchi Sovietskoy Rossii), i. e., Society of Technical Aid to Soviet Russia, 110 West Street, New York.</p>
   <p>In reply to the telegram about the disorganization, I propose to continue the work, observing accurately the directions and instructions of the permanent commission of the Council of Labor and Defense. The organized immigration, permitted in every case by KOMSTO, is very desirable and useful to Soviet Russia. Reichel arrived. I beg to postpone the Convention till May. The work should not cease, I authorize Vilya and Gorelik to sign the passports. Confirm the receiving of the <pb facs="5423967_4_0383.jpg" n="2"/>telegram. The President of the permanent Commission of the Council of Labor and Defense, A. Eyduk.</p>
   <p>In accordance with the instructions of the Council of Labor and Defense, the convention of the S. of T. A. to S. R. of March 17, will not take place.</p>
   <p>The convention is postponed till the month of May and there will be special communications about it. For further information inquire at the address of the Plenipotentiary Central Office of the S. of T. A. to S. R.</p>
   <p>Central Bureau Stars</p>
   <p>Room 603 - 110 W. 40th St., New York.</p>
   <p>Note: Pay special attention to the contents and instructions of this telegram, which was received by the Central Bureau of the S. of T. A. to S. R. from Moscow. From this telegram is seen that the S. of T. A. <pb facs="5423967_4_0384.jpg" n="3"/>to S. R. is a Bolshevist institution, and not a non-partisan organization, which was acting by the order of the commissars from Moscow. N. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
