<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-09-18">Sept. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Bolsheviks and the People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Intrigues of the Russian Communists in the Parish of the Russian Independent Church, at 917 Wood St.) by Ignatiy Grigoluk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-09-18">Sept. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOLSHEVIKS AND THE PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(INTRIGUES OF THE RUSSIAN COMMUNISTS IN THE PARISH OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT CHURCH, AT 917 WOOD ST.) BY IGNATIY GRIGOLUK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The author says that, while the bolsheviki were entirely losing their popularity in Russia, they were making the greatest efforts to get hold of every organization created by the Russian immigrants in the U. S. Thus, they have taken possession, by underhand methods, of the Russian Cooperative restaurant in Chicago, located on Division St., near Ashland Ave. They were also planning to close the Russian Independent Church on Wood St., and to take possession of the property, belonging to this church and to use it for their own nefarious purposes after having ousted all those members who were of a sincerely religious turn of mind.</p>
   <p>As these bolshevist plotters formed only an insignificant minority of the membership of the church, they had concocted, already in 1917, a truly devilish <pb facs="5423967_4_1108.jpg" n="2"/>plan as to how to get rid of the most energetic of their opponents. The author of the article, who had succeeded in gaining access to the secret meeting of the communists who had joined the church organization - a meeting held as early as 1917 - relates that the following plan was accepted: the members, both men and women, most obnoxious to the bolsheviki, were to be continually insulted, bothered and falsely accused of actions harmful to the organization. Their reputation had to be ruined by slandering them, then they would become so disgusted that they would voluntarily resign their membership, and the bolsheviki would easily impose their will on the less energetic and enlightened members, who would become an obedient herd, that could be driven, like cattle, in any direction.</p>
   <p>Also more communists should join the church organization, so that the work of destruction could be accomplished more easily. Then the victorious bolsheviki would liquidate the church and divide the spoils between themselves. However the bolsheviki were not able to put through this truly dastardly <pb facs="5423967_4_1109.jpg" n="3"/>plan, and their intrigues were understood and frustrated by the other members.</p>
   <p>(Note. Further investigations of this matter show Mr. Grigoluk's version of these intrigues to be unreliable. He seems himself to have belonged to one of the intriguing parties. Another intriguing personality was the Priest of the Wood's St. Church, Rev. I. Zheltonogo, who was dismissed about a year ago by the parishoners. He denies an article, (published in the number of the Rassviet of September 27, 1926) having had any dealings with the bolsheviki. Yet I have heard him making speeches of a distinctly bolshevist character. Later for some reason or other, he started to revile the bolsheviki. Perhaps it would be better not to stir up this hornet's nest. D. S.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
