<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-12">April 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Russians in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-12">April 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIANS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some eight or nine years ago the Russian immigrants in America were rather inconspicuous.</p>
   <p>Apart from a few rare exceptions the Russians were earning their living by physical labor. There were no Russian commercial or industrial enterprises. Only very few Russians had houses of their own. Prominent Russians would seldom come to America and settle in this country.</p>
   <p>But during the succeeding years a great change has come about. Especially during the last years.</p>
   <p>In some cities, especially in New York, there have appeared a good many Russian commercial and industrial enterprises.</p>
   <p>Everywhere there began to crop up Russian co-operatives and restaurants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1302.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many Russian farmers and workmen are acquiring houses or farms of their own.</p>
   <p>There are some Russians who buy and sell lots and farms.</p>
   <p>Previously the Russians aere living in America as passersby who had come to this country casually. Now many of them have settled here for good. They take their sojourn in America seriously, are gradually getting organized, and become established permanently.</p>
   <p>Previously very few Russians would study the English language; now even the "old timers" begin little by little to talk English. Among the young men and girls many speak English.</p>
   <p>The Russian workmen have succeeded in getting better conditions of work and higher wages. The number of Russian workmen who join trade unions is also increasing; the same can be said about the number of those who join Mutual Aid Societies and such Russian organizations as are business like.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1303.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the last years many prominent Russians have come to the United States. Among them we find scientists, artists, engineers and even writers.</p>
   <p>Slowly the Russian colony in America is getting organized, is being built up on a solid foundation and begins to make itself known.</p>
   <p>This colony is poor in comparison with the colonies of other nations. It is poor in all respects in cultural institutions, in businessmen and in material achievements. And in our Chicago colony there is also a lack of all these things.</p>
   <p>But we must remember that nine or ten years ago the poverty of the Russian colony in America was simply horrific.</p>
   <p>In course of time the Russian colony will evidently occupy the place belonging to it among the other foreign colonies.</p>
   <p>This is natural. Wherever the people may be they have to use all opportunities<pb facs="5423967_4_1304.jpg" n="4"/>of improving their mode of life, of meeting organized, of advancing.</p>
   <p>Unless they do it they are doomed to a miserable existence, to backwardness, to defencelessness. And this is what has been happening until now.</p>
   <p>But the Russians have learned much from the painful experiences of the past.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
