<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-15">Sept. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">National Culture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-15">Sept. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL CULTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Modern culture can best be defined as the combination of the separate cultures of many nations. When we speak of international culture, we are merely giving expression to the conception that national culture, the culture of one nation, has the virtue of being understood and easily absorbed by all other nations. In this virtue of easy assimilability lie the chief values of national culture for all mankind. We may concede that the culture of one nation influences the culture of another nation, but we refuse to believe that there is such a thing as international culture. Human culture in its essence will always remain national: that is, each nation will have its own distinctive culture.</p>
   <p>In recent times, many attempts have been made by various composers to create international music. These attempts, in the opinion of S. Rachmaninov, the great Russian pianist and composer, are doomed to failure. In Rachmaninov's opinion, music devoid of national motifs which express the national soul of the people and which serve as inspiration to the composer lacks meaning, <pb facs="5423967_4_0546.jpg" n="2"/>depth, and beauty.</p>
   <p>What is a national culture, and how can it be defined? National culture is the creative power, the creative genius of a nation. It finds its expression in science, in literature, in painting, in music, in song, in dance,etc. National spirit is the raw material out of which a genius creates new national values, just as a baker makes bread out of his dough.</p>
   <p>The Russian nation has given to the world such geniuses as Tolstoy and Dostoevski. Tolstoy is undoubtedly the greatest writer the world has ever known. His works have been translated into all European and into many Oriental languages. His book War and Peace is unequaled in all literature. His gloomy forebodings of the approaching catastrophe for Russia have come true. Dostoevski has been acclaimed by the entire world as the most profound judge of the human soul. He had an extraordinary gift for probing the deepest and innermost recesses of the human soul.</p>
   <p>National culture can likewise express itself in the art of the theater. The <pb facs="5423967_4_0547.jpg" n="3"/>Russian drama has for many years served as an example for other countries. The Moscow Art Theater, for instance, has for the last thirty-five years led the world in new forms of dramatic presentation and new methods of expression. The Moscow Art Theater has brought about a complete revolution in the art of the stage in many countries of the world. Feodor Chaliapin, the world-renowned singer, was an outstanding exponent of Russian culture.</p>
   <p>The Russian ballet, first introduced to the western world by its founder Diaghilev, showed enchanted audiences that it was possible, through artistic dancing and mimicry, to express every human emotion as plainly and simply as through music or singing. The ballets "Scheherazade" and "Tamara" are the two bright gems of Russian culture in terpsichorean art.</p>
   <p>So with Russian music. One need only attend a few concerts of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra to perceive the importance of Russian music in the concert repertoire.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0548.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From the foregoing examples, it is easy to understand that national culture is a tremendous power and a great treasure not only in the life of one nation but in the life of all nations. The national cultures of the several nations bring these nations closer together; they facilitate the exchange of cultural values, and they uplift the human heart and improve the human mind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
