<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-05-02">May 2, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Whether to Become an American Citizen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-05-02">May 2, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">WHETHER TO BECOME AN AMERICAN CITIZEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the current session of Congress several bills were introduced which proposed to deport to their native countries all foreigners residing in the United States. In the press and in radio broadcasts foreigners have repeatedly been accused as one of the causes of unemployment in this country. On them has been laid the responsibility for the rising crime wave. In a word, attempts have been made to make foreigners the scape goats for all the social and economic evils in the country.</p>
   <p>Moreover, these attacks are still continuing. They produce anxiety and misgivings among immigrants, their families, and their acquaintances. Is it the truth that the United States, a country created by immigrants and nursed into maturity by their generations, really intends to deport scores of thousands of men and women who have not become American citizens for one reason or another, to deprive them of the right to work, and to break up their families?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1234.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is not difficult to understand why in critical periods the presence of a large number of foreigners evokes protests from some people. "Let them go back home", they say. "We have enough of our own troubles. If we had admitted fewer immigrants, we should have had more work for our citizens." Such animosity toward foreigners exists not only in the United States. All over the world at present foreigners find themselves an undesirable element. From all countries come reports of new restrictions upon them. Everywhere at the root of this animosity are unemployment and an attitude of mistrust toward strangers.</p>
   <p>Even though in the United States this agitation produces anxiety and uneasiness among the foreigners, it is quite improbable that the proposals to deport them will meet with the approval of any considerable section of the population. Mass deportations are contrary both to common sense and to elementary justice. It would be a measure both cruel and mad. The deportation of several millions of consumers, many of them providers for their families, would throw additional millions of people, wives and children of men deported, on relief and instead <pb facs="5423967_4_1235.jpg" n="3"/>of improving things would only aggravate the evil economic condition of the country.</p>
   <p>But even though the agitation in favor of the deportation of foreigners produces unfounded anxiety, it has served a good purpose. This movement has concentrated attention as never before on the problems of citizenship. It has put five millions of foreigners face to face with the question: Shall I become an American citizen?</p>
   <p>Many thousands of aliens at present are pondering the pros and cons of naturalization. This is a problem that each one must decide independently. But discussions of all aspects of this problem may help the reader to find the correct answer. The series of articles which will be printed in this paper on the subject, and of which this is the first, has in view such a discussion. In these articles we shall subject to consideration such questions as citizenship and obtaining employment, citizenship in its relation to receiving social security, the preservation of one's own cultural traditions, the right to vote, the <pb facs="5423967_4_1236.jpg" n="4"/>importance of citizenship for the family of a foreigner, and a number of other problems connected with naturalization.</p>
   <p>Flis</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
