<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Anton F. Bernov</title>, 917 North Wood Street
<date when="1937-03-02">March 2, 1937</date><title level="a">by N. Korecki.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Anton F. Bernov</title>, 917 North Wood Street
<date when="1937-03-02">March 2, 1937</date><title level="a">by N. Korecki.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Anton F. Bernov was born on January 7, 1889 in Russia, in the province of Vilna, county of Vilna, in the village Novoselka. Having been recruited for the army in 1910 he has been serving in the 50th brigade of artillery until 1913. On July 15, 1913 he came to the United States. In April, 1915 he joined the Club "Znanie". During four years he has been a member of the Committee of this club and was one of the most active workers of this organization. In 1919 he became the President of the Club "Znanie". In the same year the Club had to be liquidated because of political dissensions which arose among its members. Towards the end of the year 1919, Mr. Bernov became a member of the Russian People's University in Chicago. He was a member of the Committee which organized the reception of the Russian Mission, with Professor Bakkmetev at the head, which was sent to the United States by Verensky's government. He was a member of the Committee which was collecting 10,000,000 pair of shoes for Russia; also a member of the Society of Technical Aid to Soviet Russia. Participated in the collection of funds for Russian prisoners of war kept in Germany; also in the collection of funds for political exiles in Russia. Was an active worker when funds were collected in 1921 and 1922 among the Chicago <pb facs="5423967_4_1651.jpg" n="2"/>Russians for the relief of people stricken by famine in Russia. In 1929 Mr. Bernov participated in the restoration of the Society "Znanie" under the name of the 50th branch of the Russian Amalgamated Society of Mutual Aid in America of which the center was in New York, and was a member of the Committee of this Society.</p>
   <p>In 1930 the Society "Znanie", or the 50th branch of the Russian Amalgamated Society of Mutual Aid in America joined the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society in Chicago the center of which is located at 917 North Wood Street. Since 1932 Mr. Bernov has been a member of the 1st branch of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. In 1934 and 1935, he was a member of the Administrative and Revising Committees of the Parish of St. George with headquarters at 917 North Wood Street. In 1932, Mr. Bernov organized the I. Bunin Memorial School in the district of Humboldt Park, and during four years he has been the Chairman of the Committee of that school. At the present time he is the cashier of the 1st branch of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society (since January, 1935). In 1935 he was Vice-President of the Russian-American Democratic League, with headquarters at 1902 West Division Street. He is also a member of the Central Executive Committee of the Russian American <pb facs="5423967_4_1652.jpg" n="3"/>Citizens' Organization. Since 1932 he is the President of the School Council of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. For the last three years he has been the Chairman of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization of the 31st ward.</p>
   <p>Signed: N. Korecki.</p>
   <p>Note: Mr. A. Bernov is the most energetic and foremost public worker among the Russian immigrants of Chicago, and by the work he has done in the field of education he has done great service to the Russian colony. (N.K.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
