<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-20">Mar. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Help the Helpless Russian Orphans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-20">Mar. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">LET US HELP THE HELPLESS RUSSIAN ORPHANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no greater joy than the joy of helping unfortunate orphans. For this reason, we appeal to the minds and hearts of all Russians in whom the true Russian generous heart still beats, and in whose veins still flows Russian blood, and, what is most important, in whom the quality of mercy has not been smothered--those emotions which have enriched the souls of all Russians. We call upon all Russians to hasten to the aid of the Russian orphans who are outside their native land. There are thousands of such orphans. They are scattered all over Europe and other continents. There are a great many of them, particularly in countries adjacent to Russia, such as Poland, Estonia, Latvia, and Finland. Some of them are in France, Czecho-slovakia, Jugoslavia; some are in the Far East: in China, Japan, Manchuria. Such is the fate that has befallen our growing Russian generation. Can this new generation of Russians be blamed for this situation? Of course not! Nevertheless, they have been subjected to trials more severe than any that history has yet recorded. We have known of orphans whose parents were dead, <pb facs="5423967_4_0309.jpg" n="2"/>but now we <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of orphans <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are still alive. A cruel, barbarous regime has torn them away from their parents because the parents refused to surrender their homes. The parents were sent as convicts into exile and hard labor with no investigation or court trial. They were sent to Solovki, to Siberia, and other distant places of vast Russia, and the children, ranging from the age of four to fifteen, were left to their own fate. These children, who were left without shelter <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and care, were scattered, and since they could find no succor and protection, many of them fled abroad.</p>
   <p>One can imagine the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> picture drawn by the flight of these children abroad, in a temperature of thirty degrees below zero, pursued by the border guards. People in Poland and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> tell us that children's frozen corpses are being found in the forests. Whole groups of such children are sometimes found in deserted dugouts. Naked and hungry, these children through some miracles manage to preserve life. We do not know how many of them individually and in groups still continue to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the towns and villages. Isn't this a horrible tragedy?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0310.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Can we Russians, knowing of the inhuman suffering of these innocent children, silently accept such a situation? Can we remain passive spectators of this drama? No, a thousand times no! Our duty is to stretch out a helping hand to these unfortunate victims. It is our duty to save them from imminent death. Then let us make haste before it is too late.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Society for Aid to Russian immigrant Children has sent $265 to Europe during the short period of its existence. The major part of this money ($165.00) was sent to the children's asylum in Poland, at Dubno, in the province of Voliin. The most acute distress among our children was found in that particular locality, for there, besides ordinary things, they also needed medicine. The rest of the money was distributed among several institutions located in Poland, Jugoslavia, and other countries. From all these places, we receive letters of thanks and appeals for further help.</p>
   <p>The catastrophe, repercussions of which echo all over the world, we adults created, and, therefore, we should stretch our helping hand to those unfortunate <pb facs="5423967_4_0311.jpg" n="4"/>children to relieve their suffering. This is our sacred duty and we should perform it.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Society for Aid to Russian Immigrant Children calls upon everyone to donate as much as he can. Donate money or discarded clothing. To some we shall give food, to others, clothing.</p>
   <p>Sign up for membership in the organization. The more members there are, the greater will be the help rendered to the Russian orphans. You do not need a large sum of money for this purpose: the membership fee is only one dollar per year. And, finally, everything does not depend on money alone. Solidarity and good teamwork for the cause mean a great deal more. Let us put an end to the quarrels that disunite us in our everyday life. Let us stretch out a brotherly hand to one another and let us all unite in behalf of this sacred cause--helping those that cannot help themselves.</p>
   <p>For all information apply to the president of the Society, Mr. I. F. Erin, <pb facs="5423967_4_0312.jpg" n="5"/>2150 West Cortez Street.</p>
   <p>Honorary President,</p>
   <p>His Grace, Bishop Leonty,</p>
   <p>President, I. F. Erin,</p>
   <p>Recording Secretary, A. Lobanov</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
