<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-26">Sept. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Maximov's New Scientific Investigation</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-26">Sept. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR MAXIMOV'S NEW SCIENTIFIC INVESTIGATION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently the American newspapers and magazines have been mentioning very often the experiments, investigations and scientific work done by the greatest scientist of our times, Professor A. A. Maximov.</p>
   <p>The modest laboratory of our remarkable compatriot in the Chicago University attracts more and more the attention of representatives of science and the press.</p>
   <p>In the beginning of this week in all American papers there have appeared enthusiastic accounts of the last scientific investigation made by Professor Maximov. This investigation of the inoculation of the tissue of the lungs with tubercular bacilli has created great interest among the prominent representatives of medical science, and it is being lively discussed in medical circles.</p>
   <p>Professor Maximov has cut out small pieces from the lung of a rabbit and has inoculated them with tubercular bacilli.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then he took tiny pieces from this inoculated tissue and put them in the hollow of a small glass plate, where they could be observed under the microscope. This glass plate is kept the whole time in an autoclave (a special cabinet) with a constant temperature of 37°. Under such conditions the tubercular bacilli do not die; they remain alive the whole time.</p>
   <p>Thus, by investigating the tissue under the microscope, the professor could observe day by day the development of the tubercles in the lung, and find out what elements participate in the formation of these abnormal growths.</p>
   <p>This work is very interesting because, if we shall understand the process of development of the disease, we shall be able to find a more effective method of its treatment.</p>
   <p>Such an experiment, allowing one to observe through the microscope the gradual development of tuberculosis has been conducted for the first time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1701.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Some persons state that the enormous importance of these experiments consists also in this: Professor Maximov has succeeded in establishing the fact that the development of tubercles goes on not only in the cells of the tissue of the lungs, as was believed until now, but that the leucocytes (white blood corpuscles) also play an important role in the development of the disease.</p>
   <p>In connection with this new scientific investigation which has been conducted by Professor Maximov, we have spoken to several Russian practicing physicians in Chicago, begging then to express their opinion about this investigation.</p>
   <p>We quote below the opinions of these physicians:</p>
   <p>Dr. I. L. Spivak: "Professor Maximov's name is so well known to the readers of medical literature that every new investigation of his arouses the greatest interest Though Professor Maximov has specialized <pb facs="5423967_4_1702.jpg" n="4"/>in histological research, his investigations reach far beyond the boundaries of the science of histology, and contact the sphere of the most general biological concepts.</p>
   <p>"He is one of the most prominent representatives of the "unitarists" as regards the problem of the origin of the white blood corpuscles.</p>
   <p>"His recent investigation of "Cancerous changes in the mammary glands, and cultures of tissues," which has been published in Virchow's Archive, has attracted the attention of wide circles. His Textbook of Histology is one of the best books on histology which have been published in the Russian language.</p>
   <p>"His present investigation shows the same characteristics which distinguish all his scientific works: it contains original thoughts expressed in a lucid way."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1703.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Dr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Krasnow: "The communication published in the American newspapers about the discovery made by Professor Maximov in connection with his latest research work, conducted by him in the Chicago University, is concerned with a question which has been debated already for a long time, namely, with the question, in how far can tuberculosis be  considered to be a disease of the blood?</p>
   <p>"The present scientific experiment made by Professor Maximov in the realm of diagnosing tuberculosis in the tissues of live organisms, as all is recent investigations in histology and anatomy, are not something new; in the medical world such investigations conducted by Professor Maximov have for a long time been considered to be the outstanding research work in this line."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
