<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-26">Apr. 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">In the Power of Hooligans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-26">Apr. 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">In the Power of Hooligans</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only quite recently the Bolsheviks asserted that rowdyism, criminal killings and other crimes existed only in the the capitalistic countries. As fas as "the country of socialism" is concerned-the country that freed itself of the cursed inheritances of the past-such criminal activity is a thing of the past.</p>
   <p>Look--the Bolsheviks told foreigners--at our newspapers. Your newspapers are filled with accounts of various sensational criminal acts whereas in our newspapers you will not find any articles of such doings.</p>
   <p>And, really, until last your the Soviet papers published nothing that would reveal that crime existed in U. S. S. R. Large pages of the Soviet papers</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0455.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>were replete with articles of political and economic nature and various other "serious material". And as far as the common every day occurences were concerned there was not a line printed. Thus, the impression is created that U. S. S. R. is free and does not suffer from rowdyism, criminal elements and other unlawful acts which are manifest in the capitalistic countries.</p>
   <p>Now the whole situation has been changed since the Soviet papers began to devote some space to such affairs. Now it is quite clear that in U. S. S. R. there is more crime than in the capitalistic countries.</p>
   <p>The criminal activity is particularly prevalent among the youth, among those "offsprings of October", who were born under the Bolshevik regime and brought up in the pioneers' camps and the camps maintained for the young communists. The rowdyism among this youth reached such proportions that the <pb facs="5423967_4_0456.jpg" n="3"/> Bolshevik authorities were compelled to promulgate a decree extending the force of the criminal laws, including capital punishment, on children of 12 years of age and over. Thus, in U. S. S. R. only children under 12 years of age henceforth will be immune from criminal prosecution. All the rest will be brought before criminal courts when they commit an offense.</p>
   <p>At present the Soviety papers are replete with items reporting murders, acts of rape, rowdyism and other crimes. Many cities find themselves under complete domination of rowdies despite the fact that they are being shot down every day.</p>
   <p>Here is how Pravda pictures the life of an inhabitant in Omsk:</p>
   <p>"Just try to pass through the streets in the center of the city around <pb facs="5423967_4_0457.jpg" n="4"/>11 o'clock at night. On the Street of Lenin, well illuminated from the show windows of the stores, a crowd of boys is engaged in a peculiar kind of sport. They spit on the citizens passing by. The winner obviously is the one who can spit with the best aim. On the Street of Republic, just opposite the monument in memory of the victims of the revolution, a group of young fellows is engaged in a fist fight.</p>
   <p>"Among these rowdies the first place is occupied by the homeless children. Just recently they stabbed a worker by the name Druzhinin, who died in the hospital. They carry out regular raids on apartment houses, stores and warehouses and ransack them. The hooligans lay regular sieges to the schools in the city, blocking all exits. On Feb. 27 a group of rowdies, former pupils discharged for misconduct, staged a raid on the school named "May First." They fractured the skull of a student named Buyantzev. A youngster by the name Vachitov, expelled from the school for hooliganism, broke into <pb facs="5423967_4_0458.jpg" n="5"/>the classroom at the head of a gang of rowdies, at the time when the teachers were ready to dismiss the pupils for the day. With Finnish knives the youthful raiders kept the school under siege for a long time and would not let anybody out. The students do not show much better conduct" (a great majority of them are young communists).</p>
   <p>In the same issue of Pravda the readers are informed that among the students in Omsk many wanton acts are committed. Among the students of the Workers' Faculty of the Highway Engineering Institute, many students and their female companions retired to vacant rooms, but not for the purposes of studying the subjects assigned to them.</p>
   <p>Students in Tomsk have gone much further in their rowdyism, and the same newspaper describes the situation as follows:</p>
   <p>"In January a student by the name of Yaschenko was attacked by four unidentified persons. They snatched the victim's brief case and then beat him up.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0459.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In the beginning of March a scientist by the name of Piliuka was assaulted by three unidentified hooligans and suffered knife wounds. On March 18, during the night rowdies fell upon a group of students and their girl companions. Several of the party were wounded. In the middle of March two women workers in the shop "Red Star" were assaulted by three young men. One of the women managed to escape and the other was raped. In almost all such cases the assailants are students"</p>
   <p>From all this one can see that hooliganism in U. S. S. R. has blossomed into full bloom. It blossomed just because the Bolsheviks themselves perverted the youth spiritually and made and developed criminal inclinations in it.</p>
   <p>Now the same Bolsheviks try to put an end to rowdyism by means of shootings, imprisonment and exile.</p>
   <p>Their "Children of October", after receiving Bolshevik bringing up, have <pb facs="5423967_4_0460.jpg" n="7"/>proved to be a very bad lot of "successors" if their activity frightens and alarms the Belskeviks themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
