<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-12-03">Dec. 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Masked Friends</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article by Rasskatov)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0861</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0861.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-12-03">Dec. 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE MASKED FRIENDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article by Rasskatov)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago, I listened to the complaints of two bolsheviki, in regard to an incident in chich the Friends of Soviet Russia, were accused of swindling the Russian people in America, in connection with the event celebrating the arrival of the Russian flyers. How these Masked Friends had obtained hundreds of thousands of dollars from the hard working laborers of the Russian people, these simple bolsheviki, sincerely believing in the noble purpose of their chiefs, had also donated twenty dollars each for the flyers.</p>
   <p>The reader remembers, how the Novy Mir (The New World), during the 2 months, prior to the arrival of the flyers, had made blatant appeals to the Russian people for donations.</p>
   <p>The bolsheviki chiefs occupied themselves repeatedly with extorting money from their bolshevik groups. Thousands of dollars were obtained from these groups <pb facs="5423967_4_0862.jpg" n="2"/>in this manner.</p>
   <p>Even, "the comrades" from Division Street "threw-away" about two thousand dollars, which also disappeared into the pockets of the swindlers - The Masked Friends.</p>
   <p>Russians of Chicago who attended the assembly at the Armory, organized in honor of the flyers, remembered how those organizors occupied themselves for the period of four hours, collecting 'donations' from the fifteen thousand odd people in the auditorium.</p>
   <p>Fifty cents was charged for admission; photographs and aouvenir buttons were sold and collection boxes passed around. Trusting people who were brought to the stage, offered large sums of money, donated in cash and checks. Everyone gave and bought. No one refused; yet the records submitted by The Masked Friends showed a net profit of only $2,800.</p>
   <p>Is this not a gross fraud and is it not insolent raillery on the Russian people?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0863.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many of us observed that much of the contributions were collected by means of a subscription list. This way no one refused. It was done in every city of the United States and Canada. Approximately a million dollars was collected, and the two bolsheviki informed me that only fifteen tractors were bought with this money, costing $7,000.</p>
   <p>This information was turned over to me under rigid secrecy and I was begged not to reveal the names, or they would be submitted to cruel punishment by the chekists. The "Big-shots" of the party are severe. Members were ordered not to discuss this matter of the Masked Friends' abjectness. So, this is the type of fighters for justice the were! At this behaviour of the bolshevik chiefs, I was not at all surprised, because their conscience is blackened by similar acts of despicable behavior. However I was astonished and deeply hurt to know that the Russian people have not as yet learned to reason, and still remain in a state of ignorance; that past experiences have not benefited them any, and that they are still an easy prey for such swindlers. Let us remember how the Russian emigrants returning to Russia in the years of 1919-1920, were deprived of their hard earned money by the commissars upon their arrival, when <pb facs="5423967_4_0864.jpg" n="4"/>at that time money in Russia was in full circulation. How many emigrants suffered at the hands of the commissars! Let us remember the medical aid, let us remember the collections for the relief of the famine in 1921 in Russia. Have not these insolent frauds of masquerading friends taught us anything? Are we not capable of reasoning?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
