<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">Feb. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Ten Million Pairs of Shoes for Russia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1918-02-16">Feb. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TEN MILLION PAIRS OF SHOES FOR RUSSIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In these arch-revolutionary times of ours, such problems as supplying shoes to our barefoot sisters and brothers in the far away homeland is regarded as something which is not deserving the attention of earnest people; as something good enough only for philanthropists. This viewpoint is reflected by many groups of the Russian American colony. The heartlessness of a mean and stubborn fanaticism lies hidden in this attitude.</p>
   <p>If one only stopped to think of the price of a pair of shoes now in Russia (between one and two hundred rubles), if one only stopped and considered the present prohibitive prices in Russia. It is worthwhile to give some thought to the letters which are coming from there and to the information which filters through the press, so full of complaints about the shoe famine. If only we stopped to think of all this, then <pb facs="5423967_4_0417.jpg" n="2"/>no one would retain further doubts of the urgent and immediate necessity for assistance, and our duty to our brethren at home would become so very clear to us that all arguments and shouting of phrases by great revolutionaries would cease as something heartless and shameful.</p>
   <p>We heartily congratulate this initiative by Russian-American organizations for their objective in giving footwear to Russia, and we appeal to our readers to cooperate with these organizations to the utmost.</p>
   <p>Russian citizens! Remember that we here, living in comfort and in plenty, are in duty bound to furnish assistance to our brethren in our distant homeland.</p>
   <p>Remember that when we return home into the fold of a free homeland, we shall be asked what we have done for them when we were abroad. Let us then do our small but useful and urgent job. Let us help those organizations whose goal it is to provide ten million pairs of shoes for Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0418.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Often those who talk big do nothing at all, while by the small talker frequently big things are done.</p>
   <p>To give shoes and clothes to the barefoot and the ragged is no small thing. Besides, how does this interfere with doing the bigger things alongside with the smaller?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
