<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-16">Oct. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">"The Day of the Russian Child"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Benefit Evening for Russian Refugee Children]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-16">Oct. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">"THE DAY OF THE RUSSIAN CHILD"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Benefit Evening for Russian Refugee Children]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is known to every Russian in America that there are tens, if not hundreds of thousands of children of Russian emigres living outside of Russian. Especially large numbers of these unfortunate, innocent victims of the revolutionary upheaval in Russia now live in countries bordering upon Russia. Even to this day, the flow of Russian child emigration from Russia continues.</p>
   <p>The lot of these young unfortunates is indeed bleak and most pitiable. Many of them become beggars, petty thieves, and even criminals, in their efforts to procure the means with which to buy their daily bread--until they fall into the hands of the police or are placed in some orphanage. These facts can be confirmed from the letters constantly coming from countries having large numbers of refugee children--from Poland, Lithuania, Jugoslavia, France, and other countries. Among these appeals for aid are many written <pb facs="5423967_4_0322.jpg" n="2"/>by Russian youngsters confined in sanitariums for tubercular children and in other charitable institutions.</p>
   <p>As a result of one of these urgent appeals for aid, the Chicago Branch of the Russian Emigre's Children's Aid Society has recently sent fifty dollars to a Russian orphanage in Dubno, Poland. The Chicago Branch is now arranging a special festival to be known as "The Day of the Russian Child". A splendid concert will be held, and there will be a variety of entertainment throughout the evening. The affair will take place October 21 in the hall of the Russian-American Democratic Club, located at 1902 West Division Street. A number of prominent Russian artists have kindly consented to participate in the concert. They include, among others, Maria Viniarskaya, singer; Nina Gedevanova, singer and entertainer; M. Vadim, baritone; Miss Disconti, dancer; Paulina Maxakova, singer of Russian folk melodies; Vera Mirova, a renowned ballet dancer; Maria Mashir, opera singer; and George Nelidov, baritone.</p>
   <p>The arrangements committee is busy attending to all the details so that the <pb facs="5423967_4_0323.jpg" n="3"/>occasion will prove an outstanding success. Many good people have contributed food and drinks to supply the bar during the coming event. The Russian clergy, headed by Archbishop Leon, has issued an appeal to all Russian congregations in Chicago urging support of "The Day of the Russian Child".</p>
   <p>The Chicago Branch of the Russian Emigre's Children's Aid Society also accepts contributions of used clothing, shoes, and other articles which can be sold. The cash realized from their sale will be turned over to the treasurer of the Society to be used in giving aid to unfortunate Russian children in foreign countries. A. V. Maksimov is the treasurer and financial secretary of the Society. His address is 1608 West Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>It is now up to all Russians living in Chicago and vicinity to give their utmost support to "The Day of the Russian Child," and thus to provide funds for the aid of poor Russian Child refugees scattered all over the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
