<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-10">Feb. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Should the All-Russian Convention Be Called?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-10">Feb. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SHOULD THE ALL-RUSSIAN CONVENTION BE CALLED?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of calling the all-Russian convention was brought up in the pages of Rassviet some time ago, but nothing came of it. It is difficult to explain why the Russian group has ceased to be interested in the destinies of its people in America. It seems to us, however, that the chief reasons are indifference, lack of interest in aspiring for higher things, and loss of confidence in their own abilities. All these negative qualities engender disappointment and pessimism which, in turn, cause apathy and complete inactivity. But worst of all is the loss of hope and faith in creative public work. Under such circumstances any good beginning is lost even before its inception.</p>
   <p>There prevails a dead calm in our community life. However, it is necessary to look for and find factors in our public life which could stir our people from their inertia and force them into active participation in the many-sided activities of our group. It is imperative to create and develop in our people the sense of public consciousness and of collective achievements. We cannot permit <pb facs="5423967_4_0580.jpg" n="2"/>our people to lose completely all their opportunities to form their own self-sufficient community. All the existing Russian societies and organizations confine their activities to those prescribed by their own particular constitutions. They do not participate in our public life in a broader sense, and do not help much to fulfill our many social and national needs. On the other hand, we should understand that not one of even the larger Russian organizations is in a position to satisfy all the needs of our group. Our general public activities cannot be squeezed into the framework of one organization or one party, and cannot be limited by the statutes of one or another organization. Each organization is doing a useful work in its own sphere of interest, but its scope is never wide enough to embrace the needs of the entire group.</p>
   <p>In order to define, systematize and bring to a proper level all public activities of separate Russian organizations, it is necessary to form a sort of synthesis of all our public needs and aspirations. Until now all Russian groups and societies have worked individually, not paying much attention to the common good of all the Russian people. Such a state of affairs has caused <pb facs="5423967_4_0581.jpg" n="3"/>stagnation and cooling off of interest in public matters among our people. The root of this condition lies in the small enmities and false prides among many of our organizations. Now is the time to look for new ways and means of successfully removing all these sore spots from the collective body of our people.</p>
   <p>Probably the most efficacious lever for lifting our Russian group to a new life would be the calling of a Russian national convention. Every person interested in the well-being of our people should wholeheartedly support such a convention. Everyone belonging to the Russian group in America should support the movement for calling the convention. The question of a convention should be taken up, in the first place, by the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and by the Russian United Mutual Aid Society, as well as by the organizations grouped around Rassviet, and by all other groups and societies, irrespective of their political or religious views.</p>
   <p>Chicago probably would be the best place for the convention. The Century of <pb facs="5423967_4_0582.jpg" n="4"/>Progress Exposition will be opened again June 1. By that time all the preparatory work can be finished. All the initial work and the working out of a program can be accomplished by our local organizations.</p>
   <p>We have had enough inactivity and quarrels among ourselves. Now is the time for unity and for work. The convention presents a serious business. No more delays! The convention should be called for next fall. Our past experience shows that no changes in our public life are possible without the calling of this convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
