<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-06">Apr. 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal from the Chicago Society to Aid the Children of Russian Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-06">Apr. 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL FROM THE CHICAGO SOCIETY TO AID THE CHILDREN OF RUSSIAN IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Compatriots: The Chicago Society To Aid The Children Of Russian Immigrants has begun to collect articles for Russian orphans. For this purpose the Chicago Society has designated the fifth week of Lent (from April 7 to 14, inclusive) as "Russian orphans week". During this week, volunteers--members of the abovenamed society--will visit homes to collect the contributions.</p>
   <p>The Society requests all Russians in Chicago and the vicinity to put aside all articles of clothing which are not needed but are still usable, as well as shoes of all sizes. All articles which are to be donated, should be securely tied into a bundle and given to the visiting volunteer. All these articles will be of inestimable value to the Russian orphans in Europe.</p>
   <p>Both the Russian and the foreign press have printed a number of articles about the suffering orphans in asylums in various countries of Europe; a whole army <pb facs="5423967_4_0307.jpg" n="2"/>could be formed of these unfortunate kids.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Society To Aid The Children Of Russian Immigrants wishes to avoid spending money to collect the discarded articles, for this money is badly needed for food, medicine, and other necessities, and it is physically impossible for the volunteers to cover the entire city. The board of directors, therefore, appeals to the members of the Russian colony to spare half an hour or an hour of their time and bring the bundles to the collection depots. The articles will be received at the following addresses:</p>
   <p>[A whole list of collection depots is given].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
