<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-21">Nov. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a"/>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-21">Nov. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American bankers have issued an appeal to all those who concur with <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in their views, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that all such persons should renounce all support of Soviet Russia and break all commercial relations with that country.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that among us Russians, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> persons who, perhaps, will welcome this appeal of the bankers. These persons will rejoice and say, That is just what these accursed bolsheviki deserve. What they should get is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> not support.</p>
   <p>One must be an out and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> his relations it his people, to rejoice when one sees that any support is denied to one's country, that this country is isolated, cursed, and spat upon.</p>
   <p>Such Russians cannot be justified, even if they do not agree with the present government of Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We can be at variance in our views with the Soviet government; we can criticize its mistakes; we can even <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> sharp remarks concerning those who, in our opinion, do act lead the people to real welfare.</p>
   <p>But such criticism will be a criticism coming from a brother who deplores the mistakes of his brother who has game astray. It will not be the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of an enery who is ready at any moment to stick a knife into Russia's back.</p>
   <p>The Soviet government has committed many mistakes and even many crimes. Since we are Russians, we can reprove that government. Only we who suffer with Russia because of its sad fate can point out these mistakes.</p>
   <p>Strangers should not intrude into the private affairs of a family when one member of the family points out the mistakes of same other member, not in order to injure the family but in order to correct the mistakes and thus to contribute to the welfare of the family.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1599.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As soon as strangers intrude, the whole family - those who are guilty and those who are not - should arise line one man and defend themselves, and not gloat over the spiteful attacks of strangers or, still worse, help to stick a knife into the of some other member of the family.</p>
   <p>We ourselves, while accusing our government or justifying it, will sooner come to understand each other and arrive at some settlement of our differences. We are one kin, and shall settle our difficulties ourselves.</p>
   <p>He is not a friend of the Russia people who helps foreigners to meddle with the affairs of the great Russian family or even sharpens a knife for a stranger who intends to use that knife for stabbing one of the members of the members of the family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
