<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Hurry!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0819</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0819.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HURRY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The period of free admission into the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is coming to an end. Only eleven days remain during which new members will be exempt from paying the regular admission fee.</p>
   <p>The great majority of our branches have already held their annual elections, and have chosen their directors for the year 1934. The new directors have taken into their hands the destinies of the branches of the R. I. M. A. S. (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) for the present year. Now their first duty is to start the work of strengthening the branches and increasing the membership of the organization. And the first step of each should be to increase the number of members in his own branch.</p>
   <p>These eleven days of grace that remain should be fully utilized in bringing new members into the branches, giving the newcomers the benefit of the exemption from the initial admission fee, which soon will be charged again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0820.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During these remaining eleven days the new directors of the branches should do their part to fill the quota of one thousand new members before the twenty-third convention of the R. I. M. A. S.</p>
   <p>The greater part of the campaigning for new members has already been done by the old directors of the branches, and, since the start of the campaign, the home office has received from the branches a large number of applications for membership in the R. I. M. A. S. The new directors must finish the campaign.</p>
   <p>According to all probability, the year 1934 will be more favorable economically for expansion of the Society than was last year. Many of our people then were simply thrown overboard from normal life by the economic crisis and by unemployment. How could they think of joining any organization at a time when they could scarcely eke out their daily subsistence? Even those who had smaller or larger insurance policies in private insurance companies had to lose them, as they could not keep up the payments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0821.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the present time, however, an improvement can be noticed. Many people are beginning to get back on their feet. This revival can also be observed in the affairs of our organization. Many of our members have owed us dues for many months; now they are paying up their arrears. So there is hope for a better future; and the new directors of our branches will have a large field of action and many opportunities during the year 1934, if they work a little and make a few sacrifices for the common good of our people. There are still thousands of Russians who are unorganized and have no insurance policies against sickness or death.</p>
   <p>There are many wives and children among our members who have not yet joined the organization of their husbands and fathers. They should join now. A good example in this respect has been shown by the youngest branch of our organization, Branch No. 18, known as the Krylov Branch. This branch has passed the resolution that every married member of the branch be obliged to bring into the organization, as members, his wife and his children. A similar measure should be adopted by other branches especially by Branch No. 1, <pb facs="5423967_4_0822.jpg" n="4"/>which has about six hundred members, and has at its command a great number eligible for membership.</p>
   <p>Thus the only way, the true way, has been shown to our national organization by one devoted branch. Remember the stronger our organization is economically, the wider and more effective will be its work in the field of its cultural and educational activities.</p>
   <p>It is possible that the frequent repetition of the slogans of the R. I. M. A. S.--"Enroll new members," "Join the ranks of the R. I. M. A. S," and the frequently repeated call for union of the Russian people in America around the R. I. M. A. S. may tire the readers of our R. I. M. A. S. page, but we cannot write about anything else, at least, at the present, when we are nearing the end of our membership campaign.</p>
   <p>There are over one million Russians in America. But only fifteen to twenty thousand of these are organized into mutual aid societies. The rest go loose, <pb facs="5423967_4_0823.jpg" n="5"/>unattached, and, like grains of sand in the desert, are blown about with the wind. This is what we are calling to the attention of the Russian group in America. This is what causes our anxiety. And, however tiresome it may be to keep repeating our warning, we shall continue to do so. We shall strike straight into the hearts of the unorganized Russians with the words: "Unite in the mutual aid societies." We shall continue to urge all Russian public workers and all members of the R. I. M. A. S. to spread everywhere the idea of mutual aid and fraternal unity, and to be active promoters of our organization.</p>
   <p>And so, dear members of the R. I. M. A. S. do not forget that there are only eleven days left for you to bring in new members exempt from the admission fee. Visit your friends, your acquaintances, and ask them to join our organization. Bring in your wives and your children, if they are not yet members of your branch.</p>
   <p>And you, Russian people who have not yet joined the ranks of the R. I. M. A. S., <pb facs="5423967_4_0824.jpg" n="6"/>answer our call, come into our ranks, and save your admission fee. The free admission period expires January 31; so hurry, bring in your wives and children. Organized as members of the R. I. M. A. S. we shall stand together, shoulder to shoulder, in defending our common interests in America.</p>
   <p>Insure the future of your family now! Only eleven days are left! Hurry!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
