<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-06-07">June 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">They Leave Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0697</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0697.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-06-07">June 7, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THEY LEAVE RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the latest reports, the Committee of the American Relief Administration and some other organizations which were helping Russia, have decided to stop their work there in the near future. The reasons for doing this are said to be as follows: The data that have been gathered show that the crop in August will be such that Russia will not need any more help from outside. The representatives of the above mentioned relief organizations stated that Russia will be able to provide herself with food. On the other hand, the newspapers are continuing to publish telegrams and letters reporting poor crops and even famine in some parts of Russia. The Soviet papers are squarely stating that there are almost five million hungry people in the Soviet Republics of Russia. The foreign papers maintain that the number of the hungry is still larger. The reports of some papers are to the effect that the number of people needing relief is from eight to ten million persons. The Nansen Relief Organization and the Quakers have figured the <pb facs="5423967_4_0698.jpg" n="2"/>same way and have decided to continue their work in Russia. As with everything concerning Russia, so also in the case of the question as to the number of those suffering from famine in that country, it is very hard to get any clear results. But it is obvious that the famine is still raging there. And that is why one cannot understand what were the reasons which prompted the Committee of the American Relief Administration to abandon its work in Soviet Russia. This organization has done a lot in the field of aid to Russia. It is to be regretted that it abandons Russia now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
