<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. N. P. Siberiakoff</title>, Pastor of the First Russian Baptist Church, Chicago, Illinois
    By Dmitri Stranden

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. N. P. Siberiakoff</title>, Pastor of the First Russian Baptist Church, Chicago, Illinois
    By Dmitri Stranden
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/><pb facs="5423967_4_1163.jpg" n="2"/>was born not in Siberia, but in Moscow where his parents were residing at the time of his birth, in 1899. He has received his first education at the Imperial Moscow School of Commerce, from which he graduated in 1918. After that he left Moscow for Vladivostok, but was detained on the way by the rising of Bohemian troops which were kept prisoners In Siberia. In Irkutsk he was forced to join Kolchak's army, and when that army was defeated he served in the people's revolutionary army of the Republic of the Far East.</p>
   <p>Before he joined that army, however, he studied law for one year in the Irkutsk University. From Irkutsk he went with the army to the Transbaikalian district to fight the Japanese troops and those of General Semenov (from 1920 to 1922). When in the summer of the year 1922 the regiment to which N. P. Siberiakoff belonged was demobilized, he went to Khabarovsk, and in the autumn of the same year left for Harbin, where he stayed till the year 1927 with his relatives. During his sojourn in Harbin he took up the interrupted study of law again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1164.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>and for one year attended lectures at the Harbin University.</p>
   <p>In April, 1927, Mr. Siberiakoff came to America (to San Francisco). He stayed there till the year 1929, and was working in a furniture factory.</p>
   <p>During his sojourn in San Francisco he became acquainted with the well-know Russian Evangelical missionary, Urbar. Even in his youth Mr. Siberiakoff had been interested in religion. Under the influence of the Rev. Urban his yearning for a religious life revived. He was converted and decided to dedicate all his life to the preaching of the Gospel. In order to prepare himself for this work, he joined the Los Angeles Bible Institute, where he studied for three years. After that he went to Kerman, Cal., where he organized a Russian elementary school for children in a colony of Russian sectarians called Pryguny (Jumpers).</p>
   <p>In the autumn of the year 1933, Mr. Siberiakoff joined the Berkeley <pb facs="5423967_4_1165.jpg" n="4"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/></p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1166.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
