<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-19">Sept. 19, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Protest against the Recognition of the Soviets!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-19">Sept. 19, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST AGAINST THE RECOGNITION OF THE SOVIETS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, the Russians--we, the sons of our crucified country, Russia--should protest, should remonstrate, through the press and by writing letters and petitions to our representatives in Washington, against the proposed recognition of the Soviet regime by the United States Government. The whole world knows the villainous methods of the bandits of the Third Internationale. By their cutthroat methods they have brought Russia,the richest country in the world, to famine, cannibalism and slow death by starvation. The world has never seen a similar example--a nation being destroyed by its own government by the systematic use of premeditated methods and by artifices for creating national famine.</p>
   <p>It is rather strange that Europe, which is well aware of this, still fusses over and dabbles with these butchers of the Russian nation, shaking their bloody hands as if they were the best of friends. But we, the Russian immigrants, believe that the noble American people and their Government will not follow <pb facs="5423967_4_0671.jpg" n="2"/>Europe's example, and will not recognize the anti-God, satanic government, which has thrown Russia and its people into the embrace of savagery and cannibalism.</p>
   <p>Mr. President, and you, the representatives of a free nation one hundred and twenty million strong, the United States of America, to your heart and to your soul we appeal, we Americans of Russian origin. Do not give recognition to the Soviet government. You know about the conditions in Russia from letters and articles written by those American workers and engineers who were employed in the Soviet hell. Before your very eyes the Bolsheviks during these sixteen years have been systematically and ruthlessly destroying the people's religion, morality, and family life, the peasants' farms, and the peasants themselves, those peasants who in the past fed by the sweat of their brows not only Russia but all of Europe. Almost before your very eyes they have annihilated over fifteen million people in Russia in recent months. All of us have witnessed the brutal destruction of our ancient memorials, the gems of our architecture. All of you have heard of the thefts of priceless masterpieces of art, and of <pb facs="5423967_4_0672.jpg" n="3"/>their sale in foreign countries, in order to provide means for the Communist propaganda work against the democracies in Europe and in America.</p>
   <p>You know well that America will not derive any material, financial gain from the recognition of the Bolshevik government. It will only strengthen the Communist propaganda against the Government of the United States. Do you, the representatives of a free American nation, really want to see yourselves and your people slaves of these hangmen and wild fanatics of the Third Internationale? Are you tired of peace and well being in your own country? Are you tired of being well fed, well clad, and free from the torture chambers of the Tcheka? [Translator's note: The all-Russian Extraordinary Commission for the Suppression of Counter-Revolution, Sabotage and Speculation.] Do you want your children, your noble Americans, to become servants of the Tcheka? Do you want to see them betray you, their parents, to this dreadful pack of wolves? Do you want your country, with an overabundance of everything, to become a country of horror and starvation, where not only dogs and cats, but also rats and mice will have been eaten and exhausted, due to the lack of food? And in the end, do you want to see <pb facs="5423967_4_0673.jpg" n="4"/>your mothers devour their own children, and the famished children eat the flesh of their parents, and even the dead bodies, in order to satisfy their hunger?</p>
   <p>No, I do not believe it nor do the Russian people, who found refuge in this free land of Washington, under the protection of the glorious banner of freedom, acquired by your heroic forefathers one hundred and fifty years ago. You are too noble and to honest for that. The principles left for your guidance by your heroes, the fighters for American independence, are too high and too noble for you to stoop to embrace the Red gospel now. No, you will not exchange your feast of freedom for the watery broth of Bolshevik promises.</p>
   <p>We Russians protest against the recognition of the Bolshevik government by America, and we ask the American Government to help Russia get rid of its bloody Communist guardians. The Russian people--clergymen, intellectuals, workers, businessmen, farmers--unite in protesting against the recognition of the Soviets by the United States of America.</p>
   <p>We have had enough of inactivity. Now it is time to act.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
