<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The New Independents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW INDEPENDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Up to the present time the only Russian Independents in America were in the Russian Orthodox parishes, which many years ago declared war on the autocratic "most holy" synod and on its officials in cassocks.</p>
   <p>At the head of this movement were the Chicago Independents, who have their church at 917 N. Wood Street.</p>
   <p>In matters of faith they and their priests proved themselves true Independents. They took in their own hands the management of their church property and possessions. They did not permit any interference from above in the inner affairs or in the affairs of their faith. Even the priests were of the parishioners' own choosing in these parishes.</p>
   <p>For this the Independents were often persecuted by adherents of the synod and its candidates.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1142.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But now, of a sudden, also the adherents of the recent synod declared themselves Independents. According to information from New York these humdrum Independents do not wish to recognize the authority of the All-Russian Church Council, and according to this same information, the Russian Orthodox Church in America becomes entirely independent, its management to be in the hands of the members and the clergy, whereas the soviet of bishops, headed by Metropolitan Platon, will be vested with the powers of the most holy synod.</p>
   <p>The reasons that urged Platon and his followers to become Independents are quite obvious.</p>
   <p>The All-Russian Church Council has, by an overwhelming majority, endorsed the government of the Soviets. In addition to this, their patriarch and shepherd, Tikhon, is being tried at present. These circumstances compelled them to turn Independents.</p>
   <p>A. Z.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
