<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-10-26">Oct. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Cultural Work Done by the Russian Center in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Extracts from the information communicated to the Rassviet by the Committee of the Russian Center).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-10-26">Oct. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CULTURAL WORK DONE BY THE RUSSIAN CENTER IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Extracts from the information communicated to the Rassviet by the Committee of the Russian Center).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the period from September 10 to October 22, 1927, the Russian Center organized eight lectures. Mr. D. L. Orlovsky gave a lecture on the theory of evolution; Mr. A. G. Ilyen lectured three times on "The Human Mind and Its Varieties," "God, Faith and Irreligion," and "Hell and Heaven"; Mr. I. Khaimovich, engineer, on "The Race Problem"; Dr. L. G. Pertsov-Kaluzhin on "The Participation of the Ukraine and of White Russia in the Future Regeneration of the Russian State"; the Rev. I. Zheltonoga on "Why are the Russians in America Disorganized, Whose Fault is It, and What Should be Done in Order that the Holy Work of Reunion May be Started by the Russians"; V. S. Khomick, on "The Power of the State and Economic Self-Government."</p>
   <p>In the near future the Russian Center intends to arrange lectures on <pb facs="5423967_4_0207.jpg" n="2"/>the following subjects: on radio (lectures by Mr. Kissel, ex-officer of the Russian navy, and by the engineers Mr. V. V. Grudin and Mr. I. Khaimovich); on statistics, chemistry and naval art(lecturer: ex-officer of the Russian navy, engineer and chemist, V. A. Meyerson). Mr. K. P. Gugis, lawyer, had promised several lectures on the laws of the United States and of the State of Illinois in particular. The following persons also promised to lecture on various subjects: Major-General Yuzefovich, Dr. A. G. Gabrielyan, Mr. Yurkevich, teacher of the Russian Douglas Park School, Dr. B. Chapman, Mr. A. G. Ilyin, D. Stranden, R. L. Strugov, the engineer V. I. Pustovoitov, Dr. L. G. Pertsov-Kaluzhin, and others.</p>
   <p>The Russian Center also planned a literary and musical evening in commemoration of the anniversary of Leo Tolstoy's death. Ilya Tolstoy junior intended to be present and to share with the public his reminiscences of the life of the great Russian writer. A similar literary and musical evening was planned for Jan. 7, 1928, the anniversary of the death of the Russian poet Yesenin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
