<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-11">Sept. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Season of Cultural and Educational Activities Opens</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0554</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0554.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-11">Sept. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SEASON OF CULTURAL AND EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES OPENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one week, all city schools will be open again. About 500,000 children will receive instruction in the public schools of Chicago this year, according to the school authorities. In addition, many thousands of young men and women, and adults as well, will continue their education in six city evening high schools. Not all the students in the evening high schools are Americans. There are many foreign-born students who are completing their studies in general subjects, or who are studying the English language, or who are learning various trades and occupations. All city schools are free and are open to everybody.</p>
   <p>At the same time many private schools and colleges are beginning their school year. Various societies and organizations are beginning to hold lectures and <pb facs="5423967_4_0555.jpg" n="2"/>special courses on a large variety of subjects. The world of art is getting ready for the inauguration of a new opera and drama season.</p>
   <p>With the opening of fall activities everywhere, the Russian Colony, too, is showing new life in some of its activities. Russian schools for children are beginning their work; here and there lectures and meetings have been announced; a Russian concert is to take place soon; and public discussions of current events and of our vital problems are now beginning to draw people from the streets.</p>
   <p>The Russian group in Chicago, however, is far behind other national groups in this city in all cultural and educational activities. Perhaps this can be explained by the fact that the Russians do not seem to possess that burning desire to improve their cultural and economic standards of life which is so apparent among other foreign-language groups in Chicago. Or there may be <pb facs="5423967_4_0556.jpg" n="3"/>other reasons why we lag behind other nationalities in preparing ourselves to take advantage of the opportunities open to everyone with the proper training. The fact is, that the evening schools have many foreign-born students of different nationalities, among whom are very few Russians, a very insignificant group when compared with the large number of Russians living in Chicago. Many attempts have been made to organize a Russian school for adults, but all these efforts have failed because nobody cared to enroll.</p>
   <p>One of the weak points in our group life is the fact that many of our organizations give concerts, lectures, and theatricals not to provide cultural, spiritual, or artistic satisfaction for the people, but in order to make money. The organizers of these affairs usually have but two considerations in mind: minimum expense and maximum audience. As a result, the quality of the lectures or the entertainments suffers. Therefore, there is no more gain from such programs.</p>
   <p>Now that the fall season of schools, lectures, concerts, and drama is with <pb facs="5423967_4_0557.jpg" n="4"/>us again, it would be wise for the Russian organizations to review their activities along these lines, revise their plans, if necessary, and establish new and higher standards for their cultural and educational work among the Russian people of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
