<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">Apr. 11, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Deficiencies of the Russian Colony and Ways to Eliminate Them</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">Apr. 11, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEFICIENCIES OF THE RUSSIAN COLONY AND WAYS TO ELIMINATE THEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The deficiencies of the Russian colony at the present time are a serious problem. It is the subject of discussion in private homes, clubs, schools, restaurants, meetings, newspapers and other public institutions. The problem is dealt with by progressives, conservatives and particularly by non-partisans and leaders of Russian organizations. Special lectures and forums are held on this topic. Thus the deficiencies and faults of our colony have become a subject of serious discussions in the whole organized and non-organized Russian colony. But all this talk leads to nowhere. In order to abolish them it is not sufficient to merely talk. It is necessary to find a right way of eliminating them and then go to work and do it.</p>
   <p>What are the demerits of our colony? If we look impartially at the social life of our colony we discern in it many delinquencies.</p>
   <p>In this article I want to point out the most important faults which are the main obstacles to the progress of our spiritual and economic life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0632.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In my opinion the most significant faults are: (1) the break-up of the colony into small groups; (2) faulty adjustment of mutual aid and mutual credit societies; (3) absence of solidarity between organizations and individual public enterprises; (4) absence of vital contacts between workers and intelligentsia; (5) absence of public institutions, such as people's homes, consumer cooperatives, high schools and poor management of schools in general, absence of people's theatres, hospitals, libraries, banks and sport facilities for youth; (6) absence of Russian settlements and larger Russian centers; (7) absence of a common year calendar to facilitate the regulation of dates for a more convenient arrangement of social events by Russian organizations. (Note: The Julian calendar is still in use.) These are our main deficiencies which have paralized the social life of our colony and retarded its development. We should struggle against these defects and find some means of effacing them as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Of course, we could find various ways of doing this, but I would like to suggest one way, which in my judgment is a good method of alleviating these <pb facs="5423967_4_0633.jpg" n="3"/>ills. It is to organize a joint committee of representatives of all Russian organizations,to invite all group leaders, and to recommend to this committee the following plan: (1) First, to improve mutual relations between organizations, in order to establish a more stable foundation of good will; (2) to endeavor to find a uniform basis for mutual aid and mutual credit societies; (3) to gradually work out projects for the creation of public institutions. Finally, it is my sincere advice to our leaders to renounce their personal ambitions and pride, for it is necessary to coordinate every effort to unite the Russian colony in Chicago, and by cooperation only can we build our strength in furthering the development of social life in our Russian colony.</p>
   <p>J. Erin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
