<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Percy</title>, 2559 W. Division Street. Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago, held on
<date when="1929-01-20">January 20, 1929</date>,
<title level="a">at the quarters of the Division St. Ymca, 1621 W. Division Street.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0200</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0200.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Percy</title>, 2559 W. Division Street. Minutes of the General Assembly of the Members of the Russian Center of the City of Chicago, held on
<date when="1929-01-20">January 20, 1929</date>,
<title level="a">at the quarters of the Division St. YMCA, 1621 W. Division Street.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The assembly is called to order at 2:30 P. M. (30 minutes too late). Present: Mr. V. D. Maslov, Mr. K. L. Kotsyubinsky, Dr. L. G. Pertsov, Mrs. S. D. Pertsov, Mr. S. G. Prokopov, and Mrs. Y. M. Prokopov.</p>
   <p>Dr. L. G. Pertsov-Kaluzhin reads the minutes of the preceding meeting which are unanimously approved without any corrections.</p>
   <p>The order of the business of the day is read:</p>
   <p>1) Election of the committee for the year 1929.</p>
   <p>2) Concerning lectures</p>
   <p>3) Concerning the by-laws</p>
   <p>4) Miscellaneous</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0201.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(a) Financial report.</p>
   <p>(b) Faying of monthly dues.</p>
   <p>(c) Sending congratulations to P. N. Milukov on the occasion of the 70th anniversary of his birth, which is going to be celebrated on Jan. 27, etc.</p>
   <p>The following persons are elected members of the committee: Mr. S. G. Prokopov, chairman for three months; Mr. V. D. Maslov, secretary for the year 1929, and Mrs. Y. M. Prokopov, treasurer for the year 1929.</p>
   <p>Re lectures - resolved: to entrust the secretary and all those members who can be helpful with the task of finding acceptable lecturers.</p>
   <p>A motion is made concerning the celebration of the centennary of the birth of the great Russian writer Griboyedov. Nobody opposes this motion. The secretary is entrusted with the task of finding a person who could read a report about Griboyedov, and also one or two artists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0202.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Concerning the matter of the by-laws it is resolved to devote one of the next general assemblies to the working up of the by-laws, making them clearer, somewhat limiting the objects of the society and, if possible, abridging the text.</p>
   <p>The ex-treasurer, Mr. K. Kotsyubinsky, burned over to the new treasurer three bank-books:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1) of the Progressive Bank -- amount</cell>
     <cell>$1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2) of the Amalgamated Bank -- amount</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3) of the Northwestern Bank - amount</cell>
     <cell>34.11</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>(Interest not included)</p>
   <p>All the members present paid to the new treasurer their dues for the month of January (25 cents).</p>
   <p>It was resolved to postpone the election of the members of the revising <pb facs="5423967_4_0203.jpg" n="4"/>committee till the time when there would be in the society at least 10 members attending its sessions.</p>
   <p>Heated debates arose in connection with Dr. Pertsov's proposal to send to Paris a greeting to Mr. P. N. Milukov, as on January 27 of the current year Mr. Milukov will celebrate the 70th anniversary of his birth. Mr. S. G. Prokopov and Mr. K. L. Kotsyubinsky opposed this motion. Ultimately the assembly settled on a compromise: it was resolved to let the greeting reach Mr. Milukov through the medium of the local press.</p>
   <p>The session is adjourned exactly at 4 P. M.</p>
   <p>It was not decided when the next session would take place. The secretary was instructed to confer later about this question with the chairman and to inform the members about the date of the assembly through the means of the press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
