<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-05">Apr. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">To the Approaching Supreme Congress of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0942</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0942.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-05">Apr. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE APPROACHING SUPREME CONGRESS OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT MUTUAL AID SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twenty-fourth annual Supreme Congress of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is approaching. In all branches of the organization elections of the delegates are now proceeding, work on compiling reports to be submitted to the Congress is going on; an intensive campaign for enlisting new members is being pressed.</p>
   <p>At the Congress it will be definitely established by what branch the best work was done, and what was generally accomplished during the year.</p>
   <p>The old members of the organization--founders of the Society--should be the first to suggest new improvements and changes to the Congress and then carry them out for the benefit and greater prosperity of the Society.</p>
   <p>In about a year's time we shall celebrate the twenty-fifth anniversary of the <pb facs="5423967_4_0943.jpg" n="2"/>founding of our Society.</p>
   <p>Twenty-five years is not a short period of time in the life of an organization. The best part of the life of many members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society was spent in and around it. For many devoted members the Society became their second home, a bit of their faraway native land.</p>
   <p>To Wood Street members of the Society threaded their way when growing lonesome for their native village, thither they went with their sorrows and joys. The women would go to the church and the men would wend their way to stand around the church, but one single feeling would gather them together around the Society and the institutions built around it--the feeling of homesickness. The members of the Society knew that when united they are stronger and there is less danger of their being lost among strange people and strange surroundings. Many of the members would bring their children to the common center.</p>
   <p>Now after a lapse of almost 25 years we see the results: a very strong brotherly <pb facs="5423967_4_0944.jpg" n="3"/>aid society has grown up to a mature stature, whose members are insured in case of sickness, and their wives and children in case of death of their fathers and husbands.</p>
   <p>The Society maintains a full page in the newspaper Rassviet devoted exclusively to its activities. Every member is free to express his own opinion in print. The Society also maintains a hall for public gatherings and a church for those who want to pray and listen to the singing in the church.</p>
   <p>Schools are provided for teaching the children in various sections of the city the mother tongue. These schools also teach music and singing.</p>
   <p>By common effort, with faith in the people and love for their culture, the members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society have united around their Society what is best among the Russians in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
