<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1923-12-26">Dec. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Russia and America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1923-12-26">Dec. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIA AND AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to latest information the recently expected agreement between Russia and the United States will not occur. Once more there have appeared difficulties in the restoration of the friendly terms between these two world's greatest republics. The Russian-American colony and our native country have learned this news with extreme regret. The many millions of people in Russia and the Russian citizens residing in America await with impatience the time of the restoration of friendly relations between these countries. At different times Russia has done much for America. America, in its turn, did the same for Russia. American aid during famine and epidemics will never be forgotten by our native country. The aid was grandiose and unexampled. America, during the famine and epidemics, saved 100,000 lives. The aid was given wide, impartially, and with American-like speed and ability. Steamships loaded with food <pb facs="5423967_4_0691.jpg" n="2"/>clothing, and medicines were sent to Russia with amazing speed. Thousands of American physicians, nurses, employees of different organizations, and officials, worked without ceasing for the aid of Russia. America gave help not only to the hungry and sick of Russia, but also to needy peasants and thousands of children. During the famine and other troubles, Russia was imbued with great sympathy towards America. One can say without exaggeration, that all of the Russian peasants, workers, intellectuals, and even children, were deeply grateful to America for its aid. Besides this there are two more reasons why Russia and the Russians in general look impatiently toward the restoration of friendly relations. The first of them is that Russia particularly needs the exchange of goods with America. This exchange is going on right now, but not on a large scale, which would be the case if America officially restored commercial relations with Russia. The second reason is as follows: hundreds of thousands of Russian citizens of different nationalities are residing in the United States. All of them keep in touch with Russia; and Russia keeps in touch <pb facs="5423967_4_0692.jpg" n="3"/>with Russians in America. Both sides are deeply interested in the restoration of good relations between the two countries. We wrote many times about the causes that are still separating these countries. In the near future we will write again about this question.</p>
   <p>But now we can certainly say that the news of their disagreement will be received by Russia very sadly. There are short telegrams about it right now.</p>
   <p>The Russian colony received this news with extreme grief.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
