<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title level="a">To the Russian - American Youth.</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title level="a">TO THE RUSSIAN - AMERICAN YOUTH.</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society hereby appeals to the Russian-American youth to fall in line and keep up the good work of this grand Fraternal Organization. The reason for making this appeal is the fact that the youth can do anything they set out to do.</p>
   <p>It is not necessary to go into much detail with regard to the reasons why the Russian American youth should join the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. We know the youth as sufficiently educated and patriotic to know that it's their national duty to belong to Russian organizations, uphold them and work hand in hand with their fathers for the betterment of their organization. However, we do think it necessary to clarify a few points regarding our Fraternal Organization. A Fraternal Organization is not merely a pure cold-blooded business proposition. It is everything that the word "Fraternal" signifies. In an insurance company, it's each man for himself. In a Fraternal Organization, we have an illustrious application of the slogan: "One for all, all for one". In A Fraternal Organization the member deals with the lodge and the lodge with the organization. If a member is unable to pay his dues, he is not suspended after thirty days as in insurance companies, but his lodge carries him for three months before he is suspended.</p>
   <p>Other advantages of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society over insurance companies are:</p>
   <p>1) It's Russian</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2) It's cheaper.</p>
   <p>3) It insures not only the member, but his nationality as well, by propagating the ideals of Russianism by engaging in educational and cultural activities.</p>
   <p>4) It does not classify its risks according to occupation.</p>
   <p>5) You pay no extra premiums for overweight.</p>
   <p>6) In the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society you take a direct hand in managing its affairs. You vote for delegates to its convention or you may be elected delegate yourself. Then you have a chance to be elected to any office in the organization. You have no such privileges in insurance companies.</p>
   <p>7) You can become an organizer yourself and get rewards for every new member you enroll.</p>
   <p>8) The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society is your organization. You are free to suggest new ideals and work for its betterment. The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society carries on campaign drives for the enrollment of new members. The chances for our youth in helping to make the drive a great success are greater then ever. Up till lately there seemed to be a great deal of objection amongst our youth to joining this Fraternal Organization. Their chief complaint was that the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society had only one kind of policy, namely, a Whole Life Policy; now it has four kinds of policies in the Adult and in the Juvenile Branches. You need insurance for your protection, you need it for the protection of your family, or your parents and you need it in the Russian Independent Mutual Aid <pb facs="5423967_4_0157.jpg" n="3"/>Society for the protection not only of yourself individually, but also of your nationality.</p>
   <p>Join now! The price of delay may be costly.</p>
   <p>Russian - American youth! Opportunity knocks at your door. Will you take it and make the best of it, or will you let it slide by?</p>
   <p>On your answer the future of the Amerykanskaya Rus depends.</p>
   <p>Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society</p>
   <p>917 North Wood Street; -Phone: Haymarket 2272, Chicago.</p>
   <p>(Note: Copied from material lent by the Secretary of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. D.S.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
