<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-01">June 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Convention of the R. I. M. A. S.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By I. Raskatov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-01">June 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONVENTION OF THE R. I. M. A. S.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By I. Raskatov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When we recall the conventions of the R. I. M. A. S. (Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society) held during the past twenty years, and particularly the first one, it is difficult to believe that from a small, insignificant group of men the Society could grow into a large and strong organization. Who would have thought twenty years ago that the Society was destined to develop into a strong force, and that its social center would become the center of social life for the entire Russian colony in Chicago and vicinity. Such a thought, perhaps, did not enter into the minds even of the founders of the Society themselves.</p>
   <p>While attending the sessions of the convention held on May 11 and 12, my thoughts went back to the distant past and to those first pioneers who laid the cornerstone of our Society. Of those men only a few remain alive at this <pb facs="5423967_4_0934.jpg" n="2"/>time. Many of them have already gone to their eternal resting place. The Society has filled their places with new and younger members, and continues to grow and prosper for the glory of the Russian name. It grows strong not in material ways alone, and the twenty-fourth annual convention did not at all resemble a casual meeting of a group of men as was the case twenty-four years ago. The convention was a well-organized, spiritually united assembly of many delegates to whose lot was entrusted the task of solving numerous problems arising out of the healthy growth of the organization. The delegates were confronted with numerous new tasks, new prospects of which the men of the first convention even did not dream. In those days the Russian people in Chicago had different desires, other aspirations, and an entirely different outlook on the future. The Russian colony in America at large entertained different hopes and had other plans as to how to build its future.</p>
   <p>The delegates to the twenty-fourth convention were confronted with problems presented by life itself and one could observe one serious stumbling block: Not many delegates possessed the gift of public speaking, and only a few <pb facs="5423967_4_0935.jpg" n="3"/>could clearly express their opinions on the subjects under discussion. Consequently, the same delegates spoke on every subject presented for consideration to the convention. It would be desirable, therefore, if the branches would take particular care to select as delegates to the convention, only such members as are able to handle the problems in the most intelligent way, and to present their own problems on the floor of the convention. It would be still better if the most active members of the Society would train themselves to speak in public. Such training would benefit both the members themselves and the Society. The convention really decides the future development of activity and consequent growth of the Society, and the more clearly the delegates are able to present their problems at the conventions, the more efficient will be their work.</p>
   <p>And the most important thing I want to say to the members of R. I. M. A. S. is this: they should be watchful and guard against the subversive activity of Bolsheviks in their midst--not to let Deviatkin and Shkliar, these Bolshevik <pb facs="5423967_4_0936.jpg" n="4"/>leaders, engender any demoralizing tendencies in the ranks of the Society, for any Bolshevik influence would be fatal to the future existence of the organization.</p>
   <p>The members of the Society should always bear in mind that these two enemies of the Russian people are always wide awake, and ready to carry the poison of their propaganda anywhere and everywhere to every place where there are Russian groups. And, unfortunately, they frequently succeed. Why? Simply because we are still too naive and credulous, and that too often we do not want, or are not able, to think for ourselves, and this is the cause of our tragedy. Nevertheless, the past convention of R. I. M. A. S. showed that gradually we begin to understand and recognize our enemies.</p>
   <p>The delegates to the twenty-fourth convention were really preoccupied with one thought and one desire--the thought of brotherly co-operation and mutual assistance. The recuperation from Bolshevism that is taking place now will bring about a great relief to the Russian colony in general, and to the <pb facs="5423967_4_0937.jpg" n="5"/>R. I. M. A. S. in particular. No matter who we are and to what particular "ism" we are attached, first of all we should remain Russians.</p>
   <p>This is demanded of us by the moral code, our native tongue, and our culture. And still more it is demanded by our spiritual being, by our Russian soul which nothing can supplant.</p>
   <p>We Russian people, have never had any serious quarrel among ourselves, and only outsiders can bring troublesome discord in our midst. Had not Mr. Deviatkin with his followers sown enmity among us, the Russian colony in America would have lived as one happy family. For this very reason one would desire that every member of the Russian colony should give serious thought to the present situation and break off every tie that binds him or her to these "comrades". We should with one unanimous voice declare that we have no need for their particular kind of guardianship. We can settle all our disagreements among ourselves in a peaceful way without intermediaries from outside. We know <pb facs="5423967_4_0938.jpg" n="6"/>what we want, and we know the road which we shall follow to attain our objectives.</p>
   <p>The twenty-fourth annual convention has already shown us that we possess the spirit of reconciliation and the sense of fair play. We have the innate desire to be and act together. This realization gives us hope that when the time arrives for our twenty-fifth annual gathering we shall understand one another still better, we shall unite more closely, and shall give the final rebuff to the enemies of all that is Russian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
