<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-04-07">Apr. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Independents--Read This!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-04-07">Apr. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENTS--READ THIS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-American Orthodox Mutual Aid Society, known as the St. Vladimir's Society, because of its erroneous insurance methods, after ten years of existence, has been forced to cease its activities as an independent organization, and to join a stronger organization. During the process of the selection of a stronger organization to join, much pressure was exerted from every side, as frequently happens in our public life, with the result that the St. Vladimir Society split into three separate groups. One group, headed by Archbishop Tikhon, joined the Union of the Russian Orthodox Fraternities of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Another group joined the Brotherly Love Society of Mayfield, Pennsylvania. The third group, not wishing to join an organization located in another state, when there was an old-established, strong, and well-managed Russian organization in Chicago, joined the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. The group adopted a new name: The Ascension Fraternity, Branch No. 22 of the R. I. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. A. S.</p>
   <p>Those who joined the Pittsburgh organization frown upon the new Independents.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0791.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No one gives them the support they so much need during their financial crisis. They cannot even get a hall for their meetings at the parish-house of the parish to which most of them belong. But those who joined the Pittsburgh organization are allowed free use of the parish hall in this same parish. This is the situation in which the new branch of the Independent Society now finds itself.</p>
   <p>It should be the policy of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society to extend its aid to every newly-organized branch, and especially now to Branch No. 22. In and around Chicago there are a number of small independent Russian Mutual Aid Societies, which sooner or later will be compelled to join some larger Russian organization for the same reason that the St. Vladimir Society had to do so. In order to keep these small societies from joining larger Russian organizations located hundreds or thousands of miles away, the members of our R. I. M. A. S. should do all in their power to convince these smaller societies that it would be to their benefit to join a strong local Russian organization. This is one reason why the old branches of the R. I. M. A. S. should give a hand to their youngest fellow-member, Branch No. 22, <pb facs="5423967_4_0792.jpg" n="3"/>which is finding it difficult to become established.</p>
   <p>Branch No. 22 has arranged a special social gathering to be held Sunday, April 15, at 1902 West Division Street. Let us show these younger brothers of ours that we are with them. Let us all come to this gathering. Let us demonstrate to this group comprising our youngest branch that the great family of the Independents is closely knit together, and is always willing and ready to help its younger brethren. All future progress and success of Branch No. 22 now depends upon our loyal support and co-operation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
