<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Memorandum on Russian Organizations in Chicago</title> Prepared for Foreign Language Project by Mark Khinoy, Jewish Daily Forward, New York,
<date when="1937-06-01">June 1, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[Russian Organizations]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Memorandum on Russian Organizations in Chicago Prepared for Foreign Language Project by Mark Khinoy, Jewish Daily Forward, New York</title>,
<date when="1937-06-01">June 1, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[RUSSIAN ORGANIZATIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We came to Chicago from Paris, via Southampton, Glasgow, London, and New York. We, in this case, means my wife, Mrs. Dina Zarjevsky-Khinoy; myself, Mark Khinoy, and our four-year-old daughter, Alexandra. We came in October, 1913. We came as political exiles from tsarist Russia, where all three of us had our taste of tsarist prisons; Alexandra, because she was born in the women's political prison at Petrograd (then St. Petersburgh); Mrs. Khinoy and I, because during our many years of underground activity in the cause of liberty we were arrested, Mrs. Khinoy six times, and I, four times. Before my final escape abroad I spent forty-three months in prison, and was twice exiled to Siberia.</p>
   <p>On our arrival in Chicago we found quite a large colony of Russian emigrants. Some of them hailed from the Baltic provinces of Russia, Letts, Lithuanians, Esthonians and Finns; some from Poland and western provinces of the Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_1636.jpg" n="2"/>empire, - Poles, Jews, and Ruthenians; some from Southern Russia and Ukrania. Very few, if any, came from the purely Russian (Great Russian) districts. The Russians proper in this multitude of Russian subjects were almost exclusively from the guberniyas (states) of Minsk, Grodno, Vilna and Holyn. It should be noted that these four districts of old Russia did not possess local self-government (zemstvo), which by that time had already established a network of public schools in the agrarian districts of the thirty-four zemstvo guverniyas. And since the four guberniyas mentioned above were non-industrial in character, the native sons they sent to this country were culturally backward, a great number of them illiterate. Economically most of the Russians in Chicago were unskilled laborers with a low standard of living, sometimes ten or fifteen men living in one "community house." The social life outside of the church was almost non-existent. The only active educational and cultural factors of the Russian community of that period were the Russian branches of the Socialist party and the non-political organizations influenced by them. Their lectures, meetings, free <pb facs="5423967_4_1637.jpg" n="3"/>libraries and schools, contributed both to the cultural betterment of the Russian colony as Russians and workers, and to the Americanization process of the immigrants.</p>
   <p>There were in Chicago in the fall of 1913 two Russian branches of the Socialist party. One of them had its headquarters in Hull House, and the other, called Branch No. 4, had its headquarters at 1233 N. Robey St. I. Laveter, one of the oldest and most active members of the Russian colony in Chicago, was the secretary of Branch 1. The other officers of this branch were Khadmovich, Levitt, and Statuyev. The officers of Branch 4, in the second half of 1913, consisted of the following: N. Ratoff, secretary; N. Matass, financial secretary; E. Nikiforoff, treasurer; and Poladneff, librarian. To these names should be added Maximenko, who became the recording secretary in June, 1914; Kravets, who was elected financial secretary in June, 1914; Juk, Gaidalovich, Bell, Ivan Lagoda, Stolar, and Likhachov, members of the executive committee during that period. Bell died in Chicago <pb facs="5423967_4_1638.jpg" n="4"/>in 1918; Likhachov, a few years later, in Russia. Lagoda has been a resident of New York since 1918.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of Branch 1, from June, 1914, to the end of 1915, consisted of the following: Loktev, Silin, Gerin, Zurman, Statuyev, and Laveter (died in Chicago in 1933, I think).</p>
   <p>Details about the Russian branches in Chicago prior to 1913 may be found in the photostat copy of the printed short history of the branches appearing in the Chicago section of the Russian daily Novy Mir (Sept. 10, 1914).</p>
   <p>Chicago at that period was also the headquarters of the Regional committee (Oblastnoy Comitet) of the Russian branches of the Socialist party in North western states. The committee was elected at a special conference which took place in Chicago in January, 1913, and consisted of the following (according to Novy Mir, Jan. 17, 1913): Belousoff, former member of the Russian Duma; <pb facs="5423967_4_1639.jpg" n="5"/>Rusoff, Stolar, Statuyev, and Mikiforoff. Belousoff, the secretary, had to leave Chicago for Minneapolis, and was replaced (in November, 1913) by Ratoff. Ratoff died in the Soviet Union a few years ago.</p>
   <p>Besides the two branches in Chicago there were three in three neighboring cities: Kenosha, Wis., where the leading spirit for years was a mechanic and Russian Social-Democrat, Chumak (executed by White officers in Eastern Siberia, 1918-19): Milwaukee, Wis., where the leader was an old metal worker from St. Petersburgh, also a social-Democrat, Timoshenko, now in Detroit; and Rockford, Ill., whose leaders' names I do not recall.</p>
   <p>Since I joined Branch 4 I am better acquainted with its activities than with any other. This branch became, in 1917, a large mass organization with hundreds of members, but even in 1914 it was an active cultural and Socialist <pb facs="5423967_4_1640.jpg" n="6"/>organization. An example of its activities is revealed in the semi-annual report of its officers, as published in Novy-Mir for July, 1914. During the six-month period the branch organized eleven free lectures with an average attendance of forty at each lecture. Also five larger educational meetings with an average attendance of 250. The branch's library had 102 subscribers. Among the lecturers should be mentioned Michael Berg, alias Grusonberg, director and owner of the Berg Progressive Preparatory School, 2058 W. Division Street, a member of the branch, who is now the editor in chief of the Moscow News, under the name of Borodin. Also Dr. Krasnow, a physician, still residing in Chicago; Ratoff, Likhachov, Stolar, and M. Khinoy. Later this list was increased with the names of L. Geruss, ex-member of the second Russian Duma; Dr. Knapfnagel, Ozol (also an ex-member of the Duma from Latvia, who lectured once); Nabatoff, from Detroit; Chumak, from Kenosha; Timoshenko, from Milwaukee; and Derman, a Lettish writer from New <pb facs="5423967_4_1641.jpg" n="7"/>York. The list is far from being complete, for there were occasional lectures by other people. Dr. Sahud, a Chicago resident, among them. However, mention should be made of two lecturers that were especially active in the years of 1915 and 1916, and part of 1917. One of them is now in Russia. Kievsky is his name. The other one, M. Polak, a brilliant speaker and lecturer, died from influenza in 1920 (?). From time to time lecturers came from New York. Among them was the secretary of the Russian federation, Melnichansky, at present a discarded leader of Soviet trade unions; Madame Alexandra Kolontai, now Soviet ambassador to Norway, who visited the United States in December, 1915, until January, 1916; and Nikolai Bukharin, who later became a leader of the Soviet Union and of the Communist International, and still later an alleged Trotskyist counter-revolutionary.</p>
   <p>Russian Branch No. 4, as mentioned before, had in 1913 its headquarters at 1233 N. Robey Street. From there it moved to 1206 N. Hoyne Avenue. This place, however, was burned down in November, 1914. The next headquarters were <pb facs="5423967_4_1642.jpg" n="8"/>established at 2131 Evergrean Avenue, where, in addition to the meeting place and library, there also functioned a might school for member and non-members. The school had four instructors: Dr. Knopfnagel, Kievsky, Polak, and Khinoy. All working without remuneration, naturally.</p>
   <p>When we came to Chicago we found there a very active non-partisan organization of Russian Socialist and Socialist sympathizers of all shades of political opinion, working under the name of Relief Society for Political Prisoners and Exiles in Russia. It collected large amounts of money that went to the victims of tsarist oppression in Siberia, penitentiaries, and other places of exile and imprisonment. The leading spirit of this organization was M. Stolar, at present city editor of the Moscow News. Others active included F. Kogan, a druggist, an escaped political prisoner (Social-Democrat) from Siberia, and his wife, a Chicago lawyer, Esther Rovsky, who alternated for years as financial secretaries of the organization. Both live now in Chicago, where <pb facs="5423967_4_1643.jpg" n="9"/>they own a drug store at the corner of north Oakley and Chicago Avenue. This organization numbered at one time more than 100 members, and among them the Dubrov family, Ivan Lagoda, Mr. F. Berg, and Miss Sheinman, seem to have been the most active.</p>
   <p>Among other organization functioning in the Russian colony in the years of 1913 until 1921 was the Union of Russian workers, a semi-syndicalist anarchist organization. The center of their activity was a workers' institute, a free evening school for Russians conducted by a Chicago lawyer and former Russian Social-Democrat, Tobinson, who, under the name of Krasnoschokov, became after the revolution the Communist leader of the Far Eastern Republic. Later he was convicted of embezzlement of state funds, and then became director of the state bank in Rostov-Don.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
