<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title>,
<date when="1917-11-09">Nov. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To All Organizations of Russian Immigrants in Chicago and its Suburbs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title>,
<date when="1917-11-09">Nov. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL ORGANIZATIONS OF RUSSIAN IMMIGRANTS IN CHICAGO AND ITS SUBURBS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian colonies of the United States will gather at a convention for the consideration of a whole series of questions which have arisen in connection with the latest events in Russia and the United States. To consider the unification of the Russian colony of Chicago and its suburbs, a conference was called in Chicago of the representatives of the Russian organization. This conference elected a provisional committee for the convocation of the proposed conference of representatives of all organizations of Russian immigrants. It was decided to invite one delegate from each organization which has twenty-five members or less and two delegates from each organization which has more than twenty-five members. The provisional committee has called this conference to meet on November 13 at 8 P.M. in the building of the Russian branch of the American Socialist Party, 1149 North Campbell Avenue. We beg all those organizations which have not yet elected delegates to the conference to elect them and <pb facs="5423967_4_0889.jpg" n="2"/>send them to the next meeting. If in some organizations there are not to be any meetings before the date set, then, we beg their secretaries to be present at the conference.</p>
   <p>The Provisional Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
