<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-13">Feb. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Details of Negotiations Concerning Soviet Debts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-13">Feb. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DETAILS OF NEGOTIATIONS CONCERNING SOVIET DEBTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press has begun to give out [some of the] details concerning the unsuccessful attempts to settle the question of debts with the Soviet government. "Behind the flat refusal of Cordell Hull to accept the latest compromise offer made by Mr. Troyanovsky, the Soviet Ambassador in Washington, is concealed a very interesting [piece of] diplomatic strategy," writes an American observer, Durno.</p>
   <p>It is estimated that Soviet Russia owes the United States seven hundred million dollars. The offer was made to the Soviets that one hundred and fifty million dollars be paid in installments. As a lure, the offer included a promise to open up a credit account with the Export-Import Bank for one hundred million dollars, the bank being organized for the sole purpose of financing trade with Soviet Russia. This amount of credit was to be renewed every five years,provided the payments were met by the Soviets regularly. In this way, American <pb facs="5423967_4_0667.jpg" n="2"/>heavy industry could receive the large orders which it needs badly.</p>
   <p>The Soviets, however, insisted on receiving cash for their consent to pay even a part of the old debt. With this money, they expected to purchase rails, locomotives, agricultural machinery, and other equipment at much cheaper prices in European countries. Uncle Sam is quite familiar with these tactics of the Bolsheviks. Of course, our industrialists, would gain nothing thereby, and the government in Washington rejected the proposal.</p>
   <p>Advices to the effect that the American envoy in Moscow, William Bullitt, will be compelled to retire from his post following the failure of the negotiations, were denied on the ground that Mr. Bullitt was the one who had suggested the course followed by Mr. Hull.</p>
   <p>Our only hope of gaining anything from dealing with Moscow lies in our firm <pb facs="5423967_4_0668.jpg" n="3"/>refusal to advance cash, because that refusal will seriously impair the credit standing of the Soviets with European countries, where they make most of their purchases.</p>
   <p>On October 15, Soviet Russia owed Germany about one hundred and twenty million dollars for its commercial transactions; it owed England approximately forty million, and close to thirty million dollars to other European countries. The Soviets owed about ten million dollars to the U. S. Their total indebtedness, therefore, amounted to about two hundred million dollars.</p>
   <p>We can force the Soviet Union to accept our goods, and our credit advances on our terms, only in the event that European countries refuse to advance further credits to the Soviets. In this connection, however, it is important to remember that Soviet Russia produces nearly two hundred and fifty million dollars worth of gold annually. One of the American proposals suggested the use <pb facs="5423967_4_0669.jpg" n="4"/>of this gold in payment of the debt, but the Soviets rejected this proposal although this gold would make possible a huge increase of Soviet purchases in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
