<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-08-26">Aug. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Amendment of the Constitution and Laws of Th Eindependent Society</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-08-26">Aug. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">AMENDMENT OF THE CONSTITUTION AND LAWS OF TH EINDEPENDENT SOCIETY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday (Note: - The convention took place on Aug. 23, 1925. N. K.) took place the last session of the 14th Convention of the Russian People's Independent Orthodox Society of St. George on Wood Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>The question discussed was that of amending the constitution of the society, which had become obsolete, and of eliminating from it clauses which had lost any practical value and, in some cases, even interfered with the expansion of the society and its activities.</p>
   <p>Among these clauses there are, f. i., such the reading of which produces in the mind of the reader of this constitution the impression that the People's Independent Society is not an organization of mutual aid, but a group of church people who are not concerned with anything beyond such purely clerical matters as the consecration of churches, confession and the propaganda of Russian Orthodox Christianity in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0097.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This prevented many persons from joining the largest Russian organization in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In reality all such clauses have already for a long time not been observed in the society, which is not a group of church people only, but a reliable society of mutual aid. Nobody forces one to visit the church and to go to confession; nobody tells one, Go and spread the Russian Orthodox faith.</p>
   <p>Now something totally different is being talked of in the society, We must expand the activity of our organization; we must insure our members, give them support and relief; loan them money, etc. As to religion, it concerns the conscience of each individual member of the society. We have a church and a parish, we have a priest, and if someone wants to become a parishioner of our church, we welcome him. The society will not put any obstacles in his way.</p>
   <p>Someone had proposed to call the society just Russian People's Independent Society of Mutual Aid, and to leave to the parish its previous <pb facs="5423967_4_0098.jpg" n="3"/>name of Russian Orthodox Parish of St. George. Every parishioner could be a member of the Independent Society, and every member of the society, or even one who is not a member of it, could at any time become a parishioner.</p>
   <p>In other words, it should be acknowledged as a necessary principle that the liberty of any of the members of the society, or of the parish, should not be violated by forcing them to believe or not to believe in certain things, or to participate in political activities or not do so.</p>
   <p>The society should not concern itself with religion and politics. Outside the walls of the society everybody can do what he likes.</p>
   <p>The parishioners of the Parish of St. George objected to such a view. A discussion took place after which the chairman, Mr. Ustich, put to the vote the question as to whether the constitution of the society should be amended or not.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0099.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As a result of voting by closed ballot, it was resolved by a majority of votes that the constitution should be amended.</p>
   <p>The meeting was quite orderly. Both those who objected to any changes in the constitution and those who thought them to be necessary were thinking only about one thing: What would be better for the society, what would strengthen it, not disperse it.</p>
   <p>Some think that it would be better to introduce some changes into the constitution; others hold that no changes are necessary. Both parties consist of persons who are undoubtedly friends of the society, who are concerned with its welfare and have been doing some work for the good of the society. It happened that the majority held that the constitution should be amended, and those who were against it submitted to the decision without any further disputations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0100.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The voice of the people is the voice of God; consequently through it the truth is expressed.</p>
   <p>After the voting a special committee was elected to which was entrusted the revision of the constitution, a new draft of which should be presented to the next convention in 1926, so that it can be sanctioned by the delegates of all the branches of the society.</p>
   <p>The following persons were elected members of this committee: Fedor Ustich, Semyor Yakimovich, Ivan Kulak, Nik. Shlyapo, Isidor Shkroba, P. Gulko, Nik. Kucherepa, Ev. Sizik, Sem. Fedorovsky, A. Keresuk, and Sem. Zavoda.</p>
   <p>These persons will have to present to the next convention a draft of an amended constitution of the society.</p>
   <p>A. Khudyakov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
