<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-05-09">May 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Russian Group Is Behind Other Nationalities in Social, Economic and Political Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. F. Erin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0573</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0573.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-05-09">May 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE RUSSIAN GROUP IS BEHIND OTHER NATIONALITIES IN SOCIAL, ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. F. Erin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When I entered the arena of political life I often had an opportunity of participating in the meetings and various social affairs of national groups other than the Russian in this city--Polish, Jugoslav, Lithuanian, Carpatho-Ruthenian, Ukrainian, etc. In my contacts with these nationalities I was always pleasantly surprised with the efficiency and success with which they conducted their meetings, their theatricals, their parties and other group affairs. It was easy to notice understanding, harmony and solidarity in all their actions.</p>
   <p>Our Russian group is trailing behind these other national groups in its general development. What are the reasons for our slowness and our failings? As far as numbers are concerned, our group occupies second place among the <pb facs="5423967_4_0574.jpg" n="2"/>national groups in Chicago and Cook County, according to the last census. In the sense of cultural values and representation in the realm of the arts we occupy first place. This fact is appreciated by other nationalities.</p>
   <p>In my opinion, the chief reason for our backwardness lies in the fact that other national groups are united and inspired by their national spirit. However they may be divided on political and other matters, when it comes to a question having a bearing on their nationality they are united as one man. Also, they are well organized. They have good leaders whom they esteem and support. And, above all, they praise highly and preserve their native culture and native arts, no matter what their social or economic position may be. They imbue their children with their national spirit and with high respect for their national values and for their older generation, with which their youth forms one well-knit social structure. They, also, with the aid and support of their leaders, strive to acquire affluence and to rise to power in politics and in city, state, and Federal service. All these facts, taken together, constitute their power and explain their <pb facs="5423967_4_0575.jpg" n="3"/>advanced position in the life of this city.</p>
   <p>In the life of our Russian group all these things are lacking. Our national spirit has been destroyed. We are not organized. We do not value our native culture and our native arts. When Chaliapin, Rachmaninov, or some other great Russian artist arrives in our city, one can meet at his concerts almost everyone but the Russians, who are so numerous in Chicago. When Paderewski is in Chicago it is a great holiday for the entire Polish population of the city. When Misha Elman or Rosa Raisa stop in Chicago the Jewish group of the city celebrates the occasion with joy, and attends their concerts in large numbers.</p>
   <p>Let us take up now the school question. The Poles, for instance, regard it their duty to teach their children their native tongue. The Russians do not pay much attention to this very important matter, saying that their children will not want to return to Russia and therefore do not need to know the Russian language. Thus the Russian parents repulse and estrange their own children, allowing them to spend their time on the streets in the worst of <pb facs="5423967_4_0576.jpg" n="4"/>surroundings rather than sending them to a Russian school, where they could learn to speak, read and write in their native tongue.</p>
   <p>We do not encourage enough our foremost citizens, those prominent and active in public life, no matter how honest and able they are. We rather push them into the background and heap abuse and slander upon them. We listen to the Communists and we crowd their meetings, while we allow true Russians, lecturers and professors, to talk, usually to empty chairs.</p>
   <p>Where are those Communist leaders who in the past so thoroughly fleeced the Russian people of their pennies and their dollars for the great Communist cause? They are all back in Soviet Russia, occupying exalted positions as commissars. Many of the Russian schools for children have been communized. Our societies have been overrun by the Bolsheviks. This is the kind of organization, of community life, and of national spirit that has been molding our destiny in this adopted country of ours. And these are the reasons why we are far behind other national groups in our general development.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0577.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>All this can be changed, however. We have among us representatives of our high cultural values; we have our own experienced people of high integrity prominent in public life; we have our youth, which has received an American education. The problem now is to attract our youth to the work and the institutions of our older generation. This can be successfully accomplished only when our young people are conversant with the language of their fathers.</p>
   <p>American public life is built around politics and political parties. Political parties struggle among themselves for control of all public institutions, local, state and Federal. In addition, there is a constant struggle within the parties, where various groups strive to gain supremacy for their favored men.</p>
   <p>The Russian nation has made many valuable contributions to the culture of our civilized world, in art, in music, in literature. But now the Russian people are themselves in great need. They need a national awakening. They are in dire need of unity among themselves and solidarity in their activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0578.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Only then shall we be treated, not as a stepchild but as a full-grown offspring of the great American family; and only then shall we take the honored place which is our due among the national groups in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
