<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-06">Apr. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization of the State of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0706</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0706.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-06">Apr. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN CITIZENS' ORGANIZATION OF THE STATE OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear compatriots, Russian people! The reconstruction that is now taking place in the social and economic life of the country compels us to be active and attentive to all that happens around us in our everyday life. To be passive and to lead an individual, secluded life, as many of us have done in the past, is no longer possible. This would be to remain out of touch with rapidly changing conditions, and it would constitute a threat to our survival among others more adaptable to the new environment. It would mean that we should be deprived of all the rights enjoyed by the citizens of this country. Formerly it was permissible for any one to retain his foreign citizenship, for nowhere except at the polls would any one ask you to show your citizenship papers. If you had strong muscles and knew your trade, you could get a job just as easily as a citizen. In all other ways you enjoyed almost the same rights as citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0707.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At present it is quite different, however. Now, because of the strict immigration laws that have recently been passed, aliens are severely restricted in many ways. If you are a foreigner, you may not, for instance, conduct certain kinds of business in your own name. Aliens are altogether barred from service jobs. A foreigner cannot get a good job even with a private firm. An alien is not entitled to receive the old-age pension or the other subsidies which are paid by the Government to citizens. In other words, your rights are limited in every way.</p>
   <p>Our return to our native land in the near future is impossible, and if some of us get a chance to go back, American citizenship will not interfere with our going; on the contrary, it may help in many ways. For that reason we recommend that every Russian shall take out citizenship papers before it is too late.</p>
   <p>But this is not all. In order to enjoy equal rights with the rest of the citizens, it is necessary to be well organized and to take active part in <pb facs="5423967_4_0708.jpg" n="3"/>the social and political life of the country on an equal footing with other nationalities. The Russian-American Citizens' organization has already made a good start in organized and systematic work. The foundation has already been laid, and the work is proceeding successfully. Now we need only the support of the entire Russian colony, both men and women. Women of other nationalities take just as active part as men in the social and political affairs of the city.</p>
   <p>So let us all put our shoulders to the wheel. We have lost much time, and now we must make up for it. We are lagging far behind others, and we should catch up with them. We must mobilize all our forces for work on the social and political front. There can be only one purpose in this work--the defense of our citizenship rights; therefore there should be no differences among us. We should all, as one man, unite in one mighty family and put up a single front for the defense of our rights and to obtain recognition, so that we may occupy our proper place among other nationalities. The sooner we get organized, the more members we shall, <pb facs="5423967_4_0709.jpg" n="4"/>have, and the more energetically we work, the quicker will our victory be, and the sooner shall we reach our goal.</p>
   <p>According to the latest statistical data there are 177,000 Russians in Cook County alone. For a long time we have been entitled, on the basis of numbers, to have our representatives in the city and the State administrations. Then let us work hand in hand in order to obtain this representation.</p>
   <p>The administration of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization calls upon every Russian residing in this State to join the ranks of our society. There is practically no expense involved in joining us, for our membership fee for a whole year is only one dollar, with no initiation fee at all, and yet the advantages may be great both for the individual and for the entire Russian colony. Do not postpone it till to-morrow; come and join us to-day at our headquarters, 1902 West Division Street. Our office is open from seven o'clock in the evening <pb facs="5423967_4_0710.jpg" n="5"/>till midnight. There you will receive all the necessary information pertaining to our organization and may pay your dues. If you want to become an American citizen, our office will fill out the application forms for you for both first and second papers. There you may bring your forms to be filled out to apply for the soldiers' bonus if you are a veteran of the World War. There you may obtain all other information. All services are rendered gratis.</p>
   <p>Administration</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
