<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-02-16">February 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Capital of Crime</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-02-16">February 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE CAPITAL OF CRIME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With such a title the city of Chicago was honored, and it was called so, not by an antagonist of the American social order, but by one of its champions. At the present time there is an election campaign going on. One of the candidates for mayor, Mr. Edward Litzinger, criticized the city and county administration. In his speech about its many sins and faults, he emphasized the fact that the present administration made Chicago the capital of crime. According to Mr. Litzinger, crime is overwhelming the city. During the last five years, the candidate says, the number of crimes increased by 93 per cent; he had in mind only killings for robbery. He puts all the blame on the city administration, which is occupied with everything but fighting crime. Mr. Litzinger promises severe punishments to the criminals if he is elected, and assures that he will clean the city of crime in sixty days. It is understood that these promises will not be fulfilled; first, because <pb facs="5423967_4_0462.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Litzinger would not be elected, and secondly, because no candidate, with rare exceptions, keeps his promises. Another reason why his promises could not be fulfilled is that fighting crime with serve measures of punishment cannot be successful. Crime, like any other social phenomenon, has its causes, and to destroy crime you must eliminate its causes. Yet, not one word about it was mentioned by Mr. Litinger. Nevertheless, Mr. Litzinger's arraignment of the present administration deserves attention. He openly speaks about the negative sides of the present order of things and crime, while others prefer not to talk about it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
