<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Bishop Leontiy of Chicago</title>, 1121 N. Leavitt St.,
<date when="1937-02-24">Feb. 24, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview With Bishop Leontiy of Chicago</title>, 1121 N. Leavitt St.,
<date when="1937-02-24">Feb. 24, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bishop Leontiy's name, before he became a monk, was Leonid Ieronymovich Turkevich. He was born in 1876 in the Province of Volyn. His father was arch-priest of the City of Kremenets. There he received his education first in the Theological Seminary, and after that completed it in the Theological Academy of Kiev. He was graduated from this Academy in 1900 with the degree of Bachelor of Theology.</p>
   <p>He went through the pedagogic stage in Ekaterinoslav and in Kursk. After that he married and was appointed a priest in Kremenets where he also taught in the Diocesan School for clergy girls of the Volyn District.</p>
   <p>In 1906 he was transferred to the North American Diocese and was Rector of the Theological Seminary and Rector of the Russian Orthodox parish in Minneapolis from 1906 to 1911. From 1911 to 1915 he was Dean of the Cathedral in New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1022.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1925 he lost his wife and took the monastic vows and in the same year was made Bishop of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Bishop Leontiy has developed an extraordinary literary activity. He started to write on Theological subjects very early in his life, while living in Russia.</p>
   <p>Later he was editor of the Russian American Orthodox Herald (Russko-Amerikanskiy Pravoslavniy Vestnik, organ of the Russian Orthodox Church in America, published in New York) from 1914 to 1930. He was also editor of the newspaper Sviet (Light) from 1914 and still remains a collaborator of this paper.</p>
   <p>He callaborated in 1917 with the Russkaya Zenilya (Russian Land),a magazine published in New York), and from 1918 to 1920 in the New York magazine Golos Tserkvi (The Voice of the Church). In 1921 and 1922 he was editor of the religious monthly magazine Dobry Pastyr (The Good Shepherd, N.Y.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1023.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He was collaborator of the newspaper Nedelya (The Week, N.Y.) in 1921; of the papers Pravoye Dyelo (The Righteous Cause, N.Y.) in 1923; Russkaya Mysl (Russian Thought, N.Y.) in 1924, and Pravoslavniy Khristianskiy Vyestnik, (The Orthodox Christian Herald, published in Cleveland) in 1924 and 1925.</p>
   <p>While living in Russia the Bishop published a pamphlet entitled Dookhovnye Russkiye Zhurnaly za 1906 god (Russian Religious Magazines for the year 1906, published in Kremenets) and some other pamphlets. He has also contributed many articles to various Russian religious magazines and papers.</p>
   <p>In the United States the Bishop has published in English a pamphlet entitled Essays on Orthodoxy(N.Y. 1918). He has also contributed articles in English in the years 1918 to 1920) to the magazine, Constructive Quarterly.</p>
   <p>Under the Bishop's editorship was published in 1934, in Wilkes-Barre, Pa. and Orthodox Prayerbook (Pravoslavny Molitvoslov), with parallel texts in ancient Slavonic and English. He has contributed many articles to the following Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_1024.jpg" n="4"/>newspapers published in America; to the Chicago Rassviet (The Dawn), to the Novaya Zarya (The New Dawn, published in San Francisco) and to the Novoye Russkoye Slovo (The New Russian Word, published in New York). He is author of Ocherki Istorii Russkoy Provoslavnoy Tserkvi v Amerikye (Essays on the History of the Russian Orthodox Church in America) published in 1928 in the Calendar Pravoslavnoye Soyedineniye (The Orthodox Union) in Pittsburgh.</p>
   <p>Finally Bishop Leontiy is a talented poet and under various pseudonyms has contributed poetry to different Russian-American newspapers and magazines.</p>
   <p>When asked by me whether the Russian Orthodox Church in Chicago carries on any anti-communistic activities, Bishop Leontiy answered in substance as follows: there is no necessity of any militant anti-communist propaganda for the Russian Orthodox Church. Its very existence here in Chicago, in the midst of a population which has been strongly influenced by communist atheistical propaganda is a protest against this propaganda. Besides any campaign against communism, <pb facs="5423967_4_1025.jpg" n="5"/>carried on by the Church, would only induce the communists to undertake a correspondingly more energetic atheistical propaganda. The only effective way of fighting bolshevistic communism is to further the moral and spiritual development of the Russian colony. When this will be done the communist propagandists will not have any success any more. As it is, during the last few years the Russian communists have not been as militant as before in attacking the Church. The communists, said the Bishop, have been unwittingly done a service to the Orthodox Church by their persecution of it. This cruel persecution has eliminated out of the ranks of both the clergy and the laity those insincere and unreliable elements which were only a burden to the Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
