<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-02-18">Feb. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Loss</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial of the RnzOv, Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshechestvo Vzaimopomoshchi, the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-02-18">Feb. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT LOSS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial of the RNzOV, Russkoe Nezavisimoe Obshechestvo Vzaimopomoshchi, The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"To the fortunate one--the enemies are dying</p>
   <p>To the unfortunate one--a friend is dying"....</p>
   <p>These words bring the sad news of the death of V. S. Levkovich. This death, suddenly and brutally snatches from the Russian colony its best friend, its great social welfare worker, V. S. Levkovich, who gave all of his time in an effort to develop among the Russians love for their native land, and to lead them on the path toward mutual aid--toward unity.</p>
   <p>There was not a single important activity in which V. S. Levkovich did not participate, giving his deep love for the Russian cause, his fervent energy <pb facs="5423967_4_0471.jpg" n="2"/>and his passion to fight for the interests and benefit of the Russian colonists.</p>
   <p>If a new branch of RNzOV was to be organized or a new Russian school was to be opened--you could be sure that V. S. Levkovich was already involved; he spoke, he encouraged, he agitated. The amount of work, energy, and money that Levkovich gave for the establishment of the Russian schools is known only to his closest friends.</p>
   <p>His desire for unity was particularly prominent. As if foreseeing his end, he, in all of his public appearances and written statements, eagerly and enthusiastically urged the Russians: "Brothers, unite, forget all your disagreements and your quarrels. Remember that we are all children of one country, one Mother Russia!"</p>
   <p>This invocation was the foundation and inspiration of the lifework of V. S. Levkovich for the past several years. He dreamt of establishing a Russian <pb facs="5423967_4_0472.jpg" n="3"/>National Hall of the RNzOV...He dreamt of establishing a goodRussian press. And now he has unexpectedly passed away. The great Russian patriot is gone forever.</p>
   <p>With deep sorrow in our hearts, we are forced to part with our compatriot, with our friend in the struggle for our common interests. And although death has seized Vladimir Semenovich Levkovich from the ranks of our independents, it cannot and will not take away from us his dream. With a wreath for his grave we give our pledge to fulfill his dream--we will unite the Russians and we will erect a Russian National Hall, and in that building his portrait will hang in honor. Do not permit those heinous murderers to rejoice and to think that they have stopped the great Russian cause which the deceased V. S. Levkovich supported.</p>
   <p>Sleep in peace, indefatigable and valiant brother-independent--in the name of the Russian cause, in the name of the bright future of your own brothers in a foreign country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
