<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Minutes of the Meetings of the Russian Center of Chicago</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Pertsov, 2559 W. Division St.)</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.6"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Minutes of the Meetings of the Russian Center of Chicago</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">(Miscellaneous Material Belonging to Dr. Pertsov, 2559 W. Division St.)</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was called to order on September 19, 1926, at 2 P. M., at the quarters of the Y. M. C. A., Division street. S. G. Prokopov was chairman and L. V. Vinogradov secretary.</p>
   <p>The following persons were present at this meeting: K. L. Kotsyubinsky, D. K. Moroz, Dr. L. G. Pertsov, V. V. Kotov, N. I. Kutnyuk, S. D. Glady shchuk, Andrews, L. V. Vinogradov and S. G. Prokopov.</p>
   <p>Accepted: The appointment of S. G. Prokopov as delegate to the Bohemian celebration of the anniversary of the independence of Czecho-Slovakia; the use by the Center of the following permanent address: 1631 S. California Avenue, D. K. Moroz.</p>
   <p>At Mr. Vinogradov's suggestion it is resolved to postpone the examination <pb facs="5423967_4_0229.jpg" n="2"/>of the financial report till the next meeting. The hearing of the report of the committee for collecting debts and tickets (note: unsold tickets for entertainments not returned by persons who had undertaken to sell them. D. S.) is also postponed. The following persons are unanimously elected members of the committee: Dr. L. G. Pertsov and V. Kotov.</p>
   <p>After the report of the committee for the organization of an evening entertainment it is definitely resolved to have this entertainment on November 14 at the Schoenhofen Hall.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pertsov is elected member of the committee for procuring advertisements to be printed together with the program of the entertainment. More members to assist his will be elected at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pertsov, L. V. Vinogradov and V. V. Kotov are elected members of the Press Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0230.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following persons were accepted as members of the Russian Center: F. Zikhehuk (?) and Andrews.</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned at 5:30 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
