<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-24">Jan. 24, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Crusade against Undesirable Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-24">Jan. 24, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">CRUSADE AGAINST UNDESIRABLE IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>D. W. McCormack, Commissioner of Immigration and Naturalization, in his report to Secretary Perkins, suggested several amendments to the immigration laws which would allow deportation of certain classes of immigrants who at present feel themselves perfectly safe.</p>
   <p>The Commissioner also demanded revision of the rules and regulations governing interdepartmental co-operation. He further recommended that judges be allowed to impose more severe sentences, and that the officers of the Immigration and Naturalization Service be given the right to arrest suspected immigrants twenty-four hours prior to the issuance of warrants for arrest.</p>
   <p>During the last year, 8,310 undesirable foreigners have been deported from the United States. Furthermore, there were sent out of the country 7,976 foreigners who had entered the country illegally.</p>
   <p>The flow of immigrants into the country has fallen off considerably. During <pb facs="5423967_4_1265.jpg" n="2"/>the last year only 34,956 immigrants entered the United States. During the same year, 38,834 immigrants left this country; and, thus, the number of immigrants in the country was reduced by more than four thousand.</p>
   <p>In 1935, according to official estimates, there were 4,922,000 foreigners within the United States; and these figures indicate a considerable falling off in the alien population, for, in 1930, there were 6,284,000 foreigners in the country and 1,500,000 immigrants who had only applied for citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>During the year 1935, 118,000 foreigners received citizenship papers, although during 1934 only 113,000 aliens were granted citizenship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
