<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>. pp. 36-38.
<title level="a">The Salvation of the Church</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>. pp. 36-38.
<title level="a">THE SALVATION OF THE CHURCH</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The salvation of the parish of St. Michael was begun by the priest of the Holy Trinity, at present Bishop A. Kukulevsky. From the time of his arrival in Chicago he conducted services in the Church of St. Michael on Sundays, in the evening and he prepared the parish for the opening.</p>
   <p>In 1913 according to a resolution of the 7th of March the very holy Archbishop Platon appointed as ruler of St. Michael's Church the Rev. Timon.</p>
   <p>The course of salvation of the parish is to be derived from intimate records in Rev. Timon's diary. Little do they tell of the spiritual experiences, but in between the lines, one might see how much sorrow and disillusion it was necessary to experience before the wheat of Orthodox was weeded out.</p>
   <p>"During the first month my soul was extremely sad, when I conducted the Liturgy-<pb facs="5423967_4_1073.jpg" n="2"/>there were only five or ten persons present later eight more were added. My hope was only in God, only in prayers have I found comsolation. A month after my arrival in Chicago, creditors through their attorneys demanded payment of notes given by Pazdry in denominations of $200, $100, $50, and $30, and within a period of two weeks I had received twelve creditors, all demanded the immediate payment of debts. In view of the unexpected discoveries I lost all hope of the possibility of holding on to the church and averting foreclosure, quite frequently the thought came into my mind, that not being able to fulfill the duty of a priest I will be compelled to leave Chicago. But, thanks to Almighty God, who does not forsake us with His goodness and mercy, I was delivered from the difficult situation.</p>
   <p>After I had become acquainted with people, and having discovered the nearby towns in which dwelt Orthodox people, I began by the grace of God, to conduct meetings, and to this cause I have dedicated all my leisure time."</p>
   <p>"June first of that year, on the eve of the Holy Trinity, the parish was fortunate in leaving the Very Reverend Archbishop Alexander to conduct an all-night <pb facs="5423967_4_1074.jpg" n="3"/>Mass. Life at the parish was improving gradually. The church property was fenced. Money was paid to three creditors - $110 - $480.50."</p>
   <p>"In the beginning of 1914 through the bequest of the daughter of a titled adviser, Enid Vetzkemich, the Very Rev. Archbishop Platon, received $2,026.19 which was used to settle the debts. Within the same year electricity was installed in the Church and hall; a mantle was bought for $50.00 remodeling done - two rooms were alloted for the choirs, a candle holder and four palms were bought as church decorations. A copy of an ikon of Virgin Mary was received from the monastery of Pochaev."</p>
   <p>"September 28th the very Reverend Alexander again offered to conduct services in honor of the Virgin Mary of Pochaev and on November 21 a Liturgy."</p>
   <p>"In 1915 a new church bell was bought and consecrated on "Labor Day" a cupola was built for $400.00."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1075.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"In that year the following episode took place: on Sunday during a public reading of the war news, through the cooperation of the Journals: Russky Palomnik and Niva, the hall was filled beyond capacity and caused the floor to cave in. The repair of this required new funds. Although this was not easy, money was found and the floor remodelled."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
