<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-26">Feb. 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Condition of the Workers in the USSR</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-26">Feb. 26, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">CONDITION OF THE WORKERS IN THE USSR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Kondrashevka is the junction station on the newly built railroad line from Moscow to Donbas. About 2,800 men are employed on the construction work. No one knows how many of them are free workers and how many are conscript laborers. The conscript laborers receive only a small part of their wages; the rest is paid into the treasury of the GPU (political police). All their food is supplied by the contractors because all conscript workers are taken off the prison or concentration camp ration [list] immediately after they have been assigned to work. The contractors pay the free workers according to the general scale.</p>
   <p>Quite recently, in January, something happened in Kondrashevka, something that forced Moscow to act. Investigators were sent down there in a hurry. The investigators found out that the tragedy had to occur, because it "was <pb facs="5423967_4_1414.jpg" n="2"/>prepared in advance".</p>
   <p>The free workers had not received any money for their work for three months, and the conscript workers had not received any wages for four months. Quite frequently the workers did not even get any bread. Thus, on December 14, 15, and 16, the workers did not get any food. There was nothing to eat on December 26, 27, and 28. On January 1, Kondrashevka received only 600 poods of flour (one pood equals thirty-six pounds) for the entire month, viz., nine pounds for each individual for a whole month.</p>
   <p>Once the contractors attempted to feed the workers on credit, by accepting in lieu of money, scrip coupons. For two days the workers received some food, but on the third day the administrators in charge of the food demanded real money. Why? They did so because the administration that issued the scrip promised to pay for them, but did not do so. Besides, the workers received <pb facs="5423967_4_1415.jpg" n="3"/>no work clothes, which are supposed to be furnished by the contractors, and, consequently, they work in rags.</p>
   <p>Instead of shoes, workers wear anything their ingenuity can devise. Walls in the workers' barracks are full of holes and cracks. As regards fuel, the contractors care as little about that as about everything else. Workers endured hardships as long as they could and used everything that they had, but when the frosts came and the temperature fell to 40 below zero, something happened. The GPU demanded that the men responsible for the negligence be punished. According to the agreement the contractors received able-bodied, employable men, but the men in charge of the construction ruined the health of these men in a short time and made them invalids. This is, of course, a direct loss for the GPU.</p>
   <p>The contractors tried to justify themselves by claiming that they had no money, but the question is: is there any Soviet institution that has any <pb facs="5423967_4_1416.jpg" n="4"/>money? The Central Grain Administration itself has no money to pay for the grain taken from the collective farms. There is no Soviet undertaking that pays the workers on time. Let us call it bankruptcy, but who is not bankrupt today?</p>
   <p>The excuse put forward by the contractors will not absolve them. But the interesting point is that the Moscow-Donbas line is being built with particular haste under the personal guidance of Stalin himself. Stalin is daily advised as to the progress of the work, and yet.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
