<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>. P. 38.
<title level="a">The Spiritual Elevation of the Parish.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>. P. 38.
<title level="a">THE SPIRITUAL ELEVATION OF THE PARISH.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The under-water stones have been trodden on! Nothing disturbs the tranquil creative church life. All Russian Orthodox people are united: practically all have joined the various Brotherhoods and Sisterhoods. Love and Peace are reigning within the circle of parishioners.</p>
   <p>The most moving and significant fact of all church goers is, that in the midst of all members there was an American-born woman teacher, Miss Shuntlev. Three years ago she accepted Orthodoxy under the name of Zinaida and since has not missed a single Sunday, staying through long services, which were conducted in a language alien to her - carrying out all instructions of the church, lighting candles and making contributions to the church.</p>
   <p>The debts provoke us no more, - already in December of 1923, when the priest of that church was transferred to the Holy Trinity Church, the entire debt amounted to $4,000.000, not a mortgage but in notes and owed to its own members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1066.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus every year saw the church spiritually elevated; this was reported by St. Michael's Church to its 25th jubilee. Two months before the celebration, a general remodeling of the church took place, the church was decorated with ikons!</p>
   <p>And the faithful in gratitude for God's love are contributing for all needs of the church.</p>
   <p>"O, God! Strengthen our church and the orthodox faith, from now and unto eternity."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
