<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview</title>
(<date when="1935-01-04">Jan. 4, 1935</date>)
<title level="a">with Dr. A. I. Nedzelnitsky (Nedzel), 1608 Milwaukee Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview</title>
(<date when="1935-01-04">Jan. 4, 1935</date>)
<title level="a">with Dr. A. I. Nedzelnitsky (Nedzel), 1608 Milwaukee Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Nedzel was born in the large village Lubomirka, in the province of Kherson (Ukraine), in 1888. He received his education partly in St. Petersburg, where he studied at the Voznesenskaya High School. But he was not graduated from this school, as in 1905, being involved in political troubles which stirred up all the Russian young people, he was discharged from the school together with several of his fellow students. Being eager to complete his education, he went abroad, to Germany, and in Dresden joined the Polytechnikum, where he studied two years. He then returned to Russia, to Odessa, passed his high school examinations and joined the Novorossiysky University in Odessa, where he studied medicine. He graduated in 1913 and, as one of the most proficient students, was allowed to remain connected with the university in order to go on with his studies, preparing himself for professorship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1660.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, the World War interfered with his studies. In 1913 he had to join the army and since the beginning of the war in 1914 till 1918, the doctor worked as a military surgeon. Then he returned to Odessa and continued his research studies at the university.</p>
   <p>In 1920 Dr. Nedzel was obliged to leave Russia and to go to Constantinople as a refugee. Here he soon found a congenial occupation: he managed the laboratories of the Russian hospital of St. Nicholas and of the American hospital.</p>
   <p>In 1923 Dr. Nedzel left Constantinople and sailed to America. He came to Chicago and since 1924 has been a practicing physician and surgeon in this city.</p>
   <p>Since 1929 Dr. Nedzel has been a member of the faculty of the University <pb facs="5423967_4_1661.jpg" n="3"/>of Illinois, College of Medicine. He is associate professor of pathology and bacteriology. He is chiefly occupied with research in the realm of localization of diseases. He has made many valuable learned investigations in this realm. Reports of these investigations have been published in the pages of several scientific reviews.</p>
   <p>Dr. Nedzel is a fellow of the American Medical Association; a member of the Illinois State Medical Society; also of the Chicago Medical Society, of the Pathological Society, of the society of Experimental Biology and Medicine, of the Medical Research Club and of Sigma Xi. He is very popular among the Russians of Chicago as a practicing physician and surgeon, and has also many patients of other nationalities, especially among Poles, Ukrainians and Galicians.</p>
   <p>Besides his activities as a scientist and practicing physician, Dr. Nedzel has always been an active social worker amongthe Russians in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1662.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every years he has been giving a number of lectures on medical subjects, especially in the years 1924 and 1925, when the club Prosvyeshcheniye (Enlightenment) was in existence. For a number of years he has been a member of the examining commissions of several Russian schools. He provided Rassviet periodically with a medical column from 1926 to 1929, and again since 1935 to the present time.</p>
   <p>He is Supreme Physician of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, Medical Examiner of the St. Nicholas Brotherhood, connected with the Holy Trinity Cathedral, and a member of the Russian American Citizens' Organization. He was president of the Pushkin Committee till September 1936.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
