<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-12">Jan. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas Tree</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-12">Jan. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS TREE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow, at the Amalgamated Auditorium, 333 South Ashland Boulevard, the traditional Christmas tree festivities, arranged by the Independent Mutual Aid Society, will take place. Each Year, without fail, these festivities are staged, and each year, successfully.</p>
   <p>This year, the ceremony promises to be particularly successful and well attended. The day set for the occasion is most appropriate. This week, we celebrated the Russian Christmas, and we all are still under the influence of the holiday spirit. Our thoughts and memories are still with our motherland; we remember the time when we used to enjoy our holidays at home, not in a strange country. For this reason, and quite naturally, we will all want to join the participants on this occasion. The program promises to be very entertaining.</p>
   <p>The parents, as well as the other Russians in Chicago who still love their native land, will have an opportunity to see their youngsters on the stage.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0925.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With joy, they will hear the children's chorus singing the folk songs of their distant homeland. They will see and hear a well-organized, well-directed chorus led by a talented conductor, who loves his art.</p>
   <p>Christmas is a children's holiday. The perennially green fir tree is the emblem of everlasting youth, never-ending life. Names and people change, but life goes on. Some people go, others come to take their places.</p>
   <p>Every year, members of the Independent Society, from Chicago and neighboring towns, gather for this occasion. They bring their children from Argo, Pullman, Melrose Park, from north and south. They gather together to celebrate Christmas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
