<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-06-02">June 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Opening, on June 2, 1927, in New York, of the First United Convention of Russian Mutual Aid Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-06-02">June 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">OPENING, ON JUNE 2, 1927, IN NEW YORK, OF THE FIRST UNITED CONVENTION OF RUSSIAN MUTUAL AID SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The editorial points out the importance of this convention for all Russian-Americans. It will be an important step towards a more complete unification of Russian organizations on the basis of mutual aid and cultural and educational activities. It is sure to influence strongly those Russian organizations which did not join the amalgamation achieved in Philadelphia in 1926, and many of these organizations will probably now join the amalgamation, says the editorial. In that case the amalgamated societies would probably form a a federation. Such a federation of various groups exists already in Baltimore; it is being discussed in Detroit, and Chicago will probably follow the example of these cities. Everywhere the Russians feel the necessity of achieving such a unification and to have some place of their own where they may <pb facs="5423967_4_0073.jpg" n="2"/>all meet and find physical and spiritual rest in a congenial atmosphere. All that is needed in those cities where such a yearning for unification exists, is some event that would arouse the Russians and transform that vague yearning into definite activity. The Russian immigrants are not poorer than other national groups; they have a rich cultural inheritance, they have the money needed, and they can have their own people's houses, theaters, reading rooms, etc., like other nationalities. They just must be aroused, and the author of the editorial hopes that the New York convention will achieve that.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
