<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title><date when="1923-07-19">July 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Way to Russia Is Closed for Single Persons</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title><date when="1923-07-19">July 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE WAY TO RUSSIA IS CLOSED FOR SINGLE PERSONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following communication has been received at the editing office from V. Skvirski, delegate of the People's Commissariat of Foreign Affairs to America.)</p>
   <p>"As a result of false rumors spread by agents of steamship companies and by private individuals about the possibility of free return to Russia a whole series of persons have left and are leaving for Germany and other countries in order to return to Russia. Such persons are not able to cross the Russian frontier as they have no special permits from the authorities in the U. S. S. R. concerned with the granting of such permits. Not having enough money for returning to America such persons apply at the offices of delegations and consulates of the U. S. S. R. empowered to grant these permits, requesting the respective officials to be allowed to cross the Russian border as an exception, motivated in their requests of various reasons. They declare that they left for Russia without having received a preliminary permit to enter the country because they were not acquainted with the rules established by the government of the U. S. S. R., or because they have been deceived by agents of the <pb facs="5423967_4_1313.jpg" n="2"/>steamship companies or some other persons.</p>
   <p>In order to avoid in the future such difficulties I am empowered by the People's Commissariat of Foreign affairs to communicate at the present to Russian citizens residing in America and planning to return to Russia that no requests of persons leaving America without having been granted a permit to be repatriated by the proper authorities of the U. S. S. R. will be taken into consideration in the future by empowered delegations and consulates of the U. S. S. R.</p>
   <p>Those who want to be repatriated must procure such permits before leaving America. If they will not do it they may incur the risk of being stopped on the way to Russia and having to remain in a difficult position somewhere in Germany or in some other country bordering on Russia where they would be prevented from crossing the Russian border.</p>
   <p>On the absence of duly empowered representatives and consulates of the U. S. S. R. in the United States single individuals have to apply for permits to enter Russia <pb facs="5423967_4_1314.jpg" n="3"/>either directly to the Commissariat of Foreign Affairs or through authorized delegations or consulates of the U. S. S. R. in Europe (in Berlin, London, Rome, Copenhagen, Riga, Reval, Warsaw and other places.)</p>
   <p>Those who intend to leave for Russia in organized groups with the help of the Society of Technical Aid to Soviet Russia, with the purpose of undertaking there agricultural or industrial activities, will get, as such organized groups do, permits to enter Russia from the Permanent Commission of the Council of Labor and Defense which supervises the immigration of agricultural and industrial worker ("KOMSTO").</p>
   <p>With the authorization of the Commissariat of Foreign Affairs.</p>
   <p>V. Skvirsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
