<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-31">Dec. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Our Problems for the New Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-31">Dec. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROBLEMS FOR THE NEW YEAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year now drawing to a close has not been a particularly good year for the Russian group in America. Our accomplishments have been negligible, our progress slight. Our group activities are almost at a standstill.</p>
   <p>The only achievement of the Russian group in this country worth mentioning is the acquisition of a farm property by the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society in New York. There have also been some insignificant and less important events in the life of the Russian group in America during the year now ending. However, these have left no noticeable mark on our life and on our affairs, and therefore need no special mention, except, perhaps, in so far as they signify the continuity of effort and the constant desire of our people to improve their way of life, their cultural and economic condition.</p>
   <p>The chief obstacles standing in the way of wider collective achievements of our people are indifference, a passive attitude toward our group life, and lack of <pb facs="5423967_4_0531.jpg" n="2"/>faith and confidence in ourselves.</p>
   <p>In the coming new year, it will be necessary to look for and find new ways and means for bringing about a closer union among all Russians living in this country. The first aim of all Russian organizations now existing in America should be the enlightenment of the Russian masses in this country. All our efforts should be directed toward that end. Educational work should form the basis of all activities of all Russian societies, clubs, and other organizations in America. Only through education can we succeed in cementing and fusing together all elements and groups into which Russian immigrants are divided. When all the Russians in this country have been united, then and only then can really productive work be undertaken with the prospect of success.</p>
   <p>The balance sheet of the dying old year may be credited with at least one achievement of some importance by the Chicago Russian colony. A Russian political organization has been formed which will embrace those Russians in Chicago and in other towns who are citizens of the United States. This is the first regular Russian political organization in America. Its chief aim is to obtain <pb facs="5423967_4_0532.jpg" n="3"/>proper recognition by the American political parties, with subsequent representation in city, county, and state administrations. At present, there are many Russian political clubs in various cities and towns of the United States. They act individually, sometimes even without knowledge of the existence of similar Russian clubs in other cities. It is planned to call a convention of all Russian political clubs in the United States with a view to adopting a common platform and harmonizing all activities.</p>
   <p>The new year may also bring us the realization of the long-cherished hope of an all-Russian convention. There have accumulated many important problems directly concerning our life and our future as a national group in this country. These questions must be openly discussed and the problems facing us must be solved if we are to make any progress. An all-Russian convention may become a reality sooner than many expect. What we need now, as the new year begins, is more faith, more self-confidence, more enterprise, and more work. Then every aspect of the life of the Russian group in America will become more attractive and more interesting. In the dawning New Year, everyone who considers himself a Russian should <pb facs="5423967_4_0533.jpg" n="4"/>give freely of his time and of his abilities to make the Russian cause in America more secure and more inviting to the young Russian-American generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
