<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-28">Jan. 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Aftermathe of the Open Letter to Ambassador Troyanovsky</title><title level="a" type="sub">by the Reverend Feodor Turchenko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-28">Jan. 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">AFTERMATHE OF THE OPEN LETTER TO AMBASSADOR TROYANOVSKY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by The Reverend Feodor Turchenko</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the open letter addressed to Ambassador Troyanovsky in connection with the Bolsheviks' execution by shooting of my brothers and sisters I, as my readers, perhaps, remember, set a last day for an answer, demanding acknowledgment not later than January 16. My desire to a certain extent has been satisfied; that is, on instructions from the American authorities a special agent of the United States Department of State, Alexander R. Burr, came the other day from Washington to Chicago.</p>
   <p>I presented myself at the appointed time and place with the Ukrainian attorney, Mr. Pelechovich. Mr. Burr was very attentive and extremely polite. Our conversation lasted for an hour and a half. I presented to him all the <pb facs="5423967_4_1366.jpg" n="2"/>information concerning myself and my relatives and also described to him all the beastly outrages perpetrated by "comrades" on the defenseless population of Soviet Russia. Besides this I gave explicit answers to all questions put to me according to the instructions of the American Government. In conclusion Mr. Burr thanked me for all the interesting information supplied by me and on my leaving the room promised that the American Government would take whatever action was possible in the matter.</p>
   <p>My advice to you, my Russian and Ukrainian comrades in misfortune, is not to keep silent about all those beastly acts which your relatives have to suffer under the dirty heel of the Third International but to demand of his excellency, Ambassador Troyanovsky, the explanation of what led the Bolshevik tyrants to take the lives of your relatives or to send them into exile, where they die a slow death. By doing this you will accomplish a great deal. A Ukrainian proverb <pb facs="5423967_4_1367.jpg" n="3"/>says that "true often hurts," and you should tell the truth, even though the Bolshevik executioners have no sense of shame. These protests, after all, will attract the attention of the American Government, and this will help it to grasp the true situation and to realize the mistake made when the Bolshevik Government was recognized [as the government] de facto and ae jure [of Russia].</p>
   <p>Always write the truth without hesitation or fear, and the most important requirement is that it be written in polite form. No matter how much we condemn and curse, we cannot excel the Bolsheviks in the abuse of our language. They will [always] take first place in this contest of recrimination. To every really cultured and naturally intelligent man invective is repugnant, from whatever source it may come, especially from an intelligent man, even when he abuses his language for cause.</p>
   <p>The American Government is an intelligent Government. It will understand us and give protection. However, we may seek solace in our sorrow, my dear <pb facs="5423967_4_1368.jpg" n="4"/>friends, only in prayer to God above. Pray not for the victims, but for their tormentors, for the former have already saved their souls and are crowned with the wreaths of martyrdom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
