<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-12-24">Dec. 24, 1924</date>
<title level="a">Poland and Russia</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-12-24">Dec. 24, 1924</date>
<title level="a">POLAND AND RUSSIA</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago, in one of the local Polish newspapers, there was published a curious editorial on Russia and bolshevism.</p>
   <p>The author of this editorial was trying to harmer into the heads of his readers the idea that "the bolsheviki will stay in power in Russia for about ten more years, and after that anarchy will take the place of bolshevism."</p>
   <p>Having made this statement, the author of the Polish editorial comes to the wise conclusion that anarchy will lead to the complete disintegration of Russia and will destroy the great Slav state which occupies one sixth of the whole area of the continents of the earth.</p>
   <p>We would not draw even the slightest attention of our readers to such an editorial, as its author is obviously very little acquainted with the history of Russia and the Russian people, if he can come to such a conclusion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1591.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Russia has outlived the Tartar yoke, several periods of internal trouble; has fought successfully the Polish troops while trouble was rampant inside its boundaries; has repelled Napoleon who had subjugated all Europe, but broke his teeth trying to conquer Russia. In spite of all these adversities Russia has regained unconquered, undivided and could not be destroyed.</p>
   <p>After all these storms and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Russia was becoming only stronger. It was tempered like <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> by these struggles and was expanding on all sides, having reached persia, Turkey and almost India in the south, the Polar Ocean in the north, Prussia in the west and Japan in the east.</p>
   <p>Russia has borne terrible, heavy blows; but nobody has dared yet to talk about its ruin.</p>
   <p>Only the author of the Polish editorial has dared to do so. Probably he does not fully realize what he is saying.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we repeat, we would not have paid any attention to this editorial <pb facs="5423967_4_1592.jpg" n="3"/>if it did not contain some things very characteristic of a man who "is fashioning the public opinion of the Poles in Chicago."</p>
   <p>The author of the editorial makes the following statement:</p>
   <p>"We need not trouble ourselves over the fact that Russia is perishing. The weaker this country becomes, the worse the state of affairs in Russia, the better for us."</p>
   <p>There you may see what the purpose of writing this editorial was, concerning Russia and bolshevism.</p>
   <p>But does the writer of this Polish editorial not err in supposing that Poland will be better off if Russia perish? Does he not see that if anarchy comes to reign in Russia today, tomorrow anarchy will penetrate into Poland? What would become of the wise author of the Polish editorial in that case?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1593.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the contrary, if Russia becomes strong and order again reigns there, Russia will extend its hand to the Polish nation which is akin to it, and will deal with that nation on equal terms. Just as Russia acted in a fraternal way in 1917, when it nobly granted to Poland <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, the right to be independent of Russia, saying as it were: "Be my neighbor, Poland, living on terms of equality with me, not a tributary under the yoke of the Russian tsars any longer."</p>
   <p>Does the wise writer of the Polish editorial remember that?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
