<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-16">Feb. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Organization Work of the Poles and the Russians</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-16">Feb. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORGANIZATION WORK OF THE POLES AND THE RUSSIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the latest issue of the Polish weekly Zgoda there was printed an official report of the expansion of the Polish National Alliance. According to this report, a thirty-day new-membership campaign had brought to the Polish National Alliance 3,695 new members--1,846 adults and 1,894 children [sic].</p>
   <p>These figures cause us to think, whether we like it or not. If the men heading our Russian organizations were to be told that one Polish mutual-aid organization had gained 3,695 new members in one month, they would probably think such a statement did not conform to the truth. But in this case we have no doubt as to the truth of the report of the Polish publication. We must stop and think, when we realize that one Polish organization was able to gain more new members in one month than any one of the Russian organizations during its entire existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0810.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When a Russian organization opens a new membership campaign, and devotes to it two or three months of effort and constant attention, it usually succeeds in gaining not more than one hundred new members, at best. But when a Polish organization opens a similar campaign, it increases its ranks by several thousand new members in a month's time.</p>
   <p>From the foregoing example it can be seen where we stand with respect to organization work in comparison with other national groups. Some of our leaders may say that the Polish National Alliance is able to attract a large number of members because there are a great many more Poles than Russians in America. But this is not exactly true. According to the latest federal census, there are in the United States 1,268,5<gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>3 persons who were born in Poland, and 1,153,624 persons who were born in Russia. In the Russian group there are included not only Russians but also other nationalities which came from Russia. However, the number of Russians in this country is large. According to the same census, there are 2,073,615 American-born Poles, and 1,516,215 persons of Russian extraction, or of parents born in Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0811.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These statistics show that our lagging behind in the matters of organization cannot be explained by our numerical insignificance in this country. Even if we exclude from the total number of the Russian-born persons in America all non-Russians, our numerical strength is still quite imposing and should have its reflection in the strength of our organizations. Yet our organizations cannot stand comparison with the strong and very efficient Polish organizations in America. The proportion of Russians belonging to various organizations is very insignificant when compared with the well-organized Poles.</p>
   <p>There may be some who will contend that the Poles are better situated financially than the Russians and, therefore, can better afford to belong to different organizations. We disagree also with this view. It is true that in the Polish group there are more businessmen and professional people than in the Russian group but, at the same time, the overwhelming majority of the Poles live under the same economic conditions as the Russians. The Poles may even be in a somewhat less advantageous economic position than the Russians <pb facs="5423967_4_0812.jpg" n="4"/>because of the fact that their families seem to be larger than those of the Russians, according to the census statistics.</p>
   <p>Obviously, the good organizing system among the Poles must be explained by other reasons. Therefore, it is necessary for the Russian leaders to give this question deep thought, and to discover the reasons which hinder the raising of the Russian organization system and organization work to the level of that of other national groups in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
