<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-21">Aug. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">About Our Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0958</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0958.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-21">Aug. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT OUR CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tribulations of the Russian people in Russia and abroad are beyond description and understanding. The Russian nation is dying from disease, hunger, and political persecution. The oppression now being experienced by Russians everywhere is most cruel. Our countrymen are undergoing these terrible sufferings only because of the lack of proper legal defense.</p>
   <p>The Russian colony in America, as a whole, is undoubtedly one of the most prosperous and stable communities in this country, being well organized and socially conscious. If it so desired, it could, and it should, ease the lot of its brothers. United into one whole, the American Russian colony would represent an indestructible force, which could be used for the defense of the interests of the entire nation in foreign countries and in the Soviet Union. After uniting, during the convention, into one whole, and for one aim--to save their nation--the Russian-Americans will <pb facs="5423967_4_0959.jpg" n="2"/>really represent a great moral and legal force.</p>
   <p>During the convention the Russian-Americans may decide many important questions, such as:</p>
   <p>(1) Influencing Washington not to recognize the Soviet government;</p>
   <p>(2) Setting up an international fund for extending aid to the Russian peasants and workers, perishing from famine, disease and executions;</p>
   <p>(3) Appealing to the whole civilized world for financial aid, in order to establish kitchens to feed the hungry and shelters to house those out of doors, and to extend medical and legal aid, which would be administered to the Russian people by special representatives of foreign nations. By such foreign intervention the Soviet dictatorship would be crushed to dust, and the foreign powers would learn of the horrors experienced by our brothers in the Soviet hell; (4) Demanding American intervention and aid in defending the human rights of those sent to hard labor by the Soviet government;</p>
   <p>(5) Instituting legal action against the executioners of the Russian people <pb facs="5423967_4_0960.jpg" n="3"/>through the League of Nations, having obtained therein our own representation; (6) Making an appeal to all nations of the world for sympathy, and for moral and financial support to all Russian wanderers living in all parts of the world since the year 1917; (7) Asking the Russian press in all countries for a wide publication of truth pertaining to the hideous conditions in Soviet Russia; (8) Uniting all Russian mutual-aid societies in America into one organization; (9) Obtaining the introduction of the Russian language in the schools of the United States and those countries in Europe where Russian children and their parents ask for it; (10) Organizing the Russian-American youth for its spiritual development, and establishing a fund for the needs of our younger generation in foreign countries.</p>
   <p>This is an approximate outline of the problems which the convention may solve for the benefit of themselves, their children, and their countrymen. It is desirable that all prominent Russian public workers, other Russians known in American circles, and also representatives of all social and cultural Russian groups in America, take part in the forthcoming convention. It <pb facs="5423967_4_0961.jpg" n="4"/>would also be proper to send invitations to the more outstanding persons in the Russian colony in Canada. We suggest that the following persons should also be invited: Leon N. Tolstoy, Alexander L. Tolstoy, Alexandra Kropotkin, the representatives of the Russian Writers' and Scientists' Union, priests, physicians, engineers, and also representatives of the American labor organizations, and representatives of those organizations having for their purpose the defense of human rights, like the one in New York City.</p>
   <p>Let us shake hands, Russian friends and brothers, in this menacing hour of our travail. Let us transform our motto, "All for one and one for all," into real action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
