<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Future of Russia</title>
by E. Moravsky <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-20">Apr. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUTURE OF RUSSIA</title>
by E. Moravsky <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Russian immigrants scattered all ever the world represent an extremely heterogeneous conglomeration when you consider them from the political viewpoint. Among them, there are monarchists, republicans, socialists, anarchists, Fascists, National Bolsheviks, and other political groups. All these groups, with the exception of a very small group of Bolshevik supporters, are anti-Bolshevik. They all agree and readily understand one another when questions arise concerning present-day Russia. Each group feels that the liberation of Russia from the barbarous yoke of Bolshevism is the sacred duty of every Russian, regardless of his political views.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1388.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But when they begin to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the question of what is to follow Bolshevism, then they no longer speak the same language and they no longer understand one another. Each group pictures the future of Russian according to its own lights. More than that, each group or party, has its own program for the future construction of Russia. Some of the groups, however, think that the will of the Russian people <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to be considered, while others are intent on subjecting the people to their own will.</p>
   <p>All of these programs, however, are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> more than soap bubbles, which will burst hen the immigrants see Russian after the downfall of Bolshevism. If the Russian people are to shed any more blood, it will not be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> so that some immigrant group can seize power, or some immigrant dictator can take the place of Stalin. The Russian people will not shed their blood in order to substitute one evil for another. They will fight only for the purpose of establishing a better social order on the ruins of Bolshevism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1389.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>from this point of view, the letters of a Red Army commander, which are being printed serially in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Chasovoy, are particularly interesting. His latest letter was written in February of this year, and, therefore, reflects fully the present sentiment in Russia.</p>
   <p>The Red commander writes that a bitter struggle between the Russian people and the scoundrels in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> is unavoidable. Nevertheless, he fore-warns the emigres and says that the new revolution in Russia will be carried out under the banner of "freedom and popular rule," and not with the aim of restoring the old order or of establishing a Fascist dictatorship. For this reason he advises the White officers to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> away entirely from the past.</p>
   <p>"The revolution," he says, "was not a riot. It was a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the natural indignation of the people against an inept ruling class and its mismanagement in the conduct of the war. We fight against Bolshevism because it distorted this revolution, betrayed the interests of Russia, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the <pb facs="5423967_4_1390.jpg" n="4"/>religious beliefs of the people, and polluted their ideals. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> solemnly declare that we shall rebuild Russia <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the aim of restoring the old prerevolutionary regime, but in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to build a me Russia, berro<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> all the good features of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> disregarding the currents of our times."</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> an appeal to all Russian <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who may be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> drawing up plans for the future construction of Russia, The Red <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> says: "It's unbearably painful to think that people live by vain <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> draw up plans according to beautiful ideals and dreams <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> unsuitable for present-day Russia."</p>
   <p>At present in Russia, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> revolution is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to run along the following lines, he says: Industry is to remain under government <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, and the private pr<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>easants is to be returned to them in confor<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>nce with agreements reparding the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of "free collective farms". Free commerce is to be re-established and the eight-hour work day guaranteed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1391.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>As far as political problems are concerned, the national order is to be established in conformance with the will of the people, expressed freely in a referendum. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> system of governement instituted by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> collective farms. To all <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> peoples living in the present <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Union, the widest <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> be accorded in order that the entire country may be converted into a "Free Peoples' Federated State". This is the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <p>which will be taken in the forthcoming Russian revolution, according to the Red commander.</p>
   <p>Whether such a plan <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the new revolution will <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>realize some now program of social reconstruction, And will not embrace the antiquated <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> For this reason, the Russian anti-Bolshevik immigrant circles would act very wisely if they ceased to engage in controversies regarding plans for the future reconstruction of Russia, and would listen more attentively to the <pb facs="5423967_4_1392.jpg" n="6"/>voice of the Russian people, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to their assistance in the hour of need.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
