<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-05-24">May 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">On the 12th Anniversary of the Brotherhood of St. George</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-05-24">May 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE 12TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE BROTHERHOOD OF ST. GEORGE</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How quick twelve years have slipped along! These years have written on the tablets of our memories one fact important for the Russian colony of Chicago of that period.</p>
   <p>Chicago plays a certain role among the Russian-Americans. It is a stormy city. It is the center of the American midlands. It is situated on the main road connecting the Western and Eastern states.</p>
   <p>At the time we are speaking of the tsarist (Note: The author means the Orthodox Mission. D.S.) Mission in America was going to pieces. The heads of the Orthodox Church were shaken; they did not take their duties seriously, they were sinning! They were committing sins of the flesh, "sins of the soul," and "sins of the pocket."</p>
   <p>And they blundered so long that the mission began to exhale a bad odor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1135.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was not the odor of incense; it was the stench of the great and small sins of the bishops and the archpriests.</p>
   <p>At the present time the Orthodox Mission is incurably ill. Then it was just falling sick.</p>
   <p>The Russians in Chicago understood this and were stirred up. They revolted against the ugly things that were being done by some of the clergy, and they began to pine for independence from priests who were paid by the government and who committed all kinds of immoral actions.</p>
   <p>And they seceded. They bought a church and a house, and they invited a priest of their own.</p>
   <p>The first independent priest was the Rev. Timothy Pieshkov, who had been recommended by me. He was a lay brother of a Russian monastery, a clever, <pb facs="5423967_4_1136.jpg" n="3"/>hearty and unsophisticated per on. Now he is finishing a course in the Harvard University in Boston, but then he was a hobo and was tramping about, as many other migratory workers. I remember when at the editorial office of Russkii Golos, I blessed jokingly a group of Russian youths, who were on their way to tramp over America. They were singing and playing guitars, and were cheerful and adventurous children of Russia. Pieshkov was among them. All of them scattered and fell behind, but one, Kallos, went over all America and in the South was jailed for vagrancy. I released him with the assistance of a United States senator.</p>
   <p>Pieshkov had passed the examination for a priest of the Independent Orthodox Church in Chicago. The people themselves examined him at the church.</p>
   <p>The new priest had to perform the divine service and preach a sermon.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1137.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Pieshkov defeated his opponent and became the first priest of the "Independents" and carried out this work. During my trip over Canada and the United States, I visited Chicago. I also was at the house of the Independent (Church), and at their gatherings I talked to them about the life of the Russians in America. I saw that Pieshkov is not intellectually developed, and knows very little; that he must first learn himself if he hopes to teach others. I advised him to visit the school. He is a meditative man. He could not agree with some people; he could not satisfy others. He had to leave the Independents. Now Pieshkov is without a job.</p>
   <p>His work gave its fruit. The Brotherhood of St. George grew up; its members built their own school and parish house, and even founded a paper of their own.</p>
   <p>The brotherhood converted its church into a house of enlightenment. It stopped the existence of an orthodoxy paid by the government, and it <pb facs="5423967_4_1138.jpg" n="5"/>led its own untrammeled existence. Not a large step forward, but the beginning was made. After the first step many others will follow, still better ones, wiser, and leading to still greater liberty. People are growing and will grow. Let them grow, but let them also think. Thus liberty and thinking will nature and will bear fruit. First a church, then a school, then a newspaper, and ultimately a social brotherhood.</p>
   <p>The Brotherhood of St. George gave the first blow to Orthodoxy, supported by the government. Although the brotherhood was not making much progress at first, still it was moving forward. At present this people manage themselves their religious affairs. Later they will come to science and will not need any religion.</p>
   <p>Father Joann Zheltonoga strives to cultivate among the members of the Independent Society religious faith and loyalty to the church. And the <pb facs="5423967_4_1139.jpg" n="6"/>newspaper, that good shepherd, instills into the conscience of the masses appropriate facts and thoughts. What we read on its pages makes the impression of continual ups and downs. But there is some movement, new things are undertaken. Things will go still better if the membership of the Independent Society will amalgamate with other Russian organizations. Working together they will widen the field of their activities and improve their life. The Russian colony has visibly grown. These twelve years have served to nurse the brotherhood to develop it, and its members have begun to live better, to warm up, to do their social duties, to become more sensible. This should be a cause for rejoicing for the whole Russian colony of Chicago, for people have emerged out of the darkness into the light, out of dissensions into brotherhood. We greet these people.</p>
   <p>Ivan Okuntsov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
