<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-09">Mar. 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Lost People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0797</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0797.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-09">Mar. 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE LOST PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the pages of Rassviet there appear from time to time letters from our readers, dealing with the situation now existing in the Russian National Mutual Aid Society, which, by the will of the Bolsheviks, came under the control of a certain Communist organization. The writers of these letters appeal to the members of the R. N. M. A. S. to come to their senses, to change their minds and free themselves from the Bolshevik yoke, and rejoin their own Russian family.</p>
   <p>All these appeals remain unanswered and bring no results. The members of the R. N. M. A. S. evidently now understand that they were caught in a snare from which they will never be able to disentangle themselves. They have already become reconciled to their sad fate, and now they have only a sweet memory of those happy days when they were free people, when they and no one else managed <pb facs="5423967_4_0798.jpg" n="2"/>their affairs, and when they paid no taxes or contributions to the Bolshevik party.</p>
   <p>Members of the R. N. M. A. S. are now prisoners of the Bolsheviks because of their own stupidity, and they are paying dearly. They are in a much worse position than the Russian nation was during the Tartar domination. The Tartars exacted tribute from the Russian people, but never interfered in their internal affairs, and never attempted to turn them into common slaves.</p>
   <p>Members of the R. N. M. A. S. are now slaves in the full meaning of the word. They not only pay their assessments and their contributions to their Tartars, but they have also lost their former independence. They cannot utter a word of complaint against their oppressors. If there are any insurgents among them, a painful retribution will be exacted not only from them, but also from their relatives in Soviet Russia. Once they find themselves prisoners in a hostile camp the members of the Russian National Mutual Aid Society must keep silent and do whatever they are told to do by their oppressors. Therefore, there is <pb facs="5423967_4_0799.jpg" n="3"/>nothing surprising in the fact that there are no replies to the fervent appeals of our readers that they should break away from this bondage. We are not astonished either by the fact that these people, regarded by the Bolsheviks as a "conscious proletariat," have lately given themselves to drink and card playing. This is frequently mentioned even in their own publication Novye Mir.</p>
   <p>According to an old Russian adage, 'some people drink from joy, some drink from grief. Members of the R. N. M. A. S., naturally, drink from grief, from despair, for they know well that they are lost people, that they are doomed to remain the Bolsheviks prisoners for the rest of their lives. For this reason, all these true Russians who write letters in the hope of arousing the members of the R. N. M. A. S. to seek salvation by breaking away from their Bolshevik overlords are wasting their efforts. The R. N. M. A. S. members should be regarded as lost to the Russian cause. No one can save them, since they themselves are making no attempt in this direction, and since they have become reconciled to their lot. These people should be left alone. There are other things waiting to be done. There is a large field of activity among the <pb facs="5423967_4_0800.jpg" n="4"/>unorganized part of our group, especially among our Russian youth. There are two large truly Russian organizations, the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and the Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society. All efforts should be directed to bringing to these two Societies all unorganized members of our Russian group, young and old. This will be a more useful and more fruitful work than trying to save the members of the R. N. M. A. S. from Bolshevik bondage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
