<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Archimandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Russian Orthodox Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>, pp. 63-64.
<title level="a">Union of American-Russian Orthodox Youth</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Archimandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Russian Orthodox Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>, pp. 63-64.
<title level="a">UNION OF AMERICAN-RUSSIAN ORTHODOX YOUTH</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the beginning of this history we mentioned the important factor in the life of Russians in America the development within recent years all over the United States of Unions of Russian Orthodox Youth. The Russian Youth has become enthusiastic it has become interested in Russian culture, its attitude toward religion has become more serious.</p>
   <p>This is the best achievement of our days. There is enough strength and enthusiasm within the older Russian generation, "there is still gun-powder in the guns," however the aid of the youth is needed. Besides, life itself is, in this new country, entirely different from that life the older generation lived in their Fatherland. The demand of time presents many questions, which can be solved more easily by the youth than by the older generation.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we are pleased, that our youth has become active in church as well as national, social affairs. The Union of Youth at the St. Michael Church is <pb facs="5423967_4_1217.jpg" n="2"/>uniting all young men and young women of the parish. They have their own hall in the basement and have daily meetings. They read reports, they arrange parties and games. The members of the Union, according to the by-laws, are required to assist in all the work of the church. For the socials of the parish they arrange concerts.</p>
   <p>One of the members of the union, Julia Samuta, always manages to instill a religious feeling among those present at the meetings and is, therefore, very highly respected. On Mother's Day, the Union of Youth buys flowers for all women in the church. On this day at the entrance of the church the names of all mothers, living and dead, are listed and are remembered at the services.</p>
   <p>The Union of Youth is the most beautiful flower in the bouquet of church organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
