<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-11-24">Nov. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Six Hundred and Forty-Two Deportation Orders</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-11-24">Nov. 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SIX HUNDRED AND FORTY-TWO DEPORTATION ORDERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the information contained in the New York Times, the Department of the Interior has handed an inquiry to the Department of Labor regarding the disposition of those Russian "Reds" and "Whites" who are illegally residing in this country. The Department of Labor at present is bringing to an end an investigation concerning 642 deportation orders, orders which can not be executed because it is impossible to obtain passports for the Russian deportees, since there are no diplomatic relations between the United States and Russia.</p>
   <p>This list of deportation orders embraces all cases of illegal entry into the United States from November 1, 1927, to the present time. Mr. Daniel McCormick, the Commissioner of Immigration, when asked if these deportation orders would be carried out immediately, answered that the question had not been decided, and that it was difficult to make any prediction as to what recommendation would be made to Frances Perkins, Secretary of Labor. Mr. McCormick promised that the <pb facs="5423967_4_1291.jpg" n="2"/>whole question would be considered carefully and sympathetically, and that in cases where the political or religious motives for immigration could be established, the Immigration Department would do all in its power to apply the most favorable clauses of the immigration law.</p>
   <p>As every one knows, Russians who had entered this country illegally could not be deported to Russia as long as the U. S. government refused to recognize the Soviet regime. But now this obstacle no longer exists, and, as a result, many Russians may find themselves in an extremely difficult position.</p>
   <p>This impending danger of deportation is especially threatening to two classes of Russians in this country. It is a menace to those who came to the United States on temporary visas, as tourists or students, and also to those who made an illegal entry into this country. Naturally, the deportation will not be so dreadful for those Russians whom the Federal Immigration Department calls "Reds," and who sympathize with the Soviet government. They will receive free passage to the Soviet paradise, a place of bliss, an abode of the highest social <pb facs="5423967_4_1292.jpg" n="3"/>achievements in the world, according to their loudly-voiced opinion. But for those Russians whom the Federal authorities classify as "Whites," and who are against the Soviets, the deportation will mean a great misfortune, a calamity equal to death because, after their arrival in Russia, their lot will be either to face a firing squad or to spend the rest of their days in prison or in a concentration camp.</p>
   <p>Persons who want to escape the dire consequences of a sudden and unexpected order of deportation should immediately try to obtain the support and backing of some known Russian or American organization. It should be remembered that all persons who illegally entered the United States before the month of June, 1921, may now legalize their entry and become rightful residents of this country. Therefore, all persons in doubt as to their legal status as residents of the United States should seek the advice of some Russian organization which is well acquainted with the immigration law of this country, and can easily determine whether or not a given person has a right to a legalized residence here. Illegal residents of the United States who entered this country after June, 1921, <pb facs="5423967_4_1293.jpg" n="4"/>cannot legalize their residence here, according to the present law. These should wait until the passage of the supplementary immigration law, which is now before Congress. It is quite different with persons who came here legally, on a visa entitling them to stay here for a definite time only, as tourists, or as students desiring to complete their education. Such persons as have overstayed their allotted time should strive now to obtain permission to become legal residents of the United States. Even in these cases it is much better if all solicitations to that effect are made through some well-known organization.</p>
   <p>In our opinion the question of the possibility of deportation is so serious that it should immediately receive the attention of all Russian organizations in America. Special committees should be formed wherever there are Russian organizations, especially in all the big cities of America. These committees should take it upon themselves to render aid and advice to all Russian immigrants who for one reason or another may be threatened with deportation to Soviet Russia, and who may not wish to be deported.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
