<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Acquisition of Land and Construction of the Church pp-34-35</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Archmandrit Timon, <title>Under the Shield of Faith</title>, Chicago: St. Michael's Orthodox Russian Church,
<date when="1934">1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACQUISITION OF LAND AND CONSTRUCTION OF THE CHURCH pp-34-35</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"And here is the first service! O, you, friends and sisters, who's fortune it was to be present! Remind yourself of this, remind yourself of your joy. It is true, the first service was not in the church, it took place at the home of a good man Ivan Gensersky." But how sweet it was to hear: "Blessed is the Kingdom of the Father the Son and the Holy Ghost" and "Father have mercy upon us!" This first blessing of the Holy Trinity upon God's soil! We are so accustomed to the exclamation: "God have mercy upon us!" And at this time the prayer sounded within our hearts with an individual feeling and significance: "Have mercy upon us God, to execute that which we began, Give us strength and patience to bear all burdens; have mercy, direct us, give us wisdom to do all for Your Glory, for the honor of Christianity, for our spiritual salvation."</p>
   <p>After this quarters were rented on the corner of Marshfield Ave. and 46th St., in which services were conducted for eight months. Soon land was obtained for the construction of the church: on the corner of 44th and Paulina, opposite <pb facs="5423967_4_1060.jpg" n="2"/>Davis Square Park, within three blocks of the Chicago Stock Yards. It was purchased for $1,850.00. A plan for the church was drawn up and a contract with the builder made for the sum of $9,400.00.</p>
   <p>A Chicago millionaire G. Mills donated $1,000.00 for the month. The construction of the Church began.</p>
   <p>The corner stone of the Church was dedicated on Jan. 10, 1910, by the very Holy Bishop Alexander Aliaskinsky. Since then the services have been conducted in the church quarters. Thus, thanks to God, the work of the church was growing and strengthening.</p>
   <p>The Waves of Life and the Tribulations of the Faithful (pp. 35- 36)</p>
   <p>But when the wheat began to grow, the enemy came and planted weeds. The Rev. M. Pazdry decided to betray Christianity and by his action brought the parish to ruin. Misunderstandings occurred with the contractor and he began court proceeding. Pazdry went to the Uniates and organized, near the Orthodox Church in construction, on 50th St., a Uniate parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1061.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The enemies of Christianity, stirred up by Pazdry, have done all within their power to injure the Orthodox people. The construction of the church ceased. The Orthodox people did not have a priest. Services were not conducted. The cause of Christianity seemed to have perished.</p>
   <p>In 1911 Rev. Sergei Vasilievich was appointed to the parish of St. Michael. His first services were to be on Palm Sunday. But, alas! the enemies of Orthodoxy did not permit the newly appointed priest to conduct services. The chaos increased.</p>
   <p>In the same year the Rev. John Grazon was appointed to the parish and he used all his influence to save the parish. A well known philanthropist, Charles Crane, aided the parish materially in order to gave it. During the term of the Rev. J. Grazone the trial with the contractor ended and the construction of the church was completed, but instead of the agreed sum of $9,400.00, the construction with legal expenditures amounted to $18,328.80. Immediately after the completion of the construction the enemies made an attack upon the church and with stones broke the windows.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1062.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These stones at present are at the school of the church and serve as witnesses of those trying experiences, which the organizers of the parish had. In the beginning of 1912, J. Grazon left Chicago. The church was them closed for the second time, since, of the people who lived nearby, only three families were left, eight others lived a long distance away.</p>
   <p>Time marched on. The interest upon the debts was mounting. The creditors demanded the payment of the debts. The waves of life seemed to be completely drowning the small boat of Orthodoxy on the South Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
