<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet, 1724 W. Chicago Ave., Chicago, Ill., by Ben Chase,
<date when="1936-11-19">Nov. 19, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Eugene Moravsky</title>, Editor of Daily Rassviet, 1724 W. Chicago Ave., Chicago, Ill., by Ben Chase,
<date when="1936-11-19">Nov. 19, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Moravsky, who in real life is Eugene Z. Dolinin, was born in Kiziany, State of Vilna (present Poland), in 1897, but was reared and educated in Russia proper.</p>
   <p>Mr. Moravsky, who has suffered imprisonment and exile at the hands of the Soviet government, does not adhere to the principles of the present day Russian regime. He claims that no country can be free without the basic principles of freedom, and that is freedom of speech, press, religion, etc., which the present Russian government denies its citizens.</p>
   <p>Mr. Moravsky came to the United States in 1924. After spending a short time in New York he left for the principal cities of United States where he lectured and held discussions about Russia. In 1926 he came to Chicago and became connected with Rassviet in the capacity of Associate Editor, and three years later became its Editor-in-Chief. Mr. Moravsky was married to Miss Mary Kowell in September of 1928.</p>
   <p>Miss Kowell, the present Mrs. Dolinin, was born in Chicago of Russian parentage and, while brought up in a strict Orthodox Russian home, nevertheless knew very little about the Russian language and only after her marriage <pb facs="5423967_4_1658.jpg" n="2"/>started seriously studying it, and according to Mr. Moravsky is at present a very fluent speaker and reader of that language. Mrs. Dolinin is in charge of the Foreign Department of the Amalgamated Bank and Trust Company, 114 South Dearborn, having been connected with that institution for the last four years. She is very active in Russian organizations and quite often helps Rassviet with translations whenever her services are required.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
