<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">If Only We Had More Like Him</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">IF ONLY WE HAD MORE LIKE HIM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who in the Russian colony in Chicago does not know Vasiliev? Everyone knows him. There are several Vasilievs in Chicago, but our colony knows only one--Aleksey V. Vasiliev.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vasiliev is in private life a building contractor. His office is located at 542 South Dearborn Street. As a businessman, he has become completely Americanized. But as soon as he leaves his office and his work, he is the Russian again, the true Russian. Mr. Vasiliev gladly supports every worth-while Russian undertaking. One cannot imagine a Russian concert, or a ball, or any other affair, without Mr. Vasiliev, accompanied by his wife and son. It is no wonder, therefore, that no other Russian in Chicago enjoys such wide popularity as Mr. Vasiliev does.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vasiliev is now engaged in the construction of the Russian Independent church on Wood Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1664.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When at home, Mr. Vasiliev and his charming wife are the supreme representatives of true Russian hospitality, comparable only to that seen in the better homes in the pre-revolutionary Russia.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we wish to express our desire for more such Vasilievs in the Chicago Russian colony. Our life would then be different than it is now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
