<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1929-11-02">Nov. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">How the Russian Herces Were Greeted in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_1541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1929-11-02">Nov. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HOW THE RUSSIAN HERCES WERE GREETED IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thursday, October 24, 1929, is a historical day for the Russian colony in Chicago and its vicinities.</p>
   <p>On this day, at 3 o'clock, in the afternoon, our compatriots from Russia, who accomplished their history making flight in the plane, Strana Sovietov, (The Country of the Soviet), from Moscow to the United States, landed in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The fliers arrived in Chicago an hour earlier than they had planned and for this reason they were not welcomed by everyone who desired to do so.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, at the airport to which the Russian fliers, Shestakov, Bolotov, Sterlingov, and Fufaev flew, an enormous crowd had gathered.</p>
   <p>Many automobiles with signs, "Welcome Soviet Fliers," were there, and we noticed several automobiles bearing the license plates of the neighboring <pb facs="5423967_4_1542.jpg" n="2"/>states of Wisconsin and Indiana. There were many Polish people present who were astonished at the daring of the Moskali (Muscovites) and their child, Strana Sovietov.</p>
   <p>The American Aero Club gave a luncheon in their honor. On the next day, Friday, October 25th, the American Aero Club greeted the honored Russian guests at the Palmer House.</p>
   <p>At this celebration official representatives of the City of Chicago were present who addressed the Russian fliers.</p>
   <p>Among others, an attorney, representing the City of Chicago, said in his speech, "Russia leads all other countries in her progress, she is far a-head in scientific research and technique, and she also has sent these four heroes who achieved this historical flight."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1543.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Modesty of the Russian Heroes of the Air</p>
   <p>All of the four fliers are unusually modest. Looking at them you are convinced that all greatness is recognized by modesty and absence of inane boasting. It seems that before you, stand four polite and naive Russian boys believing that they have achieved nothing outstanding...True heroism acts in this manner. And such are our fliers.</p>
   <p>When those present at the luncheon in honor of the fliers asked them to say something, Mr. Shestakov arose from his chair, and in a few words modestly said, "Our flight is no extraordinary achievement, and we are only seeking new ways to establish a steady air route between Moscow and New York."</p>
   <p>Later he thanked everyone for the cordial reception, pointing out that such a welcome by the Americans held him and his companions from further flight, because it was impossible to escape from such wonderful and excellent hospitality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1544.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the dining room, many photographers and newsreel men took pictures of the Russian heroes.</p>
   <p>The Greeting in Russian</p>
   <p>Several Russians came by invitation of the American Aero Club and welcomed the Russian fliers to the celebration. Among them were: Dr. Novakovsky, Mrs. Liutnicky, Dr. Reznik, Dr. Shuisky, J. J. Voronko, Mr. Jesmer, vice president of the Amalgamated Bank, Mr. Liutnicky, Mr. G. Sawicki, Managing Editor of Russkoye Obozrenie, Mr. Shuisky, Editor of Russkoye Obozrenie, and others.</p>
   <p>Dr. Novakovsky and Mr. Jesmer welcomed the fliers in Russian, and at the end J. J. Voronko delivered an excellent speech concerning the meaning of the flight accomplished by the Russian fliers.</p>
   <p>After the luncheon everyone heartily greeted the four valiant Russian knights, shaking their hands, asking questions, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1545.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Here Is Where There Is a Genuine Welcome of the Fliers</p>
   <p>On Sunday, October the 27th, the welcome of the fliers by the Russian colony was impressive. In the huge hall of the Broadway Armory with a capacity of fifteen thousand people, the Russian people gathered to greet their worthy compatriots.</p>
   <p>There was an insufficient number of seats in the hall for all who came. Nevertheless, the order kept by the huge crowd of people in the hall was exemplary.</p>
   <p>And as Mr. Shestakov arose to speak, instantaneous solemn silence fell upon the hall, as if it were a church.</p>
   <p>All the fifteen thousand people who came there wanted to hear everything and not miss a word from the speeches of our heroes. Short, but energetic Shestakov arose and in a loud voice, heard in every corner of the hall, <pb facs="5423967_4_1546.jpg" n="6"/>boomed out, "It has been known for several years in the U. S. S. R. that we have many friends beyond our boundaries. And wherever we landed, thousands of people greeted us at the airport and commissioned us to deliver their ardent and enthusiastic regards to the Soviet Union.</p>
   <p>"I am happy and honored to fulfill this commission and as an envoy of the Union, to present to you their regards."</p>
   <p>After Shestakov, Bolotov and Sterlingov made short speeches.</p>
   <p>"My dear friends," said Bolotov, "in order not to take much time, I will be brief. I want to point out that the Americans have displayed a great interest in our flight. As for the rest, I agree with Shestakov, and I shall express the same sentiments when presenting my report on our arrival in Moscow. At present, I cannot make any further statements."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_1547.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Sterlingov said, "Dear friends, our marine flier is absolutely right when he said that he could not add anything to the words of Shestakov. Flying together, doing the same great thing, we had the same experience and were inspired with the same courage. I thank you for your friendly welcome."</p>
   <p>The Russians Donated Money for Tractors Willingly</p>
   <p>During the celebration, welcoming the Russian fliers at the Broadway Armory, Russians eagerly answered the call for sending a gift from the American compatriots to the Russian peasants. The money for tractors poured freely, as if from a cornucopia, in small coins as well as in large denominations. Many of the individuals signed checks for hundreds of dollars and the same was done by organizations, one of which gave a check for $1,250. All this money was forwarded through the fliers to the Russian peasants as a gift for the purchase of tractors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
