<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Russkoye Slovo, Vol, IV, No. 472, New York, 1914)
<title level="a">Nikolai Gavrilovich Is Granted a Reprieve</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_4_0254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Russkoye Slovo, Vol, IV, No. 472, New York, 1914)
<title level="a">NIKOLAI GAVRILOVICH IS GRANTED A REPRIEVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the telegrams, Russkoye Slovo announces that Governor Edward F. Dunn advised the following: "Replying to your request I am informing you that the State Supreme Court has ruled to postpone the execution of Nikolai Gavrilovich, sentenced to death for murder.</p>
   <p>"This renders any action on my part, with reference to your request, superfluous.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>E. F. Dunn."</p>
   <p>Russkoye Slovo thereupon urges further action. It suggests pressing for <pb facs="5423967_4_0255.jpg" n="2"/>a review of the entire case or else at least a commutation from death to imprisonment.</p>
   <p>Attorney R. G. Louis, a Russian immigrant of many years, and influential in politics, is engaged for the case. A large expenditure is imminent, "yet, judging by the response from the Russian colony this will not impede the work of saving a young life from the noose."</p>
   <p>In still another article, headed "Campaign in Chicago Against Execution of Gavrilovich," Russkoye Slovo reproves slackers in the campaign, mentions branches 1 and 4 of the Socialist Party, which decided to start a campaign in earnest. Tells that the local priest promised to get his parishioners interested in the affair, and if necessary, also to give material aid. It states that the politically influential lawyer, Roman G. Louis, requested a brief on the case, but will evidently have to go for it to Edwardsville.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_4_0256.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It regrets Jane Addam's temporary absence from Chicago, but it feels certain that upon her return she will voice her return she will voice her protest against this death sentence inasmuch as she has always vigorously denounced capital punishment.</p>
   <p>It concludes with the hope that, despite the short time in which to do it, the life of the doomed man will surely be saved by energetic work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
