<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-19">Feb. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Concert of the Kalina Women's Choir</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0651</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0651.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-19">Feb. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT OF THE KALINA WOMEN'S CHOIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Kalina (Guelder-rose) Women's Choir gave a very successful concert at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Building. The hall was packed.</p>
   <p>The concert was opened by the orchestra, under Mr. E. Krotochwila's direction, which played an overture. The Kalina Choir, under the direction of Mr. F. Kondziorski, sang "Beloved Land" with orchestral accompaniment. The Philaret Choir, under the direction of Mr. B. Rybowiak, sang "Pastuszek" (The Little Shepherd), by Namyslowski, and "Goral" (The Mountaineer), by Muencheimer. The solo parts were sung very well by Mr. Thaddeus Kempski, well-known baritone. We have already heard some very successful performances by the Philaret Choir, but yesterday's performance exceeded the audience's expectations, and it rewarded the choir with a storm of applause lasting several minutes. Following the Philarets, the following choirs appeared in the order named: Halka Women's <pb facs="5423968_5_0652.jpg" n="2"/>Choir, under the direction of Mr. B. Kujawski; the Ignace Paderewski Choir, under the direction of Mr. F. Kondziorski, which sang Gburski's "Wieczorna Cisza" (Twilight Calm); and the Jutrzenka (Dawn) Women's Choir, under the direction of Mr. R. Hensel. Then Mrs. F. Czaja and Mrs. Rose Porazinski, members of the Kalina Choir, sang the duet "Blogie Wspomnienia" (Happy Memories), by Walkiewicz, after which our famous singer Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch sang "Sny Milosci" (Dreams of Love), by Kratzer, as a soprano solo with orchestral accompaniment.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Kwasigroch, as usual, charmed the audience with her singing, as a result of which the hall shook from the applause. The B. Dembinski Choir of South Chicago, under the direction of Mr. Bork, sang "Do Piesni" (To Song), by B. Dembinski. This was followed by a duet by Mrs. R. Kwasigroch, soprano, and Mr. F. Kondziorski, baritone, singing compositions of "Perly Piesni" (Pearls of Song) with orchestral accompaniment. The Chopin Choir No. 1. of the Polish Singers' Alliance sang "Hold Chopinowi" (Tribute to Chopin), by <pb facs="5423968_5_0653.jpg" n="3"/>Chopin-Muencheimer, with orchestral accompaniment directed by Mr. F. Kondziorski. To conclude the program the Halka, Kalina, and Chopin choirs sang "Do Piesni Polskiej" (To Polish Song), with orchestral accompaniment directed by Mr. Kondziorski.</p>
   <p>There was social dancing at the conclusion of this excellent and lengthy program. The polonaise, in which some two hundred couples participated, was led by Mr. F. Kondziorski with Mrs. R. Kwasigroch, followed by Mr. Kwasigroch with Mrs. Kondziorski.</p>
   <p>It should be added that all the numbers on the program came out unusually well, and the audience did not stint applause. Mrs. Kwasigroch was handed a beautiful bouquet of roses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
