<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-03">June 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-03">June 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Dramatic Club presented "Night Of Humor" last night, at the new Polish Hall to a small audience. It is a pity that the attendance was so small, though a large gathering was not expected because no tickets were sold and the play was not advertised for any length of time, as is the custom before staging big plays. This was done only during the last two days. No special efforts were made because last night's activity was only a trial or a sample of performances which will be staged by the Club in the future.</p>
   <p>Our readers are acquainted with the aim of this club, for we described it in one of our earlier articles. We wish to point out that no one who attended last night's play, "Night of Humor," was disappointed, for every one enjoyed himself immensely, and in this respect, last night's entertainment was a great success. On account of limited space, we cannot describe all the details of last night's program, which consisted of many numbers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1113.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We wish, however, to state that the following persons contributed to the amusement and enjoyment of the audience: Mr. Czekala, a very popular Polish comedian, entertained the audience with his song, "With the Salt," and with his comical impersonations. He also presented a Polish-English comedy entitled "Misunderstanding"; Mr. Kedziorski, the president of the Club, appeared in the comedy sketch entitled "Mr. Brochocki," in which he played the part of the justice of the peace. He also entertained the audience with songs and monologues in the English language; and Mr. Rosa, who presented "Burg Music," a one-act comedy, greatly amused the audience.</p>
   <p>"The Grandma Katzenjammer," a one-act comedy written by Mr. S. Zachajkiewich only last Saturday, was also presented last night, and proved to be a great success. It brought from the audience outbursts of laughter as never heard before. The following took part: Mr. Kedziorski, Mr. Czekala, Mr. Szajkowski, and Mr. Jozwiakowski, who deserve a great deal of credit and should be complimented, for they tried to outdo one another in performing their comical parts. We should also admire their improvising talent, for to do so would <pb facs="5423968_5_1114.jpg" n="3"/>be quite appropriate.</p>
   <p>The most important part of the program was comprised of solos and recitations composed by Mr. J. Kedziorski and Mr. Barwig, and recited by Mr. Jozwiakowski. The numbers were interspersed with piano solos. This varied program delighted the audience immensely. We wish to point out that Messrs. Barwig and Kedziorski as singers, and Mr. Jozwiakowski as an elocutionist, have been great favorites of the public for some time. The accompaniment to the songs was played by Mr. A. Kwasigroch. The educational part of the program was a lecture on art, and a short talk by Reverend W. Barzynski, at the end.</p>
   <p>The Polish Dramatic Club will give similar entertainments for their own members once a week, and they intend to give them for the benefit of the public once or twice a month. The ladies did not participate in the "Night of Humor." Will they refuse to patronize the Club in the future? In our opinion, this would be unfair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
