<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 51,
<date when="1897-12-23">Dec. 23, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">In the Affairs of Our National Singing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0756.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 51,
<date when="1897-12-23">Dec. 23, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE AFFAIRS OF OUR NATIONAL SINGING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers! Seeing such little support that you render our singing choirs, noting also your indifference toward them, I embolden myself then, in the name of patriotism, requesting you all to open your hearts and not be negligent in aiding our national singing.</p>
   <p>Join our singers, throng them old and young, and cooperate with us so that we can create and establish choirs in vast numbers which would bring honor for us Poles.</p>
   <p>I particularly urge that you, young folks, who know of no way to spend your leisure evenings, spending them uselessly is of no benefit to you or to anyone-else. Persons should sacrifice at least one evening during the week for culture, by participating in singing and familiarizing themselves with the Polish language and songs.</p>
   <p>Join us, young friends, and you shall not regret it. Here you shall find a real pleasure in spending your time; here you shall not only familiarize yourself and love our wonderful Polish language and song, but also shall find the possibility of culturing yourself in same and also awaken an instinct of <pb facs="5423968_5_0757.jpg" n="2"/>national pride.</p>
   <p>We sometimes hear the elders criticize the Polish singers for their poor singing, and praise the German or Swedish choirs as an example to follow. They do not stop to consider our hardships.</p>
   <p>We shall explain this as follows:</p>
   <p>The Germans or the Swedes are older singers who have had ten or more years of practice in this art of singing; none of them claims that he is too old or too tired. But unanimously they stand together with the youth and cooperate with them, not paying any attention to the gray hairs that cover their heads.</p>
   <p>And what happens with us? Can we pride ourselves with the fact that we have the full support from the older generation? No! The young people, who belong to singing circles, do not achieve any advancement or respect for us or themselves.</p>
   <p>Here's what usually happens among or to our young members. A youth, who belongs to a singing circle for two or three years, when he marries, drops this <pb facs="5423968_5_0758.jpg" n="3"/>ambition of being a member any longer with some simple excuse.</p>
   <p>Can't they sacrifice at least one night for singing and cultivate themselves in it, even though they are married?</p>
   <p>If everyone would understand their duties toward their nationality and would spend this one evening for singing, then our choirs would be above all other national choirs, and we would not then have to be ashamed of our ignorance in this art.</p>
   <p>And so, cooperate with us, you elderly brothers and you youth too, so that our song can go beyond the furthest corners of this earth and reach way over the ocean toward our brothers in Poland.</p>
   <p>Zygmunt Perlowski,</p>
   <p>A member of the Moniuszko choir.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
