<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-06">Nov. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Organization News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-06">Nov. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Halka Choir, under the direction of B. J. Zalewski, gave a concert last night at Schoenhofen's Hall. The concert was a success; the program, rich and varied, was well-chosen. [Translator's note: I have omitted the details of the program.]</p>
   <p>The general impression was the usual one. Our concerts have already established a certain routine. Yesterday another deficiency was added--the unfortunate behavior of the audience. During the choir and solo numbers, the audience kept up a steady flow of conversation. Miss Osmansk's piano solo simply could not be heard. The same was true of the lovely duet executed by the Misses Kempski. When the Filareci Choir, with its customary elan, performed its special numbers, it could not be heard.</p>
   <p>As to the rendition, the public has its set opinion already about Chicago choirs and their singing. The Halka Ladies Choir has improved considerably <pb facs="5423968_5_0696.jpg" n="2"/>under its new director; both of its numbers yesterday drew enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>As for the soloists, Miss Witt, if she will accept our friendly advice, should always sing mezzo-soprano, a compass within which she sings very well.</p>
   <p>Last night's concert was followed by dancing, which continued until long past midnight. Despite the tremendous crowding, which must have caused considerable damage to the ladies' white slippers, everyone sincerely enjoyed himself, and conducted himself properly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
