<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-21">Sept. 21, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Bazaar for Polish Orphans to Open Tonight in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-21">Sept. 21, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">BAZAAR FOR POLISH ORPHANS TO OPEN TONIGHT IN ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This evening at 8 o'clock the bazaar for the Polish orphans will open at the St. Stanislaus Kostka School Hall on Bradley Street. All proceeds from the bazaar will be turned over to the Holy Family Orphanage. Starting with tomorrow and through the days to follow, the event will be in full swing.</p>
   <p>An appeal is made to all spirited-minded citizens, organizations, societies, etc. throughout Chicago to support this noble cause.</p>
   <p>"Res Sacra Misera tenet" (It is a Holy task to deal with Misery) is a well-known saying. These words should first of all be applied to children who are homeless, without parents, incapable of self support, and those Polish orphans that have been stranded in this country without means of support. Only an institution of this kind can be of assistance to them.</p>
   <p>Your participation will help to give succor to these unfortunate children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1283.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Give them a widow's mite in order to assure them an existence that will guard them from hunger and disease.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that every public-spirited Pole will heartily support this bazaar and we feel that the Polish people will do everything possible to prevent our Polish destitute children from suffering from hunger and raggedness. It is our duty to do our part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
