<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>. Vol. XIX, No. 167,
<date when="1908-07-17">July 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Request to All Polish Polytechnic Societies and Trading Companies in Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>. Vol. XIX, No. 167,
<date when="1908-07-17">July 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">REQUEST TO ALL POLISH POLYTECHNIC SOCIETIES AND TRADING COMPANIES IN CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Citizens:</p>
   <p>On June 25th the central administration of the Polish Buyers' Society "White Eagle" published in all Polish papers a request calling a parliament of constitutional societies for the 29th of July, at Mr. Romanowicz's Hall, located at 120 W. Division Street. The Polish public is also reminded that on the same day, the consecration of the first Polish bishop in the United States, Rev. Father P. Rhode, will take place. The administration is doing everything possible to make this the greatest celebration to ever take place in the city of Chicago among the Polish people.</p>
   <p>This is a proof that our own flesh and blood, our brother, has finally achieved what the other nationalities never expected to see. Haven't the Polish people worked and slaved long enough to deserve this celebration <pb facs="5423968_5_0150.jpg" n="2"/>and make the most of it? It was agreed that the parliament of constitutional societies was postponed one week, to August 5, at the same hall at 9 A. M.</p>
   <p>As it is known, for the last four years this organization of Polish polytechnic societies and trading companies has existed under the name of "White Eagle." This organization consists of Polish business men, buyers, wholesale and retail enterprises, and the small individual businessman. This organization was formed to unite all Polish business men in one group for the betterment of business and promotion of good will.</p>
   <p>You all know that every day some businessman is met by misfortune, and we must take steps to safeguard people in this hour of need.</p>
   <p>Very often it happens that a husband dies and leaves his business to <pb facs="5423968_5_0151.jpg" n="3"/>his widow and children. When the husband dies so does the business, and especially in the case the wife does not understand the business, what is she to do?</p>
   <p>In incidents like these, our society sends out a committee, who takes charge of the business and sells out the entire stock reasonably, but not at a loss; or manages and continues the business until the widow understands the principles of buying and selling, and then leave the business in her hands, with the understanding that if she is in trouble and needs help, all she has to do is notify the society, and a committee is sent to her assistance, free of charge.</p>
   <p>Many business people belong to different organizations and societies, but none gives the protection and insurance that this "White Eagle Society" gives.</p>
   <p>All Polish businessmen are asked to form new groups. All information <pb facs="5423968_5_0152.jpg" n="4"/>can be obtained from the central administration. Information can be received from any of the members of this committee:</p>
   <p>Mr. W. Perlowski, President.</p>
   <p>Joseph Blaszka, Vice-President.</p>
   <p>Fr. Landmesser, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Albert Novak, Cashier.</p>
   <p>Mr. F. Kupski, Dr. Leonard, Mr. W. Sajewski, Mr. J. Wilkowski,</p>
   <p>Mr. J. F. Singer - Board of Directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
