<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - <title level="a">"Polish Day and Public Opinion."</title> <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1926-08">August 1926</date>, P. 4.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - <title level="a">"Polish Day and Public Opinion."</title> <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1926-08">August 1926</date>, P. 4.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The greatest and most powerful factor in any community is public opinion--not the nominal public opinion of creed or statute book, but the real public opinion of living men and women. Whatever the intelligent and influential world regards as success, ambitious men will try to achieve. Whatever means the intelligent and influential world condones in its work, the ambitious man will practice in his. On the other hand, whatever ends the world regards as dishonorable, strong men will refuse to pursue; and whatever means people disdain to use in their own interest, the strong man will reject and spurn. This dependence upon public opinion is not simply a present fact, it is a necessary basis of all free government.</p>
   <p>Five hundred years ago our ancestors had a coherent and well defined system of public opinion on public matters as well as private ones. The public opinions of those ages held that each man was born to fill a certain niche or place in society. His duties as a member of the political body were sharply defined for him by a series of traditions. At all points which the law could reach he was closely hedged about; and where the law could not reach him, public sentiment compelled him to accept the dictates of the church as to what he should think and believe. This was the essence of the feudal system. The codes of law with which we identify that system were only <pb facs="5423968_5_1140.jpg" n="2"/>its externals. After many years, however, there came a time when people ceased to be content with the dictates of this inherited opinion--a time when they wanted to make their own place in society, and serve the community in their own way instead of the way which tradition prescribed. Such men were at first treated as heretics and reprobates; but the communities which gave ear to their new principles and tolerated their new methods prospered, while those who strove to repress them, fell behind. Suffice it to say that in the course of four centuries we passed from a system, wherein each man was born into a set of rights and obligations whicnme could not change, to a system of liberty, under which each man was encouraged to serve society in his own way for better or for worse.</p>
   <p>A year and a half ago the idea of holding a "Polish Day" Festival was begotten by several young, energetic, and progressive members of Chicago Society. One or two individuals laughed and ridiculed the venture--even labeled it "a small Polish picnic". All the newspapers, the progressive clergymen, and the laity heartily supported the "Polish Day" Festival, hence public opinion is in favor of it and the "Polish Day" Association is now a corporation organized not for profit. The boy at school recognizes the obligations imposed by the public opinion of his fellows <pb facs="5423968_5_1141.jpg" n="3"/>far more clearly and consistently than he obeys the rules imposed by the master. The professional man will hold to his code of professional ethics after he has let all other ethics go; for to forfeit the opinion of those with whom he is associated is a greater evil than to lose life or liberty or chances of eternal salvation. Once let public opinion be so clear on a certain point, that a man will enforce it against himself just as much as he does against others, it can accomplish nothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
