<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-06">Dec. 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Inventors in America a Few Interesting Facts from the Office of Mr. E. L. Schultz (Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-06">Dec. 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH INVENTORS IN AMERICA A Few Interesting Facts From the Office of Mr. E. L. Schultz (Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We mentioned not long ago that a capable Polish technician, Mr. E. L. Schultz, in company with some Americans, opened up a patent-technical office to secure patents of inventions, prepare models, and assist in all similar matters. Mr. Schultz wishes specifically to assist Polish inventors, so that they can reap the benefits of their ingenuity.</p>
   <p>We originally thought that in America not many Polish inventors would be found, but the letter written by Mr. Schultz and quoted herewith is a very pleasant surprise. Mr. Schultz writes as follows:</p>
   <p>"It is a pleasure for me to note that the number of Poles applying to me with numerous inventions from all over the United States surpasses my <pb facs="5423968_5_0292.jpg" n="2"/>fondest expectations. It is true that these inventions are oftentimes submitted only in the barest outline, yet, after some corrections and technical preparations, they are at times quite valuable.</p>
   <p>"I want to mention a few here:</p>
   <p>"Mr. P. Racinski from Pennsylvania invented a pouch that is continually in motion, which will be very useful in glass mills and silk factories.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Kodis of Chicago has an excellent improvement for velocipedes which gives ten per cent greater speed, using the same propelling force.</p>
   <p>"Mr. F. Sowadzki of Chicago has an invention that will be a real blessing for our mothers; it is a children's crib that will continue rocking for twelve hours with one winding of a key.</p>
   <p>"We have also some important inventions for farm tools. Mr. Guzowski has a few. The most important is a "Karto Flarka" (Translator's note: Potato <pb facs="5423968_5_0293.jpg" n="3"/>harvester), which seems to have a great future. Mr. Szarkowski of North Dakota has a seeder which also may have a wide acquaintance.</p>
   <p>"Furthermore, Mr. Lukaszewski of Racine, Wisconsin, patented a chess table that can be folded up into a small box.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Gaya's (of Baltimore) wonderful success in receiving 100,000 for his invention has aroused many others as to the possibilities in this field. We have already in our possession three different types of couplings for cars.</p>
   <p>"A total of twelve Poles have patented their inventions, and they are all grateful for finding this security, because they had thought of various ideas, but if they did not find anyone to advise them and help them they would have forgotten all about their ideas.</p>
   <p>"We manufacture the models of practically all of the inventions we handle in our own factory, and many of these inventors have given permission to send models of their inventions to the Lwow Exposition, so we sincerely hope <pb facs="5423968_5_0294.jpg" n="4"/>that the ingenuity of Polish inventors in America will prove to be a grand exhibit in Lwow."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
