<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-12">Sept. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Central Committee Meets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1483</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1483.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-12">Sept. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY CENTRAL COMMITTEE MEETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Day Central Committee held a meeting at Pulaski Hall yesterday evening. After routine business had been attended to, the Committee turned its attention to community reports. These reports, as could be readily seen, were evidence of the great Polish Day activity in progress throughout Chicago Polonia. Since the delegates from South Chicago were not present, it was decided that a few members of the Committee's administration visit the Polish communities in South Chicago to determine the extent of activity there.</p>
   <p>On a motion by C. Zychlinski, the Committee decided to communicate with the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance concerning the use of the Liberty Bell, and to thank Mr. McDowell for permitting the use of it in the Polish Day celebration. The special committees' reports followed.</p>
   <p>The financial committee reported that as a result of its appeal, the convention of the Polish National Alliance had appropriated $400 for the Polish Day fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1484.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Of this, $150 was designated to the Central Committee and $250 to finance the Alliance's representation in the celebration.</p>
   <p>The parade committee reported that during the course of the next week it will prepare the program of the parade.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of arrangements for the celebration at Festival Hall decided to issue immediately invitations to those who will participate in the program. In addition to the American speakers, whom we named in an earlier issue, Dr. Casimir Midowicz will be invited to speak in Polish. The committee will hold its next meeting, in conjunction with the committee in charge of music, on Thursday, September 14, at the[Polish World's Fair]Reception Committee's headquarters, 141-43 West Division Street.</p>
   <p>It was further decided to appoint a committee for the arrangement of a program for a gymnastic and military competition to be held at the Stock Pavilion. This committee consists of M. J. Szameit, C. Zychlinski, and Z. Schmidt.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1485.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee on badges presented a specimen consisting of a tricolor ribbon and a small silver eagle, bearing the inscription, "Polish Day, October 7, 1893." It was decided to order ten thousand such badges. Badges will cost the committee five cents each and will be sold at fifteen cents each. The profit will be used to help cover the expense of the celebration.</p>
   <p>The publicity committee presented the printed announcements that will be sent to Polish societies outside of Chicago, and a proposed announcement to the Polish clergy in other cities, requesting them to support the Polish Day cause. Both announcements were accepted, and the publicity committee was instructed to continue with its work.</p>
   <p>Judge [M.A.] La Buy, treasurer of the Central Committee, presented his report on the state of the treasury, which now has $175.58. Of this, $58.73 was received at the last meeting, and $116.85 at this. Payment of the fifteen-cent-per-person assessment was made by the following societies:</p>
   <p>From St. Stanislaus Kostka parish: Polish Queen's Guard (20 members), $3.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1486.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From St. Casimir's parish: Holy Cross Society (24 members), $3.60; St. Casimir's Council, Catholic Order of Foresters (25 members), $3.75; St. Isidore's Society (58 members), $8.70; St. Casimir's Society (25 members), $3.75; the Stephen Buszczynski Society (30 members), $4.50. From Town of Lake: St. Lawrence Society (43 members), $6.45. From St. Adalbert's parish: Society of the Sorrowful Mother of God (60 members), $9; Sacred Name of Jesus Society (100 members), $15; King Sigmund I Society (24 members), $3.60. From Bridgeport: St. Francis Xavier Society (80 members), $12; St. Stephan's Society (60 members), $9; Uhlans of St. Paul (13 members), $1.95; St. Mary of Perpetual Help Society (54 members), $8.10. From St. Hedwig's parish: St. Hedwig's Society (84 members), $12.60; Polish National Patriotic Society (33 members), $4.95; the Star of Victory Women's Society (46 members), $6.90. The total amounted to $116.85.</p>
   <p>Following this report, the meeting was adjourned until Monday, September 18.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
