<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-11">Apr. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">More about the School Children's Entertainment in the Bradley Street Hall</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-11">Apr. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT THE SCHOOL CHILDREN'S ENTERTAINMENT IN THE BRADLEY STREET HALL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The other night, due to favorable circumstances, I found myself accidentally in the Hall on Bradley Street watching the children extending their sincere and joyous greetings to their most beloved pastor, because of his happy return from a lengthy sojourn in California for his health, which was undermined by long and tedious mission labors.</p>
   <p>I am speaking here of the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, the pastor of Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish, where the school children tutored by the Sisters of Notre Dame had the honor of welcoming him.</p>
   <p>I pass by the sincerity and frankness of the childrens' feelings, which could <pb facs="5423968_5_0808.jpg" n="2"/>easily be read in the faces of the innocent tots.</p>
   <p>I want to write a few words about something else here. I refer to the exhibition of musical prowess during the program. This exhibition, I can say without flattery, was masterful. This is not a meaningless word. I am acquainted with music and love it.... This recent entertainment in the Bradley Street hall was truly beautiful and artistic. The entire audience was entranced.</p>
   <p>Imagine, if you please, a group of young girls playing on zithers, two soloists leading them, running their bows over the silken cords; a strangely beautiful melody results therefrom, truly violin-like in tone, enriched with the quaint harmony of the zithers.</p>
   <p>Imagine, if you please, the singing of "Sub Tuum Presiduum". You hear a sweet soprano voice, whose elasticity and easy modulations remind me of the singing <pb facs="5423968_5_0809.jpg" n="3"/>of a first-class artist; then a grand alto voice, seemingly showing a miraculous imitation with its full and rounded tone of a mezzo sweetness of the birds singing; then the choir, so excellent that it dares sudden modulations, omitting the half tones.</p>
   <p>Imagine all of this, if you please, and you will have some idea of the musical banquet given by the school children of the Saint Stanislaus Kostka School, and tutored by the Sisters of Notre Dame.</p>
   <p>All honor to you, Sisters of Notre Dame, who have been able to bring forth from absolutely raw material such artistic forces.</p>
   <p>How much work and trouble was connected with this entertainment, God only knows. Once more, all honor to you!</p>
   <p>An Amateur critic of Music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
