<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The March, "Free Poland" Now on Sale at Bookshops</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARCH, "FREE POLAND" NOW ON SALE AT BOOKSHOPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beyond a doubt, it must be admitted that the march by B. Rybowiak, entitled "Free Poland" after the hymn by our great pianist Ignace Paderewski and sung all over America during the military band concerts, has aroused much interest in singers' circles; a great demand for the march has been created.</p>
   <p>During the past few months, from the time of the military band's first appearances, Rybowiak's march has become so popular that almost everyone knows it by heart. Its popularity is due to its beautiful battle motif and splendid harmony. Rybowiak harmonizes well. He has the virtue that he avoids difficult combinations, and harmonizes so that the composition can easily be sung, creating at the same time rich chords that inspire the Polish spirit. This virtue is especially apparent in "Free Poland," and for this reason, the composition is assured of great success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0434.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Free Poland" has finally been published in an arrangement for piano. Rybowiak has not yet had time to arrange it for other instruments but will do so in the near future. It will be sung for the first time by a great mixed choir during Sunday's manifestation at the Coliseum.</p>
   <p>A rehearsal of this choir was held yesterday at the Polish Women's Alliance Hall and was extraordinarily successful. A great many singers answered the appeal. A greater participation of young people is expected tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
