<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-04">Apr. 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Reception of Visitors to the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-04">Apr. 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">RECEPTION OF VISITORS TO THE WORLD'S COLUMBIAN EXPOSITION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting took place yesterday at the school hall near Bradley Street to discuss the matter of welcoming our countrymen who will come to Chicago for the World's Columbian Exposition. A large number of people, not only from the Northwest Side but from all parts of the city, attended. Father Vincent Barzynski presided and Mr. Stanley <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The question as to how the prospective visitors from Poland are to be welcomed was discussed by Father Barzyaski, Peter Kiolbassa, Count Henry Lubenski, W. <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and others. It was agreed that our duty is to make their stay in Chicago as pleasant as possible and to held them find their way about the city. The only difficulty lay in how to arrange for this. Finally, a committee of twenty-five was elected to work out the details and to take temporary charge of the matter. The committee, which was chosen immediately, consists of Father Vincent Barzynski, Count Henry Lubienski, Peter Kiolbassa, <pb facs="5423968_5_1636.jpg" n="2"/>Ralph Modrejewski, John <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Boleslaus <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Francis Skon, Signund Schmidt, Henry <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Peter Arkuszewski, Andrew Kwasigroch, Thomas Mrolik, Paul <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Stanley Szwajkart, August J. Kowalski, John Arkuszowski, Walter Smulski, E. Z. Brodowski, John Kwasigroch, Walter Kobrzynski, Joseph <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, and From among this large committee, a subcommittee of five was chosen. To this subcommittee was assigned the problem of working out a detailed plan, which is to be presented to the large group for a proval. This subcommittee includes Father Barzynski, <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Jandrejeh [sic], and B. Klarkowski. The meeting at which the plan is to be placed before the committee of twenty-five, will be held at the school hall on Thursday, April 6, at 7:30 P.M. All members of the committee are requested to be present. The decisions reached by this meeting will probably be made known to the public at a mass meeting on the following Sunday.</p>
   <p>North mentioning is the fact that the committee of five met last night at <pb facs="5423968_5_1637.jpg" n="3"/>the rectory of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church and formulated a plan in general outline. We cannot present it at this time because the plan has yet to be approved by the higher committee. We can say, however, that the project includes a special information bureau and a general headquarters for a reception committee. Guides able to speak Polish and English will be placed on the Exposition grounds for the convenience of visitors from Poland. The subcommittee is preparing also a suitable announcement, which is to be sent to Poland. We hope that the reception committee (as soon as it is appointed) will be able to begin its activities after next Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
