<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. X, No. 13,
<date when="1906-03-28">March 28, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">First Polish Bank in America Poles in Chicago Should Lead the Way</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. X, No. 13,
<date when="1906-03-28">March 28, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST POLISH BANK IN AMERICA POLES IN CHICAGO SHOULD LEAD THE WAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We need Polish banks. Our funds are present deposited in foreign banks, sometimes in unreliable and irresponsible ones.</p>
   <p>People judge us not competent nor able to organize and establish a bank.</p>
   <p>The organization committee consist of Jan Smulski, Tomasz Krolik and Theo. M. Helinski also many other energetic Polish businessmen.</p>
   <p>The bank's capital is $200,000.00 with a surplus of $25,000.00.</p>
   <p>The price of a share will be $112.50.</p>
   <p>The state auditor in Springfield has issued a certificate recognizing this organization under the control of the state.</p>
   <p>Many Polish businessmen are shareholders, and all received the news about the Polish State Bank with enthusiasm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The whole building consists at the present time of three stories located on the corner of Milwaukee Ave. and Haddon Ave.</p>
   <p>It is rented for this purpose, and about May 1 alterations will be started, for the large new bank.</p>
   <p>There will be installed in the bank "Safety Deposit Vaults" fire and burglar proof boxes for money and valuable papers, etc.</p>
   <p>The title of this corporation will be "North-Western Trust &amp; Savings Bank".</p>
   <p>The shares will soon be for sale and we are inviting all Poles to come and register.</p>
   <p>Registration for the shares is in the office of Mr. Jan Przbysz, 814 Milwaukee Ave. in the building where the bank will be located.</p>
   <p>A payment at $25.00 should be deposited on each share, the balance may be paid about May 1.</p>
   <p>Without any doubt the shares will pay good dividends, and their value will increase.</p>
   <p>Let as many Poles as possible join this successful endeavor so as to show our people a way to future business and financial establishments.</p>
   <p>Jan F. Smulski- Tomass-Krolik - T. M. Helinski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
