<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-07-08">July 8, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Students of St. Stanislaus College Stage Public Program; Awards Given</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0818</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0818.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-07-08">July 8, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">STUDENTS OF ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE STAGE PUBLIC PROGRAM; AWARDS GIVEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although heavy rain and stormy skies prevailed throughout the day yesterday, the program staged by the students of St. Stanislaus College [now Weber High School] was a success. A capacity crowd attended.</p>
   <p>Because of the inclement weather, the program had a late start, causing some of the numbers to be dropped. The program was opened with the singing of "Dzwonek Maryi" (Mary's Bell). This was followed by an address by one of the students, Simon Zielinski, entitled "Knowledge and Work Enriches A Nation." His speech was short but to the point, and he was given a generous hand as he left the stand.</p>
   <p>A short play, depicting a historic event during the times of Kosciusko, was enacted by a group of students, including J. Sobieszczyk, J. Mucha, A. Kalinowski, and others. When the curtain was dropped on this <pb facs="5423968_5_0819.jpg" n="2"/>presentation, the continuous applause delayed the program somewhat; because of lack of time the players could not oblige with an encore.</p>
   <p>Songs by the following students greatly pleased the audience: J. Mucha, F. Ostrowski, M. Macy and J. Nagorznik. This group also sang "Gdzie Domek Moj" (Where Is My Home).</p>
   <p>A violin solo by F. Kostka, who played "Kujawiak" (a typical Polish dance), was one of the highlights of the musical part on the program. He was accompanied on the piano by S. Szwajkart.</p>
   <p>F. Rekosiak gave a speech in English, and W. Tomaszewski presented a beautiful monologue. English songs by the College choir closed the regular program.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, <pb facs="5423968_5_0820.jpg" n="3"/>presented awards to the outstanding students of each class of the College.</p>
   <p>Many persons from adjoining neighborhoods were in the audience.</p>
   <p>The singing of the Polish national anthem, "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), terminated the exercises.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
