<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-21">Nov. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal Concerning Photographs for the Lwow Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-21">Nov. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL CONCERNING PHOTOGRAPHS FOR THE LWOW EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since a greater portion of the exhibit in the Polish-American pavilion at Lwow will consist of photographs of churches, schools, society groups, insignias, and so on, the Central Committee in charge of Polish-American participation in the Lwow Exposition wishes to assist the parishes, societies, and private individuals in preparing these photographs by offering a few pertinent suggestions.</p>
   <p>A special committee, whose assignment it is to take charge of this matter, after communicating with photographers in Chicago, has this to report:</p>
   <p>Of the photographs of churches, schools, societies, and so forth, the Central Committee intends to make a series of albums for display at the Polish-American pavilion. These albums will give a conception of our work as a whole. For such albums, the photographs should all be of the same size. After consultation with the photographers, it was decided that the photographs be eleven by fourteen inches, and the mounting, fourteen by seventeen inches. We request that all <pb facs="5423968_5_1369.jpg" n="2"/>photographs be made in this size, that is, all those that are to be included in the albums. It is left, however, entirely to the individuals, parishes, schools, or societies, to prepare photographs of larger or smaller sizes and, in general, to arrange their exhibits according to their own tastes, but naturally such exhibits cannot be included in the general albums. In addition, the Central Committee reserves the right to evaluate the photographs submitted and to reject such as are badly executed or otherwise not suitable. All photographs must be submitted to the Central Committee not later than January 5, 1894, in order that they may be properly arranged, bound, and sent to Europe. Photographs are to be sent to the Central Committee (141-143 West Division Street), or to the persons in charge of separate sections. Finally, they must be well packed (not rolled) to prevent damage in shipment.</p>
   <p>We ask that photographs be taken as soon as possible, for in a short time weather conditions will make this difficult, if not impossible.</p>
   <p>As to the condition for making photographs and the cost of such, the special <pb facs="5423968_5_1370.jpg" n="3"/>committee has consulted Polish photographers in Chicago, and will supply information and suggestions on request. Requests should be addressed to the undersigned.</p>
   <p>In behalf of the special committee,</p>
   <p>Henry Nagiel,</p>
   <p>141-143 West Division Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
