<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 35,
<date when="1889-08-28">Aug. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">American News - World Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 35,
<date when="1889-08-28">Aug. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN NEWS - WORLD EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no doubt whatsoever that this exposition is to be held here in Chicago in the year 1892, in honor of the 400th anniversary of the discovery of America by Christopher Columbus.</p>
   <p>As soon as there occurred an idea of holding a fair for this occasion, there began a scramble among various cities to receive this honor. Especially cities such as Washington, New York and Chicago, but our city showed its quickness and readiness to meet this event with the aid of the representatives of Congress, who will unanimously vote for Chicago. A large committee has already been selected and is composed of the most prominent known people in the state, who immediately went to work energetically on this affair. From among the Poles selected for this committee were citizen Peter Kiolbasa and Zbikniew Brodowski, an editor. Mr. Brodowski first heard about his nomination for the committee from the papers. Probably if he had known of this before he was selected, he would <pb facs="5423968_5_1670.jpg" n="2"/>perhaps have refused this honor and placed his position upon someone else, because it requires money to work on this committee, as his salary is small working as an editor for a Polish newspaper. But he eventually accepted this position and will do the best he can, because he does not care to prejudice the Polish name in any way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
