<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. II, No. 13,
<date when="1892-03-30">March 30, 1892</date><title level="a">To the Lovers of Singing and Music</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0830</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0830.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. II, No. 13,
<date when="1892-03-30">March 30, 1892</date><title level="a">TO THE LOVERS OF SINGING AND MUSIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear lovers of singing: Wishing you would all belong to the singing organization Chopin, located in Chicago, the choir and organization of Polish Singers in America! Be kind and partake in the lessons in singing, Tuesday evenings, 8 to 9 P. M., at the hall of Mr. T. Nalepinski, Chapin and Noble streets. You people have now the best possibility to learn and train your voices with the help and support of the Polish Singers' Organization of America.</p>
   <p>After all, the parents should take the responsibility in urging their sons who have reached 17 years to belong to such a useful institution, such as this organization of singing. It is a noble and useful work given to the reviving and elevating of Polish songs.</p>
   <p>From the sort of youth who interests himself heart and soul in Polish songs, we shall have real Poles and citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0831.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So I urge and beg the directors of all various organized Polish choirs in America that they should care to devote their time in uplifting the art of singing in the same manner. By working together we have already enriched ourselves with our songs and music.</p>
   <p>God gave us, even here in America, such famous people in the field of art as our fellow composers and Polish artists doctor of music Anthony Kontski, Buffalo, N. Y.; and Professor Titus Ernesti, of Utica, N. Y. These artists composed a very remarkable cantata for the 100th anniversary of the constitution of May 3, 1791, in Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
