<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-11">Sept. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Mass Meeting Held in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-11">Sept. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY MASS MEETING HELD IN ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At four o'clock yesterday afternoon (Sunday), a Polish Day mass meeting was held in the St. Stanislaus Kostka School Hall. A great many Poles were present at the meeting, which was opened by Judge [M. A.] La Buy. The Judge's short speech dealt with the need for a Polish Day celebration and the steps that have already been taken toward it. The Reverend Vincent Barzynski was called upon to preside, Judge La Buy acting as secretary. Presidents of societies were invited to the platform.</p>
   <p>After a short address, Father Barzynski called upon H. Nagiel to explain what is required from members of societies participating in the celebration. Nagiel explained that each member must pay fifteen cents to the Central Committee. Each society, collaborating with others in its community, is expected to pay for the bands that will march in the parade. He asked that all <pb facs="5423968_5_1488.jpg" n="2"/>societies which have already decided to participate appropriate fifteen cents per member from their treasuries. The following societies agreed: The Holy Name of Jesus Society (280 members), Polish Queen's Guard (20 members, for whom three dollars was paid to the secretary immediately), St. Stanislaus Kostka Society (more than 200 members), St. John Baptist Society (200 members), Heart of Jesus Society I (over 100 members), St. Cecelia Society (216 members), St. Hedwig's Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish (100 members), Society of St. Anthony (about 60 members), Society of St. Adalbert, Bishop and Martyr (about 140 members), King Jagello Society (66 members), St. Joseph Society (about 100 members), and the Holy Cross Society (about 125 members).</p>
   <p>In addition to these, representatives of the following societies agreed to bring the matter up at their meetings:</p>
   <p>Society of the Apostles Peter and Paul (about 110 members), St. Michael Archangel Society (about 140 members), Holy Trinity Society (about 300 members), <pb facs="5423968_5_1489.jpg" n="3"/>and the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish choir (55 members).</p>
   <p>Thus, sixteen societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish have signified the intention of about 2,253 members to march in the parade, for whom over three hundred dollars will be paid to the Central Committee's treasury.</p>
   <p>Proceeding to further business of the meeting, it was decided to call a meeting of society presidents to discuss the question of bands, the parade itself, etc. The meeting will be held on Friday, September 15, at one of the school halls.</p>
   <p>F. Wleklinski, treasurer of the businessmen's committee of this community, announced that he has in hand some four hundred dollars in donations toward the Polish Day celebration. Together with the donations not yet turned in by the collectors, but already advertised in Dziennik Chicagoski, the total sum amounts to more than five hundred dollars. A collectors' meeting will <pb facs="5423968_5_1490.jpg" n="4"/>be held on September 13, at which all money is to be turned in to the treasurer. It was decided that the parish shall use this money to furnish two floats for the parade (in addition to the floats to be furnished by the Patriotic Organization and the clergy). A committee of nine was appointed to take charge of the matter. The chairman of the meeting, Father Barzynski, named the committee as follows: N. Nagiel, B. Klarkowski, A. W. Rudnicki, J. Mucha, J. Tomaszewski, W. Jedrzejak, S. Zahajkiewicz, F. Zagrzebski, and J. Gniot. The committee will hold its first meeting on Tuesday.</p>
   <p>It was also decided to appoint a committee to direct Polish Day activities in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. Father Barzynski accepted the chairmanship of this committee; B. Klarkowski will be its secretary. A treasurer will be appointed at Friday's meeting. The meeting was adjourned after the discussion of a few matters of lesser importance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
