<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-16">Apr. 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Bulletproof Vest Undergoes Further Tests</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-16">Apr. 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">BULLETPROOF VEST UNDERGOES FURTHER TESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Further tests of Brother Casimir Zegan's bulletproof vest were started the day before yesterday, at a wooded site on Lake Michigan, near Evanston. This vest is being tested for its merits under a succession of rifle salvos. The value of Brother Zeglen's invention was recognized by Stanislaus Korwin Sarnecki, lieutenant of the seventh regiment of Austrian Uhlans at Lwow, who has been visiting Chicago on a furlough and is very interested in this unusual vest.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sarnecki possesses a rifle that is by no means inferior to the German or Austrian army rifles. He placed the bulletproof material on a board, one inch thick. This board was to be used as a target. The material, one inch thick and one foot square, was attached firmly to the board. In order that the construction of the bulletproof material would not be revealed it was covered with white silk.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The marksman took his position one hundred and fifty yards from the target and began firing. Each rifle bullet stuck in the material and did not penetrate the wood, and only slight indentions were noticed. Revolver bullets bounced off the target like beans off a wall. Several police officers were present to view this unusual demonstration. Mr. Sarnecki is convinced that at one thousand yards, at which range bullets from the improved rifles have caused fatal wounds, the bullets would be repelled by the bulletproof material, as they were today when the largest caliber revolver was used. The lieutenant of the Austrian Uhlans is going to test the material draped over dead horses and the final test will be on live horses.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt there are still imperfections in Brother Zeglen's bulletproof material. The reasons for this are obvious. It is made by hand and not by machine. If the material was of uniform thickness its durability would be greatly increased. Mr. Sarnecki is of the opinion that the Austrian Government will undoubtedly take over Brother Zegler's invention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0222.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Results of the tests were publicized in the American and German press and as much space was devoted to Mr. Sarnecki as to Brother Zeglen. Many of the statements made were contrary to the facts. The invention is the personal property of Brother Casimir Zeglen. Mr. Sarnecki is only acting in the capacity of expert and instructor, and he eagerly desires to see this invention perfected to such an extent that it may be used on a large scale for practical purposes. He would also like to see our compatriot get a profitable return for his efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
