<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-14">Sept. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Saint John Cantius Parish Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-14">Sept. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">THE SAINT JOHN CANTIUS PARISH FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been asked to publish the following announcement:</p>
   <p>"Those desiring to enjoy themselves should come to the Saint John Cantius Parish fair for the benefit of the parochial school.</p>
   <p>"There will be good music.</p>
   <p>"Among the gifts offered at the fair, there is a picture of the Black Virgin of Czestochowa, donated by the Women's Rosary Sodality of Saint Stanislaus Kostka Parish. The picture which is valued at two hundred dollars, will be raffled by the Women's Rosary sodalities of Saint Stanislaus Kostka and Saint John Cantius parishes. The sodalities will have their own boxes, into which the raffle tickets will be deposited. At the closing of the fair, the boxes will be opened and the name of the winner will be announced.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The Saint John Cantius Society will also have a very pleasant entertainment.</p>
   <p>"Every society will have a collection box at the fair, and every member should see to it that his or her society deposits the largest amount.</p>
   <p>"The society with the largest amount in its collection box will be rewarded with a beautiful cross carved by Mr. Jaworowski, well-known sculptor. This cross will be a nice souvenir of the first saint John Cantius Parish fair for the benefit of the parochial school. Should the question arise as to which societies cared for the development of this parish, the name of the winner will come to the force.</p>
   <p>"Every society may try to have this honor, but only one will gain it. Among other prizes offered at the fair, there are pictures of Saint John Cantius, patron saint of our parish. Every member of the parish should possess this picture, which, if secured at the fair will be a cherished souvenir.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1327.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In fact, any object won at the first fair of Saint John Cantius Parish will be a valuable souvenir for the parishioners.</p>
   <p>Reverend John Kasprzycki, C.R"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
