<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"The Sidewalks of Chicago"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Followers of Dramatic Art Give Poor Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"THE SIDEWALKS OF CHICAGO"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Followers of Dramatic Art Give Poor Performance</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening the Followers of Dramatic Art presented a three-act play, entitled "The Sidewalks of Chicago," at Walsh's hall.</p>
   <p>The title is appropriate to the theme of the play, which shows all the tricks and humbug which one finds only on the streets of Chicago. One after another there appear all sorts of exploiters, who manage to extort the hard-earned money of ignorant Polish peasants in a truly shameful and disgraceful manner.</p>
   <p>We see first the Jewish tradesman who has every kind of merchandise for sale; then an agent peddling miraculous books, a quack who knows all diseases and who has miraculous cures, gypsies who coax large sums of money out of the unintelligent people, and other personages whose aim is to extort money from Polish peasants. A whole gang of such cheats runs loose among our people, which fall an easy prey to their wiles. Men, women, young girls, and boys--all <pb facs="5423968_5_0883.jpg" n="2"/>hand over their hard-earned money to Jews and gypsies. Finally one person appears who calls the attention of the police to the criminal practices of these cheats. The malefactors go to prison, and the people lead happy lives because there no longer is anyone about to cheat them.</p>
   <p>The author's purpose was to warn the Polish people against cheats. For this reason it is too bad that so few people came to see the performance.</p>
   <p>As for the play itself, it was poorly acted. Mrs. Gutowski and Mrs. Rzepczynski were the only ones who gave even a passable performance. The other "followers of dramatic art" revealed nothing praiseworthy. Their acting showed at once that they had made no attempt to learn their lines, and to tell the truth they didn't act as if they knew them at all. Their actions on the stage were such as to make one believe that these were people who had never even seen a stage performance, and not "followers of dramatic art," as they consider themselves.</p>
   <p>Even the performance itself did not get by without a brawl, which the police <pb facs="5423968_5_0884.jpg" n="3"/>had to quiet.</p>
   <p>And all of this took place on "The Sidewalks of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
