<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-21">July 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Development of Polish Business in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">S. W. Siwicki and Company, Commission Merchants [Polish Commission Company]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-21">July 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOPMENT OF POLISH BUSINESS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">S. W. Siwicki and Company, Commission Merchants [Polish Commission Company]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In previous issues of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, we have written of the Polish moving picture company and the Polish dairy corporation, sole Polish business enterprises of their kind in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Today we are writing of the Polish Commission Company, located at 915 West Randolph Street. Our reporter visited the building personally, and saw the work that is being done there and the products that are offered for sale. Anthony Stefanski, manager and principal stockholder of the firm, an alert and energetic man, gave our reporter the desired information as to the invested and operating capital of the firm.</p>
   <p>The Polish Commission Company was incorporated, in accordance with the state laws, for the sum of $10,500, three years ago. Since that time, it has had <pb facs="5423968_5_0037.jpg" n="2"/>to compete with similar enterprises owned by Jews....The Polish Commission Company, however, proved itself too strong for their treachery. During the whole three years, it has crept slowly but steadily forward, bringing to naught the efforts of its competitors.</p>
   <p>Today, the corporation's assets amount to $15,000. It employs eleven people, including four salesmen and a chauffeur. The weekly volume of business, according to Stefanski, totals from five to six thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>More than one will say that there must be some secret reason why, despite such strong competition, the Polish Commission Company has continued to develop and to gain more and more customers, more and more confidence among people of other nationalities as well as among the Poles. The secret lies in the fact that the Polish Commission Company always has better products than its neighboring Jewish firms, and sells these products at a moderate price, treating its customers more intelligently than they are treated by other firms. Courtesy is an inherent virtue among Poles. Tradesmen value <pb facs="5423968_5_0038.jpg" n="3"/>courtesy, and so deal with the Polish firm rather than with Jews.</p>
   <p>The Polish Commission Company always has in stock fresh butter, eggs, smoked fish, vegetables, fruits, potatoes, and other foodstuffs. It sells these products wholesale to grocers and retail to individual customers. Whoever may have visited the Company's store will certainly have noticed that everything is kept in exemplary order.</p>
   <p>As we are told by one of the stockholders, farmers from the vicinity of Chicago send their produce through the Polish Commission Company, paying a commission to the Company on everything that is sold.</p>
   <p>"I do not know," said the stockholder, "whether the Polish farmers in general know of our firm. If we can help farmers of other nationalities sell their eggs, cheese, butter, potatoes, fruit, and other produce, we would certainly be the more willing to do the same for Polish farmers. We are chiefly concerned that Polish business and industry should always and everywhere be <pb facs="5423968_5_0039.jpg" n="4"/>in the lead."</p>
   <p>The above words can best introduce the firm to Polish farmers scattered throughout this part of the country.</p>
   <p>Space does not permit us to describe more broadly this sole Polish firm of its kind, so worthy of support. We recommend that our readers remember it.</p>
   <p>Whoever desires to visit the Polish Commission Company can do so at any time, and will be graciously received by Stefarski, the manager.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
