<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-30">Aug. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Concert of Pola Czechowice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-30">Aug. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT OF POLA CZECHOWICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A splendid concert will be held September 6th, 1912, at 7:30 P.M. at Schoenhofen Hall. Many prominent and talented artists of Chicago will participate in that concert. The daughter of Mr. Simon J. Czechowicz, Secretary General of the Polish National Alliance, Miss Pola Czechowicz, a young talented pianist, will make her debut.</p>
   <p>This concert is arranged by the Women's Division of the Polish National Alliance, and the proceeds are to be turned over to the Polish National Alliance College fund, at Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>Even though Miss Pola Czechowicz is very young, she shows very much promise in musical qualifications and talent, which will put her among the leaders of the many Polish Chicago Artists.</p>
   <p>Miss Pola Czechowicz, is a pupil of Dr. Anna Nyczolkowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0684.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program of the evening will consist of various selections.</p>
   <p>Beside Miss Pola Czechowicz many other prominent Polish Chicago artists will appear on this splendid program.</p>
   <p>Miss Jadwiga Smulska, who is known throughout the United States among the Polish element as the "Chicago Nightingale," will make her appearance at this concert, and will render a beautiful Polish Song.</p>
   <p>Another artist of Chicago, who is well known, Miss Augustynowicz, will play the piano.</p>
   <p>Miss Constance Krenz, who has just returned from a successful stage tour of the European countries, will make her first appearance since her return. She will play the violin and will surely hold the audience spellbound.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0685.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many choirs of the Polish organizations of Chicago will combine to sing a few Polish folk songs.</p>
   <p>Knowing that the purpose of this concert is for the benefit of the Polish National Alliance College at Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania, we assume, that our Polish element will support such a beautiful program, and that the public as a whole will assemble on this evening at Schoenhofen Hall to hear some good music and singing.</p>
   <p>This is our belief.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
