<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-11">Oct. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Fair at St. Stanislaus Kostka's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-11">Oct. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">FAIR AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Church and Parish committees of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish was held at the church rectory, Sunday, October 9, at 4 P. M. During the course of the session it was agreed to hold a fair on the church grounds for the purpose of raising funds to complete the new church tower and build a stone sidewalk and stairs in front of the church.</p>
   <p>In connection with the fair it was also agreed to hold a lottery, which will help to raise funds for the proposed improvements. This lottery, along with the fair, will open Saturday evening, October 22, and will continue for two weeks, except Fridays and days of inclement weather.</p>
   <p>The following committees were chosen to assist in this work:</p>
   <p>1. The Management Committee, which will assist Reverend Vincent Barzynski, is as follows: T. Krolik, A. Rudnicki, J. Paszkiewicz, J. Mucha, Aug. Kowalski, <pb facs="5423968_5_1659.jpg" n="2"/>F. Wleklinski, P. Ratkowski, and J. Laska.</p>
   <p>2. The Financial Committee is composed of the following: John Maca, A. Rudnicki, Paul Ratkowski, J. Lamczyk, Louis Biadaszkiewicz, and T. Ostrowski.</p>
   <p>3. The Prize Committee, besides Reverend Barzynski, is made up of the following parishioners: Aug. Kowalski, F. Wleklinski, J. Kolodziejski, and T. Krolik.</p>
   <p>4. The Cigar Committee is as follows: F. Kaczmarek, A. Rudnicki, and F. Maca.</p>
   <p>5. The Music Committee: Jacob Mucha, F. Kosnowski, and J. Walkowiak.</p>
   <p>6. Buffet and Table Committee: J. Paszkiewicz, J. Kortas, J. Arkuszewski, W. Jedrzejek, Aug. Kowalski, A. Szule, and F. Wleklinski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
