<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-12">Mar. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Amateur Theatricals by St. Innocent's Parish Group</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-12">Mar. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AMATEUR THEATRICALS BY ST. INNOCENT'S PARISH GROUP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at the Polish Women's Alliance Building, the amateur circle Wolna Polska (Free Poland) staged an unusually charming light comedy in three acts, with songs, written by Mr. F. N. Kamienski and entitled "Skalmicrzanki" (The Women of Skalmierzyce.)</p>
   <p>The play, as a whole, considering that it was an amateur performance, came out rather well, although there were many shortcomings of the sort which it is practically impossible to avoid in amateur performances.</p>
   <p>Miss S. Pieknik was excellent in the role of Dozia. Throughout the entire play she gave a true picture of the perversity of a woman who is willing to give up everything for social prestige and wealth. She was ably supported by Mr. J. Mogalski in the role of Pieprzyk, a young potter, who had an excellent conception of his part and, what is most important, possesses a rather good voice, so that Pieprzyk's songs were enjoyed by all. Mr. J. Bryl played the part of <pb facs="5423968_5_0886.jpg" n="2"/>"Count Zuroslaw" equally well. Mr. J. Anton, in the role of Schoolmaster Kwik, was not bad, although toward the end of the play, having nothing more to say, he interfered too much with the others on the stage. The part of Countess Wanda would have been better if the one who played it, Mrs. Z. Leszczynski, had displayed more life and energy. Mr. Babiarz was not bad in the role of Sapibrzuch the Steward, though his continual clasping and reclasping of his hands had no purpose in the play, and a certain part of his wardrobe was utterly out of place and only made him a laughingstock. Miss. J. Chromicz was not bad in the role of Marcinowa Grupiatka, although her characterization was not successful, and her sable Zupan [a garment of the Polish national dress] in the first act was hardly appropriate for a peasant woman. Mr. J. Walas, in the role of Colonel Sarmacki, would have been all right were it not for his monotonous repetition of "bombs and grenades," which bored the audience. The rest of the minor parts, as well as the choral numbers, came out well. Despite the above-mentioned deficiencies, the play as a whole was good and the audience applauded enthusiastically. Miss S. Pieknik received a bouquet of flowers for her good <pb facs="5423968_5_0887.jpg" n="3"/>performance.</p>
   <p>It is deplorable that our ladies take their infants along with them to these performances. They not only spoil the acting of the amateurs but disturb the audience as well. Yesterday's music, both as to the songs in the play and the musical numbers during the intermissions, deserves recognition. It is a long time since we have seen a group so well harmonized as this one headed by Messrs. F. Przybylski, E. Krotochwila, and B. Wroclawski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
