<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-15">Feb. 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">St. Casimir Young Men's Society Marks its Tenth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-15">Feb. 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ST. CASIMIR YOUNG MEN'S SOCIETY MARKS ITS TENTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special program marking the tenth anniversary of the St. Casimir Young Men's Society was presented to the public yesterday at the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish school hall. The large hall was filled to capacity when B. Klarkowski, chairman of the program, made the introductory speech. Speeches were also made by John Nering, president of the society, John F. Smulski, and the Reverend Francis Gordon.</p>
   <p>The contents of the speeches will not be mentioned in view of the promise made by the recording secretary, Leon M. Szopinski, that the full text of each will be sent to the editorial department of the Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>It would be difficult to write about the declamation presented by Miss R. Gorzynska, for her recitation of Sewerina Duchinska's patriotic poem "Jeszcze <pb facs="5423968_5_0956.jpg" n="2"/>Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland Is Not Yet Lost) was nothing short of perfection.</p>
   <p>The songs of the St. Cecilia Men's Choir were appropriate to the occasion. The numbers were especially prepared for the celebrants by F. Nowicki, and his orchestra supplied the accompaniment.</p>
   <p>W. Barwig swept the audience back to the fatherland with his rendition of an aria from Moniuszko's immortal opera "Halka".</p>
   <p>The members of the St. Casimir Young Men's Society presented a short skit, "Gramatyka" (Grammar), by S. Kozmian. Messrs. August C. Klafta. Vincent J. Jozwiakowski, Jacob Oszwaldowski, Anthony Barwig, and Mrs. Anna Jozwiakowska took part in this comedy. The response from the audience was gratifying to the players.</p>
   <p>The entire program staged by this society was enjoyed by the large audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is hoped that this group will continue its fine work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
