<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-28">Aug. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day at the World War Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-28">Aug. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY AT THE WORLD WAR EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All Poles are urged to purchase their tickets for the Polish Day at the World War Exhibition to be held on Sunday, September 15, 1918. A special price of twenty-five cents per person will be offered as an inducement to purchase the tickets early. This price will prevail until Monday, September 2, 1918. After that the price will be fifty cents per ticket. Our people are urged, therefore, to purchase their tickets this week and to buy them from places approved by the Polish Day committee. By doing so the Poles will receive credit for their efforts. Tickets may be purchased in the offices of the following Polish organizations: the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish Women's Alliance, the Polish Alma Mater, and the Polish Falcons' Alliance; [they are also on sale] in the offices of every Polish newspaper, at the local Polish church rectories and in their parish offices, at the central recruiting offices of the Polish army, at every Polish bank, and at <pb facs="5423968_5_1160.jpg" n="2"/>[the offices of] all Polish building and loan associations.</p>
   <p>These are the things of interest that one will be able to see at the Exhibition:</p>
   <p>1. Thirty trainloads of spoils of war, including such pieces as battleship guns, field-artillery cannons, bombs, machine guns, aeroplanes, submarines--in short, every type of war implement. Some of these are those confiscated from the German forces, and others are those used by the Allied armies.</p>
   <p>2. War trenches--an exact replica of front battle lines. These are planned and constructed by officers and soldiers who have built trenches on the battle fields.</p>
   <p>3. No Man's Land--just as it appears to our fighting boys. It includes a reproduction of craters formed by exploding shells and awe-inspiring cannons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1161.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. Army Camps--in which are presented the methods of training recruits into brave tamers of the wild Teutonic hordes.</p>
   <p>5. Moving pictures--official photographs taken by the American Government and by the Allied nations, showing land and sea forces in drills and in battles and army life.</p>
   <p>6. Sea maneuvers of the American fleet on the Great Lakes--a reproduction of a sea battle, bombing, laying of mines, and shooting of torpedoes, defense against marauding submarines, and sending of signals at night.</p>
   <p>7. Air maneuvers--by American and British air squadrons; anti-aircraft batteries, signals, air battles, observations, and photographing from aeroplanes.</p>
   <p>8. Exhibition from the Department of Ship Construction--food control and <pb facs="5423968_5_1162.jpg" n="4"/>the activities of the Red Cross, the Knights of Columbus, and other humanitarian organizations.</p>
   <p>9. Military and marine bands--songs by choruses of all the nationalities residing in Chicago.</p>
   <p>An appeal is hereby made to all right-thinking Poles to demonstrate our numerical strength. Let our people again prove our loyalty toward the great American Republic. Let all Poles be present at the Polish Day of the World War Exhibition on Sunday, September 15, 1918.</p>
   <p>Let us therefore purchase the tickets from the Polish committee now, while they are available at the special price of twenty-five cents.</p>
   <p>Further information on the Polish Day may be obtained from the secretary of the committee at the main headquarters, located in the Northwestern Trust and <pb facs="5423968_5_1163.jpg" n="5"/>Savings Bank at 1201 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Judge Edmund Jarecki, chairman</p>
   <p>Alderman S. Adamkiewicz, vice-chairman</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. Korzeniewska, vice-chairwoman</p>
   <p>Paul Drzymalski, treasurer</p>
   <p>Vincent Jozwiakowski, secretary</p>
   <p>Phillip M. Ksycki</p>
   <p>Joseph Zientek</p>
   <p>A. F. Soska</p>
   <p>Mary Sakowska</p>
   <p>Dr. W. A. Kuflewski</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1164.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Valentine Slosarczyk</p>
   <p>Antoinette Baranowska</p>
   <p>Committee in Charge</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
