<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-03">July 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Brother Zeglen's Bullet-Proof Material Tested at Chicago College of Dental Surgery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0214</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0214.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-03">July 3, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">BROTHER ZEGLEN'S BULLET-PROOF MATERIAL TESTED AT CHICAGO COLLEGE OF DENTAL SURGERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brother Zeglen's bullet-proof material was tested last night before a body of professors, officials of the Humane Society, the chief of police, and some newspapermen at the Chicago College of Dental Surgery.</p>
   <p>This test had an educational character and was conducted by Dr. L. Borland. A cadaver was employed for the experiment. It was set up against a wall of boards, and only the part that was covered with the bullet-proof material was exposed, that is, the breast. Stanislaus Sarnecki fired six shots at the target.</p>
   <p>The first two shots were fired from a .38-caliber gun at twenty-four feet, and the bullets were found imbedded behind the top covering of the material which was used to conceal the workmanship of the secret material. Two shots were also fired from the same gun at sixteen and eight feet. Dr. Borland <pb facs="5423968_5_0215.jpg" n="2"/>easily removed the imbedded bullets with his fingers. No mark of any kind was found on the body as a result of the firing.</p>
   <p>The bullet fired from the .38-caliber revolver, made of pressed lead and charged with an extra dose of smokeless powder, made a deep impression in the material; however, no marks were found on the body when it was carefully inspected.</p>
   <p>A .44--caliber revolver was also used. A bullet was fired from it at eight feet. Even this charge was not strong enough to penetrate the material, although the pressure broke one rib, according to a surgeon's diagnosis.</p>
   <p>These tests have demonstrated that the material affords perfect protection, for the heaviest bullets did not penetrate it or leave a bruise, nor will a blood clot form where the bullet strikes.</p>
   <p>Shots were also fired at a live dog which was covered with the same goods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0216.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A revolver used by the Chicago police force was used. Two shots were fired at five feet. At first the dog was covered with saddle-cloth and then with the bullet-proof material. A shot was fired while the dog was sitting. After the gun was discharged, the only reaction on the part of the dog was that of surprise; there was no indication that the animal had suffered any pain. The next shot was fired at the dog without the undercovering. This time he let out a yelp, as if a bee had landed on his nose, but soon afterwards he began to wag his tail. The onlookers were convinced that both shots had proved harmless. No bones were broken, nor was the dog's skin bruised.</p>
   <p>After the tests Dr. Borland and the professors of the Chicago College of Dental Surgery congratulated Brother Casimir Zeglen on his invention, which is of great significance. There is no doubt that the future tests on a live person will prove successful.</p>
   <p>This test is to take place next week. There will be no lack of volunteers for the test if Mr. Sarnecki is to do the shooting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
