<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-27">July 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Night Held at Municipal Pier Auditorium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-27">July 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NIGHT HELD AT MUNICIPAL PIER AUDITORIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish night was held yesterday evening at the Municipal Pier Auditorium. The great hall was filled to capacity, not with Polish people, one could say, but principally with Americans. It was a Polish evening, as was at any rate stated in the program, which was well executed throughout. However, we failed to notice the Polish flag among the Allied flags with which the hall was decorated. Why? We cannot see the reason for the omission. It had an unpleasant effect upon the Poles present, and even upon some Americans, for it looked as if the Poles did not have a flag of their own. We are convinced that had the committee in charge of the affair asked permission to display the Polish flag, it would not have been denied, since, after all, it was Polish night. The flags of all the Allied nations are displayed there permanently; there is no doubt that permission would have willingly been given for the use of the Polish flag on Polish night. In arranging Polish nights, concerts, or anything Polish, and especially when we appear before an audience of people of other nationalities, <pb facs="5423968_5_1175.jpg" n="2"/>we should arrange things to be typically Polish, so that everyone present should feel that it is Polish. Wherever any Polish affair is going on, our flag, as our national symbol, should be displayed.</p>
   <p>As we have already mentioned, the program was excellent, although, to tell the truth, there was too much dancing and not enough singing. Every number of the program was well prepared, and we believe that all who were present spent a most enjoyable evening that will long remain in their memories. There was not a single number on the program that did not have to be repeated, for after each number the audience applauded so thunderously that an encore was necessary. Only one song, a rearrangement of the Ukrainian song "Hulala," should have had no place on the program. It is unfortunate that we Poles cannot get along without such unnecessary and entirely gratuitous additions, which bring us nothing but discredit, as the singing of a made-over Ukrainian song, especially when we have so many beautiful Polish songs to choose from. We would not expect to hear Polish music during a Ukrainian night; on the contrary, there would be no lack <pb facs="5423968_5_1176.jpg" n="3"/>of such things as "Nie Budem Lachom Sluzyly" [We will not serve the Poles], or "Na Pochybel Lachom" [Destruction to the Poles].</p>
   <p>Let us hope that, in the future, this will not be repeated at Polish concerts --that is, if we are anxious that others should have a good opinion of us and know our Polish music.</p>
   <p>Let us love Polish music and art! Let us love our Polish flag with its white eagle!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
