<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 259,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Mrs. a Nering and the Development of Polish Songs in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 259,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MRS. A NERING AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF POLISH SONGS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The late Mrs. Agnes Nering was the most powerful lever in the development of Polish artistic life and song in Chicago. This talented artist was tireless in her efforts to organize singing groups. She never refused to participate in concerts or entertainments for charitable purposes. Her rich voice caught the attention of critics of English newspapers and the singer was urged to begin regular vocal studies.</p>
   <p>In order to complete her artistic education, she left for Europe, where she studied opera under some of the world renowned teachers, Schoen-Rene, Bellincioni and Loli Beeth. Thus endowed with the best of schooling, she made an artistic tour, visiting all the European capitals, appearing in London, Paris, Berlin, Vienna, Budapest, Milan, Rome, Naples, Venice, Cracow, Poznan, and Warsaw. Everywhere she met with great success to <pb facs="5423968_5_0389.jpg" n="2"/>which testify the praises of critics in all of the important European newspapers.</p>
   <p>She returned from abroad in 1914 as a famous songstress and from then on she enraptured the public with her voice and artistry, making appearances in all of the large cities throughout the United States.</p>
   <p>When upon her return from Europe she appeared in a concert at Orchestra Hall in Chicago, the public was enraptured to such a degree that she was showered with flowers, and the stage was transformed in one moment into a garden of flowers.</p>
   <p>Her concert in Orchestra Hall on January 18, 1914, was a really artistic entertainment. Mrs. Nering charmed the audience with the mellow tones of her soprano voice. She sang with great feeling the following Polish songs: "Ach Zejdz Do Gondoli" (Oh, come to the gondola), by John Gall;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0390.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Obawa" (Fear), by Wozela-Czynski; "Halka," by Moniuszko, and "Pamietam Zlote Dhie" (I remember golden days), by Karlowicz. The late Mrs. Nering sang Karlowicz's composition for the first time in America, and the music critics were enthralled by her singing. Felix Borowski, critic for the Record Herald, Published at that time, wrote: "Mrs. Nering deserves great credit for acquainting the Chicago public with the compositions that she sang. Mrs. Nering rendered all of these songs splendidly, especially the composition of M. Karlowicz, "Pamietam Zlote Dnie."</p>
   <p>The symphonic works of Karlowicz are of priceless value, wrote Borowski.</p>
   <p>At this concert also the Poles of Chicago greeted Agnes Nering with enthusiasm. The Polish colony in Chicago felt very proud that they had such a talented artist.</p>
   <p>Not only did we Chicagoans express our recognition, but the artist was well written up and praised by European critics also.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0391.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Before her arrival in America in 1914, Mrs. Nering gave a series of concerts in the larger cities of Europe. The critic of the Militaer-Musiker Zeitung wrote: "Mrs. Agnes Nering, Polish-American songstress, possesses a splendid power for voice. She masters with ease the most difficult parts."</p>
   <p>The same was repeated by other German newspapers, such as the Berliner Allgemeine Zeitung, Vossiche Zeitung, Berliner Tageblatt, and Der Musiksalon.</p>
   <p>Northwest Side Opera Company. Through the efforts of Mrs. Nering the Northwest Side Opera Company was organized in 1916. Mrs. Nering selected for her first presentation of opera the play "Stradella," by Flotow. Her intention was to present the opera with the cooperation of only Polish amateur singers, but this aim fell through on account of lack <pb facs="5423968_5_0392.jpg" n="5"/>of well schooled amateur singers. During that year the singing groups were good, but there was a complete lack of soloists. Mrs. Nering had to engage, therefore, those of other nationalities. The opera did not make a satisfactory impression. This was felt by the artist herself, and further appearances were abandoned. Her knowledge of what is art did not allow her to carry on any further attempts in this direction, so she devoted herself completely to concert appearances. Through her death recently, the Polish colony in Chicago has lost a great and worthy artist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
