<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 181,
<date when="1926-08-04">Aug. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Good Opportunity for Polish Youth Free Course of Study on How to Play Piano</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. VI, No. 181,
<date when="1926-08-04">Aug. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD OPPORTUNITY FOR POLISH YOUTH FREE COURSE OF STUDY ON HOW TO PLAY PIANO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well known school of music, the Gunn School of Music and Dramatic Art in Chicago, announces that Miss H. Glomska, teacher of that school, has determined to grant a free course of study on the piano during the season 1926-1927, comprising forty private lessons on how to play the piano to the boy or girl student of Polish descent, who, in a public examination demonstrates the most ability in piano playing. The one who wins that privilege will receive a double benefit - not only the study of piano under the direction of a highly capable instructor, but likewise, relations in the world of music which are given by such a well known school, and which is supported by great artists.</p>
   <p>Miss H. Glomska has worked herself up as a first-class artist in Chicago. She acquired her wide routine in a musical education under the direction of many of the most prominent and most skillful American teachers, including Leon Sowerby and Glen Dillard Gunn, the well known critic on music and distinguished pedagogue, also president of the above mentioned school. It is only proper to add that Miss Glomska has attended the Universities of Northwestern and Chicago, the Art Institute of Chicago, and is a graduate of the Chicago Normal College. She has also taught in the Medill High School, and at present is a teacher in the Lake <pb facs="5423968_5_0378.jpg" n="2"/>View High School; and in this capacity, she has directed many successful operatic presentations. As a result of such an extensive routine, she is unusually capable in the application of the scientific pedagogy of music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
