<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 188,
<date when="1922-08-12">Aug. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Concert of Miss A. Frankowska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 188,
<date when="1922-08-12">Aug. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT OF MISS A. FRANKOWSKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Antonina Frankowska belongs to those many Polish concert artists who already have won for themselves a wide circle of admirers and who, with their initial efforts, have come forth to a leading position. Miss Frankowska has distinguished herself in a series of former appearances, gaining the applause of both the Polish and American circles. Endowed with a beautiful dramatic soprano voice, she graduated with excellent marks from the Chicago Musical College, from which she finished during the past year. Everybody also remembers her appearance at the welcome of Mrs. Curie-Sklodowska, which was her great triumph.</p>
   <p>The news that Miss Frankowska is staging a concert personally, which will be a real entertainment in the way of song and music, has created a great sensation.</p>
   <p>This concert will be held Sunday, August 20th, at the Calumet Theatre in South Chicago. Her program will be composed of Polish songs, especially selections from the opera "Halka," then selections from Italian opera <pb facs="5423968_5_0404.jpg" n="2"/>and English songs with the accompaniment of the leader of the Calumet Theatre orchestra.</p>
   <p>Many prominent Polish and American artists are also taking part in the concert of Miss Frankowska and, above all, Olga Kochanska, wife of the well-known violinist virtuoso, who with the accompaniment of Mrs. Julius Smietanka, will play the violin. The program finally will be composed of a song by Louis Dubiza and a piano solo by Mr. Raymond C. Howe, who will endow the listeners with "Minuet," by Paderewski and "Evening," by Hunter.</p>
   <p>Miss Antonina Frankowska, very popular in both Polish and American circles in South Chicago, is a member of the St. Cecilia Choir and because she has taken a lively interest in everything which could be beneficial to the Polish cause, with her voice she formally enraptures her audience. Therefore, it is certain that her concert, scheduled for August 20th, will be an outstanding success; that it will bring together the ranks of music and song lovers, as well as those who wish to get <pb facs="5423968_5_0405.jpg" n="3"/>acquainted with the talent of Miss Frankowska, as hearing her sing is a real spiritual pleasure, and besides that, Miss Frankowska deserves the greatest support in every respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
