<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-07-03">July 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Polish University Club Honors Polish Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-07-03">July 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH UNIVERSITY CLUB HONORS POLISH STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first annual dinner of the Polish University Club was a huge success. It was given on Thursday, June 28th, at the City Club, in honor of the Polish graduates, class of 1928, and three eminent men, who were presented with the golden keys. A large number attended, also relatives and friends.</p>
   <p>The tables were arranged to form the letter E, symbolical of Education, for which the Polish - American student is ever striving.</p>
   <p>President Z. A. Czeslawski, master of ceremonies, requested Reverend J. Owczarek to offer the invocation. Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, President of the Great Lakes Insurance Co. was then introduced and he spoke in a jocular manner of the advantages which a toast-bearer has over the after dinner speaker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Czeslawski presented the honorary keys, while Mr. Pawloski read the resolutions which explained why the Polish University Club made these awards. The following men, well known in Polish-American circles and elsewhere, received the Golden Key: County Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, Collector of Customs, A. Czarnecki, and Professor M. S. Szymczak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1682.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Inspirational speeches were made by E. K. Jarecki, A. Czarnecki, Professor M. S. Szymczak, Dr. M. E. Urbanski and President Z. A. Czeslawski. The first four speakers texts were mainly concerned with the benefits derived from education, and the necessity of urging the Polish American students to continue with their scholastic efforts. Mr. Czeslawski outlined the purposes of the Polish University Club, and welcomed any suggestions which might be helpful to students attending universities.</p>
   <p>Musical diversion was provided by Mr. A. Kowalkowski, Violinist; Miss Wanda Swierczek, Pianist; Miss Marie Gruszczynski, Contralto; Miss Ella Kraft, Pianist; and Tenor A. Drozda. The entertainment was well received, and an ovation rewarded the artists.</p>
   <p>The success of the first annual dinner is partially due to the committee, which was composed of the following gentlemen: Henry Dankowski, Chairman; Henry Boris, Walter Kmieciak, Thaddeus Slisz, Thaddeus Szleszynski and Thomas Pawloski. The Polish University Club takes this opportunity to thank all those who attended the festival and whose co-operation made it possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
