<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Gold Mine in California</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH GOLD MINE IN CALIFORNIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two weeks ago, the Original Quartz Hill Gold Mining Company, a Polish corporation, delegated A. J. Kowalski, J. F. Smulski, and Dr. C. Midowicz to investigate the gold mine discovered by Mr. Modest Maryanski, a Polish engineer. This committee was authorized to hire a competent metallurgist for a thorough examination of the mine's possibilities. The task was entrusted to the mining engineer C. A. Luckhardt, who has had forty years experience in the California hills. His opinion is definitely authoritative. Mr. Luckhardt's report was completed Friday afternoon. The committee submitted its findings in the following telegram:</p>
   <p>"San Francisco, August 18.</p>
   <p>"Engineer Luckhardt's report confirms in full the report made by Mr. Modest Maryanski. Analyses were very carefully made. It is a wonderful investment. <pb facs="5423968_5_0305.jpg" n="2"/>Water is easily available for mining purposes. Exploitation cost will be small since the gold-bearing ore protrudes high above the ground. Collect necessary funds to meet first payment. Kowalski and Midowicz are returning to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Smulski, Kowalski, and Midowicz."</p>
   <p>Upon receipt of this important telegram, a director's meeting of the Corporation was called and the price of stock raised from twenty-five to forty dollars per share. This price will rise soon to its par value of one hundred dollars. Everyone who would like to invest in this enterprise should do so without delay.</p>
   <p>Thus, the Polish gold mine grows daily in importance. It is not a daydream nor a fantastic enterprise, but a solid and indubitable fact. In <pb facs="5423968_5_0306.jpg" n="3"/>support of Mr. Maryanski's opinion that the original capital will be returned as profit within a year's time, is the testimony of three of our well-known citizens, as eyewitnesses. Finally, we have the opinion of an expert, whose word is not to be doubted.</p>
   <p>In the face of this information, the Polish gold mine can be regarded as an established fact. To those who invest in it, the enterprise will undoubtedly be a veritable golden apple. Poles--we are certain--will take advantage of this wonderful chance to improve their material condition and to help establish a purely Polish enterprise. Investors ought to hurry in their own interests, for the time is short. The enterprise promises to be a very profitable one; let the profit be enjoyed by Polish people.</p>
   <p>Further details may be found in an advertisement in this paper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
