<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-13">July 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Original Quartz Hill Gold Mine</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-13">July 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORIGINAL QUARTZ HILL GOLD MINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great gold mine, known as the Original Quartz Hill Gold Mine, was discovered last year in Slasta County, California, by the mining engineer Modest Maryanski. According to the estimates of competent metallurgists, this mine contains an enormous quantity of gold ore, assuring great profits to those who invest in it; in all probability, the original capital will return as profit during the first year.</p>
   <p>For purposes of working this mine to its fullest possibilities, the Original Quartz Hill Gold Mining Company has been formed. This corporation received its charter from the State of Illinois on the seventh of this month, giving it the right to sell stock.</p>
   <p>Since a considerable portion of stock has already been sold, and since it is <pb facs="5423968_5_0310.jpg" n="2"/>desired that the remaining shares be distributed among Poles, our countrymen who wish to invest may apply to J. F. Smulski, secretary of the corporation, or to Judge M. A. La Buy, treasurer. The shares have a par value of one hundred dollars, while the price has been temporarily established at twenty five dollars a share.</p>
   <p>Whoever wishes to obtain shares at the above price must apply immediately, for the price will rise shortly. J. F. Smulski's address is 565 Noble Street; Judge La Buy's office is located at 581 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Board of Directors, Original Quartz Hill Gold Mining Company: E. Z. Brodowski, M. A. La Buy, Dr. K. Midowicz, Peter Kiolbassa, Victor Bardonski, Marion Durski, Modest Maryanski, Leon Szopinski, John F. Smulski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
