<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-08">Sept. 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Polish Organizations in Regard to Participation in the 1894 Kosciusko Exposition in Lwow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-08">Sept. 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO POLISH ORGANIZATIONS IN REGARD TO PARTICIPATION IN THE 1894 KOSCIUSKO EXPOSITION IN LWOW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great national exposition, an exposition showing Polish progress in industrial, agricultural, educational, and cultural lines, will be held at Lwow, one of the ancient capitals of Poland, in 1894. Held on the one-hundredth anniversary of the [third] partition of Poland, it will be a very appropriate manifestation--one worthy of our nation. The Lwow Exposition will include exhibits from Galicia, from other Polish provinces, and from abroad. The Polish element in France has expressed its intention of erecting a pavilion there, as has the Polish element in England, Switzerland, etc. Would it not be a disgrace to us if our Polish-American element--a million and a half strong, who have been called the fourth partition, of whose strength and energy so much has been said and written--were not represented?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Undoubtedly, yes. If we are not represented, it will be said of us that we are lost to Poland. Actually, we have lost practically none of our Polish characteristics; we have gained everything. We have kept our faith, and we have attained a certain measure of prosperity; we have retained our nationality, and have made substantial cultural gains. In the face of hundreds of obstacles, in spite of enormous difficulties, we have established our own churches, schools, national organizations, benefit societies, and press here in America. If we expect Poland to recognize and appreciate our work, we must show what we have done. An opportunity to do so is presented by the forthcoming Exposition at Lwow in 1894.</p>
   <p>Much has been said of the need for a closer relationship between ourselves and our motherland, of the necessity of acquainting our brethren in Poland with the fruits of our labor.....The great benefits of such a closer relationship are obvious. On the one hand, united in spirit with our homeland, we will remain Poles forever; on the other, our unhampered freedom of action may <pb facs="5423968_5_1494.jpg" n="3"/>enable us to render invaluable service to our homeland.</p>
   <p>An exceptionally good opportunity for improving relationships with our homeland presents itself now. The organizers of the Lwow Exposition have asked us to participate. They have said to us: "Come and show us that you are Poles!" They have even sent a delegate to consult with us on the matter. In truth, we have no industrial organization with which to astonish the world, but we have a religious, social, cultural, and national life. Let us show the proofs of it. Photographs of our churches and schools, the constitutions and records of our society, their insignia, uniforms, and banners, our school statistics and examples of the pupils' work, newspapers and books published here, theatrical show bills and programs--these are the proofs that will convince our brethren in Poland of our efforts, that we have not lost our national spirit, that the words of the song, "Poland is not lost," are buried deep within our hearts. In addition to all this, there will be a <pb facs="5423968_5_1495.jpg" n="4"/>few examples of our contributions to industry, which must be searched out and sent to the Exposition.</p>
   <p>We ought not to neglect this opportunity, since it is our sacred duty to inform our brethren of our strength and of our activities. Such a representation of our activities here will be, perhaps, the only bridge that can exist between Poland and America today. And if we can place our exhibit under the roof of a special pavilion, flying the Polish and American flags, then it will be clearly understood by everyone that we are a cultured and productive national entity.</p>
   <p>Polish-Americans should therefore participate in the Lwow Exposition. We ought to erect a pavilion that will fly two flags. It will mean to our brethren in Poland that we are alive and working, that we love our motherland, that we want to remain Poles. And so, when Professor Dunikowski, delegated by the directors of the Kosciusko Exposition to consult with us, called upon us for <pb facs="5423968_5_1496.jpg" n="5"/>co-operation in this matter, we the undersigned accepted the responsibilities imposed upon us and decided to devote all our efforts to making possible a Polish-American exhibit and pavilion. Understanding well, However, that such a thing as this can be accomplished only with the co-operation of everybody, we appeal for help to all of the Polish organizations in the United States. Material as well as moral support is necessary to bring this matter to a successful conclusion, and certain assessments will have to be levied on organization members.</p>
   <p>Polish-American participation in the Lwow Exposition is primarily a matter for Polish-American societies and organizations. It depends of these societies and organizations whether or not a Polish-American Pavilion will be erected, whether or not the Polish and American flags will fly in testimony of our work here and of our love for Poland. We appeal, then, for aid and support in this matter of great public interest and importance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1497.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We are confident that support to this national cause will not be denied.</p>
   <p>The Central Committee (for the entire United States): W. Smulski, president; Reverend Vincent Barzynski, S. Slominski, Peter Kiolbassa, vice-presidents; Leon Szopinski and Adam Szwajkart, secretaries; W. Bardonski, treasurer; and M. Drzemala, M. A. Labuy, Henry Nagiel, and Dr. C. Midowicz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
