<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-12">Aug. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Concert Sponsored by the Helen Modrzejewski Choir and Dramatic Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0686</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0686.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-08-12">Aug. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT SPONSORED BY THE HELEN MODRZEJEWSKI CHOIR AND DRAMATIC SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the Helen Modrzejewski Choir and Dramatic Society, held its annual concert and dance at Adam Mickiewicz hall, 3310 So. Morgan Street.</p>
   <p>The arrangement committee deserves much credit for making this beautiful and artistic concert a success. However, we regret to find it necessary to mention that the Poles of this district do not display enough interest in the songs of their native country.</p>
   <p>After the opening number, Paderewski's "Minuet," under the direction of J. Jokajtys, the concert was brilliantly under way.</p>
   <p>Moniuszko's Krakowiak was next on the program, and was sung by the Helen Modrzejewski choir. An outburst of applause then greeted the Filaret choir. This outburst of enthusiasm was not unmerited, and won the song "Zaby" by Kortabinski, directed by J. Jokajtys.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0687.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Because of another engagement, the Filaret choir was necessitated to sing "Hulaly," during the first part of the program instead of the second, as was previously planned. Mr. Wiszatycki, a member of the choir appeared as soloist in the operatic aria from Janka, he was very warmly applauded.</p>
   <p>Next on the program was the Wanda choir who sang Piesn Polska, (A Polish Song) under the direction of J. Jokajtys. Well deserved applause was given the Krakowiak and Krakowianek choir, directed by Professor J. Rybowiak.</p>
   <p>The next number on the program was a soprano solo by Miss E. Okon, who sang "Jeszcze Raz" (Once More) very beautifully. She was accompanied by Miss W. Czeslawski. The Dembinski choir followed with Co Piesn (Each Song), and was also directed by Professor J. Jokajtys. A duet by Miss E. Okon and Mrs. T. Dzwonkiewicz was next heard.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the choirs united in the song, "Duch Wojewody" (The Spirit of the Chieftain), under the direction of Professor J. Rybowiak. The audience remained after the concert to enjoy the dance which continued to <pb facs="5423968_5_0688.jpg" n="3"/>the early hours of the morning. Poles should, however, take more interest in these beautiful concerts which are conducted in the Polish language, and prove to other nations that Poles are abreast of the times in culture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
