<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-18">June 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the Play "Pan Geldhab"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-18">June 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PLAY "PAN GELDHAB"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The excellent comedy by Alexander Fredro, "Pan Geldhab," was presented last Saturday evening at the Polish Women's Alliance hall. The play was directed by the well-known amateur director, K. Wachtel. It must be admitted that he made every effort, and that the presentation was a splendid one, for in general the play was a success. Of course, there were shortcomings, but it is difficult to avoid these, in view of the fact that the actors were amateurs. In spite of everything, they played better than some professionals.</p>
   <p>Wachtel himself was excellent in the title role, and we are convinced that no one could have equalled him as Geldhab. He proved by his acting that he is an experienced amateur and that he possesses capabilities rarely found here in America. K. Kasperek was excellent in the role of the Major; he showed this time that he possesses real talent for the stage, and that he is constantly improving. His appearance as the Major was his best thus for. It must be admitted that either the role fitted him perfectly or that he fitted the <pb facs="5423968_5_0857.jpg" n="2"/>role.</p>
   <p>Miss Z. Jawdrowski played the feminine lead very well. As Flora, daughter of Geldhab, she had her better and her weaker moments, but, in general, her performance was good, revealing an understanding of the role to such an extent that, for an amateur performance, we might well say that it was perfect.</p>
   <p>J. Maciejewski, as the Prince, gave a fine performance. It could be seen that he was trying his best to do justice to so difficult a role as that of the stern, gouty old prince. Krzywonos also played quite well, but his stiffness kept him from being a good lover.</p>
   <p>Scholl, as "Lisiewicz," and Gorzynski, as "Piorko," turned in good performances. Gorzynski showed himself to be a good amateur who can improve with a little work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0858.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As a whole, the play was well done and, to all appearances, the audience was satisfied.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the public did not support the production as well as was to be expected, since the play was given for the benefit of the Polish boys in the American Army. What the reason for this was is difficult to guess. Admission may have been too high, or the weather too hot. To tell the truth, theatrical performances are not well attended during the warm summer months, but a play for so splendid a cause should have been better supported.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
