<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-17">Apr. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">[Poles Present "Chata Za Wsia"]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contribution)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-17">Apr. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">[POLES PRESENT "CHATA ZA WSIA"]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contribution)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday I went to Pulaski Hall, where the Polish drama "Chata Za Wsia" (Hut in the Village's Outskirts) was being staged. I went because I was eager to know how this beautiful play, which is so difficult to stage even for professional actors and which I nave seen many times in Warsaw, would come out.</p>
   <p>I must admit that I was astonished to see how well the play was staged, although in some parts it did not come out as it should because some of the artists were evidently tired out by the long play. I repeat, the whole came out splendidly.</p>
   <p>The principal scene represents a certain village in Podole, Poland, where a band of gypsies led by Aprasz (played by Chmielinski) and Queen Aza (played by Mrs. Rosa) arrives. One of the gypsies, the young and handsome Tumry (played by Chrzanowski), falls in love with Motuna, the daughter of Lepiuk, a peasant, <pb facs="5423968_5_1030.jpg" n="2"/>and deserts the band to remain in the village. As a result of this, the band becomes indignant and decides to leave. Aza, the queen of the gypsies, agrees to going away despite the fact that she loves Tumry. She imagines that she will forget him if they separate.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, Lepiuk (played by Wojnicki), who is descended from a gypsy family, finds out about the love affair between Tumry and his daughter Motuna (played by Mrs. Lande), opposes the union and decides to give his daughter in marriage to Kajtus the son of the village bailiff. Aware of his daughter's good nature and obedience, Lepiuk engages matchmakers and gives a party.</p>
   <p>The roles of the matchmakers--Skorobohaty and Hodylen--were played by Zolkowski and Polkowski. The role of Kajtus, the suitor, who was an accomplished idiot, was played by Chojnacki. This trio converted the second act into a perfect comedy, especially the intoxicated Hodylen and the idiotic Kajtus, who kept the auditence laughing continually. There was also the stupid Janko (played by J. F. Smulski), whose wit and irony and pretended stupidity not only carried out <pb facs="5423968_5_1031.jpg" n="3"/>the comical part of the play but pleased the audience to a great extent.</p>
   <p>P. Smulski (sic) played his role like an accomplished artist.</p>
   <p>Special mention should be made of the fine acting, especially in the third act, of Mrs. Zolkowski in the role of Jaga, the gypsy. All acting was very good, especially the parts played by A. Chrzanowski, Wojnicki, Smulski, Polkowski, Mrs. Lande, Mrs. Rosa, and [Mrs.] Kolaczynski. The excellent vocal solos by P. Darowski, as Jancz, and by Wilocki in the role of a Lyrist, and especially by Gatkowski in the role of Fedio also deserve attention. This singing, performed with comical rapture, created great enthusiasm. The choir also sang beautifully and harmoniously, for which credit should be given to Nowicki, the choir leader. The orchestra was excellent.</p>
   <p>There was also a Mazurka dance, not just an ordinary dance, but a dance of which even the Warsaw stage would have been proud. Wasilkowski was the leader of the Mazurka, and the dancers were Mrs. Dangiel, Mrs. Trzcinski, the Misses Waranko, <pb facs="5423968_5_1032.jpg" n="4"/><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Sosnowski. These dancers indeed deserved the great applause they received for this <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. There were also Hungarian and Spanish dances.</p>
   <p>For the success of this play we are <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to J. Mirski, the stage director.</p>
   <p>This play will be presented again next Sunday, April 22, at the Bradley Street hall, and the Polish public is cordially invited.</p>
   <p>The proceeds of this play will be turned over to the Polish Hospital.</p>
   <p>A Member of the Audience</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
