<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-01">June 1, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus Kostka Young Men's Society Stage  "Wicek I Wacek" at Polish Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0936</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0936.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-01">June 1, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA YOUNG MEN'S SOCIETY STAGE  "WICEK I WACEK" AT POLISH HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Wicek I Wacek" (Vince and Bill), a gay comedy with a moral, was staged by the St. Stanislaus Kostka Young Men's Society, on Sunday, May 30, at the Polish Hall, located at Bradley Street near Noble Street. Despite the excellent cast and play, a poor crowd attended. Those who failed to come missed an opportunity to see a stellar performance.</p>
   <p>Vince, played by V. J. Jozwiakowski, and Bill, enacted by August Klafta, could not have been interpreted better. Such well-seasoned actors could not be found on another stage. Both held the interest of the audience through the entire play.</p>
   <p>Other roles were played by S. Zahajkiewicz, Miss Pearl Krolik, Miss A. Bardonska, W. Wieckowski, J. Jarzembowski, A. Barwig, and Miss M. Bardonska.</p>
   <p>Scenery, production, and staging, was of the best, but it would have been better <pb facs="5423968_5_0937.jpg" n="2"/>if the director had been punctual. The audience sat ill at ease when the curtain did not go up at 8:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>During intermission and between the acts songs and piano solos added variety to the program. Two outstanding piano solos were rendered by Joseph Klass and John Tadelski, both students of the St. Stanislaus Kostka College. With more training in music they can easily become artists. The College Quartet was also admirable. Girl students also played numbers on the piano.</p>
   <p>The small audience can be accounted for, because many Polish organizations gave dances and socials that same evening. Perhaps it would be better to stage such plays during a weekday, and at least once a week.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
