<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-11">Oct. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Drill Contests Held at Stock Pavilion During Polish Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-11">Oct. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">DRILL CONTESTS HELD AT STOCK PAVILION DURING POLISH DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Casimir Zychlinski, secretary of the committee which judged the military and gymnastic drill contests held at the Stock Pavilion during Polish Day, presented his report to the [polish Day] Central Committee. The most important details were as follows:</p>
   <p>Due to the resignation of Captains Schmidt and Slupecki from the judges' committee, two new judges were appointed. The completed committee consisted of M. A. La Buy and C. Zychlinski, both of Chicago; Captain Anderson, of the United States Army, from Milwaukee; Major Patrzykowski, Major Monkiewicz, and Adjutant Smorowski, of Buffalo; Captains Szymanski and Koziczynski, and K. Witkowski, of South Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Polish Falcon Societies number one and number two, of Chicago, competed in the gymnastic contest. The award was easily won by the Polish Falcons Number One.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the second contest, the Cadets of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish competed against the Cadets of [South] Chicago. The judges awarded the prize to the St. Stanislaus Cadets, expressing a very high opinion of their abilities.</p>
   <p>The Uhlans of Town of Lake, both mounted and on foot; the Kosciusko Guard of Milwaukee; the Queen's Guard, of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish; the Knights of the Holy Virgin Mary and the Krakus Society, of South Chicago; and the Hussars of St. Martin, of St. Adalbert's Parish, competed in the military drill contest. First prize was awarded to the mounted Uhlans of Town of Lake.</p>
   <p>The contest committee's report was accepted by the Central Committee at yesterday's meeting. The Central Committee admitted, however, that a fourth award should be added to the original three--a gold medal for the best military drill on foot. The Committee will communicate with the <pb facs="5423968_5_1426.jpg" n="3"/>judges on this question. If the judges agree to this proposition, a fourth medal will be awarded in the near future. Announcement will be made [in Dziennik Chicagoski] in due time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
