<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-28">Mar. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles to Welcome Their Countrymen to Columbian Exposition</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Meeting to be Held at School Hall on April 3</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-28">Mar. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES TO WELCOME THEIR COUNTRYMEN TO COLUMBIAN EXPOSITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Meeting to be Held at School Hall on April 3</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following announcement was received for publication in Dziennik Chicagoski:</p>
   <p>"On May 1--scarcely a month from now--the World's Columbian Exposition will open in Chicago. Visitors will arrive in the city from all corners of the earth to view this magnificent display of human progress. Naturally, among the numerous visitors, we expect a great many Poles. They will be drawn here not only by a desire to see the Exposition, but also by a desire to become acquainted with their brethren, of whom 130,000 live in this city, third largest in the world in Polish population.</p>
   <p>"Our ancestors said, when a guest is in the house, God is in the house." In this free country, at least we can remember this beautiful saying, especially when we expect guests dear to our hearts. It is our duty to <pb facs="5423968_5_1639.jpg" n="2"/>show them that Polish hospitality exists here in America, that we know how to welcome them to the fullest extent of our means. True, we have no palaces or old Polish manors in which to receive them; however, this will not prevent us from making our countrymen's short stay on this soil as pleasant as possible.</p>
   <p>"But in order that this desire and intention of ours can be turned into a reality, it is high time a mutual understanding be reached. It is necessary, therefore, that the more prominent Poles of the city of Chicago get together for a conference on how to welcome our countrymen visiting the Exposition, how to make their stay a pleasant and easy one, and how to facilitate their fellowship with us. Thus, we invite all those to whom, as Poles, this matter lies close to their hearts, to a meeting at the school hall near Bradley Street at four o'clock in the afternoon on Monday, April 3 (Easter Monday). We hope to see as great a number of our respected countrymen as possible at this meeting."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1640.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Signed: Peter Kiolbassa, Stanley Kunz, A. Rudnicki, August J. Kowalski, Albert Jedrzejek, Z. Brodowski, Joseph Paszkiewicz, Andrew Kwasigroch, Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, John Kedziorski, B. Klarkowski, P. Ligman, Stanley Szwajkart, P. Ratkowski, Francis Zagrzebski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
