<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-21">Dec. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Vocal and Gymnastic Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-21">Dec. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">VOCAL AND GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the presence of hundreds of Falcons and guests a vocal and gymnastic exhibition was held yesterday at the Polish Women's Alliance building, sponsored by the Swiatkiewicz Group of the Alliance of Polish Falcons.</p>
   <p>The Falcons again displayed the progress of their work and proved unquestionably that they lead all the other Polish emigre's and that whatever they undertake they bring to a successful conclusion.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's exhibition was one more proof that the Falcons willingly undertake work and will be excelled by none in carrying it out. Every number on the varied program was a success.</p>
   <p>The Falcon's band opened the exercises with the march "Poland Rises."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0665.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After Mr. Plucinski's speech, the ladies choir of St. Hedwig sang Mallek's "November Song," "March of the Falcons," and the song "Aloft."</p>
   <p>After the Bajorek brothers' acrobatic stunts, editor H. Lokanski spoke. He emphasized the gravity of the times and the difference between us--who are acquainted with the European war merely through being told about it--and those across the sea who are shedding their blood on the battlefields.</p>
   <p>Then, Miss Gordon gave a recitation. This was followed by a selection from the Bohemian Girl played by the Falcon band.</p>
   <p>The exercises of the children were received with enthusiasm beyond description. Then Mr. Bartkowiak of Milwaukee sang. If Mr. Bartkowiak did not already have an established reputation in Chicago, yesterday he undoubtedly gained recognition as an excellent tenor from his several hundred listeners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0666.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"To arms! To Arms!" and "Lord, Father," sung by Bartkowiak, were numbers which the listeners no doubt will recall with pleasure.</p>
   <p>After the playing of "Medly of Polish Tunes" by the Falcon band, the ladies choir of St. Hedwig's sang "The Lark," with Cecelia Glon and Ursula Jankowski, singing the excellent solo parts. "Grajek" was sung as an encore.</p>
   <p>Miss Nowakowski's recitation was no less successful. The acrobatic stunts of the professional Wozniak brothers followed and added much variety to the program.</p>
   <p>The pleasant soprano voice of Miss Cecelia Glon found an excellent medium of expression in Malleck's "Flowers" and in "Wreath," which Miss Glon was forced by the audience to sing as an encore.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kruszka, baritone, sang a number. He is one of those talented singers <pb facs="5423968_5_0667.jpg" n="4"/>for whom an excellent career is predicted. Mr. Kruszka always sings well, but yesterday in the "Cossack" he surpassed even himself, and the audience with its enthusiastic applause forced him to sing "They Say That I Am Lucky."</p>
   <p>The last number on the program was a speech by Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, rector of Holy Trinity Parish. He spoke briefly but spoke as only a really patriotic Polish priest can speak. Having greeted those present and having thanked all those who took part in the exercises in the name of the Falcons of Holy Trinity Parish, Reverend Sztuczko passed on to present-day matters.</p>
   <p>"It is always fitting for us," said the Polish priest, "to mention our homeland, our mother rising from her lethargy, our Poland who is waiting for our help.</p>
   <p>"Over there in the homeland, butchery and murders are taking place. Our dying brothers are covering with their corpses the battlefields on which <pb facs="5423968_5_0668.jpg" n="5"/>nations are fighting for supremacy in Europe. Therefore, today, on this occasion, I cannot avoid mentioning that we are sinning gravely against the homeland. Have we always remembered it--our homeland? Have we not sinned by forgetting our mother, Poland? Yes! we have sinned and we continue to sin. There still are Polish emigre families in which you will not even hear Poland mentioned. Their national conscience does not tell them that "God is repulsed by those who are ashamed of their mother." Poland is our mother, whom all of us should love and serve because it is our duty.</p>
   <p>"And how many are there among the emigres who have Poland only on their lips? We plead uselessly for an independent country," ended the priest-patriot, "if our hearts do not sincerely want a free Poland. Therefore today when you sing "our country and liberty, deign to restore to us, O Lord," sing not only with your lips, but sing with your hearts, that we plead for her liberty!"</p>
   <p>After a short address by Mr. J. S. Rybicki, president of Circuit II of the <pb facs="5423968_5_0669.jpg" n="6"/>Alliance of Polish Falcons, everyone joined in the singing of "God Save Poland." A prayer flowed out of the breasts of hundreds of young people--the sincere plea repeated for many years: "our country and liberty, deign to restore to us, O Lord." And tears welled up in the eyes of the young people and slowly coursed down the cheeks of those future defenders of Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
