<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-09">Sept. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Committee Reports on Polish Gold Mine in California</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-09">Sept. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITTEE REPORTS ON POLISH GOLD MINE IN CALIFORNIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter was received for publication in Dziennik [Chicagoski]:</p>
   <p>"We, the undersigned, a committee delegated by the Polish Corporation [Original Quartz Hill Gold Mining Company] to investigate the gold mine in California, have returned to make the following report:</p>
   <p>"The State Bureau of Mines advised us to engage the engineer Luckhardt, a metallurgical expert who has spent the last thirty-four years on the Pacific coast, and who is generally recognized as a capable and conscientious man. He accompanied us to Redding, Shasta County, from which the mine is four miles distant. The mine itself is located on the left [east] bank of the Sacramento River, 220 feet above the river and 300 feet above sea level. The vicinity is densely wooded and will supply plenty of lumber for fuel and mine supports.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0301.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The mine consists of the 'Main Ledge,' 'Red Ledge,' and the so-called 'Storm' and 'Snow' claims. The total length of these claims protruding above the ground is 3,200 feet. The main vein protrudes above the ground for a distance of more than six hundred feet. The masses of quartz in this vein, reaching a height of from ten to thirty-seven feet, with a width of from twenty-one to thirty feet, form a long wall. In the center of the hill through which the main vein runs, is a tunnel extending seventy-two feet below the surface. The tunnel cuts both the main and red veins, the latter not visible on the surface at this point. A forty-five-foot well has been dug in the tunnel, which reveals that the main and red veins come together to form one mass at about a hundred and twenty feet below the surface.</p>
   <p>"In Luckhardt's opinion, with which our engineers Maryanski and Aleksander, who also examined the mine, agree, the veins, which extend deep into the earth, contain about a million and two hundred thousand tons of gold ore. This estimate is for the main and red veins alone, and does not include the other claims.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0302.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Taking the opinions of mining experts as a basis, we can count upon large profits with practical certainty; according to the above estimate, a hundred mills [mining mills for pulverizing ore] will be kept busy day in and day out for eight to ten years, each mill yielding from seven to eight dollars daily.</p>
   <p>The surface veins alone contain about thirty thousand tons of ore. The most conservative estimates, based upon analysis of the ore, set the gold content at about $150,000, after all costs of production have been deducted.</p>
   <p>"We can honestly say, then, that those who invest in this enterprise are not risking their capital, for the surface veins alone will repay it with interest, On the other hand, investors may realize an enormous profit, perhaps even wealth.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Casimir Midowicz, August J. Kowalski, and John F. Smulski."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
