<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-31">Aug. 31, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Communities and Special Committees Report Activities at Polish Day Central Committee Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-31">Aug. 31, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNITIES AND SPECIAL COMMITTEES REPORT ACTIVITIES AT POLISH DAY CENTRAL COMMITTEE MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third meeting of the Polish Day Central Committee was held yesterday evening at Pulaski Hall under the chairmanship of S. Slominski. Present at this meeting were a delegation from St. Hedwig's parish--consisting of S. Fruzyna, J. Jablonski, and J. Sakwinski of St. Hedwig's Society--and F. Kielichowski and J. Lewandowski of the Heart of Jesus Society. These delegates were appointed to the Central Committee [as representatives of their community]. At the same time, J. Lisztewnik, in the absence of J. Gniot, announced the participation of the Holy Name of Jesus Society I of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish. A similar announcement was made by J. N. Brzezinski in behalf of two societies of Town of Lake--the St. Thaddeus Kosynierzi[a division of Kosciusko's army, armed with scythes]and the Polish national society Unity.</p>
   <p>The secretary read the minutes of the last meeting and a letter from the <pb facs="5423968_5_1510.jpg" n="2"/>women's society Star of Victory, concerning this society's intention of participating in the celebration. He added that he had received similar letters from the Casimir the Great Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish and from the Tailors' Union.</p>
   <p>The Central Committee reported that after consultation with the World's Fair officials, October 7 was set as the date on which Polish Day will be celebrated; both Festival Hall and the Stock Pavilion will be at our disposal without charge. The general announcement which had been submitted to the newspapers, in accordance with a decision made at the last meeting, was read to the gathering.</p>
   <p>Next, reports of community activity were presented. On behalf of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish, J. Lisztewnik and other speakers explained that a meeting of businessmen of that community will be held on Friday, September 1, and a mass meeting on Sunday, September 3. It was also announced that the Patriotic organization had voted a sum between $150 and $250 for the production of a float.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1511.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>F. Jablonski reported for Holy Trinity parish that a meeting had been held at which twenty societies of that parish promised to participate; Holy Trinity parish will furnish two floats for the parade. K. Zychlinski reported for St. Adalbert's parish that thirty societies of that community will participate in the celebration, that the sum of $330 has already been collected, and that St. Adalbert's parish will furnish three floats.</p>
   <p>Five additional societies from Bridgeport, according to F. Behmke's report, have promised participation. That community collected $323.25 at its businessmen's meeting on Monday; it will furnish one or two floats.</p>
   <p>The delegation from South Chicago was not present, but it is a well-known fact that both of its parishes are actively engaged in Polish Day preparations. The representatives of Town of Lake, J. N. Brzezinski and Z. Schmidt, announced that their community will furnish one float. Mr. Ziolkowski promised to construct a triumphal arch in that section of the city, and J. Nuszkowski promised to make the necessary inscriptions upon it without <pb facs="5423968_5_1512.jpg" n="4"/>charge. The Holy Virgin Mary Society, numbering forty young women, will participate in national costumes. Town of Lake also appointed a committee for the collection of money, consisting of L. Muszkowski, E. Golembiowski, and L. Kropaczewski. A mass meeting will be held there on Sunday next.</p>
   <p>J. Rosinski of St. Casimir's parish announced that nine societies of his community are participating and that one float will be furnished. A mass meeting will be held there tomorrow. Finally, the delegates from St. Hedwig's parish assured the gathering that activity would start in their community shortly.</p>
   <p>After these reports had been heard and accepted, the meeting turned its attention to financial matters. Upon a motion by Z. Schmidt, it was decided to begin immediately the collection of the fifteen-cent assessment decided upon at the last meeting. The following payments were made to the treasurer, M.A. La Buy: From Town of Lake: St. Joseph's Society (seventy-five members), $11.25; St. Stanislaus Kostka Youth Society (sixteen members), $2.40; Polish <pb facs="5423968_5_1513.jpg" n="5"/>Uhlans (twenty members), $2.95; Father August Kordecki Society (twenty-seven members), $4.05; St. John Cantius Society I (forty-two members), $6.30; St. Thaddeus Kosynierzi (nine members), $1.35; King Miecislaus I Society (fifty-one members), $7.65; Heart of Jesus Society (forty-two members), $6.30. From St. Adalbert's parish: Holy Family Brotherhood (forty members), $6; Lublin Union (forty-six members), $6.90; Pole in Exile Society (twenty-four members), $3.60.</p>
   <p>On a motion by J. Manna, the Committee will issue an appeal to all other participating societies, asking that the fifteen-cent-per-person assessment be paid into the Central Committee treasury not later than September 10.</p>
   <p>Reports were next heard from the special committees. The committee on floats presented the list of floats it had prepared and the announcement it had issued to the public. Various individuals and communities reserved for themselves the following subjects:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1514.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The committee in charge of the celebration at Festival Hall presented the following program for the celebration: 1) Opening by the president of the Central Committee. 2) Appointment of a master of ceremonies and secretary. 3) An orchestral number. 4) A short speech by the president. 5) A choral number. 6) A speech in English. 7) Piano solo (probably by Mr. Katski). 8) A speech in Polish. 9) A choral number. 10) "Columbian Drill," by girls. 11) A speech in English. 12) An orchestral number. 13) "Boze Cos Polske" [God Save Poland], by the audience. Besides this, the committee prepared the following program to be held at the Stock Pavilion: 1) An orchestral number. 2) Falcons' drill. 3) Cadets' drill. 4) Drill by[Polish] military societies. 5) Presentation of awards (a gold medal to one out of each of the three groups). The Central Committee accepted this program without making any changes. It was decided to invite Judge La Buy to officiate as master of ceremonies. Bishop Spaulding of Peoria and the Mayor of Chicago, Carter H. Harrison, will be asked to speak in English. The choice of Polish speakers was postponed until later.</p>
   <p>The committee on badges and decorations presented a sample badge, of two <pb facs="5423968_5_1515.jpg" n="7"/>colors with an inscription. The choice of a badge was postponed and the committee was directed to supply more samples.</p>
   <p>Finally, the publicity committee announced that it has prepared notices to the Poles outside Chicago, but lacks funds for printing and distribution. It was decided to appropriate the necessary money.</p>
   <p>After all these important matters had been settled, the meeting was adjourned. The next meeting will be held at Pulaski Hall on September 11, at 7:30 P.M. Until this date, there is time for community activity; we are sure that progress will be made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
