<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 36
<date when="1898-09-08">Sept. 8, 1898</date><title level="a">Address to the Polish People in Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 36
<date when="1898-09-08">Sept. 8, 1898</date>
<title level="a">ADDRESS TO THE POLISH PEOPLE IN TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On this question we have decided to answer you, Polish people residing in Town of Lake; Give you our true aims and ambitions regarding our new choir, "Lutnia."</p>
   <p>Polish national songs and hymns are the true backbone of us Poles. We should endeavor to protect them and help to continue their existence. The Choir of "Lutnia," with Polish songs on their lips, travel everywhere, where the true Polish songs are needed to awaken our emotion and love for this cause.</p>
   <p>Songs of our "Lutnia" choir are sung to diversify our celebrations and awaken our souls at concerts.</p>
   <p>With Polish songs on his lips, the Polish farmer goes to work on this farms, knowing that when in high spirits he can produce more crops and show more ambition for work; with songs on their lips the Polish <pb facs="5423968_5_0749.jpg" n="2"/>soldier marched to war in high spirit; with songs in their hearts our Polish forefathers opened and defended our rights (sic); and Polish Hymns ease the pains of parents who have lots some dear one from their family.</p>
   <p>Listening to our songs sung harmoniously, it makes us Polish people feel that the melody is the sweetest ever composed and leaves us light-hearted and happy.</p>
   <p>In the name of our ideals we are calling upon you, fathers and mothers, to encourage your sons and daughters to join this singer choir "Lutnia." We are sure you will never regret encouraging this great idea. The Society of "Lutnia" Choir has lowered the initiation fee until the New Year in order to gain a larger enrollment.</p>
   <p>We are inviting all Polish citizens, or people of Polish extraction, who have intentions of joining this Society of "Lutnia" Choir in Town <pb facs="5423968_5_0750.jpg" n="3"/>of Lake and to specify on what day you want to have the meetings held.</p>
   <p>People can sign any Wednesday between 8 and 10 P. M., at Columbia Hall, located at 48th and Paulina Street.</p>
   <p>Walter Wutkowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
