<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Chicago Society's Polish Day a History Making Event</title>," <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1926-08">August 1926</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">[A Polish Day Celebration]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Chicago Society's Polish Day a History Making Event</title>," <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1926-08">August 1926</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">[A POLISH DAY CELEBRATION]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A gathering numbering over 20,000 persons and a demonstration heretofore unprecedented in the history of Chicago, under the auspices of Americans of Polish extraction marked the second annual "Polish Day" celebration, sponsored by the Chicato Society at Riverview Park on Sunday, July 18, for the noble cause of charity and education. Every Polish speaking organization in Chicago and the outlying districts lent its whole hearted support to make this worthy endeavor a success. Visitors from Poland and California and other distant places were numbered among the participants.</p>
   <p>Mr. Edward J. Prebis, President of the Chicago Society, made the address of welcome introducing Mr. Peter H. Schwaba, who was master of ceremonies in the capacity of chairman of the reception committee.</p>
   <p>The honorable Polish Consul General, Z. Kurnickowski, was the first speaker presented by Mr. Schwaba to address the assembled throng. Consul Kurnikowski in his address, congratulated the Chicago Society for initiating a demonstration of this kind; a demonstration which has such laudable purposes and whose cultural aims reflect credit <pb facs="5423968_5_1134.jpg" n="2"/>upon all citizens of Polish descent. His words were received enthusiastically by the great mass of friends to whom he has already endeared himself even though his arrival has been but recent.</p>
   <p>Education in United States Unhampered</p>
   <p>Mr. Andrew Kazmierczak, President of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the next speaker, likewise praised the aims of the Chicago Society and spoke of the oppression caused by the intervention of the Russian, German, and Austrian government which resulted in the stifling of education in Poland. This caused the people to emigrate to the United States, where they could receive the proper education unhampered by racial prejudices. Mr. Kazmierczak explained to his listeners.</p>
   <p>"I have been informed", said the Hon. Charles V. Barrett, who was next introduced by the chairman, "that the Chicago Society is composed of business and professional men of Polish extraction, and the 'Polish Day' has been inaugurated for the purpose of gathering funds for charitable and educational purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I believe that this is a laudable purpose," continued Mr. Barrett, "and everybody must realize that there is one thing in life which having been attained, cannot be lost, and that is education. It is an asset you can never lose and nobody can take it away from you."</p>
   <p>Poland in Constructive Era</p>
   <p>The Hon. George E. Brennan, who was next called upon by Mr. Schwaba, outlined the principle of personal rights and liberties which is being made the issue of our election next fall. He also told of his wide acquaintance among Polish speaking people.</p>
   <p>Our mayor, the Hon. William E. Dever, was enthusiastically greeted; and having been born in a Polish speaking section of the city, recalled many pleasant instances much to the delight of his audience.</p>
   <p>From the speech of the Reverend Jacek Wroniecki, Dominican rector of the University of Lublin, it is evident that the present conditions in Poland, which, according to the daily press, are alarming, are not more serious than in other countries in continental Europe. Poland, we learned, is now in a constructive era. "Poland," said <pb facs="5423968_5_1136.jpg" n="4"/>Father Woroniecki, "is capable, intelligent and industrious and has all the advantages, but must wait silently until the climax is reached." He also urged the Polish Americans to play an important role in the governmental affairs of this country.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the speeches the following celebrities were presented to the audience: Mr. Casimir Zuchlinski, President of the P. N. A.; Mr. Felix Garbarek, Vice President of the P. N. A.; County Commissioner Frank J. Wilson, County Commissioner John Pilka, the Hon. John Jaranowski, Mayor of Calumet City, Colonel Cedric Fountleroy, Father Kneblewski, Captain Palezynski, Mr. John Romanowicz of California, Mr. Leon Winiecki, Commissioner of Public Works and a score of others.</p>
   <p>Singing Societies Entertain Participants</p>
   <p>The speeches having been concluded and the listeners being imbued with knowledge of education and other kindred subjects, a lighter form of diversion was in order.</p>
   <p>Many of the foremost Polish Singing Societies contributed to the enjoyment of the occasion by rendering beautiful vocal selections. An orchestra composed solely of young people won great applause with its rendition of Polish airs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1137.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Artistically executed, Polish folk dances were also included among the evening's entertainment. Clowns and daring trapeze performers provided unusual merriment for the kiddies.</p>
   <p>Auxiliary Also Aids</p>
   <p>The rest of the evening was spent either in dancing at the Pavilion or going about renewing old acquaintances and happily commenting upon the success of the day.</p>
   <p>Many thanks are due to the ladies of the Chicago Society Auxiliary who have so generously contributed their time and energy in the way of assuming the responsibility of different booths. Mrs. Frank V. Zintak, President of the Chicago Society Auxiliary, supervised the activities of the Auxiliary on this day.</p>
   <p>Greater "Polish Day" Anticipated Next Year</p>
   <p>Now that the Chicago Society's Polish Day has become an institution and its proceeds are being contributed for such worthy causes, were we conceited, we would say the Chicago Society had reached its zenith; but we will not for the success of this day will only goad us on to a greater "Polish Day" next year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1138.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The South Chicago district received the beautiful silk American Flag as a prize for sending the largest number of representatives to the Festival from the south side section. Another silk flag was awarded the Chicago parish for the best turn-out of all the parishes. The winners of these valuable and beautiful prizes were highly elated.</p>
   <p>Among the cities which sent their representatives to our Festival were the following: Milwaukee,Wis.; Detroit, Mich.; Grand Rapids, Mich.; South Bend, Ind.; Indiana Harbor, Ind.; East Chicago, Ind.; Calumet City, Ill.; Los Angeles, Calif.; Stevens Point, Wis.; Buffalo, N. Y.; and Onekama, Mich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
