<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-12">Sept. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Miss Modzejewska's Performance Attracts Record Crowd]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-12">Sept. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[MISS MODZEJEWSKA'S PERFORMANCE ATTRACTS RECORD CROWD]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Helen Modzejewska's performance at the Polish Hall attracted so many people that the Hall was filled to capacity for the first time since it was built. The attendance was so large that there was no room in the hall to accommodate all who came, and many had to stand. Had the Hall been twice as large as it actually is, it is doubtful whether all who came to see the great Polish actress would have been seated. It was estimated that from five to six thousand persons had come to see Miss Modzejewska, the outstanding Shakespearian actress of all time. Indeed, it was unfortunate that there was no room for all in the Hall.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, no Polish performance in America has ever attracted so large a number of ardent theatergoers. It is doubtful whether this record attendance will be duplicated again, at least for some time to come. Even if last Sunday's attendance was not record-breaking, yesterday's was.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0569.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In spite of the rain, the public began to gather early, thus setting a new high in attendance. And who could blame the people for flocking to the hall in such large numbers? Hadn't they all come to see the queen of all Shakespearian actresses--Miss Helen Modzejewska--who was to play the role of Hedwiga, the young Polish queen? Hadn't they all come to acclaim her as their queen?</p>
   <p>Words are not sufficient to describe Miss Modzejewska's performance or to express her dynamic dramatic portrayal. Whatever we might say, it would be but a feeble description of the performance.</p>
   <p>Just as the Poles of old were happy to welcome the Polish Queen Hedwiga during her reign, so were the Poles of today happy to welcome Miss Modzejewska. Her every move and word on the stage was received with awe and, every time the curtain fell at the close of a scene, the audience showed its enthusiasm with thunderous applause. Hundreds of people felt for the first time a genuine national feeling such as they had never felt <pb facs="5423968_5_0570.jpg" n="3"/>before in their lives.</p>
   <p>It is easier to write about the play than about Miss Modzejewska's performance of the title role. The play in itself expresses the feelings of Hedwiga, a young queen compelled to give up the man she loves by her father, who has made other arrangements for her marriage which will greatly benefit the country and the people. Her father's choice was Ladislaus Jagello, the coarse-looking young Lithuanian prince. The young queen had heard that the prince was a wild man, but when she saw him she realized that all she had heard about him was false.</p>
   <p>The author excels in bringing out the emotions that were harbored in the heart of Hedwiga. To give up her love for Wilhelm would have been to deny herself her only true love--not to marry Jagello would have been to forsake her country and the people over whom she ruled. Her decision was that of a true queen, a queen that Poland has never forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0571.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every move, every word, and every feeling was genuinely portrayed by Miss Modzejewska last night. Hedwiga's indescribable emotions--her sympathy and affection, her fears and pride, her duty to the kingdom and her resignation to the sacrifice for her country--could not have been portrayed any better had Queen Hedwiga herself been there in person.</p>
   <p>Miss Helen Modzejewska's supporting cast was made up of local amateur artists. It would be unfair to compare their acting with that of the star performer. Their acting was as different from hers as a lowly peasant is different from a regal queen. It cannot be denied, however, that our amateurs did their best to support Miss H. Modzejewska. Let it be said that they had never played better. This, of course, may be attributed to the inspiration they received from the leading star. All supporting performers were applauded equally for their good work.</p>
   <p>Historical facts relative to this episode were given by Reverend V. Barzynski, who closed his commentaries with the classic story of Hedwiga <pb facs="5423968_5_0572.jpg" n="5"/>and Jagello before it was presented on the stage.</p>
   <p>Those who saw this performance will never forget it as long as they live. It will be one that will be told over and over again as the years go by, a treasure never to be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
