<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-09">Aug. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-09">Aug. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Day question, discussed many times in the columns of Dziennik Chicagoski, is the subject of the following announcement by the Polish citizens of southwest Chicago:</p>
   <p>"We, the Poles on the Southwest Side of Chicago, appeal to the Poles of Chicago in general and ask that they join us in promoting a Polish Day at the Worlds' Fair, in the month of September.</p>
   <p>"We invite all Polish priests as representatives of their parishes, as well as the presidents and captains of all societies, for a meeting on this subject, to be held at 7:30 in the evening on Saturday, August 19, at Pulaski Hall, 800 South Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>"We hope that all those invited will attend. It would be very lamentable if we Poles, numbering about a hundred and fifty thousand here in Chicago, <pb facs="5423968_5_1585.jpg" n="2"/>could not manifest our existence before the other national groups. Let all come, without waiting for special invitations, for the time is short and the matter concerns all of us alike. Representatives of societies should not delay ....; officers of societies have full authority to act upon their own initiative in a matter of such urgency and importance. As a matter of fact, they can prepare the ground for this matter at their own meetings, so far as time permits.....</p>
   <p>"Let us show that we are all Poles, that the good of our cause concerns us, and that when our cause is at stake, we can eliminate partisanship. Let us prove that, rather than bringing up the rear, we also can keep step with modern progress.</p>
   <p>"Let us show other national groups that here on American soil, where no despotism hampers our movements, we are a nation that has a right to a cultural and political existence. Brethren! let union, love, and <pb facs="5423968_5_1586.jpg" n="3"/>brotherhood once and for all rule among us! Only by joining forces can we achieve our desired aim.</p>
   <p>"With best wishes,</p>
   <p>Francis Smietanka, Joseph Napieralski, John Czaja, Joseph Rozanski, John Bednarz, John Kniola, Frank Sowadzki, Casimir Zychlinski, Anthony Stefanowicz, Stephan Napieralski, F. Marcinkowski, John Bonk, G. Kozlowski, and W. Antkowski."</p>
   <p>It is with genuine pleasure that we print this announcement, which rings with sincere patriotism and a firm belief in the possibility of unity amongst the Poles of Chicago. Its tone is still more worthy of attention when we note that the announcement is signed by members of various factions.</p>
   <p>In our part of the city, the question has already been discussed at a meeting held at the [World's Fair] Reception Committee's headquarters on June 18. The gathering, including Polish priests, admitted at the time that a Polish Day and a council of Poles ought to be held with the <pb facs="5423968_5_1587.jpg" n="4"/>co-operation of all Poles, regardless of party lines. Further discussion was deferred to the next meeting, on August 13.</p>
   <p>This meeting will be held. We have a well-grounded hope that those who attend will accept with enthusiasm this announcement from the Southwest Siders, and will join forces with them to attain the common end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
