<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A Voice from the Polish Literary and Dramatic Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A VOICE FROM THE POLISH LITERARY AND DRAMATIC ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A New Year! A new period of time, measured out for unlimited possibilities..... New dreams and plans for those who only know how to sleep and dream--new problems for the cultivators of life. The New Year!... After reviewing the accomplishments of the Polish Literary and Dramatic Alliance, we must admit that we have progressed a great deal since the foundation of this organization. Let us be thankful for this.</p>
   <p>Within us is that Polish nature which will not permit us to say farewell forever to the allurement of worldly delusions, but makes us turn our thoughts to the past.... Whenever a warrior of our cause drops out or dies, we never replace him with a new young worker to carry on. No, we place him at the very beginning in order that he may become familiar and follow in the footsteps of his forerunner. In this way he spends all his energy in learning gradually, and, in the end, he finds that he has not progressed very far. This is our task. Let us look back and count our steps from the very beginning of our clubs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1693.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They have been founded for the purpose of cultivating the Polish language and elevating and propagating our national culture. A phalanx of over enthusiastic youth plunged into the work. They have demonstrated their far reaching aims to everyone.</p>
   <p>The work was started. In reality it had to be started from nothing. For twenty years the plans were not recounted. Its existence has lived under a sweet illusion of continual progress.... But today let us take a closer look at the picture. Most groups degenerated from lofty ideals to mere play. Today they are considered places for play and conversation. More ideas are vehemently thrown upon the groups, which somehow play the role of teachers of morality, safeguarding the youth from "spoiling." There is more of this than amusement. Nothing better was accomplished since the beginning of these groups--nothing but repetition. Yet, these groups do something. They must be given credit for this.</p>
   <p>Energy is only wasted. Nothing has been accomplished that would serve as a testament to posterity. The youth is discouraged with the Polish dramatic <pb facs="5423968_5_1694.jpg" n="3"/>sketches which are produced by our disappearing amateurs. In reality, these are small in number. This, however, does not include the K. L. D. "Hearth."</p>
   <p>Polish art is lying dormant. It is abused and great talents are wasted. This has not been so for one year but many.</p>
   <p>We do not know that art is the mystery of the soul; the holiness of life, which is not to be neglected.</p>
   <p>We have stood before the portals of a great and mystical temple, its interior glittering with emeralds; a source of resplendent beauty. This is the interior that we are afraid to enter. We are gathering the crumbs in front of the temple; shy looks are cast. Some of us dream about great things and live in the midst of a grand illusion, which will be attained by us if we are permitted to step into the interior of the temple. The Polish soul, the Polish spirit rather, dreams about its great accomplishments in life.... This is <pb facs="5423968_5_1695.jpg" n="4"/>their temple of art and culture. Beautiful reflections are our seclusion; unreached and unknown is the treasure of the collective soul.... There lies our emancipation....</p>
   <p>Enough of dreams. With only one single effort can the fire of activity be kindled. Thus, awakening from the lethargy of dreams, all but the desire for action is sought. Great buildings can be built without words. With action we can leave to posterity the strength of Polish cooperation. Sheer action is needed! A helping hand can be given to the Polish people and great feats performed. Its glory extolled to the entire world. Merely action is needed! It is useless to wage war with the surging waves on the surface or lash the blustering wind; but, let us descend to the bottom like the followers of Sienkiewicz, the sailors of the "Purpury" and start the work of rebuilding from the bottom, from the bottom! Youth, Stop! Awaken! Pursue the beautiful and preserve it for your own fortune. Do not regret hardship for pursuit [effort] makes life [beautiful] and good. Arise and work!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1696.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Once more, attention is called to the groups of the Polish Literary and Dramatic Alliance to study the twelve points carefully, revise them, and strengthen them. This will [contribute to] their continued existence and welfare. All the groups must make great sacrifices to awaken Polish art, so that the Alliance will not become an illusion and an unattainable dream.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
