<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-16">March 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Theater Polish Play,"Popychadlo" (Drudge,) a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-16">March 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH THEATER POLISH PLAY,"POPYCHADLO" (Drudge,) A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Poles who attend theatrical plays, either do not realize or forget that these plays are performed by amateur actors. They have, however, demonstrated their great ability and talents. Each play supplies new material for practice and discloses the fact that these amateurs possess genuine talent. In other words, they have sufficient ability and confidence to merit a regular Polish theater of our own; a temple of dramatic art that will bring cheer to our hearts and souls in this adopted Country. Yesterday's theatrical performance disclosed the very interesting fact, that we have in our own settlement a Polish hall which is in every respect suitable for such occasions.</p>
   <p>We refer to St. Stanislaus Hall.It is equipped with all modern conveniences, especially adopted for theatrical plays, such as beautiful scenery, a large stage and a good lighting system. The Hall is large and the seats are comfortable. Yesterday's play, "Popychadlo" was a comedy depicting everyday life; stressing such human faults as stupidity, malice and their consequences. The heroine of the play is a janitor's daughter who is mistreated by her stepmother. This difficult role was played so well by Miss Wieckowska, that it brought tears to the audience. Our amateurs proved that they can characterize not only the common folk, but also the refined individuals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
