<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-08">Mar. 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Polish People Give Great Ovation to Their Virtuosos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1685</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1685.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-08">Mar. 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH PEOPLE GIVE GREAT OVATION TO THEIR VIRTUOSOS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night, at the Polish Women's Alliance Hall, one of the finest violin concerts of the season was given by Michael Wilkomirski and George Spinalski. Although this concert was not given much publicity, the hall was nevertheless filled to capacity. The Polish Arts Club should be commended for the splendid work it did in arranging this concert.</p>
   <p>In writing about this Polish violin concert, it is difficult to select one item for particular attention--the great moments were many. The fame of the artists' work has been carried far and wide by the people, which is proof of the fact that the noted accomplishments of these Polish artists are truly appreciated. Criticism of a professional nature cannot be offered. There only remains the description of emotional impressions. Even this, on the whole, cannot be adequately done. The impressions were solely emotional ones, which are difficult to express.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1686.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The selections played by Wilkomirski on the program were the highlights of the evening. They were not heavy or filled with gloom, but of a nature depicting American feeling and understanding. Along with selections of notable musical prestige, which moved every listener to the core, the lighter and gayer of the classics were presented, adding much to the delight of the audience.</p>
   <p>Just as our lives are varied, so also the feelings of the soul are infinitely diverse. Music is akin to them in this, that it is infinitely rich in melodies and harmony, and one can hear in it the everlasting divine echoes of the Creator resounding throughout the universe. One must be an artist in order to understand and interpret these feelings, and to awaken the dormant emotions of the listeners. Transposing these feelings into music is truly an artist's gift. It aids him in his quest for the sublime and immortalizes his work.</p>
   <p>In all this Michael Wilkomirski, ably assisted by George Spinalski, another violin artist, displayed his genius while playing the most beautiful musical selections last night. The music, as presented by these two artists, was not <pb facs="5423968_5_1687.jpg" n="3"/>just a display of brilliant technique. Besides the purely technical skill shown, the performance was soulful, and much genuine feeling was put by the artists into the flowing strains of the violins as they poured out immortal music.</p>
   <p>Listening to these artists of ours, these "Kings of the Violin," we realize that they are true masters of music and of the violin. The performance was really an outstanding one. It was so completely perfect that we abstain from all criticism.</p>
   <p>Program</p>
   <p>As a solo, Michael Wilkomirski played Tartini's "Devil's Trill Sonata." Then he and George Spinalski played as a duet Bach's "Vivace," "Largo," and "Allegro." The audience did not stint in the applause to the great violinists. Van Grove was the accompanist.</p>
   <p>After a short intermission the program was continued. Wilkomirski took the stage as a soloist. He played "The Fountain of Arethusa," by Szymanowski;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1688.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Mazurka, in A major, by Chopin; and "Polonaise," by Wieniawski. With his associate he played "Navarra (Spanish Dance)," by Sarasate.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wilkomirski played several encores to reward the audience for its unstinted enthusiasm and applause.</p>
   <p>As was mentioned before, the concert was a great success. The famous violinists were given a grand ovation in appreciation of their talents. Throughout the entire performance perfect quiet reigned, testifying to the attention of the audience.</p>
   <p>The Polish people proved by their enthusiastic demonstrations that they readily recognize and appreciate a fine performance by their own countrymen. However, the people have patronized the false god of pretentious entertainment for a long time in the past, and to this day they too often pay their respects to him.</p>
   <p>Among those in the audience were the Consul General of the Polish Republic, Dr. Zdzislaw Kurinkowski; Zygmunt Stefanowicz, editor-in-chief of the Polish <pb facs="5423968_5_1689.jpg" n="5"/>Roman Catholic Union paper, The Polish Union Daily, with his wife; Simon Wroblewski, director of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; many representatives of the local Polish press, and Miss Paczynski and Miss Dyniewicz, members of the Polish Welfare Society.</p>
   <p>From a journalistic point of view we must refer to one important fact, namely, that the concert, the audience, and the artists were Polish. Some were not thoroughly familiar with the English language, but in spite of this all but one of the members of the Program Committee addressed the audience in English. If announcements had been made in Polish, a far better impression would have been made on the Poles who were present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
