<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-18">May 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">"Macko Z Borkowic"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-18">May 18, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">"MACKO Z BORKOWIC"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, in the Bradley Street Hall, the Saint Casimir Young Men's Society gave a performance of the difficult drama by Rapacki, entitled "Macko Z Borkowicz."</p>
   <p>The plot of this beautiful drama, based on Polish historical events of long ago, revolves around the feud of two noble families--Nalecze and Napiwonie. The leader of the latter family--the insolent Wojewoda Poznanski--organized a revolt against King Casimir The Great, and murdered the king's messenger, the youthful Benjamin of Wola (of the Nalecze family), who was loved by his (Poznanski's) own daughter, Bogna. He was severely punished by King Casimir for his misdeeds.</p>
   <p>The drama is replete with beautiful scenes, appealing and touching. Although this was not the first time this drama has been played here, yet it attracted a large and intelligent audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The amateurs gave a beautiful performance--the title role, especially, portrayed by Mr. Vincent Jorwiakowski, was excellent.</p>
   <p>The two feminine roles were played in an accomplished manner. Mrs. Grabowiecka played the role of Bogna, and Mrs. K. Murkowska that of the fortune teller Zdzislawa.</p>
   <p>The role of Benjamin of Wola was rendered very effectively by Mr. August Klafta. Mr. J. Grabowiecki, as the king, was powerful and imposing. Mr. J. Nering, Mr. J. Oszwaldowski, Mr. R. Szajkowski, Mr. J. Jarzembowski, Mr. M. Siudrinski, Mr. A. Barwig, and Mr. J. Kikulski acted excellently, intelligently, and with a full understanding of the roles they portrayed.</p>
   <p>The entire performance was wonderful. Even the minor roles were fine. And again, the show was a success--as usual.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
