<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-19">Mar. 19, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Central Committee of the Kosciusko Exposition at Lwow Meets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-03-19">Mar. 19, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL COMMITTEE OF THE KOSCIUSKO EXPOSITION AT LWOW MEETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee in charge of Polish-American participation in the Kosciusko Exposition at Lwow held a meeting last Saturday at which several questions were settled.</p>
   <p>The first business in the order of the day was the reading of a letter from Professor Dunikowski of Lwow, Poland, who stated that construction of the Polish-American pavilion has begun and is progressing very rapidly. The pavilion will be ready on time; it will be located between the Fine Arts Building and the pavilion of the city of Lwow, which is considered a very good location. Professor Dunikowski acknowledged the receipt of money from America.</p>
   <p>Next, Anthony Groenwald gave a check for twenty-nine dollars to the secretary of the Committee, in the name of the Polish National Alliance. This money was received at the headquarters of the Polish National Alliance from the <pb facs="5423968_5_1347.jpg" n="2"/>following sources: Sobieski Society, Group No. 21 of the Polish National Alliance in Braidwood, Illinois, $5; Glowacki Society, Group No. 90 of the Polish National Alliance in Detroit, $5; Polish Tradesmen Society, Group 162 of the Polish National Alliance in Detroit, $5; Uhlans of St. Paul, Group 206 of the Polish National Alliance in Chicago, $2; Kosciusko Society, Group 198 of the Polish National Alliance in Hegewisch, Illinois, $2; Hussars of Sobieski, Group 103 of the Polish National Alliance in Red Jacket, Michigan, $5; and Symon Jacewicz, of Manticoke, Pennsylvania, $5. Total $29.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the members of the Committee decided to publish a third list of gifts and ask for more donations, because they are still short about fifteen hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>The administration [of the Alliance] was advised to devise other means to obtain the necessary funds for [participation in] the exposition; it also received instructions to make a report of its activities at the next meeting of the Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1348.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was decided to proceed at once with the sorting and packing of donated exhibits, which are to be shipped before the first of April. The exhibits will be packed by experienced packers, who will be supervised by a special committee. No exhibits will be accepted after the first of April, which is the last day for shipping. Within the next few days the Committee will issue an official announcement in regard to this matter.</p>
   <p>Shipping expenses will amount to approximately $250 or $300.</p>
   <p>The secretary of the Committee has been instructed to communicate with other committees in Baltimore, Cleveland, Buffalo, and other cities, in respect to the funds and exhibits which they have on hand.</p>
   <p>It was decided to hold another meeting next week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
