<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-17">Dec. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Societies of South Chicago Meet to Discuss Plans for a Business Enterprise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-17">Dec. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETIES OF SOUTH CHICAGO MEET TO DISCUSS PLANS FOR A BUSINESS ENTERPRISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following interesting and important article was received by the Dziennik Chicagoski for publication.)</p>
   <p>The announced meeting of all officers of the Polish societies of South Chicago was held on Sunday, December 15. The purpose of the meeting was to discuss plans for organizing and operating a Polish business enterprise.</p>
   <p>Officers from all the societies were present at the meeting. John Szostakowski was appointed chairman and W. Pacholski acted as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The chairman announced the reason for the gathering. He said that the meeting was called for the purpose of working out a plan for the establishment of a large department store (on the pattern of The Fair or other such stores) in <pb facs="5423968_5_0256.jpg" n="2"/>which all items used in the home may be purchased.</p>
   <p>Money for this venture will be raised through the selling of stock at a par value of ten dollars a share. The reason for setting the par value of the stock at this low price is to give all Poles an opportunity to become a part of this business enterprise. This matter greatly interested the Poles of South Chicago.</p>
   <p>At the meeting the following spoke on the subject: Reverend Adolph Nowicki, pastor of St. Michael Parish, Reverend F. M. Wojtalewicz, pastor of the Immaculate Conception Parish, Mr. Pacholski, J. Dudek, and others.</p>
   <p>All speakers stressed the advantages of such a department store for the Poles of South Chicago. The Jews, the leeches of Polish society, have monopolized business to such an extent among the Poles in this section of town that a number of Polish businessmen have been forced to close their doors. If this condition is allowed to continue all signs of Polish business in South Chicago <pb facs="5423968_5_0257.jpg" n="3"/>will be destroyed. Only combined Polish effort will be able to compete with the Jewish businessmen.</p>
   <p>That the Poles of South Chicago are aware of this was evidenced by the attendance at the meeting and by the number of shares sold. Four hundred shares were sold, representing four thousand dollars. The officers of each society have taken it upon themselves to promote this idea among the members.</p>
   <p>The following temporary promotion committee was chosen: Reverend Nowicki, Reverend Wojthlewicz, J. Dudek, J. Szostakowski, C. Witkowski, T. Gordon, S. Sulski, Reverend Rydzewski, J. Hyma, W. Folmer, W. Forman, A. Walkowiak, and W. Pacholski.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held on Friday, December 20, at the parish rectory on 83rd Street and Bond Avenue.</p>
   <p>Hope is expressed that this project will soon be carried out. All that is <pb facs="5423968_5_0258.jpg" n="4"/>needed is work, energy, unity, and co-operation. To work, brothers, and God will help us!</p>
   <p>W. Pacholski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
