<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Pole Invents New Aeroplane</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLE INVENTS NEW AEROPLANE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At 2160 North Irving Avenue lives Gregory Chmielinski, a tailor by trade, with his wife. Chmielinski has been in the United States for fifteen years. He was born in [Russian-occupied] Poland in the village of Chmielun Wielki.</p>
   <p>An industrious man, always interested in aiding the Polish cause in any possible way, Chmielinski began nine years ago to apply his thoughts to aeroplanes, in which he foresaw a great future. He read works on aviation, air currents, and so on. Finally, as he told this newspaper's reporter, after working many nights so as not to be interrupted, he invented an airship that bids fair to revolutionize aviation all over the world. On the surface, this statement appears somewhat fantastic, but upon examining the matter more closely, one becomes convinced that after surmounting a great many obstacles Chmielinski has reached his goal, for recently he was notified by the Patent Office in Washington through Victor Evans and Company that his invention would be patented in a very short <pb facs="5423968_5_0041.jpg" n="2"/>time, and that it has aroused great interest in aviation circles by its construction and its ingenuity.</p>
   <p>Construction of Chmielinski's Aeroplane</p>
   <p>The construction of Chmielinski's aeroplane is really strange. The apparatus is a four-cornered affair of some twenty-four cubic feet. It has four motors, two of which serve to propel it through the air in such fashion that if, for example, the aeroplane is to turn to the right, the motor on the right side lessens its speed and the motor on the left side increases its speed. Here Chmielinski used the same principle that is applied in driving teams of horses, that is, if the driver desires to turn to the right, he retards the horse on the right side, giving more rein to the horse on the left. The propellers on the motors of the aeroplane will be eight feet long and five feet wide. Its gasoline capacity will be 128 gallons, and it will carry from sixteen to twenty passengers. It will be made of aluminum, but Chmielinski is already planning to build one of steel.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0042.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It should be added here that Chmielinski's aeroplane will find wide application in the field of aviation and will do much to spread the fame of the Poles. To our knowledge, military authorities are seriously interested in Chmielinski's invention. The inventor informed our reporter, however, that he will not sell his patent to any private concern, for he wants the invention to remain in Polish hands, unless the American government should desire to purchase it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
