<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-29">Jan. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Contest and Concert Arranged by the Dudziarz Choir</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-29">Jan. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CONTEST AND CONCERT ARRANGED BY THE DUDZIARZ CHOIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon the long-announced contest for prizes arranged by the energetic Dudziarz Choir Number 91 of the Polish Singers' Alliance took place at J. P. Krechniak's hall, West Huron and Noble Streets. The concert was given in the evening with the participation of many of the local choirs and the excellent vocalist Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch. The contest was opened by a short address by Mr. S. Rzewuski, one of the founders of the choir, who invited the presidents of the contesting choirs on the stage to draw lots to decide the order in which the choirs were to sing. He also announced that there were four prizes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Z. Galinski, president of the De Reszke Brothers Choir, was fortunate in drawing the first number. The choir was applauded enthusiastically after singing a lovely tune under the direction of Mr. Z. Filisiewicz.</p>
   <p>The Dembinski Choir Number 2 of the Polish Singers' Alliance was scheduled to sing the second number, but since its members did not arrive on time, this number was left for the end.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Next in order were the following choirs: Kurpinski Choir, directed by Mr. P. Herek, which sang "To the Spirits of the Prophets," by B. Debinski; Lira Choir, of Pullman, directed by J. Jakajtis, which sang "The Day Has Passed," by Jakajtis; Harmonia Choir, directed by A. Holland, which sang "In the Silent Night," by B. Rybowiak; New Life Singing Society, directed by B. Zalewski, which sang "The Sailors' Song," by Zelenski; Polish Women's Alliance Choir, directed by R. Hensel, which sang "Beyond the Niemen"; Varsovians' Choir Number 96 of the Polish Singers' Alliance, which sang "To the Cottages," by M. Zukowski; and the Philomen Choir of Town of Lake, directed by B. Zalewski, which sang "Forest Violet," by J. Galla.</p>
   <p>At the end it was found that all the members of the Dembinski Choir had not arrived yet, so the choir was eliminated from the contest.</p>
   <p>The contest ended shortly after 5 P.M. with a recess for dinner, which gave the judges the opportunity to decide on the distribution of the prizes. At 6:30 P.M. the committee headed by Mr. S. Rzewuski announced the decision reached by the judges, who were Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, Mr. H. Schule, Niemiec, and Z. Perlowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0656.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The first prize was awarded to the New Life Singing Society, which won 247 points. The prize consisted of a picture of a lyre inlaid with a beautiful collection of real butterflies, composed of seventy different varieties, and totaling more than eight hundred butterflies. The value, for one who likes this sort of thing, would exceed a hundred dollars. The second prize, a silver cup donated by St. Innocents' Parish, was awarded to the Kurpinski Choir of St. Casimir's Parish, which won 246 points. The third prize, a silver medal depicting a lyre, a gift of Commune 75 of the Polish National Alliance in St. Innocent's Parish, was awarded to the Varsovians' Choir Number 96 of the Polish Singers' Alliance, which won 225 points. The fourth prize, a gold medal set on ribbons in the national colors (red and white), was awarded to the Philomen Men's Choir of Town of Lake, which won 212 points. The remaining choirs won the following points; Harmonia Choir, 200 points; Polish Women's Alliance Choir, 183 points; De Reszke Brothers Choir, 176 points; Lira Choir, 165.</p>
   <p>Following this, the concert, consisting of fifteen numbers, was begun. Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, our well-known vocalist, took part in the concert. In spite of the damp weather, Mrs. Kwasigroch was in good voice, and when she finished singing <pb facs="5423968_5_0657.jpg" n="4"/>J. Galla's "When The Stars Shine," op. 30, No. 1, the hall shook from the applause, and the audience forced our star to sing an encore.</p>
   <p>Among the choral numbers the following deserve special mention: New Life Singing Society, for Wagner's "Song of the Giants"; Kurpinski Choir, for its excellent rendition of Czubski's "Jagello's Prayer," in which Mr. Szlajchert sang the bass solo; Dudziarz Choir, for "Before the Storm," in which the solo parts were excellently sung by R. Kwasigroch, soprano, and Josephine Wachowiak, alto.</p>
   <p>The concert was followed by social dancing to Mr. Hensel's orchestra. A few score couples joined the Polonaise, which was led by L. Panek, president of Commune 75 of the Polish National Alliance, and Mrs. Kwasigroch. The dancing continued far into the night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
