<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-20">June 20, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Additional Donations for the Saint John Cantius Parish Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-20">June 20, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">ADDITIONAL DONATIONS FOR THE SAINT JOHN CANTIUS PARISH FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following donations have been received for the fair to be held in behalf of Saint John Cantius Parish:</p>
   <p>J. Bandziulewski, 200 Chicago Avenue, one table lamp; Jacob Swiatek, one barrel of beer; Valentine Jezior, 170 Chicago Avenue, 25 cents; Martin Bieszcrad, 170 Chicago Avenue, 25 cents; Anthony Kasprzak, $1; Frank Piotrowski, 25 cents; John Orzeszynski, ten bottles of wine; John Giza, 25 cents; Albert Wojcieszak, 25 cents; Joseph Knebel, 50 cents; Andrew Meger, 50 cents; John Klafta, 25 cents; John Haluch, $1; C. Konwinska, 267 Sangamon Street, 25 cents; Jacob Kowalczyk, 151 Chicago Avenue, one ham and ten pounds of sausages; Emil Gimner, 165 Chicago Avenue, one hundred cigars; Roman Kotlowski, 258 Sangamon Street, a quarter barrel of beer; Dorothy Ruszynska, 245 Sangamon Street, one bird in its cage; W. Paluchowski, 253 Sangamon Street, 50 cents; Joseph Pankowski, 235 Sangamon Street, three pairs of pigeons; John Urbanowski, one canary in its cage; Jacob Cholewczynski, 336 Sangamon <pb facs="5423968_5_1257.jpg" n="2"/>Street, three barrels of beer and one case of wine; John Morawczynski, one barrel of beer; A. Lackowski, 2 Lessing Street, one barrel of beer; Joseph Wysocki, 325 Sangamon Street, one barrel or flour.</p>
   <p>A sincere God bless you to all the kind donors.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
