<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-10-18">Oct. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of Stockholders in Polish Gold Mine Held at Palmer House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-10-18">Oct. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF STOCKHOLDERS IN POLISH GOLD MINE HELD AT PALMER HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the stockholders of the Polish Gold Mine of Shasta County, California, was held last night at the Palmer House. In the absence of the president, Dr. Casimir Midowicz, and the vice-president, Rev. Gruczy, Victor Bardonski presided.</p>
   <p>A large number of stockholders were present. From a total of 3554 shareholders, 3006 were represented.</p>
   <p>From the official reports presented by the secretary, the treasurer, and one of the directors, Reverend Vincent Barzynski, it is apparent that the mine is in a sound condition.</p>
   <p>An official report of the status of the mine will not be given until after the special committee, which was appointed to check the books has made its findings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0260.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A copy of this report will be published and a copy will be sent to each stockholder.</p>
   <p>The following members were chosen for this committee: Thomas Krolik, Max Drzymala [also Drezmal], and A. Kowalski. This committee will be allowed four weeks to complete its work.</p>
   <p>The gold mine has very few debts, and by the end of the year these few debts will have been paid off. So it will not be long before the company will be making a clear profit and paying dividends.</p>
   <p>Over one hundred thousand dollars has been invested in the mine and expended for carrying out the work. Thus far over twenty thousand dollars' worth of gold has been mined.</p>
   <p>After the gold has been mined, it is weighed, and then shipped to the treasurer of the company in Chicago, who has it smelted and sold in the open market at <pb facs="5423968_5_0261.jpg" n="3"/>the prevailing prices. Up to yesterday the treasurer had received a total of one thousand and five ounces, or eighty-three and three-fourths pounds (of twelve ounces to the pound), of gold. Thus far he has received $16,755.13 for the gold he has sold. There are, however, still a few thousand dollars' worth of gold on hand. When this has been sold the total sales will amount to over twenty thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Because the term of some of the directors had come to an end an election was held, and the following were elected on the board: Mr. [J. F.] Smulski and Judge M. A. LaBuy for three years, Peter Kiolbassa for two years, and A. J. Kowalski for three years.</p>
   <p>Upon a motion made by Dr. C. Venn it was agreed to reward all the members of this organization who have made this venture a success through their untiring efforts, with gold crosses of the first gold mined. Dr. Venn made especial mention of Reverend V. Barzynski. He proposed, and the motion was carried, <pb facs="5423968_5_0262.jpg" n="4"/>to give gold crosses to, Reverend Barzynski, Reverend Gruczy, J. F. Smulski, M. A. LaBuy. It was also agreed to present crosses to Dr. Midowicz and Dr. Venn.</p>
   <p>After the meeting of the stockholders, a directors' session was held. The board elected the following members to office for the coming year; Reverend Vincent Barzynski, president; Reverend W. Gruczy, vice president; Judge M. A. LaBuy, treasurer; J. F. Smulski, secretary. The following were elected to the board of directors; Peter Kiolbassa, A. J. Kowalski, Dr. Charles Venn, and K. Raryanski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
