<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-10">Sept. 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Dramatic Club Gives Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1023</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1023.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-10">Sept. 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DRAMATIC CLUB GIVES PERFORMANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Saint John Cantius Parish Polish Dramatic Club gave a performance of the play "Wlicznik Warszawski" (Warsaw Hoodlum) last night for the benefit of the newly built church. The play, staged at Walsh's Hall, was a great success: artistically and financially--in spite of a heavy rain and the fact that another play was going on on Bradley Street.</p>
   <p>Under the supervision of a competent stage director, the new dramatic club, in spite of the fact that most of its members were appearing in public for the first time, gave a performance that surprised us all. "Warsaw Hoodlum" is a comedy, and the main role, that of "Rzemyczek," was played by Anthony Chabowski, who from his first appearance on the stage until the end of the play entertained the public with his comic acting. He also played a difficult role very well. Other amateurs were Miss Helen Piatkowski, who played beautiful "Aggie"; Miss Kunkowski, in the role of "Kunegunda;" Mr. Wasilewski, as <pb facs="5423968_5_1024.jpg" n="2"/>"Rabek"; Mr. Walinski, as "Piaskarz": Miss Anna Kowalski, in the role of "Smieciarka," a girl of the streets; and Mr. Ranajczak, who played "Safaniak".</p>
   <p>The less important roles were played by Zbilski, Gliniecki, and Gorski. The play was concluded by three tableaux and a monologue which the public enjoyed immensely. The monologue, "A Lost Greenhorn," was delivered by Anthony Chabowski. The performance ended very early, at 9 P. M. After the play, there was an entertainment in which many people who had seen the "Renegat" at the school hall on Bradley Street participated.</p>
   <p>The new dramatic club earned a good reputation, with the result that it gained a few new members that very evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
