<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-01-08">Jan. 8, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish Drama, "The Renegade", a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-01-08">Jan. 8, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Polish Drama, "The Renegade", a Great Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very beautiful Polish patriotic drama, entitled "Renegat" (The Renegade), was presented last night at the School Hall on Bradley Street. The hall was filled to capacity and the performance was a great success in every respect.</p>
   <p>The plot of the play was very interesting. Based on the incidents that took place in the year of 1830, just before the Polish Insurrection of November of that year, the plot centers in the story of Lutowidzki, a Polish renegade who, as a henchman of Russia, persecuted and imprisoned his own countrymen. At the end of the play even his own son turns against him, fate turning Lutowidzki into his murderer.</p>
   <p>This play has many scenes--thrilling and dramatic. Some of them, such as the scenes depicting the prison, the oath of the conspirators, and the street fight <pb facs="5423968_5_1040.jpg" n="2"/>in the last act, are very picturesque.</p>
   <p>The play was performed excellently. Mrs. Kiolbassa and Mrs. R. Kwasigroch, experienced and talented amateur actresses, played the most important feminine roles. Miss Nering and Miss Sikorski played their parts with great success, to say nothing of Mr. J. Grabowiecki, who played the difficult role of "Butowidzki" like an experienced actor. Mr. Grabowiecki was very tragic, especially in the last two acts, displaying high artistic qualities throughout the whole performance. Mr. Vincent J. Jozwiakowski played the role of the noble and enthusiastic "Stanislaus," and Mr. J. Nering that of "Valentine," the servant. Mr. F. Kwasigroch, who was cast for the role of the unhappy "Zenon," played his part with great zeal. "Old Dabrowy" was portrayed by <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Cywinski, who also played successfully. Others who played well were Mr. R. Szajkowski, as "Dr. Piegurski," A. Klafta, and J. Oszwaldowski. Even the minor roles were played excellently, and in this connection honorable mention is due to A. Barwig, J. Kikulski, J. Anderszat, W. Malinski, F. Budzban, M. Reptowski, and S. Ligman. The success of the play, as a whole, is due to the skill of Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz, the stage director.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
