<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Financial Accounts Closed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY FINANCIAL ACCOUNTS CLOSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An administration meeting of the Polish Day Central Committee was held last Saturday at the editorial offices of Dziennik [Chicagoski] for the purpose of closing accounts [and] clearing up the remaining business which the Central Committee had entrusted to the administration at its last meeting.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary, W. Bardonski, presented his report, which showed that the income from Polish Day was more than nineteen hundred dollars, while the expenses totaled more than fourteen hundred. The cash remaining in the Central Committee's treasury amounts to $466.97. In addition to this, the Committee has in its possession 1,542 unsold Polish Day badges. The report was checked and accepted; due to lack of space, we will publish it in tomorrow's issue.</p>
   <p>From the sum of $446.97 [sic], it was decided to reserve $150 for the purchase of gold medals for the societies which participated in the contest at the Stock Pavilion, and $30 for the printing and distribution of a Commemorative pamphlet. The sum of $286.97 remained. It will be disposed of as follows: $25 to the small Polish church in Cragin, and $251.97 to the Kosciusko Monument <pb facs="5423968_5_1383.jpg" n="2"/>Fund. The remaining 1,542 badges will be sold at cost price, that is, five cents each. The Committee will appeal to the public to buy up these badges, which will serve as a memento of the occasion to all Poles. They can be purchased at the home of W. Bardonski, corner of Noble and Ingraham Streets. The income from the sale of these badges will be donated, half to the Kosciusko Monument Fund and half to the fund for the erection of a Polish-American pavilion at the Lwow Exposition.</p>
   <p>The Committee's secretary, H. Nagiel, was instructed to prepare the Polish Day pamphlet as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>K. Zychlinski was instructed to procure the gold medals for the contest winners. The medals will be presented with appropriate ceremonies at Pulaski Hall. Zychlinski was also instructed to engage the hall for this purpose. Any income from these exercises will be donated to the Pulaski Hall Foundation. After the above decisions were made, the meeting was adjourned until such a time as when the remaining badges are all sold, at which time its activities will be at an end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
