<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chopin Chorus Gives Jubilee Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHOPIN CHORUS GIVES JUBILEE CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chopin Chorus Number One of the Polish Singers' Alliance gave a concert on Sunday, September 1, 1918, commemorating the thirty years of its existence. The concert was given before an overflowing attendance in the Polish Roman Catholic Union's spacious hall.</p>
   <p>The program was arranged as follows. The concert was opened with a brief speech by Mr. R. J. Goszczynski, president of the Chopin Chorus. This was followed immediately by choral renditions of the American anthem and a Polish song entitled "Z Dymem Pozarow". The next speaker was the Reverend C. Sztuczko, pastor of Holy Trinity Church. After this the Chorus sang a typical Polish pastoral entitled "Dworek Polski" and followed immediately with an operatic aria, the "Anvil Chorus". A duet composed of Messrs. B. J. Zalewski, director of the Chorus, and M. J. Nowakowski sang the beautiful "Autumn Song" (Piesn Jesienna). The Chorus [then] sang the "Dance of the Skeletons" (Taniec <pb facs="5423968_5_0628.jpg" n="2"/>Szkieletow). Mr. T. Serdiuk sang an aria from the well-known Polish opera "Halka".</p>
   <p>After a brief intermission the second half of the program began. It was opened by an orchestral and choral rendition of Chopin's "Funeral March". Mrs. A. L. Zebrowska-Perlowska then played a violin solo entitled "Carnival Russe," by Wieniawski. This piece was rendered with such masterly perfection that the audience insisted that the talented soloist play an encore, and she complied, playing the "Barcarole". The Chopin Chorus next was called upon to sing "The Dawn of Liberty" (Swit Wolnosci). A quartet composed of Messrs. Serdiuk, Boguszewski, Nowakowski, and Zalewski followed with a composition entitled "The Lonely Rose" (Samotna Roza). In conclusion the Chopin Chorus sang two Polish folk songs.</p>
   <p>The entire program was exceptionally well executed, and the selection of numbers was good. Everything was satisfactory except the last folk song, which <pb facs="5423968_5_0629.jpg" n="3"/>was merely an adaptation from the Ukrainian. Polish critics of music had previously called the Chopin Chorus' attention to [the fact that] this song [was foreign]. It is felt that there was sufficient time to replace the Ukrainian folk song by some Polish national piece. It is almost impossible to comprehend why we Poles resort to insignificant adaptations of [the music of] other nations. We have an abundance of our own beautiful Polish songs and should be proud to sing them before any audience and even more so before our own people. No insignificant adaptation can compare in beauty with our original Polish songs.</p>
   <p>This is not the only point of criticism. There still remains the patriotic aspects. We should remember, especially now, that the Ukrainians have cast calumnious aspersions upon our people. In return, instead of resenting their attitude, we sing Ukrainian adaptations at our jubilee concerts. The Ukrainians at the present time are our open and most confirmed enemies. They are prepared to exert every ounce of their energy to do us harm. Let us bear this in mind.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0630.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Music and international choral renditions should be recognized, that is true. But it must also be remembered that during these exceptional times German music and songs are ostracized by all the Allied nations. Why, then, should we tolerate the songs of our enemies?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
