<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-01">April 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Chopin Nite</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-01">April 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CHOPIN NITE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An evening musical under the auspices of the Chopin Choir, which is afilliated with The Polish Singer's Alliance of America, was held last night in Walsh's large Hall to honor the Master, Fredrick Chopin. The stage was suitably decorated. There mere flags, flowers and a large portrait of Chopin in the center, surrounded by palms and floral displays. A surprisingly large audience was assembled, and the general conduct and order was commendable. The program was short but well arranged and performed with a brilliance that commanded the undivided attention of all. Mr. F. Przybylski, leader of the orchestra of 16 musicians, rendered many selections from Chopin's works, including "Nocturne", Op. 9., No. 2, and the famous "Funeral March".</p>
   <p>Our musicians, fascinated by Chopin's melodies, played excellently to the great delight of the audience who applauded generously. Many encores were given. A Tribute to Chopin was sung by the Chopin Choir, under the direction of Mr. Rybak; and also sang "Chopin's Funeral March". It was apparent that every member of this choir as well as the director had put forth his best effort; the selection were masterfully performed and justified the prolonged applause. Appropriate speeches were made by the Reverend W. Zapala and Mr.S. Orpiszewski, each one paying homage to the memory of this Great Man and his immortal compositions which have within them simplicity, but do not fail to inspire in the Polish heart the feeling which he poured into every selection, every note.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0727.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speeches commanded the undivided attention of the audience. Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, honorary member of the Singer's Alliance and a well-known singer, selected "Czyjai Wina" (Who is at Fault) and "Gdybym Jabyta Stoneczkiem Naniebie (If only I were the sun in the Heavens,) for the vocal part of the program. Her efforts were rewarded with well sustained applause.</p>
   <p>Another solo selection, "Leca Liacie Zdrzewa," (The Leaves are Falling) was sung by Miss Helen Kemoski. Her sonorous voice evoked intense admiration and the audience insisted on many encores.</p>
   <p>The Senior Women's Choir, Halka, gave the Chopin slection "Pozegnanie" (Farwell) and an encore.</p>
   <p>A collection for the benefit of the Siner's Alliance netted $23.97.</p>
   <p>We also wish to announce that the master of ceremonies for the evening was Mr. I. Stankiewigz, president of the Chopin Choir; he was assisted by Mr. Joseph Chmielinski, president of the Western Division of the Polish Singers Alliance of America. After thanks were extended to the public for their large attendance and good conduct, the musicale closed with group singing of the national hymn "Boze Cos' Polske" (God who created Poland).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0728.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The audience, homeward bound, retained lingering memories of an inspirational eveing, dedicated to the great master Chopin, whose works comprised the major part of the program.</p>
   <p>It is fitting to give all due credit to the Chopin Choir who made this spiritual feast and the development of Polish music possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
