<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-07-29">July 29, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Concert Staged by Polish School of Music a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-07-29">July 29, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT STAGED BY POLISH SCHOOL OF MUSIC A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Young Polish pupils of Miss Mary Hayne, who is the teacher of ballet dancing in Mr. Jasinski's school of music were very successful in their task. If we want to be progressive and keep up with the times, we must create new fields of culture and art. To that progress in art, in our Chicago Polish settlement, undoubtably belong the idealistic activities of Mr. Jasinski's musical institution. This school of Music exercises a vital influence on the community, and serves as an encouragement for others by its recitals, concerts and other musical entertainments. Even the American public of artistic taste has learned about it from the articles which have appeared in the English press. Some of these articles were very complimentary.</p>
   <p>Last Friday's performance of ballet dancing, under the direction of Miss Mary Hayne, met with a great triumph. Miss Mary Hayne is a very competent instructor of ballet dancing, who applies the latest scientific methods in her instruction including the knowledge of anatomy and psychology and <pb facs="5423968_5_0576.jpg" n="2"/>implanting simultaneously in the pupils the principles of ethics and aesthetics. It is an undeniable fact that Mr. Jasinski's School of Music is a first class institution, because, the public who attended its last ballet dance was greatly charmed by the performance. Each number was performed with such great skill, and there was such a great variety of numbers that the public was enthused during its entire performance.</p>
   <p>It was hard to tell which number was the best because the public applauded every act tremendously. Besides the ballet dancing there were also other acts. A note worthy of praise should be given to the senior and junior orchestras which played several selections under the direction of Mr. Jasinski. Mr. W. Malinowski, a young Polish violinist, played "Hungarian Dance" by Brahms, for which he was greatly applauded and he obliged his audience with an encore. At the close of the performance Mr. Jasinski introduced Miss Mary Hayne, the ballet dancing instructor, to the audience and lauded her untiring efforts in the field of fine arts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0577.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The audience expressed its appreciation by long applause. We wish Mr. Jasinski's Music School success. The school is located at 1110 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
