<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution on the Death of Anthony Mallek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION ON THE DEATH OF ANTHONY MALLEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now when the great war rages in Europe, inexorable death, as though mocking our fate, strikes in our ranks, taking away our leaders and Poland's best sons, not only on Polish soil but in all the countries where thay have gathered to work for her deliverance from bondage.</p>
   <p>Here we stand at the bier in which rest the remains of Anthony Mallek, our dear brother in the Alliance, indefatigable worker in the nationalistic field and in the Alliance, the first composer and father of Polish song in America, secretary general of the Polish National Alliance, a citizen of great virtues and deserts.</p>
   <p>Whereas, Anthony Mallek, as one of the first pioneers of the Polish emigres in the United States, continued from beginning to end in his noble work for the homeland; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Anthony Mallek took over the office of secretary general of the Alliance at the eighth convention, at a most difficult and critical time, when from <pb facs="5423968_5_0454.jpg" n="2"/>all sides thunderbolts were being hurled at our small ranks in an attempt to break them up and destroy them, and to bury the patriotic work begun by the Alliance; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Anthony Mallek, as secretary general, persevered in his policy, and by great effort, tact, and good advice saved our organization from destruction; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That the members of the Central Board of Directors, gathered today at their meeting of February 5, 1917, motivated by deep grief at the loss that the Alliance bears through the loss of this fearless champion, honor him by rising; and be it futher</p>
   <p>Resolved, That they shall be guided by his example and will persevere in the work for the homeland to the end; and be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That this memorial resolution be entered in the minutes and published in the Alliance publications for the information of all brothers <pb facs="5423968_5_0455.jpg" n="3"/>and sisters in the Alliance, and that a copy of this resolution he sent to the family of Anthony Mallek with expressions of deep sympathy in the sorrow which has unexpectedly been visited upon them.</p>
   <p><gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, president</p>
   <p><gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, secretary general</p>
   <p><gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, treasurer</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
