<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-11-15">Nov. 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Modjeska Stages Benefit Performance at Grand Opera House for Polish Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-11-15">Nov. 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">MODJESKA STAGES BENEFIT PERFORMANCE AT GRAND OPERA HOUSE FOR POLISH HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the inclement weather a near capacity crowd of Poles, Americans, and people of other nationalities attended the performance of "Mary Stuart," a benefit show staged by Helen Modrzejewska [Mme. Modjeska] for the Polish Hospital, at the Grand Opera House last night. The house would have been sold out, but some of the people misunderstood and thought that the play was going to be performed in Polish.</p>
   <p>The performance was excellent. Our star displayed the acme of acting, which inspired her supporting cast to give their best. Applause was not stinted as the curtain fell at the close of each act.</p>
   <p>After the third act, the queen of the dramatic stage was given a beautiful bouquet of fresh roses trimmed with golden lace, a token of appreciation from the Polish editors of Chicago. Mme. Modjeska also received a floral frame <pb facs="5423968_5_0567.jpg" n="2"/>with the inscription "Polish Hospital" made of small flowers, above which was a large star made of American beauty roses. The Polish actress was greatly moved by these two gifts.</p>
   <p>At the close of the first act, the Polish editors went backstage by special invitation and exchanged friendly greetings and, above all, thanked her for her kind gesture. They thanked her in the name of the Polish orphans and the Sisters of Nazareth. All regretted her departure when the bell sounded for the curtain to rise for the second act.</p>
   <p>Miss Proctor, who portrayed the role of Elizabeth, received a beautiful bouquet of flowers from the administration of the Polish Hospital at the close of the fourth act.</p>
   <p>This evening Mme. Modjeska is appearing in Shakespeare's immortal drama, "Macbeth"; tomorrow evening in "Camille," and Wednesday in "Mary Stuart." This is her final appearance on the Chicago stage this year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
