<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-20">Apr. 20, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Concert Staged for Polish Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-20">Apr. 20, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT CONCERT STAGED FOR POLISH HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unexpected death of Joseph, father of the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, brought sorrow to the entire parish of St. Stanislaus Kostka. This indirectly affected the attendance at the benefit concert staged last night, for the Polish Hospital, at the parish hall. Attendance, though large, was not up to expectations. This was unfortunate! The concert was extraordinary. Not only all the local talent took part in the program, but also all the first ranking amateurs who appear on the concert stages all over Chicago.</p>
   <p>The musicale was opened by the St. Cecilia Men's Choir, under the direction of Andrew Kwasigroch, singing the spirited "Polish Hearts". This song characterized the entire program--Polish songs and music for Polish hearts.</p>
   <p>Miss Lillian Roemheld followed with a violin solo, "Song without Words," which was made popular with the Polish people by the bow of the renowned Wieniawski. Her second rendition was Wieniawski's popular "Rondo elegant," <pb facs="5423968_5_0773.jpg" n="2"/>which captivated the audience to such an extent that at its conslusion the applause practically stopped the performance. After playing Brahm's "Cradle Song," the talented Miss Roemheld played Wieniawski's fiery "Mazurka," which was recently played, in Chicago, by the talented Polish youth, Huberman. Her rendition was of such quality that even the composer would have been proud to hear it. Although the vigorous pressure of the bow caused one of the strings to snap, the expert player finished the number without losing a note, or any of its melodic quintescence.</p>
   <p>One of Chicago's most famous singers, Mrs. Paula Biederman, who has graced many a concert stage, followed Miss Roemheld. "Herzens Fruehling" by Wickede, "Soguani Reverie" by F. Sehir, and "Yes Thou Art Mine" by Arnold Haymon gave the songstress an opportunity to display her talents. The quiet during the renditions and the applause at the conclusion, were just tribute to this concert star. Many bouquets of flowers were bestowed upon her by the Polish women. Although she is not of Polish blood, she was willing to take part in this program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0774.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The third number on the program was a piano, violin, and violoncello trio. Ralph Modrzejewski played the piano and the Messrs. Schauffled played the other string instruments. Mr. Modrzejewski's piano playing can be compared to the acting of his mother, Helen Modjeska; otherwise he would not be bold enough to ask the famous Schauffled brothers to accompany him. The Modrzejewski Trio was well received on the concert stage.</p>
   <p>An unexpected number followed. Mr. Kwasigroch presented a mixed group of young people from the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Choir. The choirmaster held the baton, Mrs. Mary Barzynska played the piano, and Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch stood at the head of this youthful choir. The hymns "Nolite Temere" and "Gloria" captivated the hearts of the audience. It would not be wrong to call this singing miraculous, and the choir could easily be representative of the Polish efforts in the United States. Mrs. Kwasigroch's singing was on a par with that of Mrs. Biederman.</p>
   <p>This review must come to an end because the writer does not feel capable of <pb facs="5423968_5_0775.jpg" n="4"/>imparting by the written word all the fine qualities of the concert. Those who are doubtful of its success are requested to ask verification from any one of the two thousand people who attended. Despite this large attendance, the hall was not filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>Among the many guests present, we saw Count Anthony W. Rozwadowski, Italian counsul in Chicago, and his wife. Both are great lovers of music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
