<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-05-08">May 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Holy Trinity Literary Circle Presents "Am I Intruding?"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ziednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-05-08">May 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HOLY TRINITY LITERARY CIRCLE PRESENTS "AM I INTRUDING?"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not meaning ourselves, kind reader, but that is the title of the play that is to be presented by the Holy Trinity Literary Circle on May 12th at the new Holy Trinity Auditorium. "Am I Intruding?" is a thoroughly modern mystery comedy causing laughter galore, and just chock-full of suspenses and thrills. It is different from all other mystery plays in that you know the villian from the start, and the mystery is revealed. But in this case we dare not disclose it until Sunday night.</p>
   <p>The cast consists of some of the best amateurs for whom the circle is prominent, and that includes Aurelia Dobkowski, Walter Merchut, Pauline Wilkowski Joseph, Theodore Slisz, Aurelia Jankowski, Joseph Gorski, Sophie Kuta, Stanley Jakubczak, Matt Woscinski, and Helen Kosturkiewkz.</p>
   <p>The direction of the play is in the able charge of Miss Florence Praczukowski, well known for her versatility in dramatics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0843.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The action of the play hinges around the efforts of Horace Vare, a wealthy business man, to keep from being frozen out of the Bluebird Motors Corporation in which he is the principal stockholder. Blair Hoover, an adventurer, acquires some notes of Vare when the latter is short of cash, and threatens to ruin him unless he will sell his Bluebird stock at a low figure.</p>
   <p>Throughout the entire play the rapid action brings about one situation after another in which are mingled thrills and laughs. The comedy is natural, not forced, and the interest is well sustained to the final curtain.</p>
   <p>"Am I Intruding?" as played by the Literary Circle Amateurs bring a new and distinctive type of play into the non-professional field. An invitation is extended to the readers of this paper and their friends to attend the Literary Circle presentation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
