<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-02">Mar. 2, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Dramatic Circle of the St. Stanislaus Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-02">Mar. 2, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE DRAMATIC CIRCLE OF THE ST. STANISLAUS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(We have received the following correspondence, with a request that we publish it in the Dziennik Chicagoski.)</p>
   <p>A meeting of the Dramatic Circle, and of those amateurs who wish the Dramatic Circle of the St. Stanislaus Parish would continue to exist, was held yesterday afternoon. The meeting was called to order by the pastor, Reverend Eugene Siedlaczek, who had issued the call for the meeting. The subject of discussion was the reorganization of the Circle.</p>
   <p>According to an announcement, the members present at the last meeting had decided to dissolve the Circle.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as the constitution of the Circle provides that the organization shall continue to exist so long as there are ten or more members (and at the time it was decided to dissolve the organization there were more than ten <pb facs="5423968_5_0983.jpg" n="2"/>members), and inasmuch as the members should have received written notification before such an important step was taken (and they did not receive such a notification), those present at the meeting yesterday voted to reconsider the motion to dissolve the Circle. They then voted that the society should be reorganized, and should continue to function.</p>
   <p>After this motion was passed, four members who were opposed to the continued existence of the Circle walked out of the meeting, and all those remaining--men and women--announced, that they wished to continue as members of the Dramatic Circle, and to continue their labors in the dramatic and patriotic fields.</p>
   <p>After a lengthy discussion, it was decided to revise the constitution, and three members were delegated to do this.</p>
   <p>The election of a new administration followed. The following were elected: John Czekala, president; Scczesny Zahajkiewicz, vice-president and dramatic director; Andrew J. Kwasigroch, musical director; Ladislaus Barwig, recording <pb facs="5423968_5_0984.jpg" n="3"/>secretary; J. Burchardt, financial secretary; John Nering, treasurer; F. Budzban, and J. Nowak, marshals; J. Kikulski, costumer; Miss T. Bock, costumer; J. Jarzembowski, stage manager; A. Drzonek, host.</p>
   <p>This concluded the meeting. The Dramatic Circle, therefore, exists and will continue to function.</p>
   <p>Ladislaus Barwig,</p>
   <p>recording secretary of the Dramatic Circle</p>
   <p>of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
