<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-16">Apr. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet of Polish Grocers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-16">Apr. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET OF POLISH GROCERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Society of Polish Grocers held a magnificent Easter banquet, which was attended by many members of the society and their families, as well as by many other guests. The two small rooms at Walsh's were filled with guests, who sat down at the heavily-laden tables to share the Easter egg [an old Polish tradition] and consume a good dinner, washed down with excellent liquors taken in moderation.</p>
   <p>Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, who was called upon to act as toastmaster, gave the blessing and said a few words to the assembled grocers. He congratulated them for organizing, not only for their own benefit, but for the benefit of the consumers as well, for, by pooling their buying, they can purchase merchandise cheaper from the wholesalers and thus be able to sell it to their customers at lower prices.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0061.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. S. Orpiszewski, editor of the Polish National Alliance publications, spoke in the name of the press. He stated that the Polish press had always supported and would always support Polish commerce and industry and expressed the hope that the Polish merchants would some day make enough money to support the Polish papers with their advertisements, so that the latter would not have to accept the advertisements of strangers.</p>
   <p>The following merchants spoke in the order named: Mr. Kasprzyk, president of the Society of Polish Grocers; Mr. Kowalczyk, secretary; Mr. Sokolowski, treasurer; Mr. Trebaczkiewicz; Mr. Buczynski; Mr. Przysiecki; Mr. Waszko; Mr. Napiorkowski; Mr. Kaszubowski; Mr. John Singer, director of the Polish National Alliance; Mr. Jelinski; and others. Their speeches dealt on the subject of raising the standard of Polish commerce and industry.</p>
   <p>During the banquet, our hungry brethren in Poland were not forgotten, since <pb facs="5423968_5_0062.jpg" n="3"/>$78.80 was collected for this cause.</p>
   <p>It should be added that the Society of Polish Grocers now has 250 members, and there could be many more if all the Polish grocers belonged to this organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
