<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-06">July 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Development of Polish Industry in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">International Photoplay Company Only Polish Film Company in United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-06">July 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOPMENT OF POLISH INDUSTRY IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">International Photoplay Company Only Polish Film Company in United States</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many readers of Dziennik Zwiazkowy have asked us for news concerning the sole Polish film company in the United States. That the film company exists is known even in the small country towns. But as to its capital, its officers, how it works, and what its prospects are for the future, little is known. Thanks to the courtesy of F. Szczepkowski, one of our reporters was able to visit the studios where Polish movies are filmed, and to gain the desired information.</p>
   <p>The firm's studios are located at 3501 North Kenton Avenue, near Edison and Milwaukee Avenues. From afar, the sign "International Photoplay Company" can be seen upon the brick building. The entire surrounding neighborhood is suitable to the studios purposes. On one side are the railroad tracks, and on the other two sides, empty lots heavily grown over with grass. Here and there are <pb facs="5423968_5_0051.jpg" n="2"/>trees in their springtime garb.</p>
   <p>Our reporter entered the studio accompanied by Szczepkowski. It was the noon hour, and so no one was in. In the center of the studio stood a table with actors' equipment, and in the corner stood the director's desk, covered with typewritten scripts; beside it stood a few inviting chairs, and all about the room were strewn pieces of heavy cardboard, used in the preparation of scenery.</p>
   <p>In the studio proper, which has a glass roof, there was no lack of boards, cardboard, and in general, all of the equipment necessary for the making of pictures. It took but a short time to visit every portion of the building. It remained but to step outside and view the building from the lawn surrounding it...</p>
   <p>In his conversation with Szczepkowski, who is thoroughly familiar with the affairs of the film company, our reporter learned the following facts:</p>
   <p>The International Photoplay Company was organized in 1915 by A. Czechowicz <pb facs="5423968_5_0052.jpg" n="3"/>and a few others. As with all other beginnings, the beginnings of this firm were difficult. Many obstacles had to be overcome, funds had to be obtained, and, most important of all, it was necessary to make a name for the company and to gain the confidence of the people of our own and other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Despite great obstacles, the affairs of the firm slowly but steadily improved. The number of shareholders increased every month. At the present time, the firm has about a hundred shareholders, representing an investment of more than fifteen thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The officers of the International Photoplay Company are as follows: J. Wojtalewicz, president; F. Szczepkowski, secretary; F. Szwed, treasurer; and S. Zielinski, director. The board of directors consists of Kaszubowski, Mancarz, Wielbacki, Kucharzewski, Snopek, and Czechowicz. The photography is done by S. Snopek.</p>
   <p>The firm has one traveling agent in the person of S. Snopek, whose duties are to rent out completed films to Polish and American theaters and to sell the remaining shares of stock to Poles of Chicago and elsewhere.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0053.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Director Stephen Zielinski, in the opinion of experts, possesses great capabilities in this particular field of art. It is his duty, in addition to selecting and training actors, to write out the individual roles, prepare scenery, and often even to write whole scenarios or create the more important episodes and scenes.</p>
   <p>The staff of players consists of well-known Polish actors and actresses of Chicago. The less important roles are played by the more talented amateurs and lovers of the stage. Often, for special roles, professional people are hired. For example, an actual coachman plays the role of a coachman, an actual policeman that of a policeman, and so on.</p>
   <p>The surrounding neighborhood has plenty of roads, farms, houses, woods, rivers, and so on, and is entirely suitable for this kind of work.</p>
   <p>At present, the International Photoplay Company has on hand four full-length feature pictures with Polish subtitles. These, known already to many of our countrymen, are:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0054.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Freedom: Here and There", two thousand feet of film; "Zdymem Pozarow" [With the Smoke of the Conflagration], seven thousand feet; "Hypcio and Hypcio at the Summer Resort", fifteen thousand feet, and "Engaged After Death", two thousand feet. Other pictures are nearing completion.</p>
   <p>We shall not stop here to consider the Artistic value of these pictures. As in all pictures, there are certain faults in these also. But they have a great many good points. One of their best points is the fact that these pictures have Polish subtitles, and are Polish in thought.</p>
   <p>According to Szczepkowski, the International Photoplay Company has good prospects for the future. The completed pictures are paying for themselves and making possible the production of other films which will soon be available to many Polish and American theaters.</p>
   <p>It might be well to add here that the only other Polish film company has suspended activities, making the International Photoplay Company the only Polish film company in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
