<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-10-19">Oct. 19, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Concert to Be Held for St. Hyacinth Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-10-19">Oct. 19, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT CONCERT TO BE HELD FOR ST. HYACINTH PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A benefit concert for St. Hyacinth Parish will be presented tomorrow evening at the Andrew Schultz Hall, 697 Noble Street.</p>
   <p>The concert will have a diversified program. There will be solos by Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch and Andrew Kwasigroch. Both will sing arias from the "Haunted Castle," by Moniuszko, a Polish composer. Miss Barwig and Mr. Kondziorski will sing the duet from the Polish opera "Halka". Songs by the St. Cecilia mixed choir are also on the program.</p>
   <p>Two piano teams will play duets. They will play Schubert's "Marche Militaire" and the "Awakening of the Wolf," by Katski. The teams are composed of Mrs. Kwasigroch and Miss Mary Barzynska, and Stanislaus Szwajkart and S. Kostka.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0817.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A violin solo will also be played by our well-known Mr. Kostka, who will be accompanied on the piano by Mr. Szwajkart.</p>
   <p>A zither and violin duet will be played by Mrs. Mueller, teacher of the zither, and Mr. Kostka. There will also be a mandolin and guitar duet. A mandolin orchestra is also on the program.</p>
   <p>The above selections and performers will give the public an idea of what it may expect.</p>
   <p>A dance will be held after the concert. This, however, is independent of the concert. The dance program has been prepared by the King Ladislas Jagellon Society. Popular as well as native dance music will be featured. Proceeds of the dance will also be turned over for the benefit of the parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
