<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-08">Jan. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-08">Jan. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unless our ears belie us, we can safely say that on January 24, 1915--the date set for Polish Day--American Polonia will really show what it can do. News has reached us that all Polish communities are making great preparations for a contribution drive that may add hundreds of thousands of dollars to the Polish relief fund.</p>
   <p>The more patriotically inclined Polish leaders and pastors of Polish parishes in the United States predict that all of the collections made in churches during that day will be placed at the disposal of one of the five central treasuries of the Polish Central Relief Committee. The example they set should be followed by others who have thus far done little or nothing for the cause.</p>
   <p>Polish organizations such as the Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish Falcons' Alliance, the Polish National Council, the Polish Women's Alliance, <pb facs="5423968_5_1192.jpg" n="2"/>and the Polish National Alliance have already issued appeals to their members, calling upon them to exert all their efforts in making Polish Day a success, for this day ought not be Polish in name only, but also in the results that it shows.</p>
   <p>We know that the councils of the Polish National Alliance in all of the larger Polish communities are discussing arrangements for a contribution drive on January 24. [Translator's note: The larger division, or gminy, of the P.N.A. were formerly called "communes" in English. The term in general use at present is "council".]....We repeat--the drive should not be limited strictly to Polish localities, but should cover the entire city and suburbs so that people of other national groups may also contribute to the relief of Polish war victims, toward whom the American papers are now so sympathetically inclined.</p>
   <p>It is a certainty that if the drive is competently conducted in the churches, the city streets, and before public buildings, it will have important results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1193.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The essential thing is not to be lazy, for a drive such as this needs honest, sincere effort. There cannot and ought not be any lack of willing hands in this task.</p>
   <p>[The drive is to be conducted during the day]; what, then, will be done with the evening? And the evening hours of Polish Day ought not be wasted. Let meetings be held on that day in all cities and communities where Poles reside; let vocal and orchestral concerts be held; finally, let the national exercises commemorating the 52nd anniversary of the January Insurrection[1863], be postponed. There is plenty of time for the January exercises, which can be held in conjunction with Polish Day activities.</p>
   <p>The most important thing is to ponder seriously on what is to be done with the evening of Polish Day so that it, too, can be really "Polish", dedicated to the Polish cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
