<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-11">Jan. 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Drama Presented by Dramatic Circle of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0967</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0967.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-01-11">Jan. 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DRAMA PRESENTED BY DRAMATIC CIRCLE OF ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The play "Dwie Sieroty" (The Two Orphans) was presented by the Dramatic Circle of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish at the Polish Hall last night before a capacity audience. Encouraged by the enthusiasm of the crowd the amateur players surpassed themselves in their acting, despite the difficulties of their lines.</p>
   <p>Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, author and director of "Dwie Sieroty," triumphantly announced that the difficulties of his play had been overcome by the capable cast. This was brought about through hard work, he said.</p>
   <p>Although the play was rather long--eight acts--it was over a few minutes before 11 P. M. This was made possible by the little time that was taken for intermission and between the acts.</p>
   <p>Who was the outstanding actor? Whose performance was the best? It would be <pb facs="5423968_5_0968.jpg" n="2"/>difficult to say because all of the actors played their best, including those that appeared on the stage for the first time. The outstanding feminine roles were played by Mesdames Tarkowska, Gorzynska, Jozwiakowska, Koppa, and Baczynska. The leading male roles were ably done by Messrs. Jozwiakowski, Nering, Kikulski, Brochocki, Czekala, and Drzonek. The most difficult parts were expertly acted by Mr. and Mrs. Vincent Jozwiakowski, who played the parts of the two orphans. Although Mr. Jozwiakowski's part was that of a crippled waif, his wife was not able to outshine him in the acting.</p>
   <p>Last night's performance can easily be considered the best since the appearance of Madame Helen Modjeska. The Dramatic Circle can be classed as the best Polish amateur group in America. It is evident from the number in the audience last night, that the Poles of Chicago are aware of this standing.</p>
   <p>Judging by the enthusiastic applause of the audience, it is safe to say that if the Dramatic Circle were to repeat this performance within the near future a like crowd would attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
