<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-22">Jan. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Allied Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-22">Jan. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALLIED BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Allied Bazaar at the Coliseum ended Saturday, and the ending was in keeping with the entire bazaar. Never have such crowds been seen at the Coliseum an there were Saturday. This is a great thing for us, because Saturday was Slavic Day, of which the Poles formed the most important part. A majority of the people called it, not Slavic Day, but Polish Day. That is why all who were interested in the bazaar were greatly pleased by the fact that more people came on that day than on any of the preceding ten days of the bazaar. It was estimated that more than 60,000 people were at the Coliseum Saturday. It is difficult to say how many of them were Poles. One can only approximate the number. There must have been at least 20,000 Poles at the Coliseum Saturday. The crowd in the entire Coliseum was so great that several times during the evening the main entrance had to be closed, and more than 5,000 people were denied admittance. The hall was so crowded that a special division of the fire department was called in order to see to it that a panic did not break out, because occasionally <pb facs="5423968_5_0900.jpg" n="2"/>some woman fainted and upset the people nearby.</p>
   <p>All of the Coliseum was crowded, but the greatest crowding was in the Polish section. At about 9 P. M. such a mob gathered about the pastry booth where Mrs. Preyss was holding forth that the counter almost collapsed. It was about to topple when someone succeeded in placing a beam under it just in time and was thus able to support it.</p>
   <p>Business in the Polish section was very good Saturday. Practically all of the merchandise was sold. At about 10:30 P. M. an auction was begun in the Polish section, at which practically all of the remaining merchandise was sold. The auction lasted until 1:15 A. M. The crowd laid siege to the Polish booth until closing time.</p>
   <p>Saturday's income in the Polish section reached about $4,400. Adding to this the income of the previous days and the money donated directly to the main bazaar committee, the Polish section has so far made about $17,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0901.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We wish to emphasize the fact that the accounting has not yet been completed, and that is why we are annopuncing only approximate figures. The exact amounts will be published in the Polish papers just as soon as they can be announced. The Polish Committee has already begun working on an accurate statement.</p>
   <p>We must now say a few words about all those who contributed so many beautiful items to the Polish section. They all deserve thanks. All the Polish people who so generously supported the Polish section also deserve praise. The success which the Polish section scored was remarked upon by all the other nationalities, which is a feather in the cap of all the Poles.</p>
   <p>We have stated that the[Polish]Committee is working on an accurate report, which it will try to publish in the very near future.</p>
   <p>As for the items which were to be raffled off, we wish to report that some have already been raffled off and others will be raffled off soon.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0902.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. K. Modecki, 1825 Thomas Street, won the motorcycle. The names of those who won other items will also be announced.</p>
   <p>It has been estimated that the income from the entire bazaar will exceed half a million dollars. The main committee and its accountants are also working on their report, which they want to complete and announce as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>One more thing must be said. How nice it was to hear first one and then the other Polish hymn repeated throughout the evening Saturday at the Coliseum. All the Polish numbers played by the band under W. Kowalski's direction were rewarded with thunderous applause, and when the band played "God Save Poland" and "Poland Is Not Lost," the crowd of thousands of people began to sing. How nice it was then at the Coliseum!</p>
   <p>In the smaller hall, where space was reserved for a cabaret, Mrs. Agnes Nering, our well-known artist, sang. Our well-known violinist Antoinette Zebrowski-Perlowski played, and Mrs. Smulski played the piano.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0903.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We repeat that an accurate report of the bazaar, giving a detailed account of each of the Polish section, will be announced in the Polish papers just as soon as it is completed.</p>
   <p>(Signed)</p>
   <p>Committee of the Polish Section</p>
   <p>of the Allied Bazaar</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
