<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-20">May 20, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Commentary on the Paintings in St. Stanislaus Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-20">May 20, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">COMMENTARY ON THE PAINTINGS IN ST. STANISLAUS CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(In today's issue of the Gazeta Katolicka [Catholic Gazette], a weekly, there is published the following letter from Casimir Chodzinski, sculptor from Cracow, who recently arrived in Chicago in connection with the Kosciusko Monument project.)</p>
   <p>After arriving in the new world I was eager to become thoroughly familiar with it. I tried as hard as possible to be everywhere, in order to get a good perspective of the progress of this great country. I have seen amazing things, improvements everywhere: huge factories, gigantic machines and practical buildings. But, despite all this, to my mind there was something lacking, for as an artist I was not searching for practical things but rather for the artistic. The monstrous and costly buildings are an eyesore. In truth one can find beautiful homes in some of the residential communities. These homes are of an original architecture, a transformed copy of the classical, often not conforming to any one architectural style. But although they create a <pb facs="5423968_5_0533.jpg" n="2"/>pleasant feeling one must search further for real beauty, because most of the cost is spent on making them practical.</p>
   <p>Among the monuments, statues, and sculpture, which should be works of art, one often finds ugliness. There are very few creative pieces of art, and when I did find something of merit it always turned out to be the work of a familiar artist whom I knew in Europe. I thought that I would find something of the artistic in the churches, since I am familiar with many churches in Poland and their interior as well as exterior works of art. I felt certain that there would be more concern about beauty here, but I was wrong. With the exception of the imported figures from Munich, whose beauties are familiar to me, I found the altars, pulpits, and general make-up of the churches lacking the sense and value of the artistic.</p>
   <p>How differently things have affected me since I entered the interior of the St. Stanislaus Kostka Church and espied the paintings of Mr. Zukotynski. I felt great respect for him, because I found that for which I was searching.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0534.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He immediately awakened the artistic feeling within me and fully satisfied my desires. I cannot say whether I have found another Krudowski, a famed Polish religious artist, one who can better depict the beauties of religious art. In everyone of his brush lines in the paintings one can see holiness and nobleness of thought and character, comparable to saintly life. Throughout the entire figures the lines stand out in their beauty, the flow of the drapes and garments and the color effect are pleasant and harmonious. Nowhere is there an imperfection.</p>
   <p>The painting of St. Joseph is outstanding. His countenance is filled with holiness and heavenly light. In the figure of St. John Cantius one readily sees the simplicity of character, the humility, the venerableness, and under all this one sees a great learned man, as the man himself was. The flow of the drapes on the figures of St. Stanislaus, St. Adalbert, and St. Cyril was greatly to my liking. Perhaps I was not thoroughly satisfied with the beard on St. Stanislaus, but that is because I am accustomed to another type. But one cannot criticize Zukotynski for this because he adhered more closely to <pb facs="5423968_5_0535.jpg" n="4"/>historical facts. The painting in the center, over the main altar, is or St. Stanislaus Kostka kneeling before the Blessed Virgin, who holds the Child Jesus. This is of unusually charming composition, as well as of religious beauty. There is a good tonal quality of colors between the two figures and a contrast with the angels that are overhead.</p>
   <p>The artist should be congratulated for his talent as an artist, and may he make the most of it. Credit should also be extended to the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, for turning over the artistic work to such a capable artist. The people of the parish who so generously support their church, also deserve praise.</p>
   <p>The interior of the church, when completed, will be one of the outstanding in Chicago. And the Poles can be proud that they have a church where the walls are covered with our outstanding Polish patron saints.</p>
   <p>C. Chodzinski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
