<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-03">Nov. 3, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Bit about the Polish Singers' Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-03">Nov. 3, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A BIT ABOUT THE POLISH SINGERS' ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every Thursday's edition of the Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy is a semi official organ of the Polish Singers' Alliance. (That organization is joined in an inseparable union with the Polish National Alliance.) In each of these editions there can be found a separate singers' section, written by the capable editor of the Polish Singers' Alliance, Mr. Joseph Szwarce. This newspaper wishes to call the attention of all of its readers to this previously mentioned singers' section. It recommends that every Pole read diligently the information pertinent to the life and development of our choral group and the educational articles on the Polish national songs.</p>
   <p>All great nations hold their national songs in high esteem. Songs precede history. People begin to sing of great events in the life of their nation before writing or describing them. Poetry has its origin in songs, and from <pb facs="5423968_5_0705.jpg" n="2"/>poetry comes history. Fortunate, indeed, are those nations which can point with pride to great poets and singers in their early history, as, for example, the Greeks to their Homer. Songs of such narrators become the nation's priceless asset and fortune--a real temple of national spirit, an eternal, living source of love for the homeland, and an inspiration to great deeds. With the progress of civilization and the development of national consciousness, there develops also the educational power of national songs. The cultivating of this most noble of fine arts spreads from the rather small group of the chosen to the entire mass of people. Numerous choirs are formed in various cities and towns, and these in time become united in powerful organizations, in large alliances, and after some time they arrive at a point where nearly the entire nation sings of the glory and heartaches of its motherland, in the same way that the whole nation sings the glory of God in the temples and places itself under His care.</p>
   <p>Nothing is more proper than the elevation of choral singing to the dignity of a national institution. After all, it is not a plaything; it is intended to <pb facs="5423968_5_0706.jpg" n="3"/>fulfill the artistic needs of innumerable individuals, but it is a service rendered to a nation in a great and magnificent style. He who sings for the glory of his people serves them in a twofold manner: he elevates the listeners to ideal heights and at the same time he ennobles and perfects himself and thus enriches the nation with one more valuable individual.</p>
   <p>Let our Polish people therefore gather to our national choruses as they gather to the Falconry, to the military alliance, and to every other national service. Enroll in the choirs now existing, create new ones in places where there are none. No right-thinking Pole will begrudge either the time or the money used for this purpose. It is a beautiful expression of service which will repay its contributors a hundredfold.</p>
   <p>The combining of the Polish Singers' Alliance with the Polish National Alliance was an act of greater sincerity and better judgment. Work dedicated to national causes should be concentrated, not divided and dispersed into small sections. Only in unity can there be strength, only in a great organization can work be <pb facs="5423968_5_0707.jpg" n="4"/>done--work which does not burden individuals and is yet important in its results. One person alone, or a hundred, or a thousand, or even ten thousand, cannot accomplish anything great. Today it would seem that only millions of people could venture to accomplish important things, and, where they are lacking, hundreds of thousands--people striving toward one goal, marching in one direction. Every partition of people into various camps not only weakens them but also destroys the best efforts of those individuals who work a great deal and accomplish great deeds. If a hundred thousand people pull in one direction and fifty thousand in another, the national wagon will in fact move, but only with the strength of fifty thousand people, the remainder having been balanced by the opposite pull.</p>
   <p>In the lives of American Poles, organized for a national cause in the Polish National Alliance, the singers already occupy a rather prominent position. True, they do not approach the Falcons in numbers, but it is up to them not to remain too far back of the others. It is only necessary to understand the <pb facs="5423968_5_0708.jpg" n="5"/>obligation of co-operative work and the dignity of their position, and everything will be well. It is essential to understand that even for the singers, their greatest task today, besides developing their art, is organizing the Poles and gathering our people under our native banner. Let everyone work in behalf of his Alliance; let the Falcons pull to themselves, the singers to themselves, the military groups to themselves, and all together simultaneously to the only national and political organization of Poles in America, the Polish National Alliance. Only by working in that manner is it possible to increase the smaller special Alliances and, at the same time, the vast general Alliance, and, hence, perform a useful twofold task. Without this uniting, the conditions would be considerably different; people working for the smaller Alliances would harm the great one, and those working for the great alliance would harm the smaller ones. Instead of co-operation, there would be rivalry; instead of unison, there would be dissension; instead of good service rendered to a national cause, there would be an inadequate and less effective service.</p>
   <p>It is with exactly this in mind that the best people in the National Alliance, <pb facs="5423968_5_0709.jpg" n="6"/>in the Falconry, in the choral group, and in the Polish military organization, have worked so long and incessantly on the idea of unison. With this in mind they defend this idea even after it has become victorious. True, even today the idea has its opponents, but these antagonists are either conscious dispersers of national unity and solidarity or unaware but isled victims of these dissenters. The Polish people are therefore urged not to be swayed and misled by such evildoers if they should meet them. The Poles are encouraged to work in behalf of our songs, in behalf of our native art, in behalf of our Singers Alliance and, through it, in behalf of the Polish National Alliance as well, with the conviction and assurance that they work for the welfare of our motherland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
