<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-15">Oct. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Max Drezmal Urges Club to Continue its Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-15">Oct. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">MAX DREZMAL URGES CLUB TO CONTINUE ITS WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the close of a very interesting lecture on Henry K. Sienkiewicz, one of the most famous of Polish writers, Mr. Max Drezmal, a prominent attorney, made the following pertinent comparisons between the accomplishment of Poland's creative artists and those individuals, who, during their life time, receive much greater popular recognition for more money. Chopin, Mickiewicz, Sienkiewicz and other great Polish creative artists died poor in worldly goods, but they left for mankind, a more precious heritage. The fortunes left by men and women benefit only a few, usually the nearest relatives; often they are dissipated and vanish. The cultural treasures left by great thinkers, poets, writers, composers, and painters are the common property of the world. They can be shared alike by rich and poor, the high or the low, in fact all who are to devote a little time to cultural purposes.</p>
   <p>To the intellectual Titans of the previous century, this age, notwithstanding the great strides made in science and the wonderful inventions in general use, would appear grossly materialistic. A pugilist, for a forty minute exhibition of his skill with his fists receives far more money than Henryk Sienkiewicz earned during his 40 years of arduous labor. An Irving Berlin gets more in royalties for one of his insane jazz songs, than Fredric Chopin got for all of his beautiful compositions during his lifetime. I have noticed recently in the Time magazine that with the years names are forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1701.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The income in 1926, of one of the world's greatest women and benefactors, Madame Sklodowska Curie, was $1,500., an amount certainly less than that received by many frivolous movie beauties in Hollywood, for one week of posing before the camera. Such a state of affairs may strike us as unjust, but there remains this consolation that the publicity of the pugilist and jazz composer is transient. Outside of giving a momentary thrill, these individuals serve no useful purpose. In a few years they sink into oblivion, but the fame and influence of the great writers, thinkers, artist and composers endures forever. Their works brighten human existence, elevate the character, enable the mind, refine the taste, and broaden the human vision. It was, to promote those aims and thus counteract the materialistic and sordid tendencies of the times that the Polish Arts Club was founded.</p>
   <p>A more commendable organization among the younger generation of the Polish people, cannot be found. You have the good wishes of all right minded, public spirited citizens; and I trust, that among the many talented members of your organization, some day we will discover a budding Matejko, Paderewski, Mickiewicz and a Henry Sienkiewicz, whom the English writer, Monica Gardner, justly refers to as the "patriot Novelist of Poland."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
