<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-27">May 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Philaret Chorus Gives Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-05-27">May 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PHILARET CHORUS GIVES CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual concert and ball of the Philaret Male Chorus was held yesterday evening at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall. Before the program opened, F. Trawinski delivered a short address, during which a "service flag" was unfurled. This flag bore fifteen stars, which meant that fifteen members of the Philaret Chorus had enlisted in either the American or the Polish army. The chorus then sang "The Star-Spangled Banner" and "Z Dymem Pozarow" [With the smoke of the conflagration], after which the Kipowski Brothers orchestra played the "Marseillaise" and a medley of Polish hymns. For its next number, the Philaret chorus sang the "Polonaise" from the opera "Halka," by Moniuszko. The solo parts were sung by W. Derlacki, L. Majewski, T. Kempski, and B. Dombrowski.</p>
   <p>Miss S. Jozefowicz then sang Jan Gall's "Roj Gwiazd" [Starry Skies] and an aria <pb facs="5423968_5_0634.jpg" n="2"/>by Moniuszko. The storm of applause that followed forced her to return for an encore. She was followed by the Philaret Chorus, which offered "Piesn Pastuszka" [Shepherd's song], by Lachman, the solo passage being sung by J. Ernest. P. S. Kozuch then sang Gall's "Piesn Ludowa" [Folk song], and was forced to give an encore by the seemingly unending applause.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the Chorus sang "Balada C Florianie Szartm "[Ballad of Florian the Gray], by Moniuszko. The solo passage was sung by F. Kempski.</p>
   <p>The Polish Army Band from Camp Kosciuszko at Niagara-on-the-Lake was also to have taken part in the program, but did not arrive at the hall on time because it was delayed at the concert it was giving in Hawthorne. The band finally arrived, however, about midnight, but the boys were very tried after having played all day in various parts of the city. In view of this, they played one number and retired.</p>
   <p>It must be mentioned here that all of the numbers on the program were executed in very fine style. The Philarets sang very well, as is usual with them; they <pb facs="5423968_5_0635.jpg" n="3"/>can hold their own with any Polish chorus.</p>
   <p>The ball was held after the conclusion of the concert program and continued until late at night. A good time was had by all, as is usual at Philaret affairs. The attendance was rather smaller than expected, but this was probably due to the hot weather.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
