<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Halka Chorus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE HALKA CHORUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Halka Chorus held a reception for its members on Wednesday, August 28, 1918, at the Eckhart Park Hall, commemorating the ten years of its existence. Founders of the choral organization, who even today are well-known popular members, as well as all the more recent members, were present at the banquet. On this occasion the Halka Chorus surprised Miss Marie Mysliwiec, president of the organization and a member of the group from its very beginning. Mrs. W. Przybylska, on behalf of the Chorus presented Miss Mysliwiec with a golden lyre as a token of appreciation for her sincere and untiring work. Miss Mysliwiec thanked her choral friends, adding that it is not her intention to work merely for high honors, but that her primary purpose is the preservation of Polish songs, which as a true Pole she values above all others. In the course of the reception Misses J. Kmiecik and W. Bandysz delivered beautiful declamations. This was followed by two piano solos rendered by the two <pb facs="5423968_5_0632.jpg" n="2"/>charming and talented sisters, Misses W. Hejnal and E. Hejnal. The reception was concluded by the singing of the Polish national anthem, "God Save Poland," by the entire group.</p>
   <p>A jubilee concert of the Halka Chorus will be given on the 13th of October, 1918, at the Polish Women's Alliance hall. The program, according to the committee, will be exceptionally well rendered.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
