<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-02">Oct. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Central Committee Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-02">Oct. 2, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY CENTRAL COMMITTEE MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The seventh consecutive meeting of the Polish Day Central Committee was held on Saturday, September 30.</p>
   <p>The unfinished business of the last meeting was first attended to. [K.] Zychlinski again raised the question of participation of two floats from St. Adelbert's Parish in the Chicago Day [parade]. In accordance with a motion by Zychlinski, a hundred dollars was appropriated from the Committee's treasury to cover the cost of participation. The [Polish National Alliance] float, "Third of May," will also participate, at the Central Administration's expense.</p>
   <p>A. Stefanowicz reported, in behalf of the Committee to take charge of visitors, that no suitable quarter could be found for the Kosciusko Guard [Milwaukee]. A new committee, consisting of Stefanowicz, [F.] Smietanka, and Kozlowski, was instructed to request the State militia for space in its local barracks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1459.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee on decorations was instructed to complete the decoration of Festival Hall with the addition of the Polish arms and two Polish flags; twenty-five dollars was appropriated for this purpose. The committee was also instructed to inquire of the Fair officials whether it would be permissible to hang a Polish flag in front of the building. The committee is to report at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>The publicity committee is to arrange for the printing of a hundred and fifty decorated tickets and invitations (in English), to be distributed among prominent American citizens, officials, priests, representatives of Polish organizations, etc. Seats will be reserved for holders of these tickets. The committee was also instructed to order two thousand tickets, which will be placed on sale, and five thousand programs for the celebration at Festival Hall. Programs of the parade and the celebration will be published in both Polish and American papers.</p>
   <p>Next followed the parade committee's report. The original route of the parade, which was to have gone through the center of the city, had to be changed after a conference with police officials. The parade will start at Union Park, <pb facs="5423968_5_1460.jpg" n="3"/>proceeding down Jackson Boulevard to Michigan Avenue, thence to Twelfth Street. From Twelfth Street, it will turn up Michigan Avenue and the Lake Front to Van Buren. This route was accepted by the gathering. The parade committee was instructed to complete the parade program by indicating the time and place at which each division of the parade is to meet.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of arrangements for the celebration at Festival Hall reported some changes in the musical portion of the program.</p>
   <p>[K.] Zychlinski, in behalf of the committee in charge of the contests to be held at the Stock Pavilion, reported that three contests are planned--one in gymnastic drill, another in Cadet's drill, and a third in military drill. A gold medal will be awarded to the winning group in each contest. The contest judges are to be Peter Kiolbassa, [M. A.] La Buy, Captain Slupecki, Captain Z. Schmidt, and K. Zychlinski. Contest rules will soon be announced through the newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1461.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It was further decided that sixty-two special badges will be made for members of the Central Committee. Special invitations will be sent to Archbishop Feehan, Governor Altgeld, and Erasmus Jerzmanowski, of New York.</p>
   <p>Efforts have already been made to have all Polish policemen released from their duties on that day, so that they may lead the parade in a body. Police authorities have tentatively agreed to permit this; a list of Polish policemen has been submitted to Polish Headquarters.</p>
   <p>Judge La Buy, treasurer, reported that the following additional societies have paid their fifteen-cent-per-member assessment:</p>
   <p>King Casimir's Society (50 members), $7.50; St. Vincent De Paul Society, of Immaculate Conception Parish, South Chicago (100 members), $15.00; St. Joseph League, Immaculate Conception Parish (60 members), $9.00. In addition, J. Dudek, of South Chicago, collected $7.50 from private individuals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1462.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The meeting adjourned after a few more pertinent matters had been discussed. The next meeting, which will probably be the last, will be held on Wednesday, October 4, at Pulaski Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
