<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-23">Aug. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day at Child War Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-23">Aug. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY AT CHILD WAR EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many prominent Chicago Polish leaders met in the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall on Thursday, August 22, 1918. The purpose of the meeting was to make intensive preparations for the forthcoming Polish Day at the World War Exhibition to be conducted in Grant Park.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of the World War Exhibition dedicates a special day to each nationality. The Polish people will receive their date, which will be between the second and the fifteenth of September, 1918. Judge Edmund K. Jarecki has informed the Polish press that Polish Day will be the fourteenth or the fifteenth of September, although this information is not official.</p>
   <p>This Exhibition is of primary importance, since we American Poles have at all times been interested in the affairs of this country. Our people have proved their loyalty to America so often and so actively that perhaps no one <pb facs="5423968_5_1167.jpg" n="2"/>can deny us the privilege of having a Polish Day at the Exhibition. But the oftener and the more emphatically we demonstrate to the American people our solidarity and strength, so much the greater will their sympathy be for our people. Poland today is an officially recognized Allied power having its own army on the battlefield. It is the nation which has been most persecuted by the three aggressor powers--Germany, Austria, and Russia.</p>
   <p>The meeting was presided over by the president of the Polish National Alliance, Mr. Casimir Zychlinski. He opened a rather lengthy discussion on how to make the forthcoming Polish Day a success. This task is of the utmost importance and will not be easy to accomplish properly. At must be remembered that now in the hot season it will be difficult to work. In addition to that two Polish conventions are now [regularly] held: the Polish Convention in Detroit and the Polish National Alliance convention in Pittsburgh. Because of these every Pole active in organization matters has his hands full. It will be necessary to summon all the Polish choral groups <pb facs="5423968_5_1168.jpg" n="3"/>for the occasion. Above all else it is important to make certain that all the tickets are sold prior to the Polish Day.</p>
   <p>President Zychlinski, after listening to the suggestions of numerous speakers, proposed that a committee of eleven citizens be chosen to be put in charge of the whole matter. This committee would have the power to include other individuals at will. It would also have the power to form subcommittees whenever the need to do so arise. Mr. P. Zrzozowski made the timely remake that it would be most beneficial to the cause to make use of the numerous civic committees already organized for the Polish army, together with their subcommittees, which exist in every Polish parish.</p>
   <p>Mrs. P. Korzeniowski proposed that new subcommittees be added to those already existing in the Polish parishes. Their duties would be to sell the tickets in territories assigned in their own neighborhoods. A lively discussion was held on the question of co-operation among the choral groups.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1169.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A committee was finally chosen as follows: Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, Mr. Phillip Ksycki, Dr. Walter Kuflewski, Alderman S. Adamkiewicz, Mrs. M. Sakowska, a member of the board of directors of the Polish National Alliance, Mr. V. Slasarczyk, Mrs. A. Baranowski, Mr. Joseph Niemiec, Mr. Paul Drzymalski, Mr. S. Soska, and Mr. Vincent Jozwiakowski.</p>
   <p>Particular emphasis was placed on urging the Polish people to purchase tickets for the Polish Day only from concerns and societies that are in contact with the Polish Day committee because then only Poles will receive credit for it. Those Poles who have already purchased tickets for the World War Exhibition are urged to attend on Polish Day so that this Day will prove to be the most successful even from the standpoint of attendance.</p>
   <p>With the completion of the general discussions the meeting was adjourned. The committee selected, however, remained in session and began work on the program of its coming activities. Judge Edmund K. Jarecki was selected as chairman of the committee. Judge Jarecki was already chairman of the Polish <pb facs="5423968_5_1170.jpg" n="5"/>committee to sell the third issue of Liberty Bonds. He also remains in constant contact with the central committee of the World War Exhibition. This fact in itself indicates that he is well qualified for the chairmanship of the Polish Day at the Exhibition and will perform his duties capably.</p>
   <p>Alderman S. Adamkiewicz of the Seventeenth Ward was chosen vice-chairman of the committee. He is well known for his activity and his ability. Among the women Mrs. P. Korzeniowski was selected as chairwoman of the committee. Mr. Vincent Jozwiakowski of the Northwestern Trust Bank was selected as secretary.</p>
   <p>Dr. Kuflewski made a motion authorizing Mr. Jozwiakowski to choose a secretary to aid him in his work. He also moved that the sum of fifty dollars be appropriated for that purpose, the sum to be charged against the prospective sale of tickets for the Polish Day. Particular emphasis was placed on finding a person able to place all his or her time at the disposition of the committee. This would prevent the necessity of the committee's relying upon borrowed help.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1171.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Work that is done as a favor is often cone unwillingly and as a result inadequately, thus doing more harm than good.</p>
   <p>With regard to the tickets it was decided to apply the old saying, "Strike while the iron is hot". Mr. Paul Drzymalski offered to place his automobile at the disposition of the committee. The automobile will be used on Saturday and Sunday, August 24 and 25, 1918, to visit all Chicago Polish churches and distribute tickets for sale. This task was assigned to Messrs. Phillip Ksycki and S. Soska and Mrs. M. Sakowska.</p>
   <p>Then followed a discussion on the position taken by the foreign press toward the Polish cause. Although this discussion was not in order, it was impossible to deny that Dr. Kuflewski was justified in this complaint that American newspapers give entirely too little space and attention to Polish matters. Mrs. Sakowska agreed with the position taken by Dr. Kuflewski, adding that we should exert every effort to make certain that every feature of our life finds its expression in the American journals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1172.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The next point in order was the matter of badges. One group favored a simple type of badge upon which should be printed Polish emblems and a picture of President Wilson. The majority, however, did not share in this opinion. They contended that the demonstration at the Exhibition is more for the purpose of gaining the good will of the American people. Hence, they concluded, the badges should be decorative rather than simple.</p>
   <p>It was also decided to leave the matter of obtaining estimates of the price of the badges to Mrs. Slusarczyk and Mrs. Korzeniowski. They were to give a report on this matter at the following committee meeting.</p>
   <p>Mr. Phillip Ksycki called attention to the importance of the Polish Day, since Poles only will receive credit for that day, and to the sale of tickets. He then requested the committee that in its future discussions its members confine themselves to the order of the day and refrain from touching upon other unrelated topics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1173.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Judge Jarecki proposed that representatives of all Polish choral organizations as well as all the organists be invited to attend the next committee meeting. A proper motion to that effect was made and unanimously carried. It was then decided that the next meeting shall be held on Saturday, August 31, 1918. He then explained that the entire affair will be conducted in accordance with the program of the central committee. He urged the committee to exert every effort to make the Polish Day a success. The meeting was then adjourned at twelve o'clock midnight. The next meeting will be held in the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
