<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-09-07">Sept. 7, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Brother Zeglen Invited to England and Germany</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-09-07">Sept. 7, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">BROTHER ZEGLEN INVITED TO ENGLAND AND GERMANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The French Consul put Brother Casimir Zeglen's bullet-proof vest under a personal test yesterday and was dumfounded by the results. He used his own revolver, which was loaded with cartridges using dynamite. Ten shots were fired at the vest, and in each instance the bullets ricocheted, leaving the vest intact. The Consul asked Brother Zeglen for newspaper clippings relative to the various tests held on this invention and promised to submit a favorable report to his government.</p>
   <p>In the meantime Brother Zeglen is to leave for New York City at the request of an official of the Japanese government. On September 15 tests are to be held in the presence of the Secretary of War, the Secretary of the Navy, members of the New York State Militia, the Chief of Police, and ambassadors from other countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0204.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Brother Zeglen also received an invitation by letter from London and Berlin to come to these cities and demonstrate the value of his invention.</p>
   <p>After his return from New York, Brother Zeglen will go to England, and whether or not he will go to Berlin from there is not definitely known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
