<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-26">Aug. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Polish Day Central Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-26">Aug. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE POLISH DAY CENTRAL COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Thanks to your initiative, gentlemen, there is no longer any doubt that a Polish Day will be celebrated. The only question that remains is how it will be celebrated. You are now considering this question; whatever you decide will, of course, be good and proper. Although I am a newcomer here and have not as yet had a chance to become acquainted with you, I hope you will be kind enough to accept a suggestion from me. I believe, as you do, that nothing that has to do with our homeland can be of indifference to us.</p>
   <p>"When the Polish Day question was still a matter for speculation, I read in Dziennik Chicagoski the list of floats that were to embellish the parade. In this list, I noticed the absence of one float--Polish womanhood--which cannot be omitted if the allegorical panorama is to be complete. If the aim of such a parade is to emphasize the important events in a nation's history, <pb facs="5423968_5_1529.jpg" n="2"/>then more so in our history than in any other do women occupy a noteworthy place. They have had this place since the very dawn of Polish history to its final hour--beyond it even, forming a glorious bridge between the past and the future. Wanda, who drowned herself in the Vistula River rather than marry a German prince [legendary]; Rzepicha [wife of Piast, first Polish ruler, also legendary], that first example of capable, hospitable Polish womanhood; Dabrowka, by whose efforts Miecislaus I accepted baptism at the hands of Bohwid and introduced Christianity into Poland[962]; Kunegunda, the saintly wife of Boleslaus, who discovered [the salt mines of] Wieliczka, the greatest deposit of its kind in the world; Jadwiga, that Lithuanian Dabrowka, who christened Lithuania and gave it and the Jagellons to Poland [1386]--what a splendid array of women! What nation can boast of its like? Later, there was Chrzanowska, whose valor exceeded that of the men at Trembowla [1675]; Teofila Zolkiewska, the hetman's widow....; finally, Emily Plater, who fought and died for liberty [insurrection of 1831]; and Mother Makryna, who by her saintly life, endeavored to appease God's anger.</p>
   <p>"And later? Later, the number of heroic women was counted by the thousands, and although there are no longer wives of kings or daughters of generals, the Polish woman arises--she is the wife of an insurrectionist, or an exile's <pb facs="5423968_5_1530.jpg" n="3"/>mother--and stands guard over the nation's memories. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Polko!'] cried the poet Mickiewicz, and in truth, no longer on the sword of her husband, but on the tear-washed prayer book, she teaches her children to rand in Polish, there where one is not even allowed to think in Polish. Often she must <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to save her child for Poland and for the Catholic faith. From the villages of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> all the way to the exile camps of Siberia, she travels the bloody read with a babe at her breast, leaning upon the are of her husband, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the tears of Poland 'in her hair', as the poet says, sowing the seeds of future vengeance.</p>
   <p>"Hail to our Polish women, who have aroused everyone's admiration, and who are feared by our enemies; it was not long ago that the Iron Chancellor [Bismarck] said that Polish we anhood is the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Polish nationalism (Polskosc).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1531.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Let us then pay tribute to Polish womanhood on so solemn and significant an occasion as Polish Day. Would that you could share by views,gentlemen! With this fond hope, I am,</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"Stanislaus <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
