<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-27">Dec. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The Gold Mine of Cripple Creek, Colorado</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-27">Dec. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOLD MINE OF CRIPPLE CREEK, COLORADO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>News has reached us from Cripple Creek, Colorado, where one of the Polish gold mines is located, that the production of gold mined daily is increasing.</p>
   <p>Count Henry Lubienski, manager at the Bonanza Cripple Creek Gold Mining Company, has recently returned to Chicago from Colorado. He will stay here a few weeks and is to come to some kind of understanding with directors of the mine relative to the purchase of steam-powered machines for working the mine. Count Lubienski says that work has progressed to such an extent that hand labor can no longer be employed.</p>
   <p>According to H. Lubienski, production of gold in various gold mines in Cripple Creek now exceeds a million dollars a month. The figures for October were set at over $1,500,000. He said that there are 173 mines in operation. Capital of <pb facs="5423968_5_0253.jpg" n="2"/>the East, and even of Europe, is beginning to show interest in these gold mines, and for the past few months speculation in the stock of gold mines began on the stock exchange.</p>
   <p>Count Lubienski became an active member of the mining exchange at Cripple Creek and in the adjoining town of Victor. Plans are being made to open a mining exchange in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Local exchanges play an important role, for they supply information as to the value of shares and the condition of the various mines affiliated with them.</p>
   <p>On the one hand they spread speculation, but on the other they prevent the public from being swindled.</p>
   <p>There have been American "gold mining" companies, shares in which were sold in Chicago, but which never owned a mine. Today, investment in gold mining <pb facs="5423968_5_0254.jpg" n="3"/>stock has been put on a sounder basis, one that is much safer for the public.</p>
   <p>It must be added that Prince John Sapiecha (son of Prince Adam Sapiecha of Galicia) is an outright owner of a mine in Cripple Creek.</p>
   <p>As to the Bonanza Gold Mine, Count Lubienski is its manager and Ralph Modrzejewski, of Chicago, is the president.</p>
   <p>During the absence of Count Lubienski, his wife manages the affairs of the mine at Cripple Creek. She resides in Victor, near the Bonanza Gold Mine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
