<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-06">Sept. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">No Foundation to Rumors of Bankruptcy of the Polish Gold Mine</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-06">Sept. 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NO FOUNDATION TO RUMORS OF BANKRUPTCY OF THE POLISH GOLD MINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Readers of the Dziennik Chicagoski probably recall reading an article we published relative to the rumors of the failure of the Polish gold mine in California. This fictitious story was released for public consumption by a certain Mr. "R," correspondent of the Kuryer Warszawski (Warsaw Courier).</p>
   <p>Mr. "R" falsely stated that the mine had defaulted, that it was unproductive, that the cause of this syndicate's failure was J. F. Smulski, and other stories.</p>
   <p>Our article, based on all known facts, repudiated the claims made by Mr. "R's" article and the Kurjer Warszawski was requested to rectify its error.</p>
   <p>Yesterday we had another occasion to see the treasurer of the Polish Gold Mine, Judge M. A. La Buy, who expressed his indignation about the false rumors that have been spread by the article in question.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0264.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To protect the interest of the Polish investors of this enterprise, we repeat the words of Judge La Buy:</p>
   <p>"If I only could get my hands on this Mr. 'R'", said the judge, I would certainly show him a thing or two. He is a liar of the highest degree. The company has failed! The mine operations have stopped--what nonsense.....Please take note about the following particulars as to how our gold mine is failing. As the treasurer of this enterprise, I received from California on August 5, eight pounds of gold, on August 20, five pounds and today, six pounds. This makes a total of nineteen pounds.....This is not bad!.....To this must be added the fact that the manager of the mine, Dr. Midowicz, has informed me that ten new machines have been purchased and put into operation. Work now will be doubled. In short, this explodes any grounds for the rumors. The mine is progressing rapidly. All obligations have been met and our interest is very sound. Attorney Smulski does not head any syndicate, but is only a stockholder, a member of the board of directors and secretary. This is the story of the status of our mine", concluded Judge La Buy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0265.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These are basic facts of the condition of the Polish Gold Mine. Judge La Buy has also stated that a meeting of stockholders of the mine will be held in two months, and in this respect all persons will be given an opportunity to find out the true status of this company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
