<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish-American Participation in the Lwow Exposition of 1894</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Dunikowski's Announcement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH-AMERICAN PARTICIPATION IN THE LWOW EXPOSITION OF 1894</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Dunikowski's Announcement</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"To my countrymen in the United States of America:</p>
   <p>"The Kosciusko Exposition--in which all Poles, from Galicia and other parts of Poland, as well as our brethren whom the decrees of Providence have scattered in other lands, will participate--will be held at Lwow, Poland, in the year 1894.</p>
   <p>"The Exposition will bring us closer together, giving us in Poland a chance to embrace those whom fate has exiled to other countries. We will each display the fruits of our labor and prove to the world that the Polish nation does not lag behind others but keeps pace with progress. We wish not only to display examples of our art, science, and industry, but also to present <pb facs="5423968_5_1554.jpg" n="2"/>a general view of Polish life--our activities, our trends.</p>
   <p>"Never doubting that the powerful and patriotic American Polonia would also participate, the directors of the Exposition have already set the matter before you in an appeal, which was favorably commented upon in your newspapers. I have been delegated to extend their sincere and heartfelt invitation that you take as great a part as possible in the Exposition.</p>
   <p>"I have already had the good fortune to become acquainted with you, my countrymen, as Poles who have not forgotten their mother country, and who received enthusiastically my idea of opening relationships with their brethren in Poland. This is hardly the time to describe to you the tiresome work connected with the realization of these plans. I wish only to call your attention to the fact that participation in the Lwow Exposition is an important step in this direction, for it will provide an opportunity for all Poles, especially those of Russian-occupied Poland, to become better acquainted with you. Let <pb facs="5423968_5_1555.jpg" n="3"/>no one suppose that because there are few Polish factories and business enterprises in America, the Poles cannot be represented at the Exposition. The directors realize that you are but beginning to establish yourselves on a higher level in American society by dint of hard and honest labor. They expect only such exhibits as you can send them. Send us photographs of your churches and schools, your books and newspapers, emblems and constitutions of your societies, statistical data of your national organizations, schools, migration of the Polish people, etc. Those in a position to do so may send us examples of Polish industry, Polish inventions, etc. Thus you will create a panorama of your activities and trends here on this hemisphere.</p>
   <p>"I have no doubt that everyone will do his utmost to bring these plans to fruition. I speak to everyone--to the Polish priests, to the teachers, the officers of societies, publishers, editors--everyone who stands at the head of American Polonia as a leader or educator. I appeal to everyone individually, whether he works with his hands or his head, to lend his support to this patriotic <pb facs="5423968_5_1556.jpg" n="4"/>endeavor. And with the necessary co-operation, it is a certainty that a Polish-American Pavilion will appear in the beautiful Kilinski Park in Lwow, and beside the Polish national flag will wave the Star-Spangled Banner of the United States. Thus will our ardent desire be achieved: that a Polish-American department, of which I have the honor of being a director, be opened at the Lwow Exposition.</p>
   <p>"With the purpose of organizing efforts in this matter, I have appointed, by authority given me by the directors of the Exposition, eleven commissioners, who will constitute a central committee for the entire United States. The following are the gentlemen who were kind enough to accept appointment to this committee: The Reverend Vincent Barzynski, Peter Kiolbassa, W. Smulski, S. Slominski, Judge [H. A.]La Buy, Dr. C. Nidowicz, W. Bardonski, Adam Szwajkart, M. Drzemala, L. Szopinski, and H. Nagiel.</p>
   <p>"The task of this committee will be primarily to decide what sort of exhibits <pb facs="5423968_5_1557.jpg" n="5"/>will be sent to the Exposition; besides this, it will appoint local committees for every Polish colony in the United States wherever there are people who wish to co-operate in this work. Immediately upon my arrival on American soil, a committee of this kind was formed in New York, which received my full approval plus the right to appoint new members.</p>
   <p>"I respectfully ask that all Polish newspapers copy this announcement.</p>
   <p>Dr. Emil Habdank Dunikowski,</p>
   <p>Chicago, August 18, 1893."</p>
   <p>The first meeting of the commissioners appointed by Dr. Dunikowski was held yesterday. Most of the members of the committee were present; those who were not, due to other arrangements, signified their willingness to accept the decisions of the majority. Father Barzynski, who was unable to attend, sent a letter in which he promised to take active part in the committee's work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1558.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>After a detailed explanation of the matter by Dr. Dunikowski, and a short general discussion, the committee decided to elect officers. The results were as follows: W. Smulski, president; Father Barzynski, P. Kiolbassa, and S. Slominski, vice-presidents; L. Szopinski, first secretary; A. Szwajkart, second secretary; and W. Bardonski, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The committee plans to begin its work immediately. At the first meeting, which will be held on Monday, the most urgent phases of the matter will be discussed. It is planned to solicit co-operation at the conventions of both the Polish National Alliance and the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
