<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Development of Polish Industry in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">White Eagle Dairy Company Flourishes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOPMENT OF POLISH INDUSTRY IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">White Eagle Dairy Company Flourishes</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Slowly but steadily, various branches of Polish industry are developing in Chicago, thus preventing those of other nationalities from profiting by the labor of our countrymen, and proving that, by forming companies and corporations, we can accomplish much. Our motto, "Patronize our own countrymen," which has been ignored for many years, stands again before the eyes of our brethren, reminding them chat in mutual support lies a great power, through the development of which our nation can stand high among industrial nations.</p>
   <p>Yesterday we wrote of the sole Polish moving picture corporation in the United States which, despite mounting difficulties, has grown each month until today its foundations are firm.</p>
   <p>Today we are writing of a Polish dairy corporation, the White Eagle Dairy Company, which was visited by a Dziennik Zwiazkowy reporter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0044.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The White Eagle Dairy Company is located in Town of Lake, at 4914-16 South Loomis Street, where for years Jews, Germans, and Irishmen have done good business among the Poles living in that community. The small group of Polish businessmen, who formed the company in May of this year, knew that the struggle with the strongly organized dairy companies of other nationalities, which have hundreds of thousands of dollars in the banks, would be a very difficult one, and that the competition against a Polish firm would be very great. But despite this, trusting in their own strength and in the good will of their countrymen, this handful of Polish businessmen did not hesitate for a moment in bringing its previously thought out plans into effect.</p>
   <p>Thus, in May of this year, a Polish dairy company was incorporated according to the laws of the State of Illinois, with a capital of fifteen thousand dollars. Whoever could afford to, hastened to obtain shares, and thus become a co-owner of the corporation. Shares were extremely cheap-ten dollars. Whoever felt that his financial condition permitted, bought several shares of stock, believing, naturally, in the success of the enterprise. Thus far, the <pb facs="5423968_5_0045.jpg" n="3"/>corporation has about seventy shareholders. The number is steadily growing, for more and more Poles are following the example set by the original shareholders.</p>
   <p>The corporation's administration consists of energetic and capable businessmen of Town of Lake. Michael Zaczek was elected president, Michael Czworniak secretary, and John Wieciech treasurer. The board of directors consists of the following: Casimir Tomkiewicz, B. F. Kowalski, John Kozubowski, T. Kozubowski, J, Wieciech, M. Czworniak, F. Zaworski, J. Kukulski, Andrew Twaroosz, Thomas Urbanski, M. Zaczek, Stanislaus Garpiel, and John Polaszewski. The administration and directors immediately rolled up their sleeves and went to work, knowing that work is the only means of success in life.</p>
   <p>Board member Tomkiewicz, well known P.N.A. member and proprietor of the drugstore at the corner of 51st and Loomis Streets, conducted our reporter through the entire building which houses the dairy company, and showed him the machinery and dairy equipment, explaining their operation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0046.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The building is divided into several sections. First, one enters a small vestibule which opens upon the office of the directors, and then to the dairy proper, which also is divided into several sections. In one section stands the machinery that purifies the milk, bottles and caps it, and sets the bottles aside.</p>
   <p>The process of purifying the milk is extremely interesting. The milk is brought directly from the farmers of Illinois and Indiana and poured into a great reservoir, from which it is piped to the floor below to the pasteurizing machine. Here it is heated to a temperature of 180 degrees Fahrenheit for the purpose of destroying any germs it might contain. The milk is then piped to the purifier, where all impurities and foreign matter are removed, the cleansed milk passing on to the cooling machine. Here, through the use of coils containing cold water, the previously heated milk is brought to a temperature of 38 degrees Fahrenheit. The purified and cleansed milk is then piped to a machine which automatically bottles and caps it and sets the bottles aside. A workman then moves the bottles of milk to the refrigerator in the next <pb facs="5423968_5_0047.jpg" n="5"/>department. From here, six horse-drawn wagons distribute the milk to grocery stores and private homes, although many people buy their milk at the dairy.</p>
   <p>The first thing to strike the eye of a visitor who pays strict attention to everything that is to be seen, is the perfect cleanliness of all of the machines through which the milk passes. The machines are of the newest type. Each of them, whether it is the separator, the purifier, or the cooler, or whether it is the butter churn or the cheese machine, or the machine used for cleaning empty cans and bottles, as well as the refrigerator, operates swifty and accurately. Throughout the whole process of purifying, heating, cooling, and bottling the milk, it is untouched by human hands. From time to time the dairy is unexpectedly visited by inspectors from the health department to make sure that everything is as it should be.</p>
   <p>According to Tomkiewicz, the firm is now worth $26,000. Business is in-creasing steadily, and the number of shareholders is also growing.</p>
   <p>Polish grocers, who at first eyed the dairy with distrust, are being convinced <pb facs="5423968_5_0048.jpg" n="6"/>that it is in no way inferior to dairy companies operated by persons of other nationalities. It is true that it does not operate on so large a scale as some German and Jewish dairies that have been in existence for a great many years, nor does it have hundreds of thousands of dollars at its disposal, but in respect to the purity of the milk it sells, it can match any other dairy in the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The price of milk from the Polish dairy company is the same as from other dairies. At present, milk is sold at ten cents a quart. The reason for the high retail price is the price demanded by the farmers.</p>
   <p>The Polish dairy is very troublesome to the Germans and Jews, we are told by Town of Lake citizens. In their own opinions, the Germans and Jews think they are especially privileged to do business among the Poles, to draw money from Polish pockets so that in case of necessity, they will have the wherewithal to fight the Poles. We have heard that agents of German firms are circling around the Poles like crows around a victim, casting aspersions upon <pb facs="5423968_5_0049.jpg" n="7"/>the Polish dairy. These methods should be condemned at every step. Our earnest advice to the housekeepers of Town of Lake is that they try the strength of their brooms on such agents, and that they stop using the milk of other firms and patronize the Polish dairy instead.</p>
   <p>In the development of Polish industry lies the secret of our nation's strength. If we organize companies and corporations, if we support each other and eliminate foreign leeches from our midst, we shall soon find ourselves among the strong and influential groups with which everyone must reckon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
