<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-02">Apr. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">New Literary Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1730</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1730.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-02">Apr. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEW LITERARY SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The interest of the Polish youth of Chicago in the study of their forefathers' language, history, and literature is growing slowly but constantly.</p>
   <p>That this is true can be proved by the number of literary circles and societies which are being organized to meet the demands of the young people.</p>
   <p>Many of our young folks are ashamed of the fact that, although they call themselves Poles, they cannot speak Polish and know nothing at all of the history and literature of the land of their forefathers. Therefore, our young people receive the news of the formation of a new literary group with joy, because they know that there they will be able to learn many things which they consider worth while.</p>
   <p>Yesterday a group of young Poles met at the home of one of their colleagues and organized a literary society, which will be called "Znicz" (Torch). Quite a <pb facs="5423968_5_1731.jpg" n="2"/>number of young men joined at this meeting, and the society's development appears assured, inasmuch as every member is required to bring in at least one new member.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the Znicz Society is to afford its members an opportunity to study Polish literature and history. It will also provide discussions, debates, speeches, and lectures on the most vital [Polish] national questions.</p>
   <p>The society plans to publish a literary and educational monthly magazine, in which original works will be published.</p>
   <p>More details about the plans and work of the members of Znicz will be announced in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
