<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 210,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Polish School of Music Is Advanced.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 210,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SCHOOL OF MUSIC IS ADVANCED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cultural and artistic life of our city is making slow but steady strides forward, organizing and developing more and more cultural outposts.</p>
   <p>Progress is being made in the field of music. The former Polish School of Music, as a result of the well-deserved success, which it has enjoyed, has been changed into a Conservatory of Music. The director of the former school, Mr. Stephen Sieja, who became known as an esteemed musician, singer and composer, at one time an active co-organizer of the children's choirs, invited on the 30th of the current month, the most prominent Polish musical artists to the office of the Conservatory, where a joint deliberation took place. After a discussion on organization matters, a program of activity was worked out. The Conservatory has three courses: lower, intermediate and higher. Everyone learning some special subject benefits without extra charge, from added lectures for six months on theory and practice.</p>
   <p>The professors personnel is composed of: A. Karczynski, M. Pierzchala, K. Knoch, T. Orzada, E. Walkiewicz, P. Kapalka, and Director S. Sieja.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0399.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The educational program covers playing instructions on all instruments and solo singing lessons, which will be given by an artist from the Warsaw opera-Miss K. Surzynska.</p>
   <p>This is the first co-operation of outstanding artists; some of them are the pride of music, not only that of the Emigration, but of the general Polish creative power of music. Besides musical talent, every individual mentioned has already done meritorious service in community and national work. That gives a guarantee that the Polish Conservatory of Music desires to give to society good and honest work and calculates on the general support of that society, which more and more values these noble impulses and diligent work. The central office of the Conservatory of Music is located at 1235 N. Ashland Avenue with branches in Town of Lake and Avondale.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
