<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-28">Apr. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Inventions and Patents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-28">Apr. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">INVENTIONS AND PATENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish work of developing inventions and applying for patents in America is running ahead of a normal pace. The Bureau of Patents, in its notices, has brought to the attention of all the many accomplishments of Polish inventors. In this field of endeavor Mr. Leon Chmielewski, Chicago painter and decorator who was born in Warsaw, Poland, has met with great success in securing patent rights for three of his inventions, all of which have excellent marketing possibilities.</p>
   <p>One of the patents is for a steam bath apparatus and cabinet which may be adapted to home use. The second is an adjustable surgery table which can be used for hospital surgery and likewise as an examination table for physician's office use. The third, perhaps the simplest and most practical of the group, is one which will find its way into every home as a domestic utility; it is an adjustable curtain and drape frame, constructed in such a manner that the housewife is able to hang her curtains and drapes and shades without climbing on chairs, tables or sills; thus many accidents will be averted. This new <pb facs="5423968_5_0144.jpg" n="2"/>device does not require any nailing or drilling into the wall or window frame.</p>
   <p>Mr. Chmielewski's articles are on display at his office, and he is daily receiving orders for them. If you desire any of these articles, or any information about them, write or call Leon Chmielewski, 22 Evergreen Avenue, Chicago. Phone Humboldt 1082.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
