<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-09">Aug. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Our Victory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-09">Aug. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">OUR VICTORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of whether the works of Polish artists now on exhibit in Jackson Park are eligible for participation in the competition to be held there, has been settled in our favor. The protests of the German and Austrian commissioners were in vain. It was finally decided that the Polish paintings have the same rights as all other paintings exhibited, and cannot be disregarded. The day before yesterday, the jury made a careful inspection of the Polish Art Section at the Palace of Fine Arts and judged the pictures. Naturally, the results are not yet known. According to information from a private source, the Polish section is said to have won eight medals, which, in view of the mere thirty odd artists represented, is much better than some of the other sections have fared. Among the artists whose paintings are supposed to have won awards are Matejko, Gerson, Popiel, Zmurko, Alchimowicz, Chelminski, and others.</p>
   <p>No matter how the awards will be distributed, the mere fact that the Poles were allowed to compete is in itself highly encouraging to us. The difficulties, <pb facs="5423968_5_1589.jpg" n="2"/>open and secret, which have been thrown in our way by the representatives of Austria and Germany, have been brushed aside. We have been given equal rights and have been allowed to compete with the others. For this, our highest acknowledgment should go to noble and free America--and to all well-meaning people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
