<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-16">Nov. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Polish Societies in Reference to Their Participation in the Lwow Exposition of 1894</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-16">Nov. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO POLISH SOCIETIES IN REFERENCE TO THEIR PARTICIPATION IN THE LWOW EXPOSITION OF 1894</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Stanislaus Szwajkart, of the Central Committee in charge of shipment of Polish-American exhibits to the Lwow Exposition, has sent the following appeal to all Polish societies in America. We publish it here for the benefit of those societies whose addresses were not available to the Central Committee.</p>
   <p>"The Central Committee in charge of Polish-American participation in the Kosciusko Exposition at Lwow has given the undersigned the task of preparing a treatise on the Polish societies in America. This treatise cannot be prepared without the help of the societies. I therefore request the societies to authorize their secretaries to send me the following data as soon as possible:</p>
   <p>1. When and by whom was the society organized?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1374.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. Is the society affiliated with any larger organization? If so, name organization.</p>
   <p>3. What are the aims of the society and, in particular, what benefits do its members derive from it?</p>
   <p>4. How large is the society's membership?</p>
   <p>5. What phases has the society passed through since its organization?</p>
   <p>6. Since its organization, how much money has the society paid out in sick benefits, death benefits, and other welfare causes?</p>
   <p>"Further, I request that a copy of the society's constitution be sent to me. Inasmuch as the task of preparing the treatise will take a great deal of time, especially as the data itself will constitute a considerable portion <pb facs="5423968_5_1375.jpg" n="3"/>of it, I must ask for the greatest possible expedition in this matter. Only a few days are needed to send me the necessary material; I have no doubt that the societies wish to be mentioned in the treatise, and I judge, therefore, that by the fifteenth of January all societies will have supplied me with the necessary information.</p>
   <p>"As to photographs of banners and [members] of societies, a special committee on photographs will issue an appeal at the proper time. At the moment, preparation of the treatise is of the utmost importance, and I ask again for the speediest possible submission of the above-outlined material.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Szwajkart,</p>
   <p>143 West Division Street, Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
