<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-01-25">Jan. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Literary Department Formed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-01-25">Jan. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">LITERARY DEPARTMENT FORMED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, January twentieth, the literary department of the Polish Arts Club, held it initial meeting, in the Crearar Library. Mr. M. Kaletta was elected chairman, Miss S. Kobylanski the secretary. A general discussion concerning the program to be followed resulted in the proposal of a lecture, from 8 to 9 P.M., a subject or author of Polish Literature, and a general discussion or reading during the second hour.</p>
   <p>The meeting will be held the first and third Friday of every month, in the classroom of the Crerar Library, located on the 12th Floor at 86 East Randolph Street. The next meeting will be held on Friday evening February 3rd, at which time Dr. Marie Krol will lecture on the works of the great Polish author Stanislaus Przybyrzewski. This subject was announced for the meeting last week, but, due to illness, Dr. Krol was unable to attend.</p>
   <p>Anyone interested in the serious study of Polish literature is requested to get in touch with the chairman of the Literary Department, Mrs. M. Kaletta, by calling Kildare 3766. On Saturday evening, January 28, the Dramatic Department of the club will have a theatre party at the Goodman Theatre of the Art Institute. Anyone interested in joining this group may secure all information by phoning Miss Jane Palczynski, at Spaulding 1346. The next lecture of the club will be held on Sunday February 12th, at the Art Institute. Mr. Alfonso Ianelli, a noted sculptor, will lecture on. The Prophecy of American Art.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
