<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 12,
<date when="1922-01-16">Jan. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Concert by W. Kochanski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0411</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0411.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 12,
<date when="1922-01-16">Jan. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT BY W. KOCHANSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> by <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Kochanski can be called a real success of the artist, and also a comprehension of the necessity of supporting our artists by broader masses of our public. The Polish public closely filled the concert hall of the Cohan <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>rand Opera <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, by which it displayed unto itself evidence of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the masterful artistry and appreciation of Kochanski's playing.</p>
   <p>The violinist played the "Sonata in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>" very exquisitely, but a slight nervousness could be felt which nevertheless did not flow unfavorably even for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> moment in the performance of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> composition. A great storm of applause was gained by the artist for his execution of the very beautiful and difficult composition "Faust," by <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Dance," by Brahms-Joachim and "Caprice," by Forilla was played solo by the artist with truly perfect technique, then "Romance," by Karlowicz in the performance of Kochanski can be called a masterpiece.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0412.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The public was enraptured by the playing of the artist, from which we can feel proud having Kochanski among our nation as the best violinist.</p>
   <p>It would be desirable that Mr. W. Kochanski would stay a little more after these splendid artistic treats not only downtown but in the heart of our Polish population; so as to convince the greater part of our public that music is the greatest artistry, that music flows favorably upon the perfection of characters. Unfortunately, our Polish people did not attend in very great numbers. The concerts in our section staged by local singing groups, singers, violinists, pianists, through non-support of the concerts, discouraged the willing artists into inactivity. Our Polish people stir only when a violinist of great fame arrives and our newspapers announce it day in and day out. It should not be so. Every concert given, whether it is by a great artist or a beginner, our even by a group of singers, deserves our support, because Polish music and song in a foreign land is the main factor in joining us with the culture of our brothers beyond the ocean.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0413.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is to be hoped that Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Kochanski will not overlook certain efforts, so that Polish music will be better propagated in Chicago. Our violinist was accompanied by Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Campbell, recognized by critics as an excellent pianist, and his playing yesterday belongs to the technically best. It is a pity that the public did not give more attention to the pianist, who played certain solo parts, and at the conclusion of playing by W. Kochanski, not waiting for the last tones, showered him with much applause. This is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> understood because we value our artist, but under artistic <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> it is proper to wait for the last tones of the piano.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
