<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 14,
<date when="1903-04-02">Apr. 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 14,
<date when="1903-04-02">Apr. 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the honorable Polish Undertakers and the Public in General:</p>
   <p>We are informed through the Polish papers that the Polish people in America do so little to establish factories, but the Poles with all their strength should endeavor to accomplish this. Therefore, the undersigned owners, after a long consideration, decided to open a factory under the name of Standard Coffins and Casket Company. Such factory requires a great deal of care and material outlay for which we are prepared, but what we need most is the general support, and therefore we call on you now, bretheren, and inform you that we have succeeded, and that a Polish factory of caskets is in existence on 110 Augusta St., where we already have a great selection of ready caskets in our warehouse for the customers who will have the opportunity to bury their relatives or friends in the caskets made by Poles. Our workmanship has been examined by certain undertakers and it was declared good; and those undertakers who have not yet visited us are invited <pb facs="5423968_5_0182.jpg" n="2"/>to come and for those who live outside of Chicago and in other cities of the United States of America, we, in the meantime, will devise a few of the new patterns, and at the same time, the prices. We appeal to you to support the Polish factory of caskets, which will serve you just as good as the German or the Jewish ones.</p>
   <p>The owners of the company and the workers:</p>
   <p>Mikolaj Kordel</p>
   <p>Bronislaw Roclawski</p>
   <p>Antonio Ostrowski</p>
   <p>Stanislaw Ambrozewski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
