<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 187,
<date when="1922-08-11">Aug. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Success of Polish Department at Exhibition of Progress</title><title level="a" type="sub">Governor of the State of Illinois, Mayor of Chicago and President of the Exhibition have visited the Polish Booths</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 187,
<date when="1922-08-11">Aug. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESS OF POLISH DEPARTMENT AT EXHIBITION OF PROGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Governor of the State of Illinois, Mayor of Chicago and President of the Exhibition have visited the Polish Booths</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the combined efforts of several Polish groups, the Polish department in the international section of the Chicago Exhibition of Progress on the Municipal Pier has been enriched with a new shipment of fine lace work, wood carvings, etc., sent by J. M. Rozan of Buffalo, one of the founders of the Association For the Propagation of the Polish People's Art in America, to which association belongs also Dr. Fronczak, former head physician of the city of Buffalo, who visited the exhibition last Monday at the invitation of the Main Committee.</p>
   <p>As we have already mentioned, the Polish department is rich, very diversified, narrow, however, because in a space of 200 square feet it is difficult to present properly the immense Polish economic development, its natural riches, its intellectual and artistic life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is plainly underlined in a historical pamphlet issued through the efforts of the Committee of the Polish Department at the exhibition, of which many thousands of copies have been distributed gratis among the American public visiting the exhibition.</p>
   <p>In every instance there is a Polish representation at this year's exhibition of progress, even if it emphatically stipulated that it has neither the right nor the means to appear in a general representative character.</p>
   <p>The Polish Department, enclosed in such a modest frame, is greeted sympathetically by the American public, and during the past week it was visited by the governor of the state of Illinois, the mayor of the city of Chicago, also the president of the exhibition, Dr. Robertson, who thanked our committee for arranging the Polish Department.</p>
   <p>The income from the Exhibition of Progress is to be used for the building <pb facs="5423968_5_1145.jpg" n="3"/>and establishing of a large dental clinic for the children of the city of Chicago. It is a plain fact that the Polish children, who have been somewhat neglected in this sphere, will benefit in a great measure from this institution. From this then, the visiting of the exhibit at the Municipal Pier is at the same time a voluntary donation for the cause of the health of our children. In this regard then we ought to speak strongly to the Polish people, including them to visit the Exhibition of Progress, and to linger just for a moment to view the exhibit of the Polish Department.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
