<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-10">July 10, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Contributions for Benefit Bazaar in Saint John Cantius Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-10">July 10, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">CONTRIBUTIONS FOR BENEFIT BAZAAR IN SAINT JOHN CANTIUS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The initial contributions for the benefit bazaar to be staged in Saint John Cantius Parish have been received. Proceeds of the bazaar are to go toward the completion of the new church building and a new school. Donations that were received by the parish bazaar committee are:</p>
   <p>F. Kobierowski, half a barrel of beer, 150 cigars, and six bottles of cognac; S. Dornecki, three boxes of soap; A. Szulc, two dozen bottles of wine; J. Gniot, one barrel of beer; J. Mrukowski, one hundred cigars and two cases of pop; R. Kotkowski, half a barrel of beer, 100 cigars, and two cases of pop; R. Kotkowski, half a barrel of beer, 100 cigars, and two cases of pop; J. Badura, half a barrel of beer and 200 cigars; Krupka, two cases of pop; A. Szykowny, one barrel of beer; J. Kepczynski, 100 cigars; John Kowol, 500 cigars; Max Pancek, half a barrel of beer; McCormick, one-fourth barrel of beer; A. Eltman, two cases of soda and six bottles of whiskey; Francis H. Naas, half a barrel of beer; W. Schmith, one case of pop; A. Czajkowski, fifty cigars; Sokup, one stove; N. C. Bartoldey, one bird cage; F. Wleklinski, ten dollars <pb facs="5423968_5_1231.jpg" n="2"/>worth of bread and one tart; R. Stobiecki, one table and one cradle; T. Suchomski, 18 live chickens; W. Dyniewicz, a book of songs; J. F. Smulski, a book valued at five dollars; B. Niemierowicz, six ducks, ten pounds of Polish sausage; Joseph Pankowski, two canaries and two pair of pigeons; F. Rominski, articles valued at four dollars; John Nowakowski, one live rooster; Kopielski, one coat and three suits; Majewska, articles valued at five dollars; Kosinski, stand for a mirror; F. Biedka, two hams and ten pounds of Polish sausage.</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to all donors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
