<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 8,
<date when="1915-02-24">Feb. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Merchants and Manufacturers Association in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 8,
<date when="1915-02-24">Feb. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH MERCHANTS AND MANUFACTURERS ASSOCIATION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish merchants and manufacturers in Chicago have finally grouped themselves into one association with the aim of cooperating in the work to be done in their field.</p>
   <p>About 200 Polish merchants belong to this association, which is already beginning to unfold a blissful activity for the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday, at 2 P. M., marked the opening of a bazaar in the Polish Women's Alliance hall for the benefit of the hungry in the fatherland.</p>
   <p>His Excellency Bishop Rhode accepted the invitation of the committee, which requested him gracefully to attend the opening of the bazaar so that with his talk he could start the work which should prove beneficial to the increasing of the funds necessary to save our poor countrymen suffering in want on account of the present war.</p>
   <p>The Polish merchants and manufacturers fear that the hall at the Women's Alliance <pb facs="5423968_5_0069.jpg" n="2"/>will not be long enough to hold all the well wishing countrymen desiring to participate in the bazaar and by this opportunity to come also into possession of several valuable and useful articles which will be raffled off. Every cent spent at this bazaar will not only help this noble cause but will also bring a marked percentage of profit.</p>
   <p>The bazaar will last three weeks as follows: Four Sundays, three Mondays, three Wednesdays. During all the days of this bazaar the Polish choirs will make the stay of those present more enjoyable with their singing and also the bar and the restaurant will be prepared to take care of the guests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
