<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement from the Polish Day Committee on Floats</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT FROM THE POLISH DAY COMMITTEE ON FLOATS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All Polonia, without exception and without regard to individual views, agrees that a Polish Day must be celebrated at the 1893 Columbian Exposition in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Our countrymen are already working to make this project a reality. A central committee was organized to take full charge; this committee decided that a magnificent parade through the city streets, embellished by floats depicting scenes from Polish history, should form an important part of the program. In accordance with the will of the majority, the provision of floats was left to the participating communities and to the representatives of various businesses and professions; the undersigned committee of nine was appointed to direct efforts along these lines into a general program, and to assist those who want to help in this way, in making the celebration a success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At its first meeting, on August 26, the committee decided to invite Mr. Brenert, S. Zahajkiewicz, S. Szwajkart, and K. Zychlinski to assist it in its work. Next, the committee made up the following list of possible subjects for floats:</p>
   <p>1. Washington, Kosciusko, and Pulaski. 2. Lithuania embracing Christianity, or Jagiello and Jadwiga. 3. The Lublin Union. 4. Poland at the height of its power. 5. Nicholas Copernicus and the solar system. 6. King John Sobieski after the battle of Vienna. 7. Constitution of the Third of May. 8. Poland in chains. 9. Literature and art (Mickiewicz, Krasinski, Slowacki, Kraszewski, and Grottger). 10. Scene from Siberian mines. 11. A Cracow wedding. 12. Slaughter of Unites [United Greek Church], according to Elias. 13. Poles under the American flag. 14. Resurrection of Poland (according to Elias' painting).</p>
   <p>Since this list may be inadequate, or the subjects not wholly satisfactory, <pb facs="5423968_5_1520.jpg" n="3"/>a new one will be prepared; in addition, each community or group of businessmen has the right to choose any subject that it regards as appropriate.</p>
   <p>In any case, the undersigned committee asks that all representatives of communities and business groups communicate their choice, whether it be from the above list or not, to the committee, at 141-143 West Division Street, or to announce it at the Central Committee's meeting, to be held at Pulaski Hall (800 South Ashland Avenue) on August 30. All such decisions must be made by September 10. This is absolutely necessary in order to prevent duplication. Complete details of any given scene will be supplied upon request. The float committee, by authority of the Central Committee, will supervise the production of the floats.</p>
   <p>We request the sincere co-operation of everyone and ask that the choice of float subjects be made as soon as possible. Declarations to this effect <pb facs="5423968_5_1521.jpg" n="4"/>already made will shortly be announced publicly. We are sure that this [project] will be given the greatest possible support.</p>
   <p>The Committee: H. Nagiel, F. Jablonski, B. Markiewicz,</p>
   <p>G. Kozlowski, M. J. Szameit, P. Wikaryasz,</p>
   <p>E. Wiedeman, J. Roszak, and W. Smulski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
