<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Mrs. Waydowa Leaving!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-known Singer Is Going to Detroit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">MRS. WAYDOWA LEAVING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-known Singer Is Going to Detroit</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>News has reached us that the well-known Polish singer, Mrs. Jeanneatte Korolewicz-Waydowa is going to leave our city in the near future.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Waydowa has just signed a long contract that will take her on a concert tour through many western cities. She will start very soon. Before the holidays, however, Miss Waydowa has ample time to go to Detroit.</p>
   <p>When Mrs. Waydowa had some free time she came to Chicago to give her support to the delegation from upper Silesia. We all know how much of her time she has sacrificed and how devotedly she has worked. Her services will be remembered for a long time by our citizens.</p>
   <p>A group of her friends is arranging a farewell concert for her, which will be held at the recreational hall of the Polish hospital, in the evening of December 14. When this popular Polish singing star arrived in Chicago she was shown <pb facs="5423968_5_0425.jpg" n="2"/>about the town. During the sight-seeing tour she was taken to the Polish hospital. Although her visit was short, she made many friends there. Because of here attachment to this place, her friends decided that it would be fitting to have her give her farewell concert in this hospital.</p>
   <p>Special plans are being made to accommodate the many friends and followers of Mrs. Waydowa. It is expected that a large number will turn out to hear her sing and bid her adieu. Chicago Poles will certainly miss her beautiful voice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
