<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-12-10">Dec. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Second Anniversary of Polish Arts Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1697</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1697.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-12-10">Dec. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND ANNIVERSARY OF POLISH ARTS CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several hundred members of the Polish Arts Club and their friends will gather, next Wednesday evening,at the Art Institute of Chicago, to celebrate the second anniversary of the organization of the club and to express their appreciation to the retiring board who has been largely responsible for the work the club has accomplished, the recognition which the club has received and for the growth in membership which to date numbers more than 250.</p>
   <p>There will be a dinner at 6:30 P.M., in the dining room, followed by a short program in the club room from 8 to 10 P.M., so that members who can not be present at the dinner at 6:30 P.M. can be accomodated at anytime to 10 P.M. Among the guests who will be present are Prof. David H. Stevens of the University of Chicago. He will make an announcement definitely outlining the courses of lectures which Prof. Roman Dybroski will deliver at the University of Chicago next year. Other guests who will be present are Dr. Z. Kurnikowski, Consul General of Poland, Mr. Eric DeLamarter, assistant conductor of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, Mr. Charles Kelly, assistant curator of the Art Institute of Chicago, Mr. Llewellyn Jones, Literary Editor of the Chicago Evening Post.</p>
   <p>Dr. M. J. Kostrzewski, will deliver a short address in appreciation of the contribution by Stanislaus Przybyszewski, to Polish literature, at the time of his death, November 23, 1927.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
