<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-11">Dec. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Elocution Contest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1733</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1733.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-11">Dec. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ELOCUTION CONTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon at the school hall in the district of Holy Trinity Parish a very interesting elocution contest took place. This was the first contest of its kind ever held, not only in the Holy Trinity Parish, but probably in all of Polish Chicago. As a result people came in such numbers that the hall was crowded. The young people from the Literary Circle participated in this contest. They were trying to win large awards for the best reading, and a gold medal for the best monologue. These medals were offered by the Literary Circle.</p>
   <p>There were eleven contestants, each of whom performed very well. They were all amateurs of the declamatory art, yet we can say without fear of contradiction that finished artists from dramatic schools could not have done better. One's heart filled with pride at the sight of the extraordinary abilities of these young people of the district of Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1734.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was rich and varied. [Translator's note: Here follows the entire program.]</p>
   <p>The judges were: Mr. P. Mindak, attorney, Reverend Martin Hanyz, and Mrs. Mary Olgiert Kaczorowska. They observed the contestants' abilities of memorization, diction, and gesticulation. The prize for the monologue was unanimously granted to Miss Mary Nowakowski; the prize for reading was given to Miss Wladyslawa Kwiatkowska. The following also deserve special mention: Mr. Roman Janiszonski, who almost won a prize; Misses Anna Jakowaniec, Helen Warszewski, and Josephine Borucki.</p>
   <p>The Literary Circle intends to conduct a similar contest at the end of next month for all the young people's organizations in the district of Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
