<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[St. Casimir's Parish to Celebrate Polish Day]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1538</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1538.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH TO CELEBRATE POLISH DAY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter was received for publication in Dziennik Chicagoski:</p>
   <p>"In accordance with a suggestion of the pastor of St. Casimir's parish, a meeting of representatives of all societies in this parish was held on August 21, concerning the Polish Day question. Father F. Kroll, in opening the meeting, spoke of the purpose of and the necessity for a Polish Day, and encouraged all Poles to participate in its celebration. Since the Stephen Buszcynski Patriotic Society and St. Casimir's Society were represented at Saturday's meeting in Pulaski Hall, a committee of five was chosen from among them. The following societies, each of which delegated its president to assist the committee, also decided to participate: 1. St. Anthony's Society of Hawthorne, Joseph Mikolajczyk. 2. St. Stanislaus Society of Hawthorne, F. Maciejewski. 3. St. Francis Society of Chicago, A. Wachowski. 4. Holy Cross Society of Chicago, Michael Klosowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1539.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. Society of St. Casimir the Prince, Anthony Eichstead. 6. St. Isidore's Society, Joseph Trebacz. 7. St. Casimir's Council, Catholic Order of Foresters, John Grzegorzewski.</p>
   <p>"Thus, nine societies from St. Casimir's parish will participate in the Polish Day celebration. In addition, this parish will furnish a float with an allegorical picture and a triumphal arch. God bless our Polish Day, and long live the Poles!</p>
   <p>"John Rosinski, secretary."</p>
   <p>It seems as if each Polish parish will furnish at least one float. St. Stanislaus', St. Adalbert's, St. Casimir's, and both parishes from South Chicago have already, more or less, pledged themselves. There will be plenty of floats!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
