<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-07">Feb. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polonia Pays its Last Respects to the Father of Polish Song in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-07">Feb. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLONIA PAYS ITS LAST RESPECTS TO THE FATHER OF POLISH SONG IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the time of writing, crowds of people are gathering at the home of the late Anthony Mallek, 2125 Haddon Avenue, to pay their last respects to the father of Polish song, the meritorious national worker who practically to the end of his life remained a champion and who did not let go for a moment of the ploughshare with which he plowed a hard and frequently ungrateful soil.</p>
   <p>Great preparations have been made for the funeral, which will be unusually impressive. The procession will leave the house of mourning at 10:15 A. M. and will proceed on Haddon Avenue to Division Street, passing before the Polish National Alliance building, which has been draped in mourning. The family of the late Anthony Mallek has considered the suggestion of the Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance of having the body rest for a while at the Alliance building too difficult of execution, because of lack of time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0440.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, the funeral procession will halt in front of the Alliance building, where everyone will get out of the automobiles and walk to Holy Trinity Church.</p>
   <p>The entire Board of Directors, together with the honorary vice-president and Mr. S. Litko, official representative of the censor of the Polish National Alliance, will proceed en masse to the house of mourning to witness the sad rite of transporting the body of the former secretary general and member of long standing of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The Requiem Mass will be celebrated by Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, rector of Holy Trinity Parish, where the deceased fulfilled his duties for many decades and was the spirit of the parish. Reverend Roman Marciniak and Reverend Iwaszewski will assist.</p>
   <p>The choir of the Society of Polish-Lithuanian Organists will sing during the <pb facs="5423968_5_0441.jpg" n="3"/>Mass under the direction of Mr. Alexander Karczynski, organist of St. Peter and Paul Parish.</p>
   <p>Many people from other localities have come to Chicago for the funeral, among them Reverend W. Kruszka of Milwaukee and Reverend T. Trusinski and B. Sztuczko of South Bend, Indiana. The obituary will be spoken by Reverend Casimir Sztuczko at Holy Trinity Church.</p>
   <p>The funeral rites at the cemetery will be performed by Reverend W. Zapala, rector of St. Stanislaus College, and Mr. K. Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, will speak in the name of the Alliance and other friends.</p>
   <p>We wish to add that during the funeral procession the offices of the Polish National Alliance will be closed and the employees will repair in a body to the church for the services, with the exception of those departments which must work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0442.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The respect with which the work and deserts of the father of Polish song are regarded by our people is attested to by the unusually large number of people from all strata of society who are taking part in the funeral.</p>
   <p>The casket will be carried from the home to Holy Trinity Church and from the Church to the hearse by John F. Smulski; John Scherman, Stanley Pliszka, Leon Wojczynski, Caesar Dluzewski, Stephen Gorecki, John [B.] Pallasch, Peter Rostenkowski, August [J.] Kowalski, and Teophile Weyna.</p>
   <p>The honorary pallbearers are Judge Michael Blenski, Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, Judge Joseph La Buy, Judge E. Dankowski, Casimir Zychlinski, Joseph Magdziarz, John Zawilinski, K. B. Czarnecki, Captain Casimir Szeszycki, K. Drzymala, Anthony Klimek, Albert Rostenkowski, Joseph Ruszkiewicz, J. S. Konopa, L. Zamorski, Teophile T. Gordon, W. Bardonski, J. Nehring, J. Olbinski, Michael Rzeszotarski, S. Orpiszewski, S. Szwajkart, J. J. Chrzanowski, Jacob [M.] Romanowicz, Frank Rezmerowski, M. Idzikowski, Paul Nawrot, <pb facs="5423968_5_0443.jpg" n="5"/>Alderman Zwiefka, Alderman [John] Szymkowski, Alderman [Stanley] Walkowiak, Alderman Sitz, and Alderman B. Adamowski, F. P. Danisch, Commissioner F. Rydzewski, Commissioner Albert Nowak, S. Kunz, Stanley Adamkiewicz, W. Kloska, W. Szrojda, F. Koraleski, J. Gilmeister, F. Schweda, Paul Drzymalski, T. M. Holinski, Vincent Jozwiakowski, Lawrence Przybylski, A. Zembal, I. Stankiewicz, S. Kuflewski, A. Chmielinski, W. Szymanski, Joseph Szeszycki, Joseph Sminiewicz, Jacob Sadowski, Anthony Kaczorowski, Paul Giersch, A. Majewski, W. Dobinski, J. Schweda, M. M. Nowicki, F. X. Wleklinski, P. Mazurkiewicz, Joseph Hellmuth, Lieutenant Joseph Palczynski, Attorney J. Janiszewski, W. Stanczewski, F. Konkowski, J. Derpa, N. Dudzban, Albert Wachowski, Albert Orzechowski, N. L. Piotrowski, A. Czarnecki, Ludwig Pinderski, Joseph Wieczorowski, M. Majewski, John Czekala, Stanley Glomkowski, W. Perlowski, Joseph Chelminiak, F. Perlowski, F. Kendziora, Z. Perlowski, M. Perlowski, J. Urban, Julius Smetanka, J. R. Zielinski, L. Parzynski, John Gorny, John Hibner, Leon Dyniewicz, Simon Wojtalewicz, <pb facs="5423968_5_0444.jpg" n="6"/>H. Siwecki, Joseph Konczyk, Herman Fry, M. Wojtecki, J. Lorkoski, J. P. Szymanski, Michael Kolassa, J. Steinbach, F. J. Klajda Dr. A. Balcerzak, Dr. W. A. Kuflewski, Dr. Statkiewicz, J. [F.] Singer, S. Zahajkiewicz, F. Marchlewski, Dr. A. Szwajkart, F. Wegierski, W. Szrojda, W. Modrzejewski, F. Urbanski, the Brummel brothers, H. Darmar, A. A. Suwalski, A. Suchomski, M. Gatkowski, K. Wiechecki, J. Tuszkiewicz, B. J. Zaleski, I. Wrzeszcz, K. Mikitynski, M. Thiel, R. Hensel, Andrew Byczek, K. Pettkoske, W. Balassa, F. Garbarek, A. Stachowicz, and others.</p>
   <p>Great masses of flowers and wreaths, sent to the house of mourning, were placed about the casket of Anthony Mallek. We have noted flowers and wreaths from the following organizations, alliances, and individuals.</p>
   <p>Laurel wreath from Judge M. Blenski of Milwaukee, Wisconsin, censor of the Polish National Alliance; laurel wreath from the Central Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance; laurel wreath from the Board of Directors of <pb facs="5423968_5_0445.jpg" n="7"/>the Polish Women's Alliance; also wreaths from the following groups: Goplana Singing Society of Milwaukee, Kurpinski Singing Society, First Choir of St. Hedwig's Parish, St. Hedwig's Choir of St. Hedwig's Parish, church committee of Holy Trinity Parish; choirs of Holy Trinity Parish, K. G. Mallek's choirs in Milwaukee, Building and Loan Association of Holy Trinity Parish, United Butchers Baking Company, the Polish Attorneys' Society, Father Gordon Building and Loan Association, Polish clerks of the Municipal Court of Chicago, friends of the Pulaski Club, Society of Polish Organists, B. Dembinski Singing Society of South Chicago, and Holy Trinity Singing Society.</p>
   <p>Flowers were sent by the following individuals: J. F. Smulski, T. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, Helinski, Mr. and Mrs. K. J. Mallek of Milwaukee, Mary Mallek, Professor Fitzeka, Mr. and Mrs. Medrzecki, Joseph P. Smiszniewicz, John J. Mallek, Stanley Pliszka, Mrs. Mary Kuza, Mr. and Mrs. Joseph <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, the deceased's grandchildren, Mary, Joseph, and Robert, the pupils of Miss Cecilia Mallek family, the Brummel brothers, Mr. and Mrs. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> F. Ohala, Joseph Blaszka, Joseph Szeszycki, Dr. J. B. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> John S. Derpa, Attorneys <pb facs="5423968_5_0446.jpg" n="8"/>Royal W. Irving, Joseph Pisza, James M. Breen, Robert C. Busse, Leslie E. Cole, Patrick E. O'Neill, F. Grzeszkowiak, John Harris, John Victoria and Joseph Januszewski, and many others.</p>
   <p>We will publish the details of the funeral in tomorrow's issue of our paper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
