<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-06">Feb. 6, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to All Polish Church and National Singers' Groups</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0785</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0785.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-06">Feb. 6, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO ALL POLISH CHURCH AND NATIONAL SINGERS' GROUPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The home can be destroyed by fire.....treasures can be stolen by thieves, but the muse of song always remains untouched,"says a poet.</p>
   <p>From time immemorial song has filled the hearts of man the world over. The mother puts her tear-stained baby to sleep with a lullaby; melodic songs prevail at gay social functions; the stirring military song warms the hearts of men and leads them on the field of battle; the national song is filled with the glory, yearnings, and misfortunes of individuals and legions of people; nations are made to feel proud through their expression of song, and it is through the medium of song that the works of God are glorified! How then could one not love song? Song makes life a pleasure; it banishes worry, <pb facs="5423968_5_0786.jpg" n="2"/>awakens the heart, adds temper to the soul; it finds itself everywhere for it passes through prison bars, and reaches the frozen Siberian steppes; it lives with the unfortunate exile in the most deplorable hut as well as in the marble halls of the regents.</p>
   <p>It can safely be said that there is not a heart in the world that has not felt the strains of a song, a song that touches the fibers of the heart.</p>
   <p>In this respect it is our duty to care for this faithful friend. Above all, our parish choirs and singing groups should be concerned with spreading and fostering national song.</p>
   <p>If it is true that certain individual groups and one large association have made an effort in this direction, for they each have conducted some kind of instruction classes in their own particular corners.</p>
   <p>Everyone is aware of the fact that religious, patriotic, and social music <pb facs="5423968_5_0787.jpg" n="3"/>reaches greater heights through the joint efforts of one common organization. Every joint enterprise is much easier to put over because more effort and time can be given to it and the responsibilities minimized by spreading the work to be accomplished. The more there is in common the more can be realized. This is true in all branches of this kind of work, whether it is the cost of material, whether it is the finding of new talent, or whether it is the awakening of the desire for music in all, and the consequent influencing of the esthetic knowledge of the people.</p>
   <p>The power of music is great; yet, to many wholesome religious music is unknown. A part of this is the fault of our small and often neglected church choirs.</p>
   <p>"Sursum Corda!" The combined strength of the voices of our youth, both girls and boys, will open the portals of heaven, and even the angels will join with them in the song, "Gloria in Excelsis Deo".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0788.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Choirs and singing societies, providing they work out an adequate plan, will receive greater support from the clergy and the parishioners, for worship which is due the Almighty and love of man demand that religious and national songs be beautiful and more beautiful.</p>
   <p>Because of this we have a hope that all choirs and singing groups will recognize the need for a "Singers' Union", whose aim will be to safeguard church and national songs through co-operation and mutual work.</p>
   <p>Choirs and societies that recognize this need and agree to join such an organization, are requested to appoint a delegate or two and send them and their directors to a general meeting to be held on March 7, at 4 P.M., at the St. Stanislaus Kostka school hall, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The St. Cecilia Men's Choir, of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, has aired this <pb facs="5423968_5_0789.jpg" n="5"/>proposal thoroughly, and has decided to send the following questionnaire to all choirs and choral groups:</p>
   <p>I. Does the choir (society) recognize the need for a "singers' union" or a Catholic parish Choirs'union"?</p>
   <p>2. Does the choir desire to join this "union"?</p>
   <p>3. Does it consider it necessary that the members pay dues and, if so, how much?</p>
   <p>Those choirs or societies that are not in a position to send delegates to this meeting because of some previous engagement are urged to communicate by letter with the secretary of the temporary committee of this project: A. Klafta, 668 Dickson Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0790.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>During the first part of the meeting the following business will be taken up:</p>
   <p>1. Reading of the constitution, corrections, and a vote on its acceptance.</p>
   <p>2. Organization.</p>
   <p>Anticipating early replies to this appeal we remain,</p>
   <p>Your compatriots,</p>
   <p>The Committee:</p>
   <p>A. J. Ewasigroch,</p>
   <p>John Kondziorski,</p>
   <p>W. Barwig,</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0791.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Andrew Stachowicz,</p>
   <p>S. Zahajkiewicz,</p>
   <p>John Nering,</p>
   <p>A. C. Klafta.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
