<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-17">Aug. 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Certain</title><title level="a" type="sub">Forty-seven Societies Promise to March in Parade</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-17">Aug. 17, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY CERTAIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Forty-seven Societies Promise to March in Parade</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There can no longer be any doubt that Polish Day will be celebrated at the World's Fair. A meeting of Polish businessmen and administrative officers of Polish societies was held on this subject at the St. Stanislaus Kostka school hall last night. The enthusiasm of those present effectively demonstrated the general attitude toward the project. Our St. Stanislaus parish and St. Michael Archangel Parish of South Chicago are ready to do their part. What is most important, it was agreed that the Poles will unite for this occasion, without regard to partisanship. This determination, given actual proof yesterday by the harmonious conduct of the meeting, is one of its most significant results.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski called the meeting to order with a prayer and a short speech. He explained the significance of a Polish Day and pointed out that every other nation either has had or will have its "day" at the <pb facs="5423968_5_1562.jpg" n="2"/>Fair. He emphasized the fact that it is our duty to celebrate a Polish Day for the preservation of our national honor which, after all, is not merely an empty phrase but a condition upon which our very existence depends .....Only the Chinese have not had their "day" at the Fair; surely we cannot allow ourselves to be compared with the Chinese. Even the present hard times do not release us from the necessity of celebrating an occasion which may not be equalled again for years. Father Barzynski's speech was vigorously applauded.</p>
   <p>W. Jedrzejek was named chairman of the meeting and H. Nagiel secretary.</p>
   <p>On behalf of the initiators of Polish Day plans, the secretary read a report of all that was accomplished thus far. He pointed out that the original idea was to arrange for a Polish Day in connection with a general "Council of Poles," but that it had been finally decided to concentrate efforts on a Polish Day celebration alone. He described the proposed program as discussed at the last meeting (parade with floats and celebration at Festival Hall on the Fair <pb facs="5423968_5_1563.jpg" n="3"/>grounds. See Dziennik, Aug. 14,); he pointed out the means by which the costs could be covered....namely: calling upon Polish businessmen and representatives of various professions, with as light a levy as possible upon representatives of societies. Finally, he explained that, in the opinion of the initiators of the project, the matter can be brought to a successful conclusion only by the united efforts of all Chicago Poles, regardless of factional differences. Thus, the present meeting ought to be regarded as a preparatory one, while final decisions will be reached at the general meeting, at which Poles from all sections of the city will gather at Pulaski Hall on August 19. In conclusion, the secretary read the following letter, received before the meeting opened:</p>
   <p>"To the Poles Gathered for a Discussion of the Polish Day Question on August 16:</p>
   <p>"Since duty prevents us from being present at today's meeting, we feel it necessary to notify you, on our own behalf and on that of our fellow Polish <pb facs="5423968_5_1564.jpg" n="4"/>policemen of Chicago, that we are wholeheartedly united with our countrymen in a desire for a Polish Day celebration in Chicago, and that the project will receive our support. Polish Day ought to be celebrated, and it is possible only if we can cast aside our misunderstandings for the time being and work hand in hand for the greater good of Poland. We, the Polish policemen, will give whatever moral and material support we can. Hail to the Polish Day in Chicago!</p>
   <p>Joseph Polczynski,</p>
   <p>Louis Kroll."</p>
   <p>The letter was thunderously applauded.</p>
   <p>A discussion of the secretary's proposals began. Since partisanship had been mentioned, it was again emphatically stated that as far as Polish Day affairs are concerned, parties and factions do not exist; we are all Poles, ready to work together in brotherly unity. Words to this effect by Father Barzynski, Slominski, Lisztewnik, and Tomasik were applauded vigorously. The final decision that Polish Day would be celebrated was made by acclamation, <pb facs="5423968_5_1565.jpg" n="5"/>without the usual formalities of motions and voting.</p>
   <p>On a motion by Father Barzynski, the officers and representatives of Polish societies came forward to announce their intention to participate in the parade. Such announcements, more or less definite, were made by forty-seven societies, which were represented as follows: St. Michael Archangel Society (St. Stanislaus parish), by J. Luka; St. Cecelia Society, by Mr. Czekala; Polonia Society, by A. Majewski; St. Casimir Youth Society, by [J.] Nering; St. Joseph's Society, by Mazurkiewicz; Harmonia Society, by W. Bardonski; St. Stephen's Society, by J. Wydral; St. Stanislaus Council, Catholic Order of Foresters, by W. Bardonski; Sigmund Council, Catholic Order of Foresters, by J. Tomaszewski; Kosciusko Council, Catholic Order of Foresters, by I. Krakowski; Polish Policemen's Kosciusko Monument Club, by J. Polczynski; Kosciusko Society, by A. Lisztewnik; St. Anthony's Society, by F. Szatkowski; Polish Falcons II, by L. Nowak; St. Stanislaus Kostka Falcons and St. Stanislaus Kostka Youth Society, by S. Zahajkiewicz; St. Hedwig's Society (St. Stanislaus parish), by I. Lama; King Ladislaus Jagiello Society, under <pb facs="5423968_5_1566.jpg" n="6"/>the protection of Jesus Christ, by M. Gawron; Holy Cross Society, by F. Grabowski; Polish Cyclists' Society, by L. Majewski; Kosynierzi [Translator's note: The peasant soldiers of Mosciusko were armed with scythes and were called Kosynierzi,] of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, by Mazurkiewicz; Adam Mickiewicz Society, by J. Slowikowski; Sixteenth Ward Democratic Club, by A. W. Rudnicki; Dramatic Club or the Patriotic Organization, by S. Zahajkiewicz; St. Valentine's Society, by A. Galkowski; J. Kilinski Polish Cobbler's Association, by P. Kawrot; St. Stanislaus Parish Choir, by Andrew Kwasigroch; St. Stanislaus Kostka Cadets, by P. Lama; St. Nyacinth's Society, by J. Bloch; three military orders: Queen's Guards, Uhlans, and St. Martin's Society, by F. Jagus; St. Adalbert, Bishop and Martyr, Society, by J. Zborowski; King John Sobieski Society, by I. Lanski; St. Martin's Society, by H. Kaczmarowski; Holy Trinity Society, by W. Jedrzejek; Holy Virgin Mary Society, by B. Klarkowski; St. Joseph Societies, numbers 1 and 2, by F. Fuhl; and Young Businessmen's Association, by J. Adamowski.</p>
   <p>Societies from St. Michael Archangel parish in South Chicago were represented as follows: St. Michael Archangel Society, by F. Przybylewski; Knights of <pb facs="5423968_5_1567.jpg" n="7"/>St. Casimir, by M. Kusnierz; St. Stanislaus, Bishop and Martyr, Society, by J. Kuczynski; Knights of the Holy Virgin Mary, second division, by R. Bielawski; Thaddeus Kosciusko Society, by W. Pacholski; Cadets of St. Michael and Kosciusko Kosynierzi, by L. Machnikowski; and Krakus [Translator's note: Krakus is a Polish legendary figure. Krakusy was the name given to a division of peasant soldier's in Kosciusko's army.] Society, under the protection of St. Stanislaus Kostka [St. Michael Archangel parish], by F. Pawelski.</p>
   <p>The declaration of the societies created a very gratifying demonstration. Each new declaration, the name of each new society, was greeted with great applause. Faces shone with joy when it was seen that Poles would march under one banner regardless of individual party affiliations.</p>
   <p>Following this, a broader discussion was taken up on various details of the projected celebrations. The floor was taken by the Reverends Barzynski and A. Nowicki, by S. Slominski, A. W. Rudnicki, Judge [M. A.] La Buy, A. Lisztewnik, W. Bardonski, A. Majewski, Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, J. Czekala, <pb facs="5423968_5_1568.jpg" n="8"/>W. Tomasik, Czaplinski, and many others. Judge La Buy insisted that the Poles in other cities be asked to participate. Lisztewnik expressed the enthusiastically received hope that the Poles would turn out for their "Day" wearing "Konfederatki" [plural of "Konfederatka," a dark-red four-cornered cap worn by the Confederates of Bar (1768)]. Slominski suggested that the businessmen hold a meeting of their own before Saturday to determine, more or less, the extent to which they can be counted upon to support Polish Day plans. Organization of a general committee with subcommittees for each section of the city was also discussed. Father Barzynski stated that the Polish priests will probably contribute a float to the parade. Father Nowicki also promised one float from St. Michael Archangel parish of South Chicago.</p>
   <p>The following decisions were made:</p>
   <p>1. On Friday, August 18, a special meeting of Polish businessmen will be held. During today and tomorrow, the businessmen present will sound out their <pb facs="5423968_5_1569.jpg" n="9"/>fellow-merchants on the matter of furnishing floats. An announcement of this meeting appears elsewhere is today's Dziennik.</p>
   <p>2. Each of the societies represented here will send two of its officers (president and secretary) to the general meeting to be held at Pulaski Hall on August 19. Report of the present meeting will be made by the chairman, Mr. Jedrzejek, and the secretary, Mr. Nagiel. On a motion by Mr. Jedrzejek, S. Slominski was also delegated to represent the present gathering. With this, the meeting closed.</p>
   <p>The large delegation from South Chicago, headed by Father Kowicki, and which had to leave before the meeting ended because of the lateness of the hour, was given three cheers at its departure.</p>
   <p>In general, yesterday's meeting was unusually harmonious. Poles of all factions joined hands, ready to work together. This fact is a gratifying one; let us hope it will bring the best results in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
