<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
    <date when="1908-06-08">June 8, 1908</date><title level="a">Poles in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
    <date when="1909-06-08">June 8, 1908</date><title level="a">POLES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reports given to the Dziennik Zwiazkowy, regarding the performance, yesterday, at St. Stanislaus Hall of one recently arrived Pole who was not familiar with the sentiment and the customs of this country, were of a very critical nature. An attempt of the reporter, therefore, to prove himself neutral, brought about the following brief summary of the reporter's apology: "I find myself in a very precarious position as a result of my review regarding the drama, yesterday, at St. Stanislaus Hall. I wish, therefore, to say herewith that I enjoyed the play, and to extend my respect and appreciation to everyone who gave his time, even for only a few moments to this worth cause.</p>
   <p>The drama drew a large attendance. It can be summarized as follows: in the 14th century, in the castle of Zyllejskim, the ruler was Herman II. He was the proud possessor of four daughters, one of which was adopted, and the granddaughter of Casimir the Great. Because of her beauty, she was a thorn in the eyes of the other three, who were vexed to a degree of murder.</p>
   <p>Unusual circumstances, however, prevented this fatal occurrence; she married <pb facs="5423968_5_0907.jpg" n="2"/>the Polish King Jagiello.</p>
   <p>The star, Miss Agnes Nering, acting the role of Anna, thrilled and delighted the hearts of all present, and was awarded not only a tremendous applause, but also a basket of beautiful flowers.</p>
   <p>Mr. John Hering played the role of King; he was, though, an amateur and lacked the necessary emotional warmth.</p>
   <p>Miss Mary Dobrocka was beautiful in her costume, as were the three girls playing the roles of the daughters of Herman II.</p>
   <p>The count excelled in his acting.</p>
   <p>Mr. Marcelli Gatkowski, as a troubadour, also made a favorable impression.</p>
   <p>Miss Helen Kubiak, who appeared as the dressmaker, was very charming. The heroes in the play did not display as much valor as they should have; however <pb facs="5423968_5_0908.jpg" n="3"/>they displayed outstanding characteristics; Count Adolph too, made a favorable impression.</p>
   <p>The play, as a whole, was success, in spite of the costumes, which were not of the best.</p>
   <p>Producer and author of the play was S. Zahajkiewicz, Musical director, A.P. Kwasigroch.</p>
   <p>P.S. There is no record of the use of chewing gum during the fourteenth century; nevertheless, it was used in the play by the dames on the stage.</p>
   <p>Plozczanin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
