<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Significance of Childrens' Choirs for the Immigrants in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-12">Jan. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE SIGNIFICANCE OF CHILDRENS' CHOIRS FOR THE IMMIGRANTS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When one wanders about Polish communities, whether in large metropolitan centers like Chicago, New York, Buffalo, and Detroit or in small towns, one cannot help noticing the large number of Polish children. Children are our greatest and most valuable treasure, for, after all, what would be the use of toiling day and night, trying to earn a few pennies or a few dollars, if one neglects to look after one's children? Neglected children become irresponsible and, after the death of their hard-working parents, will squander the hard-earned savings left to them.</p>
   <p>It is evident that many children are neglected to judge by the great number of them that play about the streets unguided. One plays on a dirt pile, others amuse themselves by throwing dirt or mud at fences and walls, others run after a passing truck, and others use vile language and plot schemes to damage someone's property.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yet all of them were fondled by their parents, who called them "darlings" when they were babies. They received all the attention in the world during infancy, but, due to lack of guidance, as they grew older they took to the streets, where their souls were contaminated.</p>
   <p>Every child is a potential genius. All one needs to do is to awaken his dormant ambitions, teaching him to appreciate the finer things in life. Proper training will do the rest.</p>
   <p>When Herbert Hoover, Marshal Foch, and other dignitaries went to war-shattered Poland, the populace displayed their greatest treasure--children. So it happened, Marshal Foch and Herbert Hoover were so bewitched by them that they stayed a while longer.</p>
   <p>It is well understood that another Polish nation arose in this country, which is not as yet a pure American nation. There are, however, national groups <pb facs="5423968_5_0599.jpg" n="3"/>that individually exert an effort to influence the development of the present American nation, which is in the process of creation.</p>
   <p>As a result, the Germans, the Irish, the English, the Swedes, and other Anglo-Saxon groups consider us, especially our children, raw material. They believe that by using us as such they will be able to create an American nation in which not even a trace of us will remain.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Polish youth is essential to our future if we are to carve cut an equal niche in the field of culture and citizenship, that is, in legislative institutions, in administrative bodies, in education and in every other field.</p>
   <p>After all, what will our children brought up under such strange methods think when they grow up and realize that although they are of Polish they parents they possess strange characteristics that make them vanish as Poles?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0600.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What will Poland think of her four million children in America who have so easily let themselves be subdued by the Anglo-Saxons? With what disdain will the other national groups look upon us who possess such priceless treasure and yet let it slip out of our possession!</p>
   <p>This is one of the reasons, brother Poles, why we--as singers who preserve the beautiful traits of the Polish character with the help of songs, melodies, tempos, harmonies, and the various other ways associated with the world of music--are making an appeal to you to become our associate workers. Let us all become ardent workers among the children by organizing children's choirs, not for two or three months, but for an indefinite period of time. In this way they will be given constant care and guidance; the talents of thousands will be uncovered and the raw gold that may appear will be brilliantly polished by offering opportunities to those that show promise, who in time will become bright shiny stars admired not only by the Polish people but also by the world at large.</p>
   <p>Let us bear in mind that a good portion of Poland's budget is spent for the <pb facs="5423968_5_0601.jpg" n="5"/>school system; besides, the Polish people pay out large sums for the education of their children, many of whom attend private schools.</p>
   <p>Let us follow this example of the homeland, where the people know what they are doing. Surely, we all know the importance of education today--education is might.</p>
   <p>Let us organize children's choirs to satisfy our traditional craving for music; let us organize children's orchestras, getting true musicians to conduct them; let our talent smooth and polish the imbedded and rugged ambitions of our children. There is no greater reward than that of seeing the blossom of a flower that has been under our constant care.</p>
   <p>When Poland crumbled as a state, it was only in the fields of music, literature, and art that our people stood together. Because of this, let us not be sparing in the time, money, or work spent for the training of our children in all the fields of art; let us organize children's choirs so that our <pb facs="5423968_5_0602.jpg" n="6"/>children may retain our characteristics.....The Polish Singers Alliance has received a letter from the secretary of I. Paderewski, in which the world-renowned musician thanks the Singers Alliance for the honorary diploma which the latter bestowed upon him at the General Assembly held in 1926 in South Bend, Indiana. The secretary states that the concert master accepts honorary membership in the Polish Singers Alliance. He also informs us that Mr. Paderewski is so interested in the work of this organization that he contemplates building a home for the Polish singers in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The following committee was delegated to welcome and honor Mr. Paderewski during his next visit in Chicago: Col. A. Karcynski, director; Col. W. Petrykowski, president; Col. E. Pawlowski, vice-president.</p>
   <p>Because of important developments, the meeting scheduled for January 18, has been postponed for a week by the Komitetu Budowy Domu Spiewaczego <pb facs="5423968_5_0603.jpg" n="7"/>(Singers' Home Building Committee). All delegates are requested to attend this meeting, to be held on Wednesday, January 25, at 8. P. M., at the hall of the Polish National Alliance, Noble and Division Streets. Delegates of all the choirs, are invited to attend. The purpose of this meeting is to discuss plans of reorganization and install new officers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
