<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-11">July 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-11">July 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Dramatic Club under the auspices of the Polish Patriotic organization held another meeting last Thursday night, at which the members of the club spent a very pleasant evening and profited intellectually. Encouraging good literature, reading poems for the purpose of selecting and memorizing some of them, even if it does not bring any other benefit, is in itself sufficient for congratulating the club sincerely. We are giving a list of persons who took part in last Thursday's activities, although we can not describe all details for lack of space, for which we are very sorry. This list will serve as proof that our youth welcomes good recreation, if it is encouraged and supported.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Miss Olejniczak with a greeting which was characterized by its seriousness and humor. This was followed by a recitation by Mr. Jozwiakowski, which was as usual recited with emotion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1106.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Next attraction was a beautiful duet sung by Misses Olejniczak and Zukowski. Miss Kwasigroch entertained the public by reciting Mazurka by Ujejski. A boy who was introduced by Mr. Czekala as his sonny, sang--in English--and played his own guitar accompaniment. Miss Gorczynska recited. Miss Chlebowska sang such a gay song that she could not refrain from laughing herself. Mr. Klafta recited "Polewanko" with Mr. Dombek,accompanied by a zither sang a very touching song about the love of a mother. Mr. Zahajkiewic related a humorous anecdote. Miss Zukowska sang a solo. Mr. Zahajkiewic played a certain composition on a zither so beautifully that the thrilled audience, listened breathless with great emotion and compelled him to play another composition. Miss Bock recited "To a Polish Mother" with emotion. Mr. Kondziorski sang in real Cossack style U Nas Inaczej--It is Different in Our Country-- Mr. Czekala entertained the public by his humorous solo appearance, promising to sing a duet next time. Mr. Oszaldowski, Miss Czerwinski, Mr. Dombek, Mr. Anthony Barwik <pb facs="5423968_5_1107.jpg" n="3"/>again recited. Mr. Kwasigroch related and sang a humorous nocturnal adventure of a knight. Mr. Nahajkiewicz, yielding to the public's demand played the zither again. Several compositions, written by Mr. Zahajkiewicz were selected by the members of the club for that production without the knowledge of the author.</p>
   <p>It was a profitable and pleasant pastime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
