<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Day Central Committee Meets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DAY CENTRAL COMMITTEE MEETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Day Central Committee, appointed Saturday at a mass meeting, held its first meeting at Pulaski Hall last night.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Judge [M.A.] LaBuy. The secretary of the previous meeting, H. Nagiel, informed the gathering that after the adjournment of Saturday's meeting, the following societies promised to participate in the celebration of Polish Day: The Polish Industrial Craftsmen's Association, of St. Adalbert's; the Prince Joseph Poniatowski Society, of St. Stanislaus Kostka's; the Father August Kordecki Society, of Town of Lake; and seven additional societies from St. Casimir's parish. In addition to these, the committee meeting was attended by representatives of the following societies: St. Francis Xavier Society, from Bridgeport (K. Eylenfeldt); Pulaski Guards (S. Surzynski); and St. Martin's Society (F. Jurkiewicz), of South Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first business of the meeting was the election of officers....The result <pb facs="5423968_5_1541.jpg" n="2"/>of the election was as follows: S. Slominski, president; J. Napieralski, Z. Schmidt, and J. Rosinski, vice-presidents; H. Nagiel, first secretary; Casimir Zychlinski, second secretary; W. Bardonski, financial secretary; and Judge LaBuy, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The next business of the meeting was to set a date for Polish Day. After a long discussion, it was admitted that the time was too short to permit its celebration on September 12 [anniversary of Sobieski's defense of Vienna] It was decided, therefore, that the day would be observed in the last week of September, on Saturday, if possible. A special committee consisting of Peter Kiolbassa, K. Bielinski, and Judge LaBuy was appointed to consult the Fair officials on this matter. The date will definitely be made known at the next committee meeting, to be held on Friday of this week.</p>
   <p>The program and the funds necessary for its execution were subjects of a very detailed discussion. It was finally agreed that the Polish Day program would consist of a parade with floats through the city streets and a celebration <pb facs="5423968_5_1542.jpg" n="3"/>at the World's Fair. There was such a variety of opinions as to methods of raising funds that it was decided to appoint a committee to outline a plan, to be presented at the next meeting. The financial committee consists of A. Stefanowicz, J. Rosinski, W. Jedrzejek, and K. Smietanka. Besides this committee, it was decided that the following special committees are necessary; a parade committee of seven, a float committee of nine, an arrangements committee of seven for the celebration at Festival Hall, a music committee of three, a decorations committee of three, and a publicity committee of three. These special committees will be appointed by the president of the Central Committee at the next meeting, so that they will begin their work as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>With the decision that the next meeting be held at Pulaski Hall on Friday, August 25, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
