<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-19">Jan. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Milwaukee Avenue State Bank Adds Three Polish Directors under New Administration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-19">Jan. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">MILWAUKEE AVENUE STATE BANK ADDS THREE POLISH DIRECTORS UNDER NEW ADMINISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a special meeting of stock-holders of the Milwaukee Avenue State Bank, three Polish directors were added yesterday. This session also brought about an entirely new policy of this well-known banking institution of the near northwest side.</p>
   <p>The Polish directors are: John Schermann, N.A. La Buy, and John Smulski. This has brought the total number of directors to twelve. The others are as follows: John P. Hanson, F. H. Herhold, William Johnson, A. C. Lausten, John McClaren, Thos. G. Morris, Paul O. Stensland, and Soren D. Thorson.</p>
   <p>Officers of the bank are: Paul O. Stensland, president; Andrew C. Lausten, <pb facs="5423968_5_0346.jpg" n="2"/>vice president; Chas. E. Schlytern, cashier; and Donald L. Morrill, counsel.</p>
   <p>The Poles are well represented in the stockholding group. Out of forty-nine stockholders, sixteen of them are Polish, namely; Victor Bardonski, Max A. Drezmal, Anthony Groenwaldt, Albert Jendzejek, Peter Kiolbassa, Joseph Kowalski, Miss A. La Buy, M. A. La Buy, I. P. Mikitynski, P. P. Okoniewski, Julian Pischke, John Schermann, Stanislaw Slominski, John F. Smulski, Frank Wleklinski, and John H. Xelowski.</p>
   <p>This bank was formerly a private concern, under the direction of Paul O. Stensland and company. It has become well-known to the Poles of this section of town. Many of them have been doing business here for years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0347.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Milwaukee Avenue State bank is located at Milwaukee Avenue and Carpenter Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
