<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-29">Nov. 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A. Kwasigroch Feted by Polish Choir Group from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0814</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0814.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-29">Nov. 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A. KWASIGROCH FETED BY POLISH CHOIR GROUP FROM ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The St. Cecilia Choir of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish staged a special affair last night at Schultz's Hall in tribute to its director, Andrew Kwasigroch. During the course of the evening Mr. Kwasigroch was presented with a beautiful baton and a beautiful gold ring. This affair was staged to celebrate his birthday, which is tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The program opened with music and song in concert style. The Nowicki Brothers' Band supplied the music, while members from the St. Cecilia Choir, namely, Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, Miss Wanda Barwig, the men's quartet, composed of W. Barwig, J. Nering, F. Kwasigroch, and J. Kedziorski, and a duet team made up of Miss Wanda Barwig and J. Kedziorski, gave out their best in song.</p>
   <p>During the presentation ceremony, Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, Mr. Mucha, and J. Kedziorski made speeches. All mentioned the downfall of the weekly Djabel (Devil).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0815.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many other speeches and songs followed until midnight.</p>
   <p>When the guests were leaving, they all wished Mr. Kwasigroch many years of good health, happiness, and success.</p>
   <p>The occasion will remain memorable not only to the celebrant, but also to the members of the St. Cecilia Choir and the guests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
