<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-14">Nov. 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Falcons Entertain</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-14">Nov. 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH FALCONS ENTERTAIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great many Polish Falcons gathered together for the entertainment arranged by Groups 213 and 266. In spite of the severe cold, there was an enthusiastic parade along Oakley Avenue.....There were 123 Falcons, men and women, in the parade, not counting the Falcon orchestra of Group 192, in full regalia. This was a rather impressive [scene] for an ordinary entertainment by one of the groups. The entertainment was a great success. The group was visited by members of the Polish Falcon's Alliance: Mr. Latuszewsk, Mr. Lokanski and Mr. Ruszczyk. The entertainment included flag exercises, which were performed admirably, by the Falcon women of St. John Cantius Parish. It is too bad that Falcon Zbyszko Cyganiewicz was unable to be present, having an afternoon performance at the Star Theatre on Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Even more people were present at the ball given by Group 266 at Cragin, Illinois.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The hall was crowded with uniformed [people]; and, to make the entertainment more picturesque, the scenery in the hall was changed every few minutes, transforming the hall into a training camp. Group 192 of St. Hedwig's Parish performed beautiful pyramids [exercises]. A group of ten women Falcons of St. John Cantius' Parish also performed with admirable precision.....</p>
   <p>This valiant group, under the direction of Mr. Gnutkiewicz, was rewarded with a storm of applause for each formation.</p>
   <p>The public viewed with great interest the acrobatics of Members Niziolek and Kielbasa of Group 192. They certainly were worth seeing. These members are true artists, as is attested by the fact that they are constantly being engaged by American theatres.</p>
   <p>In the interval between the gymnastic exhibitions, Mr. John Kikulski, president of the Polish Falcons Union, made a speech to which the audience paid close attention. The ball was alive with true Falcon spirit; and the choir, <pb facs="5423968_5_1199.jpg" n="3"/>gathered together at the moment from among the guests, thundered out the Falcon anthem, Warszawianka, and pleased the audience by singing softly "Za Niemen het precz".</p>
   <p>Intricate pyramids exercises were performed.....Other exercises were also performed by ten valiant members of Group 192 under the direction of Mr. Budzynski of Circuit II.....It should be added that Group 192 arrived with its president, Mr. Janusz.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: The omissions represent names of groups of the Falcons or names of individual participants.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
