<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 31,
<date when="1889-06-30">June 30, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">To the Polish Singers of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 31,
<date when="1889-06-30">June 30, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE POLISH SINGERS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Poles scattered in this American land, are devoting their time and talent to various pursuits. Other nationalities, seeing us busy like ants, admit that we are also people, and have strength, a soul, and possess a great ability, sometimes even greater than theirs. We can convince ourselves with facts that we hold great interest in all branches of industry and in numerous events. In order to continue to aid ourselves morally and materially, the Poles have built and continue building churches, schools, establishing various public and church organizations, also the necessary activities in singing.</p>
   <p>What is dearer to a person if not a song? How wonderful it is sometimes to watch in the early morning the lark ascending to the heavens and its Creator, singing a hymn of adoration and praise. In watching a thing of this sort, does it not urge every person to confine his thoughts and heart to God? If not, well, an evil one knows nothing of a song. Our Polish anthems, like every other branch of arts, had difficulties in staying on their feet, or one might say "tracks." We saw how the organizations of singers rose and fell, frequently from the lack of support, or from lack of funds and Polish tunes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0839.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everything was quiet, as if everybody was sleeping. It looked as if the Poles did not know how to sing.</p>
   <p>It was quiet and sad -- until a few years ago a couple of these organizations, which were subject to the feeling of failure, re-organized themselves on a new and stronger foundation and created "The Organization of Polish Singers in America." This was started and did not lack strength because there is plenty of it, especially upon this large American land, if only every one wanted to sincerely help and lend a helping hand and work for the benefit of this organization. Our aim is:</p>
   <p>To rise, and wake the nation's soul by our Polish song, to acquaint the nation with the creations of our artists, as on an occasion held before on the first concert that had taken place in Chicago in the month of May 1889. Another aim is to be supporters for these new creations pertaining to music, by donations and increasing our fund for this aim.</p>
   <p>So for this reason, then, our organization of Polish singers in America requests all other existing organizations to join us and work together, bringing praise to the Polish names. As for others, who do not yet belong to any such kind of an organization, and feel capable of singing, should join an existing singers organization, and help aid together this one large Polish Singers' Organization in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0840.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the first concert sponsored by Organized Polish Singers of America, held in Chicago, there were represented three choirs: The Chopin Singers' Organization as the first; the Harmonia Organized Singers as second; and the Z. S. P. Choir from Milwaukee as third.</p>
   <p>Which organization shall be the fourth choir? We hope that in the future gathering of singers in Milwaukee, there will be at least ten choirs represented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
