<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-06">Sept. 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Helen Modrzejewski [Modjeska] on the Polish Amateur Stage in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-09-06">Sept. 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">HELEN MODRZEJEWSKI [MODJESKA] ON THE POLISH AMATEUR STAGE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In her appearance as "Mrs. Kogucina", Mme. Modrzejewski, gave our amateurs still other valuable lessons. [Translator's note: This article is continued from September 5.] The effect which the great actress has upon her audiences is due to her ability to assume completely the character of any role she is playing. In the role of "Mrs. Kogucina", such an artiste as is our Mme. Modrzejewski assumes that character to the smallest detail in dress, gestures, facial expressions, and voice; she overlooks nothing. It is not that she desires to be admired as an artiste, but that the audience may see in her the character of "Mrs. Kogucina", just as she herself or the author imagined that character; she does not forget this for a single moment, and her every action is calculated accordingly. Similarly, her chief aim is not just to entertain the audience, and this she never exaggerates; she never makes a situation unnaturally funny; during the course of the play, she is "Mrs. Kogucina" and nothing more. This is true art.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1074.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beyond a doubt, our amateurs also try to assume as completely as possible the characters of the roles they play; but, since they have not the same ability to adapt themselves, and since they have considerably less skill, they always appear more or less unnatural on the stage. Some are chiefly concerned with amusing the audience or causing laughter, others want their faces, hands, or costumes to be admired, and, as a result, they forget that the face, or the gestures, or the costume must be suited to the role they are playing; others, again, when their attention, at least for appearance's sake, should be turned to the other actors on the stage, watch the audience, or smile at inappropriate times to see what effect it will have on the audience. They remember too well that they are actors performing before an audience, when they should be concentrating all their efforts upon being only those characters whom they represent during the course of the play. Exaggeration, unnaturalness, and excessive attempts at comic effect sometimes do entertain an audience, but they never have the effect which the author of the drama or comedy intended to produce, and that, after all, is the whole purpose of the performance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1075.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We do not mention these things with the intention of criticizing our amateurs. Their efforts, and the zeal with which they apply themselves, deserve acknowledgement. But profiting by this opportunity, as the appearance of our top-ranking artiste will not soon be repeated, we wish to call attention to some of the details that mark a true artist, this should serve as a constructive lesson to our amateurs. By taking these lessons to heart and stopping to consider the points that make for true artistry, they will become better amateurs and will earn even greater acknowledgment.</p>
   <p>Our beloved amateurs certainly do not expect to see a detailed report of their respective performances in this article. We said in advance that this was not to be a review of the play, but that we would only call attention to the lessons that could be learned from Mme Modrzejewski's performance; we will therefore neither criticise nor review any of the roles. We would like to mention, however, that two of the feminine roles were played by name-day celebrants. Yesterday was St. Rosalie's [Day]; the role of "Mary" was played by Mrs. Rosalie Kwasigroch, and the chambermaid was played by <pb facs="5423968_5_1076.jpg" n="4"/>Miss Rosalie Zukowski. It was with real pleasure that we greeted the return of Mrs. Kwasigroch after her long absence from the stage. Others who had the honor of appearing with Mme. Modrzejewski were: Andrew Stachowicz, J. Kedziorski, A. Huntowski, S. Zahajkiewicz, Adam Stachowicz, and V. Jozwiakowski,</p>
   <p>When she sang her couplets toward the end of the performance, Mme Modrzejewski, in a separate verse, gave her word that "within a week 'Mrs. Kogucina' would return as a lady and a queen." This was her way of promising that she would return to our stage as "Jadwiga, queen of the Lechites [Poles]."</p>
   <p>A few beautiful bouquets expressed, though rather weakly, the homage which our public pays to this great artiste's talent. She has done much to spread the fame of Poland throughout the civilized world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
