<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-25">Mar. 25, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Concert Staged at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-25">Mar. 25, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT CONCERT STAGED AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A benefit concert, under the auspices of the Polish Fellowship Club, was staged at the Polish Hall yesterday at 8 P. M. The proceeds of the musical concert were assigned to the destitute Poles of Nebraska and the Polish Hospital of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The concert, starring Miss Mira Heller, Polish musical celebrity, was a great personal triumph for the Polish artist, as was indicated by the overflowing crowd and the enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>In Miss Heller we have an artist of inimitable qualities, one whose voice is not only brilliant but of sparkling magic, an artist who has gathered laurels in Poland, and throughout Europe, and who still has many more years of success ahead of her.</p>
   <p>Last night's concert will remain as an outstanding musical triumph; not so much <pb facs="5423968_5_0511.jpg" n="2"/>from the standpoint of the magical rendition of masterpieces of song by a Polish artist, but because by her singing she created a triumphant unity of a Polish artist's heart with the hearts of the audience, for the sole purpose of helping her needy compatriots.</p>
   <p>We do not feel competent to criticise the singing of the various songs executed by Miss Heller, but she has scored many successes among her own people as well as among strangers. She is comparable with all great opera stars. Her execution of the tragic scene from "Sappho" and the beautiful "Romance" from "Cavalleria Rusticanna", as well as the national airs, thrilled the audience.</p>
   <p>Miss Heller was supported by two talented artists from her troupe, Miss Lily Roemhold and Miss V. Murphy.</p>
   <p>Miss Roemhold, the well-known violin virtuoso, captured the ear of the audience with her capable rendition of the national Mazurkas and Kujawiaks. [Translator's note: This is a type of Polish dance popular in the Cracow region of Poland...</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0512.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no English term for it.] Her sister is married to a Pole, and because of this connection Miss Roemhold not only became introduced to Polish music but also became an enthusiast of it.</p>
   <p>The second supporting artist, Miss Murphy, who is an excellent concert pianist, played three numbers on the piano. Both guest performers were given a great hand by the appreciative audience.</p>
   <p>So much for the concert from the artistic point of view. Aside from this, the rest of the program was filled with ovations for Miss Heller.</p>
   <p>At her own request, the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish Choir was the first to greet her with a group of Polish songs. There were countless presentations of bouquets.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the performance, two little girls presented Miss Heller with a basket of fresh flowers, and one of them recited an original poem written for the occasion by Szizesny Zahajkiewicz. The girl that presented the recitation was <pb facs="5423968_5_0513.jpg" n="4"/>rewarded with a kiss from Miss Heller.</p>
   <p>The parish order of knights presented the Polish star a salute of honor by standing at attention. This was indeed an impressive moment, and though it concluded the program the audience was reluctant to leave. The artist was moved by this and began to toss flowers from the stage to the audience. The women waved with handkerchiefs and the men with hats as she made her exit.</p>
   <p>A special reception for Miss Heller was arranged by the women of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish in one of the smaller halls of the school building.</p>
   <p>Although the Reszke brothers, John and Edward, well-known opera stars, were compelled to decline an invitation to participate in the concert because of illness, which may keep them out of the entire Chicago opera season, they did not forget their fellow countrymen. A letter was received from them through Ralph Modrzejewski, one of the members of the concert committee. The letter read as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0514.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Auditorium Hotel, Chicago. March 23, 1895.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: With real regret I must let you know that it will be impossible for me to attend your concert, owing to a severe case of influenza, which has attacked me for the second time, and which does not allow me to sing today in 'Les Huguenots'.</p>
   <p>"I am afraid that this illness will be prolonged, and I doubt whether I shall be able to sing even once more in Chicago. The whole repertoire had to be changed and 'Die Meistersinger', which was announced for Monday, is to be replaced by 'Le Nozze di Figaro.'</p>
   <p>"At this very moment my brother received a rehearsal bulletin for tomorrow evening, so he also will not be able to attend the concert. In such a way illness shatters all the plans of a singer.</p>
   <p>"We ask you, dear sir, to make our apologies to our countrymen, and accept from me a sum of two hundred dollars and from my brother one hundred dollars as small donations to be distributed among our poor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0515.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"John Reszke"</p>
   <p>A check for three hundred dollars was enclosed with the letter.</p>
   <p>Due recognition should be accorded our Polish artists for their generous contribution.</p>
   <p>On the whole, the concert was a financial success. The net proceeds will amount to several hundred dollars. A complete financial statement will be published in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
