<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 124,
<date when="1923-05-27">May 27, 1923</date><title level="a">Sculptor Szukalski to Marry an American Woman. the Bride Is the Wealthy Miss Walker, Likewise an Artist from Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 124,
<date when="1923-05-27">May 27, 1923</date><title level="a">SCULPTOR SZUKALSKI TO MARRY AN AMERICAN WOMAN. THE BRIDE IS THE WEALTHY MISS WALKER, LIKEWISE AN ARTIST FROM CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Stanislaus Szukalski, well, known Polish artist-sculptor in America, has arrived in Chicago from New York, to marry Miss Walker, an especially able artist, daughter of Dr. Samuel Walker, one of the most prominent physicians in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The wedding will take place in a few days. After the wedding the young couple will go to Canada for their honeymoon and will most likely return to New York for a permanent stay.</p>
   <p>Miss Walker is known widely in society circles, not only in Chicago but also in New York. Mr. Stanislaus Szukalski is famous as one of the best Polish sculptors. His works have been given exceptional recognition by such artists and critics as Harry Payne Whitney, John Sloan, Robert Henri and many others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0529.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Artist Szukalski, when barely sixteen years of age, created several works, which won fame not only in the Academy of Fine Arts in Cracow, but even amazed artists from Petersburg and Vienna.</p>
   <p>It was about that time that his father emigrated to America, and started a blacksmith shop in Chicago. The young artist with money received for some of his statues, also came to America. He was then eighteen years old.</p>
   <p>Already as early as 1914 the Americans became interested in him. Particularly his originality was commented upon by American critics.</p>
   <p>In the year 1916 a Chicago artist critic wrote of Szukalski: "The one who acquaints himself with the life history of Szukalski, that one will understand the spirit from which springs the creative power of the artist".</p>
   <p>"Artist Szukalski was born in Poland in the town of Gidlach in the year 1895. He studied art at the Academy of Fine Arts in Cracow, where as a student he received as a reward for his works, two gold medals and six honorable distinctions."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0530.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"A few years ago (written in 1916) he came to his father in America. However, last fall his father was killed by an automobile and again the artist was left alone, practically without acquaintances and without friends. The mother of the young artist lives in Poland, amid the war hurricane which is at present going on there. His nineteen year old sister likewise lives somewhere on flame covered Polish soil."</p>
   <p>Further this critic wrote:</p>
   <p>"When someone expressed his emotions about the misfortunes of the artist, Mr. Stanislaus called out, 'That is only a trifle. We are accustomed to misfortune in our family. My grandfather had nine sons; eight of these either were condemned to death by the conquerors or were sent into exile to Siberia, because they fought as revolutionists for the independence of their native land. My father alone was left.'"</p>
   <p>In the end the critic adds:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0531.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"That longhaired, slim Polish youth, with the face of a poet, is unquestionably a genius - and the difference between a genius and talent is, that a genius is inflamed by the light of his own works."</p>
   <p>So much did the American art critics write about Szukalski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
