<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX,No. 214,
<date when="1908-09-12">Sept. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Readers Should Remember This</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX,No. 214,
<date when="1908-09-12">Sept. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE READERS SHOULD REMEMBER THIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That every person, men as well as women, should save money as long as their health and life continues along the road of success, mainly between the age of 20 to 50 years. After this age your life and health begins to decline and this is the time when your savings come to your rescue, in the hour of sickness and need.</p>
   <p>That deposit books can be had in the Polish bank located at 810-14 Milwaukee Avenue, near Division Street; this is the best insurance for old age.</p>
   <p>That the savings in the Polish bank pay $3 interest per year from every one hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>That this interest is paid to the depositors every half year in January and in July.</p>
   <p>That every half year this interest is added to your amount in your <pb facs="5423968_5_0146.jpg" n="2"/>bank book and from this time new interest is growing the same as it would grow from your deposits.</p>
   <p>That bank accounts in this Polish bark can be had by married women and are solely their own personal accounts under their personal control.</p>
   <p>That bank accounts can be had by minors and the deposits remain under their own control.</p>
   <p>That parents can sigh and start accounts for their children in this Polish bank and have full control over such deposits.</p>
   <p>That this Polish bank rents deposit boxes at the small charge of $3 a year, in which you can safeguard your jewels and valuable papers from fire and robbers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_0147.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That the Polish bank sends money to all parts of Poland as well as to any section of the world.</p>
   <p>That the Polish bank at 810-14 Milwaukee Avenue, corner of Haddon Avenue, settles and arranges all bank interests on the same level as the largest banks in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
