<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-27">June 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Acknowledgment of Contributions for St. John Cantius Parish Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-27">June 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF CONTRIBUTIONS FOR ST. JOHN CANTIUS PARISH FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Fair Committee of St. John Cantius Parish wishes to acknowledge the following contributions for the coming fair:</p>
   <p>Apollinaris Jasinski, 2 Carpenter Street: two barrels of beer and two bottles of cognac.</p>
   <p>M. Mazurkiewicz, 74 Front Street: two cases of soda water.</p>
   <p>Felix Kalisz, 73 Front Street: two barrels of beer.</p>
   <p>J. Cholewczynski, 336 Sangamon Street: three barrels of beer and twelve bottles of wine.</p>
   <p>Adam Rekowski, 323 Sangamon Street: one barrel of beer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Francis Berka, 4 Lessing Street: twelve bottles of Tokay wine.</p>
   <p>Charles Jaeger, 15 Lessing Street: a container of milk.</p>
   <p>John Tesmer, 297 Carpenter Street: one barrel of beer.</p>
   <p>J. Swiatek, 186 Chicago Avenue: one-half barrel of beer and two boxes of cigars.</p>
   <p>Carol Kopkowski: one dollar.</p>
   <p>X. Guminger, 105 Chicago Avenue: two boxes of cigars.</p>
   <p>Blonder Brothers, 158 Chicago Avenue: one dollar.</p>
   <p>J. Malkowski, 147 Chicago Avenue: one barrel of beer and four boxes of cigars.</p>
   <p>J. Pasowicz, 143 Chicago Avenue: three cases of soda.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>M. A. Antkowiak, 320 May Street: one barrel of beer, two boxes of cigars and two bottles of whiskey.</p>
   <p>Michael Plotka, 331 May Street: one barrel of beer, two cases of soda and six bottles of wine.</p>
   <p>Francis Schultz: one barrel of beer.</p>
   <p>Francis Kantak, 93 George Street: one heating stove and one ton of coal.</p>
   <p>[?] Nawrocki, 339 Carpenter Street: one goat.</p>
   <p>Anthony Eitman: one barrel of beer and twelve bottles of wine.</p>
   <p>Theophillus Suchowski, 33 Front Street: one dozen hams.</p>
   <p>Joseph Korzeniewski, 320 Carpenter Street: five dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1290.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Max Marach, 27 Fay Street: one dollar.</p>
   <p>John Michalowski, 84 Front Street: five hundred cigars.</p>
   <p>J. Kowohl: five hundred cigars.</p>
   <p>M. Megera, 320 Carpenter Street: three boxes of caramels and one box of cigarettes.</p>
   <p>E. Lempelius, 319 Sangamon Street: one bedspread valued at twelve dollars.</p>
   <p>H. F. Stenzel, 119 Front Street: one container of milk.</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to the donors.</p>
   <p>The Committee</p>
   <p>(The entire proceeds of the fair are to go for the upkeep of St. John Cantius Parish.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
