<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-06">July 6, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title><title level="a" type="sub">Kosciuszko Play on Polish Stage in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-06">July 6, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Kosciuszko Play on Polish Stage in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>St. Casimir's Young Men's Society staged an amateur Play last night at the Polish hall on Bradley Street. The audience was large, and it enjoyed a very pleasant pastime.</p>
   <p>Well learned roles, properly arranged scenery; audible, distinctive, and beautiful diction; attractive costumes, and artistic decorations, suitable to the occasion, made a very good impression as a whole, and revealed the theatrical tendencies of the young society. Most of the members of this society are very young, yet for a long time they have proved how fervently they love their native land, how patriotic are their feelings, and also how they strive to remain Poles on American soil. Some of them were born in America, but they do not seek distinction by renouncing their nationality. On the contrary, they are trying to bring honor to their nation by their worthy endeavors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1109.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be impossible to describe all the characters of the Play as presented. The Play, "Four Episodes from the Life of Thaddeus Kosciuszko," depicts the moments in which this great Polish hero had some of the most thrilling experiences, patriotic as well as personal, for during there moments he was associated with the object of his first love, Louise Sosnowski, who later became Princess Lubomirski, and these moments were epochs in his life.</p>
   <p>One of the episodes presented a scene at Sosnowice, Poland, in 1786, when he was obliged to bid his love farewell, for she had submitted to the will of her father, and had agreed to Marry Prince Lubomirski. Kosciuszko, then departed for America for the purpose of taking a part in the war for independence. Another scene presented and incident at Cracow Square, in 1794, where he was greeted as a liberator. He organized an insurrection against Russian domination, and for this purpose he received donations from the nation, and also from the unknown veiled lady, widow Lubomirski, a laurel leaf as a symbol of victory. Then a scene presenting the sublime moment of April 4, 1794, <pb facs="5423968_5_1110.jpg" n="3"/>after the victory at Raclawice, Poland, when Princess Lubomirski makes herself known to him, and pays a homage to the "Savior of the nation." Finally, a scene presented Kosciuszko in exile at Solotnurn, Switzerland, on the occasion of his birthday. He received good news from his Fatherland about the new hope awakened by Napoleon; also gifts from his countrymen; and where Princess Lubomirski, again, presents to him her two young sons, asking him for his blessing.</p>
   <p>This thrilling meeting of Thaddeus Kosciuszko with Princess Lubomirski, impersonated by John Nering and Frances Bock, was presented to the public by the young amateurs last night with profound respect apropos to a solemn occasion. The leading actors were aided greatly by the members of the society, who participated in the production.</p>
   <p>Several young ladies participated in the Play, and contributed largely to its success. Especially do we mention Miss Frances Bock, who surpassed herself in last night's performance, charming everyone. She deserves the sincere <pb facs="5423968_5_1111.jpg" n="4"/>acknowledgement and gratitude of all members of the society. We also mention Misses R. Siuda, W. Chlebowski, R. Eukowski, Antoinette Kaczmarek, J. Kowalewski, Anna Nering, K. Kaminski, M. Czerwinsk and M. Siuda.</p>
   <p>We should not overlook here the Polish orchestra which moved the public to almost continuous applause by playing beautiful Polish selections between the acts. This orchestra deserves our support also.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
