<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-14">Aug. 14, 1893</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_5_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-14">Aug. 14, 1893</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The World's Columbian Exposition of Chicago has assembled all the peoples of the world. Every nation has had or will have its day--a special day on which it manifests its national vitality at the Fair. Are we Poles to be left in the background? No, a hundred times no! Polish Day, a day dedicated especially to the Poles and their cause, ought to find a place amongst the World's Fair celebrations. Otherwise, the hundred and fifty thousand Poles of Chicago would be disgraced. The projected Polish Day, which was first brought to public attention by the press, is now nearing realization.</p>
   <p>A group of Polish citizens of this part of the city have already met twice and discussed the problems involved in the proper observance of such a day. Almost simultaneously, the Poles on the Southwest Side decided to call a meeting for discussion of this matter at Pulaski Hall on August 19. Judging that in a matter such as this, which can be accomplished only with the <pb facs="5423968_5_1580.jpg" n="2"/>cooperation of everyone, we must unite, we recognize the necessity of uniting with our brethren on the Southwest Side and of working hand in hand with them.</p>
   <p>With this purpose in him, we have decided to call a meeting of the officers of Polish societies and businessmen on the Southwest Side, to present to them the ideas already developed and to determine the problems that will confront the general meeting scheduled for Saturday at Pulaski Hall.</p>
   <p>Quite obviously, our meeting must be held before Saturday. We are calling our meeting for Wednesday, August 16, at 8:30 in the evening, at St. Stanislaus Kostka's School Hall. All Polish businessmen, representative citizens, and officers of societies are invited to attend.</p>
   <p>The matter is of great importance and concerns our honor as Poles. Let us all stand together, regardless of partisan views. Let us join hands. By this Polish Day, let us show other national groups that Poland is not yet lost--nor ever shall be!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_5_1581.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In behalf of a group of Polish citizens,</p>
   <p>The Committee:</p>
   <p>Reverend A. Nowicki,</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski,</p>
   <p>J. Tomaszewski,</p>
   <p>L. Szopinski,</p>
   <p>S. Zahajkiewicz,</p>
   <p>F. Jurkiewicz,</p>
   <p>K. Nagiel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
