<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-21">July 21, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Organize Aid Committee for New Ulm, Stricken City in the Northwest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0960</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0960.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-21">July 21, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZE AID COMMITTEE FOR NEW ULM, STRICKEN CITY IN THE NORTHWEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held in the library of the North Side Turner Hall, Chicago, to consider Emil Dietzsch's appeal to arrange a Garfield Festival and to give the proceeds to the stricken inhabitants of New Ulm, Minnesota. [Translator's note: General news items in earlier editions gave a detailed description of a cyclone which destroyed the town and killed people and livestock.]</p>
   <p>The majority of the people present were members of the Turngemeinde (Turners' Association). Messrs. Dietzsch, Hoechster, Madlener, Mannhardt, Friedman, Stimming, and others were there; the meeting was well attended. Mr. Hoechester was nominated chairman after Mr. Dietzsch had declared that he considered it best to postpone the Garfield festival for the present, and that something should be done immediately to help the people of New Ulm.</p>
   <p>S. Loewenthal, treasurer of the Turnverein (Turners' Society) of New Ulm and <pb facs="5418474_9_0961.jpg" n="2"/>delegate of that city's aid committee, was then asked to address the assembly. He gave a short account of the catastrophe which had destroyed the town and explained that he and Henry Weyhe, another committee member, had been delegated to seek help in Chicago. Mr. Loewenthal then cited an incident which occurred yesterday, while he was calling on Mr. Schwab, of the firm of Selz, Schwab and Company. We append the report verbatim to show to the Germans of Chicago as well as to out-of-town customers of the concern what Mr. Schwab's attitude is Mr. Loewenthal said:</p>
   <p>"In collecting contributions today I was introduced by Benjamin Eisendrath of the firm of Schnadig, Foreman and Company to Mr. Schwab in the latter's office and explained the object of my visit. Mr. Schwab declared that no details of the misfortune were known. I asked politely whether he had read the newspapers, and he retorted by asking, whether those people in New Ulm were not all Dutchmen. I replied that he was mistaken; that to the best of my knowledge the people there were Germans. He replied:</p>
   <p>"'It makes no difference; I would'nt help those Dutchmen up there anyway. They <pb facs="5418474_9_0962.jpg" n="3"/>have never bought anything of me, and if a Dutchman was starving across the way, and I could save him by giving him a cent, I would not do it. It is all a fair punishment for the people of New Ulm.'"</p>
   <p>As might have been expected, this account caused great indignation among those present, and what they said was not complimentary.</p>
   <p>A committee was then appointed to nominate fifteen citizens to make collections. The committee held a short consultation and reported through its chairman, Mr. E. Mannhardt, that the following gentlemen had been selected: F. Madlener, August Beck, A. C. Hesing, H. Schultz, George Schneider....[all together fifteen names].</p>
   <p>The nominations were accepted, and the committee was requested to publish the following appeal:</p>
   <p>"To the People:</p>
   <p>"The frightful catastrophe which befell the people of New Ulm last Friday has <pb facs="5418474_9_0963.jpg" n="4"/>induced a number of prominent citizens to hold a meeting at the Turner Hall to devise ways and means to provide prompt and effective aid to the unfortunates of that city. Messrs. H. Loewenthal and H. Weyhe, delegates of the New Ulm Relief Committee (headed by W. Pfaender, chairman, the Reverend Alexander Berghold, secretary, and Charles Wagner, treasurer), explained to the meeting the dire need in which their fellow citizens are. Two hundred and twelve families are homeless and have lost everything; several have lost the members who provided for them, and many face the same situation, since seventy-five persons were seriously injured, and up to last Monday twenty dead had been buried.</p>
   <p>"This is the third time that New Ulm has been afflicted with terrible misfortune. The first disaster was the Indian massacre; then came the grasshopper plague, which lasted seven years; now the storm. Chicago is the metropolis of the Northwest, and it is the city's duty as such to help a sister city in time of distress, especially since the world generously helped us [after the Chicago fire]; and it is our especial duty to help New Ulm because that city sent the <pb facs="5418474_9_0964.jpg" n="5"/>first carload of flour to the starving, homeless people of Chicago when we experienced disaster.</p>
   <p>"Help is needed urgently. The summers of northern Minnesota are short, and money must be sent immediately, so that the people can at least get temporary shelter before the approach of cold weather.</p>
   <p>"The undersigned, members of the committee, will call on their fellow citizens and ask them to donate liberally for the cause. But it is impossible to see every one, and those who feel sympathy for others are therefore requested to seek the committee members."</p>
   <p>The following amounts have been received up to the present date: S. Friedman, $100; Marshall Field, $50; Chicago Turngemeinde, $50; ladies of the Turngemeinde, $25; Schnadig, Foreman and Company, $25; E. Rothschild and Brother, $25; Eddy, Harvey and Company, $25; Heath and Milligan, $25.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
