<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-05-04">May 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The American Germanism. Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-05-04">May 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN GERMANISM. Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Lutherans of this country protest against the accusation of disloyalty and, especially, against the insinuation of being in any way connected with the German Empire or German Imperial house. In American circles the opinion prevails, that the Germans in America are inseparably connected with the German Empire. This statement is as untrue as can be. The German Americans leveled their own way, without the slightest help from the other side of the ocean. Until 1870 the Germans of this country stood in a hostile attitude towards Germany. The prevailing European narrow mindedness brought hundreds of thousands of Germans over here. Later, the immigration was fostered by economic conditions. An inclination towards the German government was not noticeable in this country even after 1870. Militarism never inspired the Germans in America. The lieutenant of the guard and the court martial were considered as the principal types of the military spirt, and therefore highly unsympathetic. Prussian feudalism was a thorn in thier flesh. The German churches, which were founded in this country, prove in their organization a sharp contrast to those of Germany. Here they are democratic, and over there monarchistic. This contrast is also noticeable in the <pb facs="5418474_9_1665.jpg" n="2"/>religious perception. The German church in America is tolerant of independent sentiment, in contrast to the faith of letters in Germany, which is dictated to the church from the superior officials. The Germans in America always have considered religion as a private affair, and not, as in Europe, a compulsary affair of the state, which lowers the church to its purpose.</p>
   <p>Rightfully the Lutherans, as well as the other German church synods can state, that no spiritual or even political connection exists between them and Germany.</p>
   <p>Their language is German, but their sentiment is absolutely American.</p>
   <p>Also the German schools, especially the public schools in which German is taught, have not the slightest connection with Germany. Agitators, who, according to their character, are not inclined towards truth have insinuated that the instruction in the German language is only serving the purpose of Germany's ruling classes. This of course, is in direct contradiction, because German schools were organized 100 years ago, when Germany was nothing more than a geographical concept. Their aim is purely educational; to teach, next to the <pb facs="5418474_9_1666.jpg" n="3"/>native language, another language, and the knowledge of foreign languages has been until today an evidence of education.</p>
   <p>In the last three centuries school societies were organized in Germany for the purpose of promoting the knowledge of the German language in foreign countries, but they Never contributed one cent for the support of German schools in this country. Apart from the money not being Needed it never would have been accepted because the instruction in the German language was always for the benefit of American institutions and not for those in Germany. Political Germany never found any consideration, only the cultural Germany. formed subjects for instructions.</p>
   <p>In all high schools, at least three foreign languages are taught and only a completely ignorant person can assert, that with each language learned, mission to the foreign nation unalterably ensues. should not accept the judgement of persons, who are not culturally inclined and, therefore. do not comprehend its meaning.</p>
   <p>In consideration of this, the German newspapers shall not be ignored. In this <pb facs="5418474_9_1667.jpg" n="4"/>case the demonstration is very easy, because the loyalty of the German newspapers is generally acknowledged.</p>
   <p>This loyal sentiment exists in all churches, in all lodges, and in all Germans, for the same reasons; that the development of American Germanism was accomplished in conformity with the views of this country. The agitation against the German language is beyond all understanding and the instigators commit themselves against truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
