<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">German Relief</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mass Meeting of the German-American Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN RELIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mass Meeting of The German-American Aid</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Man should be noble, ready to help, and good!" That was the motto of those who assembled for a meeting in Wicker Park Hall last evening at the invitation of the German-American Aid. The attendance could have been much better, but the enthusiasm was unsurpassable. Inspiring addresses by the speakers of the evening intensified the spirit of sacrifice.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank Friedensdorf, the chairman of the Society, opened the meeting and introduced the first speaker, Dr. H. Gerhard, the business manager of the German-American Aid, who pointed out that Americans of German descent had been made wary by certain happenings in connection with previous collections. In order to avoid any suspicion, he explained the activity of the Aid. He stated that the greatest need in Germany is milk for infants. He said that three weekly shipments of one hundred pounds of powdered milk have been forwarded to the Food Ministry at Berlin; <pb facs="5418474_9_0613.jpg" n="2"/>and that official body has been requested to notify the Aid of the receipt of these shipments. He also said that one hundred packages of this milk are sufficient to feed twenty-five hundred infants for a week, and that the amount sent each week would be increased. Later, fats also will be sent. These shipments are to be consigned to the various mayors for distribution to public kitchens which are being established throughout Germany and Austria. American citizens of German parentage are thus attempting to atone for sins committed against the German people.</p>
   <p>The Americans of German descent have been guilty of a great sin of omission, Dr. Gerhard declared, "namely that of failing to protest against the continued blockade which left unspeakable misery in its wake, especially in the Erz Gebirge, where ninety per cent of the children under one year of age died of rickets. There, weeds are the only available food--if one can call weeds food. Most of the children cannot attend school because they have no clothing, and they run about the country looking like skeletons."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0614.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Attorney Leopold Saltiel, who was the next speaker, said:</p>
   <p>"Let us not relax our efforts in behalf of this great charitable work. It is impossible to describe the full scope and the degree of the misery. Immediate and extensive help is necessary. The World War was a conspiracy of capitalists. German steel industries were a thorn in the side of our steel magnates who succeeded in obtaining control of steel production."</p>
   <p>Reverend Alfred Meyer emphasized the fact that we must help, that we want to help, and that we can help. He pointed out that the survey made by Hoover showed that the need is greatest in the industrial centers. Despite that fact, the Peace Conference demanded one hundred and sixty thousand milk cows from Germany.</p>
   <p>The contributions amounted to $189.25, the poultry raffle yielded $141.25, and $31.50 was received from the sale of buttons. The Junger Maennerchor contributed <pb facs="5418474_9_0615.jpg" n="4"/>$20, the Schiller Liedertafel, $90, the Schiller Ladies Auxiliary, $10, and R. Ewald, $26, making a total of more than $500 contributed to the good cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
