<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-12-06">Dec. 6, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Agent of the German Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-12-06">Dec. 6, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE AGENT OF THE GERMAN SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Report for Month of October</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Employment obtained for</cell>
     <cell>117</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Passes for poor immigrants</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located relatives or funds for</cell>
     <cell>20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located baggage for</cell>
     <cell>13</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Corresponded for</cell>
     <cell>36</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Assisted in financial matters</cell>
     <cell>12</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Families lodged</cell>
     <cell>3</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sick families provided with food</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lodged for one night</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Provided medical care and medicine for</cell>
     <cell>4</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>214</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1240.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Report for Month of November</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Employment obtained for</cell>
     <cell>95</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located relatives or friends for</cell>
     <cell>12</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located baggage for</cell>
     <cell>10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Corresponded for</cell>
     <cell>42</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Assisted in financial matters</cell>
     <cell>14</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sick aided</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Provided medical care and medicine for</cell>
     <cell>5</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>186</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>(On account of illness the agent was not able to compile and publish the report for October in due time.)</p>
   <p>Although immigration has decreased greatly during the past month, after the arrival of each ship a number of immigrants have come to Chicago from New York and an occasional few from Baltimore.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1241.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the winter months there is a strong demand in rural districts for laborers at a salary of from eight to ten dollars per month; however the supply is not sufficient to meet this rural demand, although many workers vainly seek employment in the city, and continue their fruitless quest until they have spent their last dollar. There is always ample opportunity for employment for girls, and the wages paid are high. Since winter weather has made shipping impractical, many workers, some of them very able men who worked in the sawmills of Michigan, have returned here; they complain that promises with reference to wages were not kept, that it was difficult to collect wages, and that prices of food and clothing are abnormally high; they recommend that only strong men accustomed to hard work apply for work at the mills, and that they demand a written contract. A written contract and (at the final accounting) a note signed by a responsible employer would protect many workers and their families against losses. This advice is also good for workers who hire themselves to the first available farmer, and it would be profitable for the latter to bind workers to serve for the duration of the harvest, by demanding that they sign a written agreement to that affect--after the usual month's <pb facs="5418474_9_1242.jpg" n="4"/>probational work.</p>
   <p>Winter weather having set in very early, some needy people come to the German House every day to ask for help; although Chicago has remained one of the most prosperous cities of the country despite the unfortunate conditions which generally prevail during these trying times.</p>
   <p>The first charitable offerings arrived at this office last week: two barrels of flour from a German merchant, and one dollar from a woman who does not wish to have her name mentioned. In this connection I wish to ask that the German citizens of Chicago continue to contribute to the support of the sick and the needy. Your agent will follow his custom of thoroughly investigating each case; and though some heartless people claim that the deserving poor are denied help, please do not believe them, for such statements are usually made by persons who have never done anything to alleviate the misery of unfortunates, and never will; they advance such claims merely as an excuse for not assisting in this cause. Where is there even one worthy person who can truthfully say <pb facs="5418474_9_1243.jpg" n="5"/>that your agent refused to help him? Very often these suspicious statements come from people who provide vagabonds with letters of recommendations, and make strenuous efforts to secure aid for bums who have been driven out of nearby cities. I can cite many instances in proof of my statement.</p>
   <p>The agent is in his office every morning from 9 to 12 A.M., and will be glad to accept gifts and donations. The public may be assured that these will be used only to administer to the needs of deserving persons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
