<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Relief Fund for the Destitute</title><title level="a" type="sub">Only a Little More Than Half a Million Dollars Collected So Far</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0723</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0723.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE RELIEF FUND FOR THE DESTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Only a Little More Than Half a Million Dollars Collected So Far</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Relief Fund for the war victims in Germany and Austria which is being collected in German-America, and for which a goal of two million dollars has been fixed, may hardly have topped the half million dollar mark, according to the Press Bureau of the German-American National Bund. The Press Bureau has based its calculations on compilations of reports of German newspapers giving the results of collections all over the country.</p>
   <p>A sum of twenty-five thousand dollars, in proportion to its inhabitants the largest amount collected (a little over ninety-one thousand) was contributed in Reading, Pennsylvania. If the German element in other cities would display the same generosity, the sum of two million dollars would soon be raised. Unfortunately, this is not the case. In Philadelphia, whose population is <pb facs="5418474_9_0724.jpg" n="2"/>sixteen times as large as that of the capital of Berks County, not quite eighteen thousand dollars had been collected, according to a collection list published September 27, even though the Relief drive started as early as August 9. In other cities the collections do not make much progress either.</p>
   <p>There is too much sympathy by word and too little sympathy backed by action in German-America. One is too generous with beautiful phrases, but too tight with the pocketbook. One is satisfied to have a collection list circulate among one's friends without giving an inspiring example by reaching into one's own pocket and sending a substantial amount to the treasurer of the local Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>And it is a strange fact that the spirit of sacrifice is much more in evidence with the little fellow who is not blessed with earthly possessions, <pb facs="5418474_9_0725.jpg" n="3"/>and with those German women who find it hard to make both ends meet, than in German-American circles where pennies don't have to be pinched any more, because they have made their pile. If people, who are reputed to be worth one hundred thousand dollars find it hard to pledge even one hundred dollars, we can only say that it must be a lack of affection for the old country and an indication of false "economy".</p>
   <p>Neither have German vereine and societies lived up to the expectations which could properly be placed in their generosity and spirit. A good account was given by the lodges of the Hermannessoehne and some war veteran societies, like the one in Omaha, Nebraska, which turned their entire building funds of twelve hundred dollars over to the Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>Of course the most shining example of German charity was provided by the Hod Carriers Union of Chicago which, as has already been reported, contributed five thousand dollars out of their treasury to the Relief Fund. This noble <pb facs="5418474_9_0726.jpg" n="4"/>deed of true humanity and patriotism deserves to be inscribed with golden letters in the history book of German-America.</p>
   <p>Everybody should make it his duty to give ten per cent of his weekly income for the good cause during the next five weeks. Of our well-to-do and effluent German fellow citizens we can justly expect that they donate one per cent of their fortune to the War Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>If that is done, not only two million, but at least ten million dollars can be sent as a gift from German-America to the old country. It is also recommended not only to make good resolutions but to carry them out. He who gives quickly, gives double. This is not a drive for voluntary contributions for a monument or a hospital, but a campaign for aid to our old country which is bleeding from a thousand wounds inflicted while fighting off her enemies.</p>
   <p>In this campaign we must not be tight with our purses and pinch pennies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0727.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Anybody who is indifferent to the plight of his native land, to which we are tied with a thousand bands, who keeps his pocket closed in the face of distress, who is still debating with himself and hesitant to make a contribution, who wants to see first what his friends and neighbors are doing and who will not move unless the others have done something first, should be ashamed of himself from the bottom of his heart.</p>
   <p>Because this campaign has made such slow progress, comparatively, we think it is about time to talk cold turkey. We want to see these contributions come in fast and plenty. It is certainly wrong if the German element of a great metropolis point to a collection of twelve thousand dollars and call it a "large amount for our city." It isn't that at all. On the contrary, it's a disgrace--a public confession of indifference and lack of [German] patriotism.</p>
   <p>This is not an everyday charity affair. It is an action of love for our <pb facs="5418474_9_0728.jpg" n="6"/>old country, which for the first time in forty-four years needs our help again. He who remains callous and indifferent now, when his "Mother Germania" is in distress, isn't worthy to bear a German name; he is in fact a fellow without a country, with on conscience, with no compassion for his blood brothers and his Volkstum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
