<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-17">Oct. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Great Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-17">Oct. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GREAT FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the following letter was sent to Mr. Philip Sheridan: You who once were called Duke of Shenandoah, you should now in Heaven's name take possession of Ogden's house in which 300 shelterless could be put up. Correct in this way the partiality of providence and be blessed by hundreds who have no roof over their heads.</p>
   <p>(Signed) H. Raster.</p>
   <p>It is our conviction that General Sheridan should carry out this suggestion. It is a shame that the military arm has confiscated houses on the West Side on which rent has been paid in advance, while the house of the twenty-fold millionaire Ogden, the only one that remains on the North Side, should stay untouched. This house must be confiscated for the shelter-less, or the conviction will become general that the rich Yankeedom wants to reconstruct Chicago as a Yankee city, at the cost of the poor Germans and Scandinavians. Also for another reason - hundreds of those who have lost everything have become half insane, and have only the one thought that there should be equality in misfortune. How if one of these unfortunates, with the idea of compensating an injustice of fate, were to put <pb facs="5418474_9_1132.jpg" n="2"/>the burning torch to the millionaire Ogden's house? Would it not be desirable in order to obviate any such temptation to make this house a refuge for the victims of the fire? That, in any case, would make the compassion of the rich Americans for the poor, burnt-down Germans and Scandinavians more convincing, than all merely oratorical expressions of sympathy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
