<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-17">Aug. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">German Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Monthly Session of the Executives</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-17">Aug. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Monthly Session of the Executives</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular session of the Executive committee of the German Home for the Aged was held on Thursday afternoon at the Atlantic Hotel. President Scheunemann acted as chairman. After reading the minutes and considering current business problems, the following persons were considered acceptable for admission, on the strength of recommendations made by the Committee on Acceptance: Miss Anna Mueller, 68 years old; Mr. John Busch, of the same age; Bernhard Gerke, 68; John Beerbaum, 68; and Gustav Sturz, 72 years old.</p>
   <p>The report of the secretary, Mrs. Constance Eberlein follows, giving its salient features: The monthly session of the administration was held on Thursday, August 7, at the institution. Present were: Messrs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0387.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Scheunemann and Goetz, as well as the following ladies: Mrs. Schmidt, Mrs. V. Wysow, Mrs. Wieboldt, Mrs. Kuehl, Mrs. Koop and Mrs. Eberlein. All books and bills were carefully examined. The total expenditures during July amounted to $4,549. Mr. Theodore Ritter, and Mrs. Alwine Schlief, were accepted as new inmates. The former on July 2, the latter on July 30.</p>
   <p>We regret the demise of several of our wards.</p>
   <p>Everything is in the best of order throughout the premises. The following ladies were nominated as members of the purchasing committee: Mrs. Schmidt, Mrs. Kuehl, and Mrs. Juergens. The room committee consists of Mrs. Schmidt, Mrs. Hetzel, Mrs. Koop, and Mrs. Wieboldt; all are members of the administrative council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
