<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-28">June 28, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to the German-Speaking Citizens of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-06-28">June 28, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO THE GERMAN-SPEAKING CITIZENS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At various times we have called attention to the fact that the membership of the German Society, which has assisted so many of our countrymen during times of distress, is not in proportion to the number of Germans living in Chicago.</p>
   <p>During the last few years various means have been tried to call the attention of the local Germans to the welfare activities of the German Society and, although membership has increased somewhat in consequence, it has not at all kept pace with the growing German element here which, incidentally, has become more prosperous while the demands made upon our Society have mounted steadily. If one considers the fact that in 1854, the first year of the Society's existence, membership amounted to about 250 with total annual dues of $1,600, one would have to go quite a bit out of the way to find a good excuse for the lack of a charitable spirit among our countrymen and to explain the fact that the names of most of them still cannot be found on the membership list of the German Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every year about eight thousand persons are aided and receive advice. In the last year alone 1,711 persons were placed into jobs; 408 were successfully recommended to the County authorities and 322 more sent to the Chicago Aid and Relief Society, where they were furnished with clothing; 40 received medical aid; 97 sick persons were sent to the hospital and 44 to the dispensary, where they were accepted and treated; 140 people received free transportation, and 366 partial transportation. Direct monetary assistance, which taxed the reserve funds of the Society itself, amounted to nearly two thousand dollars during the same year.</p>
   <p>Having only a slightly larger membership than during the first year of its existence and with a smaller annual contribution, the German Society has indeed no cause to look with satisfaction on the co-operation which our German compatriots have rendered in its efforts during the past twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>If it be desirable, in view of the above facts, that there should be a manifold increase in membership, how much more desirable should such an increase be at times like these, when greater immigration will augment the number of <pb facs="5418474_9_0091.jpg" n="3"/>aid seeking persons considerably and the demands made on the German Society will be more urgent than ever before. And it takes only the nominal amount of four dollars for annual dues to become a member of the Society.</p>
   <p>Of the many healthy workers who will presently emigrate here we can expect that a great number, before finding gainful employment, will have urgent need of the advice and the assistance of our Society, since they do not know the language here and will easily fall victim to adverse circumstances.</p>
   <p>But if we extend a helping hand to these newcomers at first we will, through them, preserve a part of that immense working power and efficiency of our people which has won the admiration of all thinking persons not only here, but also on the other side of the ocean.</p>
   <p>We can, therefore, take the liberty to tell our German countrymen that we consider it their duty to support the German Society by giving it more enthusiastic co-operation. They will thereby liquidate their obligation to <pb facs="5418474_9_0092.jpg" n="4"/>those who are forced by adverse conditions of everyday life to call upon the Society for temporary aid.</p>
   <p>There is no real reason why the majority of our better situated Germans should not consider the membership list of the German Society as an honor roll, bearing their names as so many testimonials of their charity and interest in the common welfare.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that there were far fewer well-to-do Germans in 1854 than are now blessed with earthly goods, the German Society should have progressed on a far larger scale than has actually been the case. There should not be just 260 members but thousands of them.</p>
   <p>We are, therefore, addressing an urgent appeal to our German fellow citizens to join the German Society and, by helping in the fulfillment of the hard task with which it is confronted, to erase the poor marks of the past forever.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0093.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In behalf of the German Society:</p>
   <p>The Promotion Committee:</p>
   <p>Jack Beiersdorf, 184-86 Wabash Avenue:</p>
   <p>Max Eberhardt, Corner Canal and Randolph Streets;</p>
   <p>Geo. Buehler, 78 Fifth Avenue;</p>
   <p>Art. Erbe, City Hall;</p>
   <p>Henry Biroth, 86 Archer Avenue;</p>
   <p>W. A. Hettich, Sherman House;</p>
   <p>Carl Lotz, 73 W. Twelfth Street;</p>
   <p>Henry W. Hill, 142 Dearborn Street.</p>
   <p>P. S. Membership applications will be accepted at the office of the German Society, 51-53 La Salle Street; also by members of the Promotion Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
