<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">German Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an effort to be able, to some extent, to stem the want among needy families during the approaching winter months, the German Society of Chicago will have to get a few thousand dollars together, because its own cash is not sufficient. To be sure, kind-hearted donors, enumerated below, bestow larger gifts for which the heartiest thanks are expressed in the name of the needy persons. Owing, however, to the disquieting and continually increasing unemployment situation, and to the cold weather which set in early, the claims upon the Society became so numerous that a large part of its means has already been used up.</p>
   <p>The kind donors who enabled the Society to continue its humane work were: the Swabian Society, $200; Germanic Rundfunk, as net proceeds from the "Fledermans" performance, $235.37; German Day Association, from the net proceeds of the German Day celebration, first $300 and later $600. Of <pb facs="5418474_9_0471.jpg" n="2"/>the latter sum, half should be given, according to stipulation, exclusively to German-Austrian and to German-Hungarian families.</p>
   <p>During the months of October and November, the German Society gave aid to fifty-eight families with 171 children, procured admission for seven persons in private hospitals, for ten in the county hospital, for two in the institution at Oak Forest--all free of charge. It further provided free medical treatment for six, including drugs, etc. To hundreds it gave advice in their dire need, or pointed out to them the right places where they could obtain help.</p>
   <p>Nearly six thousand unemployed went in and out of the office of the Society seeking work. Thus the usually average number was exceeded by 2200 per month. The Society could give employment to only 150 persons, but the wages offered were low and the figure for steady jobs was lower by 505 (sic).</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0472.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The planned great celebration on the occasion of the eightieth anniversary of the German Society will take place at the beginning of next year, perhaps in January or February. It will mainly serve the purpose of bringing in the funds necessary to keep up the activities of the German Society. The day and locality will be announced later.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
