<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-04">Aug. 4, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Think of New Ulm</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Has Not Done its Duty by Any Means</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0931</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0931.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-04">Aug. 4, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THINK OF NEW ULM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Has Not Done Its Duty by Any Means</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The contributions for New Ulm, so far as Chicago was concerned, had only reached $9,000 up to yesterday evening. Of course many committees have not yet submitted their reports, but nevertheless, the result was anything but satisfactory. Above all other cities it is Chicago's undeniable, sacred duty to help its sister city [Translator's note: Sister city in this case refers to the fact that New Ulm was originally settled by Chicago Germans, members of the Turners' Association] in the proper manner until a sum commensurate with the losses caused by the catastrophe [cyclone] has been raised.</p>
   <p>The benefit concert will be given tomorrow evening at Mc Cormick's Hall. It provides an opportunity for those who can contribute only moderately to the <pb facs="5418474_9_0932.jpg" n="2"/>relief fund to do their share, since the tickets cost only fifty cents, and every cent goes to the fund. The concert in itself will be fully worth the price, since the program presents the best selections of the combined choral numbers given at the last song festival and various choral pieces sung by our various clubs, including numbers by such soloists as Hugo Lindau, E. Schultze, A. Leivermann, and others. [Translator's note: In another article the name is spelled Leiermann.</p>
   <p>Miss McCarthy cannot appear, unfortunately, since she will not be able to reach Chicago in time, and Mrs. Bartlett-Davis, who gladly consented to participate, has suddenly been taken ill. The concert will therefore be given without the participation of any women [singers] and in this respect will be a novelty.</p>
   <p>The last rehearsal will be held this evening at Mc Cormick's Hall, and all participants are requested to be present at eight o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
