<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-19">Oct. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Decide to Consolidate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-10-19">Oct. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DECIDE TO CONSOLIDATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Lincoln Turner Hall a well-attended meeting of the Deutsch-Amerikanische Hilfe (German-American Aid [Society] took place last night for the purpose of discussing the planned consolidation with the Oesterreichisch-Ungarischen Hilfsgesellschaft (Austro-Hungarian Aid Society).</p>
   <p>From the arguments it became clear at once that the D. A. H. is absolutely convinced that the relief work for destitute Germany has to be done as efficiently and quickly as possible and that the amalgamation of the two great aid societies is not only desirable, but, in the interest of the destitute over there as well as the local German element, is almost imperative.</p>
   <p>It was unanimously resolved to unite the two societies.</p>
   <p>Dr. Otto [L.] Schmidt, the president, appointed a committee which is to meet on Tuesday afternoon at 4:30 P. M. at the Hotel Randolph where the amalgamation <pb facs="5418474_9_0581.jpg" n="2"/>will be organized by a combined consolidation committee of the German and Austrian societies. Appointed were Mr. Frank Friedersdorf, first chairman; Mr. Kurt Hildebrand, second chairman; Dr. Brune, secretary; Dr. Gerhart, business manager; Josef Sieben, treasurer; Reverend Alfred Meyer and Ernst Kruetgen. Dr. Schmidt, president of the D. A. H., and Ferdinand Walther of the [Austrian] aid society will also be present at the Tuesday meeting.</p>
   <p>The meeting took cognizance of the death of Reverend Kohlmann, a zealous member of the D. A. H., and appointed a committee to attend his funeral tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The financial report showed that the D. A. H. had collected about twenty-five thousand dollars, and had sent about three thousand dollars' worth of milk to Germany. For this week further milk shipments amounting to ten thousand dollars are scheduled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
