<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-12-08">Dec. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">German Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Detailed Annual Report by the President. Mr. Eberhardt</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0860</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0860.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-12-08">Dec. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">A DETAILED ANNUAL REPORT BY THE PRESIDENT. MR. EBERHARDT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Society held its annual meeting last night. Its President, the Justice of the Peace, M. Eberhardt, read the annual report of the society, which extented over the period from December 1, 1890, until December 1, 1891. The activities of the German Society were beneficial and successful. The income was increased and the expenses were restricted to the most necessary requirements. All reasonable claims of those seeking help and assistance have been readily granted. The membership of the society increased during the last two years from 675 to 1001, exclusive of 83 members who left the society. This large increase is evidence of the generosity of the Germans and of the successful activities of the society's workers.</p>
   <p>The amount of regular contributions by members has increased by $2703 and 37 members voluntarily raised their combined contributions by $75.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0861.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to a pretty accurate estimate, 100,000 immigrants came to Chicago, of which approximately one third Germans. It is not possible to ascertain definitely how many of these remained in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The employment office of the society revealed the glad news that the inquiries for workers by employers increased remarkably. The German Society was able to place 3169 workers, and 3226 inquired for work. Good farm help was much in demand.</p>
   <p>During the year a total of 445 families with 1162 children, and 202 single persons obtained help from the society. The amount of $2008.77 was spent for this purpose. The expenses have been reduced compared with the previous year, because it was easier to place those who wanted work.</p>
   <p>The German Society received during the past year 458 letters to be delivered to immigrants, and only 30 of them had to be returned as unknown.</p>
   <p>President Eberhardt praised the agent of the German Society. O. Kuhne, and his assistant, A. Sander, for their energetic and untiring efforts in behalf of the society. He also expressed gratitude to the County Agent, to the Chicago Relief <pb facs="5418474_9_0862.jpg" n="3"/>and Aid Society, and to the Bureau of Justice for services rendered. A tribute of thanks was likewise extended to the physicians and pharmacists who had given assistance free of charge, as well as to the German, the Alexian, St. Lucas, County, and M. Reese Hospitals for the admission of patients.</p>
   <p>The treasurer of the society, C. L. Nichoff, gave the following financial report,</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Income</cell>
     <cell>$21,562.47</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on Dec. 1, 1890</cell>
     <cell>2,859.60</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$24,422.07</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Expenses</cell>
     <cell>22,827.62</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand, Dec. 1, 1891</cell>
     <cell>1,594.45</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$24,422.07</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
