<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-13">May 13, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The German Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-13">May 13, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Board of Directors of the German Hospital has sent out a call to the Germans of Chicago stressing the importance of a German hospital. Chicago with its 250,000 German residents is in need of a hospital of considerable size. We know, that every German at the sound of his mother language is put in mind of home, and how much more influence would these sounds produce in the spirit of a sick person, if he were surrounded by people speaking his language, familiar with the customs of his country, and whose wishes they also understand.</p>
   <p>It is the sacred duty of all Germans, to work towards the erection of a hospital which would devote its services especially to the suffering persons of German birth. Our interest should be awakened by the fact that other cities in this country, large and small, show much more <pb facs="5418474_9_0232.jpg" n="2"/>concern in this matter, and it is hightime that Chicago's Germans become duty conscious and keep pace with these cities. A small group of our German citizens interested in the erection of such an institution, commenced with this good work in 1883, when they asked December 17th, of that year for the incorporation of the German Hospital of Chicago. Since the late summer of 1884 the private building at 242 Lincoln Ave,, has been used for hospital purposes and since that time the hospital has taken care of 223 patients with excellent success in each case.</p>
   <p>The need for a larger hospital is obvious, the applications for admittance to the hospital are becoming more numerous every day, but for lack of room patients have to be turned away. The German Hospital of Chicago owns a building lot at the corner of Grand Place and Larrabee Street, and it is the intention of the Board of Directors to begin with the building of the hospital immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0233.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Only one wing of the building planned will go into construction at the present time, with a frontage measuring 36 feet and 80 feet in depth. This building, which will provide room for about 85 or 90 beds, will to a certain extent help lessen the urgent need in this matter. The building cost will be approximately $14,000 to $15,000, and the Board of Directors trusts that Chicago's Germans will help and by giving their support to this humanitarian undertaking.</p>
   <p>Geo. Schneider, Chas. Emmerich, John Konig, Adolph Sturm, M. Bauer, Chas. G. Meyer, J. W. Kindt, H. Metzzer, John E. Burmeister, F. J. Henning, Max Eberhardt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
