<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">What the People Say</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Letters to the Editor]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0694</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0694.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE PEOPLE SAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Letters to the Editor]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With your article "Parcel Post to the Rescue," you finally hit the nail on the head. Your appeal has taken the words out of my mouth, because I have pondered such a plan for quite some time. England wants to condemn seventy million German men, women, children, old people, and babies to slow starvation, a plan which shows such diabolical bestiality that only a satanic brain could have doped it out. And are we to remain inactive in the face of such a colossal outrage? Whether German or non-German, a protest must be raised right here and now on behalf of humanity; and not a paper protest either, but backed up with plenty of action!</p>
   <p>Parcel post service provides us with the means to combat this British scheme hatched in hell. We will get much more satisfaction out of helping our beloved ones and friends at home personally, than to give to the "Red Cross," <pb facs="5418474_9_0695.jpg" n="2"/>generous though our gifts have been. And if we had just one dear person in the old country, if we had given to the Red Cross time and again, now we will open our pockets once more, to support this program of pure brotherly love. And people who are inclined by nature to rebel against any kind of oppression will welcome this opportunity to take part in this fight against the mean and cowardly starvation warfare of the perfidious British Government.</p>
   <p>How can we carry out our plan? Just to send flour to Germany would not only be impractical from a business point of view, but absolutely without purpose, as long as we can send victuals across which contain a much higher nutritional value by volume, not requiring any higher postage. The British blockade is not limited to flour alone, but includes any kind of imports to Germany. Our parcel post service must accept any kind of foodstuffs for shipment, including meat products. It would be advisable, therefore, to send other, more highly nutritional and concentrated foodstuffs, which contain the greatest possible energy value for any given weight.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0696.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I have had in mind the establishment of several sales and service centers. The meat packers, the wholesale milling firms or flour dealers may find it profitable, for instance, to put up their goods in standard packages, which could be kept in stock at these sales centers. Lower prices could probably be obtained also. The customers could make their selection and the merchandise could be made ready for shipment right on the spot. A simplified mailing system could probably be worked out with the Postoffice Department. Lots of German women and girls would feel honored to act as sales clerks and help with the mailing.</p>
   <p>However, these are details that will take care of themselves. The main thing is to get started. If our experiment is successful here, the movement will spread quickly all over the United States. Maybe the German American National Bund would co-operate too.</p>
   <p>Once our enterprise meets with the desired and anticipated success, the mail steamers now in service between here and Germany, via Holland, Denmark, and <pb facs="5418474_9_0697.jpg" n="4"/>Italy will not be able to handle the traffic. This obstacle has to be overcome. The Postoffice Department will have to let more boats carry the mail. More than a hundred additional ships have changed to American registry, making use of the new law. A large number of them has been chartered by our chemical manufacturers for the sole purpose of bringing German chemical products over here via Rotterdam. Maybe we could use these bottoms for our purposes as well. Then we'd dare anybody to tinker with our mail! Our Government in Washington has taken a lot of things, but in this respect they have always been very touchy.</p>
   <p>[signed] Kurt Pietrusky</p>
   <p>Permit me to touch upon the controversy as to whether it is possible to send flour to Germany, as you have suggested in your issue of last Saturday. It is my opinion that this should have been done much sooner because now it will be a real tough job, since England (God punish her!) will carry out her threat and seize all goods going to or coming from Germany. A little while <pb facs="5418474_9_0698.jpg" n="5"/>back it could have been done, because if food ships could be sent to Belgium for the "poor children" there, there would be no reason why they could not have been sent for German children as well. But there was nobody to organize such a thing. I am certain that every German would have given a quantity of flour or something of the kind. I myself have wondered, for weeks past, whether there wasn't some way to get foodstuffs over there. The United States could not refuse to let American cargo vessels sail for Germany. Two ways are open, the direct and the indirect. The latter, of course, would be much more expensive and would take longer. As to the first, Germany would have to furnish convoy protection, which she gladly would and could do. Thats' the way I figured it out, providing,Italy would not object to transshipment.</p>
   <p>[signed] G. Roemmelt</p>
   <p>Your plan to use the parcel post [for food shipment] is certainly an excellent one and of great importance, if it is feasible, and every German and Austro- <pb facs="5418474_9_0699.jpg" n="6"/>Hungarian should welcome it. The mailing expenses naturally are very high, but it would be ridiculous to apply business standards here where it is a case of charity. A few dollars or shillings do not mean so much when a crisis can be averted. Let us not forget that our folks over there make much greater sacrifices. Should we let a few dollars stand in the way? Of course not! We must go to the rescue! Every German and Austro-Hungarian will surely do his best to make your plan a success.</p>
   <p>[signed] M. Geberger.</p>
   <p>Your article of March 13 regarding parcel post flour shipments to Germany really contains the best suggestion we have come across since the war started. If we can do it, we would again prove our noble sentiments to our fellow Americans, while John Bull will have a fit and lose another poison fang.</p>
   <p>We will proudly carry that ten-pound parcel to the post office. By the way, we may soon find a business firm which would put up standard packages at <pb facs="5418474_9_0700.jpg" n="7"/>reasonable rates and take over the mailing job.</p>
   <p>[signed] J. W. Richter</p>
   <p>Today I read your article "Parcel Post to the Rescue". I beg you to work for the realization of your plan as you have outlined it at the conclusion of your article. But it must be made the business of all Germans and German sympathizers in the country, by means of an effective propaganda campaign (one week isn't enough) in all pro-German newspapers of the country, by German and pro-German associations, by petitions circulated among club members, and then a day or, should I say, a certain hour should be fixed, when everybody would dash for the post office with pushcarts and express wagons, and make it hot for those clerks, mailing the flour parcels.</p>
   <p>Those poor folks in Germany must be suffering right now according to a letter received from the old country. Right now is the time to do something about it. Many thousands would be willing to wrap and mail parcels for a week.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0701.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>And if this thing works out it may be done regularly, say at the first of each month. We would not begrudge Uncle Sam all the postage he'll get, even if he acts very unfriendly toward our native land at present.</p>
   <p>The war will end with a great German victory. Then Germany and the world will recognize with amazement the great moral deed done by the German-Americans. And all the Anglo-maniacs here, and over there, will shamefully confess, "We have not fed the nations with bread, but with cannon".</p>
   <p>[signed] Reverend Karl Ostenkoetter</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
