<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-13">Dec. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas Aid for Needy Germans</title><title level="a" type="sub">Benefit Performances in the New Lorelei Theater on Friday, December 23</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-13">Dec. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS AID FOR NEEDY GERMANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Benefit Performances in the New Lorelei Theater on Friday, December 23</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Christmas is not just a festival of joy--it should, especially in our times, also be a festival of brotherly love. Bitter want has invaded hundreds of families. It is obvious that hardship is doubly felt at the time of the holidays. Is it not the duty of all those who have not been immediately affected by the misery of the times to contribute their share, to the best of their ability, so that want among our German brothers may be mitigated for the holidays?</p>
   <p>Reflecting upon these thoughts the management of the new Lorelei Theater on Belmont and Sheffield Avenues is planning a benefit performance for Friday, December 23. In this, it is aided by the publishers of the Abendpost and Sonntagpost, and the entire proceeds will go to German countrymen <pb facs="5418474_9_0492.jpg" n="2"/>suffering want.</p>
   <p>All proceeds from the moving picture performances of that day will be given over to be distributed in equal parts among the needy of the German Society and the German-Austro-Kungarian Charities Committee. It will be done so that possibly many shall receive a small Christmas gift.</p>
   <p>On that day there will be, as usual, five film performances from 1 P.M. to midnight. Admission fees are the same as on other days, i. e., twenty-five cents from 1 P.M. to 6 P.M. and thirty-five cents from 6 P.M. on.</p>
   <p>All circles have thus the possibility to take part in the benefit drive knowing that their few cents will be given in full to charity and that they will have seen a good German sound film.</p>
   <p>The proceeds are not to be lessened by reductions, for the management is donating the film, the theater, and the performance free of charge, while <pb facs="5418474_9_0493.jpg" n="3"/>the admission tickets were printed gratis by the Adria Printing Company.</p>
   <p>Although the prices of admission are low, it will be possible to gather a sizeable sum for the purposes of charity, but only if our German brethren would all attend. Everyone should have the few cents to spend, this the more so as he is getting to see a good film and, what is more, to help a German in need.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
