<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-13">Dec. 13, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Our German Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-13">Dec. 13, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO OUR GERMAN WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The glorious Christmas festival for our children draws ever nearer. What longing is awakened in young minds when we mention Christmas!</p>
   <p>Our memories of a happy childhood are the outstanding features of our declining years, and Christmas, above all, is indelibly impressed on our minds. How many poor children come to realize their abject poverty, when the world in general is merry and joyful, while the destitute are forgotten! In order to reach those children over whom dire want holds sway, and among whom the joys of Christmas are unknown, the Ladies' Aid of the German Society has decided to provide a number of children with warm clothing again this year and, incidentally, to arrange a festival for them.</p>
   <p>The concert, which had been arranged to provide funds for the purpose, unfortunately did not produce enough money to pay for the clothing which we intended to distribute, and therefore the ladies of the German Society found it <pb facs="5418474_9_0989.jpg" n="2"/>necessary to appeal to benevolently inclined Germans to help complete the work.</p>
   <p>Donations--small or large--are always appreciated. The Ladies' Aid Society decided not to make a general collection, but to appeal to those benevolently inclined people who would gladly provide the needed funds, so that poor children also may have a Merry Christmas.</p>
   <p>The following committee members will gladly receive your contributions: North Side: Mrs. Claussenius, 149 Cass Street; Mrs. Molter, 484 Dearborn Avenue; Mrs. Ebener, 401 Larrabee Street.</p>
   <p>West Side: Mrs. Bluthardt, 43 South Peoria Street; Mrs. Rapp, 217 West Madison Street; Mrs. Buehler, North Avenue and Robey Street.</p>
   <p>South Side: Mrs. Clara Berger, 431 Prairie Avenue; Mrs. Blumenschein, 328 Cottage Grove Avenue; Mrs. Marie Werkmeister, 129 Archer Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
