<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-05">Aug. 5, 1881</date><title level="a">New Ulm</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Success Expected</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0926</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0926.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-05">Aug. 5, 1881</date><title level="a">NEW ULM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Great Success Expected</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The benefit concert for the stricken people in New Ulm will be given by our local singing societies tonight in McCormick Hall. Quite aside from the purpose for which the concert is to be given, which should fill the hall to overflowing, the concert itself deserves liberal patronage. The program consists principally of typical male choral selections, simple songs for four voices, which should have been featured by our German singing societies but have been generally neglected. Male voices are never more effective than in these unpretending compositions of folk-song character, which invariably remind one of fields, verdant forests, and vineyards on hills--in short, of our beautiful German fatherland. And since these songs arouse our feeling for the land of our origin, it was a particularly fortunate idea to make such a selection for a concert which is to be given for our destitute countrymen. The singing societies accepted the idea in the proper spirit and in their performance offer that with which they are <pb facs="5418474_9_0927.jpg" n="2"/>most familiar, and therefore the public may expect to hear a real German male choral concert.</p>
   <p>In regard to the soloists who have promised to participate, Hugo Lindau of Cincinnati deserves special mention. He was scheduled to appear at the last festival concert but because of his father's sudden death did not come to Chicago. He is a highly gifted tenor and is bound to appeal to the audience. Let us hope that as an encore--which will surely be demanded after he sings the great aria from "Joseph"--he will oblige us by singing a simple German folk song, the more unpretentious the better. Mr. Leivermann intends to sing a popular air if an encore is requested and will not give us the "Porter's Song" from "Martha". Edward Schultze will also select some attractive German air, for which his appealing voice is so highly suited, instead of an opera part.</p>
   <p>As far as the financial aspect of the concert is concerned, we have assurances that the advance sale of tickets has been more than gratifying, and that the <pb facs="5418474_9_0928.jpg" n="3"/>ladies of the festival chorus have spared no efforts in disposing of the tickets. If some of the kind ladies who did not receive any tickets believe that they can place a few, then J. P. Hand, 176 Madison Street, first floor, or A. Bucher, 143 Wabash Avenue, will gladly supply them.</p>
   <p>The price of the tickets is only fifty cents, and the entire proceeds go to the people in New Ulm.</p>
   <p>The Program</p>
   <p>Tenor Solo, "Gebet vor der Schlacht".........................................Moehring</p>
   <p>Edward Schultze</p>
   <p>"Liebesfruehling".................................................................Zech</p>
   <p>Gesangverein Frohsinn</p>
   <p>Chorus and Solos, "Ossian"......................................................Beschnitt Schiller Liedertafel, Chicago Saengerbund, a section of the <pb facs="5418474_9_0929.jpg" n="4"/>Catholic casino Frohsinn, F. Spreyne, tenor, and P. Spod, bass</p>
   <p>"Fantasia from Rigoletto"...............................Liszt</p>
   <p>C. F. Balatka</p>
   <p>"Das Einsame Roeslein"..................................Hermes</p>
   <p>Orpheus Male Chorus</p>
   <p>Aria from "Joseph".......................................Mehnl</p>
   <p>Hugo Lindau</p>
   <p>"Brunnen Wunderbar".....................................Abt</p>
   <p>United Chorus and Hugo Greiner, baritone</p>
   <p>Aria from "Ernani".........................................Verdi</p>
   <p>A. Leivermann</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0930.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Mutterseelenallein"........................................Braun</p>
   <p>United Chorus</p>
   <p>"Gute Nacht"................................................Fischer</p>
   <p>Alemannia Maennerchor</p>
   <p>"Salomons Tempelweihe".................................United Chorus, H. Balatka, conductor, and A. Leivermann, bass</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
