<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-06">Aug. 6, 1888</date><title level="a">The Druid Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D I</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-06">Aug. 6, 1888</date><title level="a">THE DRUID MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After many years of planning, the Druid monument was dedicated yesterday at the Waldheim Cemetery. The ceremony was held in the presence of an exceedingly large crowd of members of local and other Chapters of the Druid Order. A train of sixteen coaches transported most of the members to the well-known German cemetery yesterday morning. There all preparations had been completed for this solemn festival--the dedication of the beautiful Druid monument.</p>
   <p>The crowd soon gathered around the magnificent monument which was located between shade trees and draped with a white cloth. Beside the monument a platform was erected and decorated with evergreen branches....Mr. W. H. Meyer, the master of ceremonies, opened the program by introducing the members of the monument committee.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koepke, one of the committee members, addressed the assemblage, giving a brief sketch of the history of the monument. According to his statements, <pb facs="5418474_9_0072.jpg" n="2"/>the monument was erected by Mr. A. Kistenbroker and cost $4,175. The monument was unveiled, and the speaker turned the ceremony over to Mr. Klemm, president of the Cook County Chapters of the Druid fraternity. The following are quotations from his speech:</p>
   <p>"This monument of the Druids is the only one of its kind anywhere upon the globe. At every fitting opportunity brethren from far and near should gather around it to express the one ideal and purpose of the Druids--to assist all brethren in need, and to comfort them in misfortune and distress....."</p>
   <p>The master of ceremonies then introduced the principal speaker for the occasion, Mr. A. Thorpe, who spoke in part as follows:</p>
   <p>"When I look over the large gathering of brothers and sisters of our Druid Order, I can see many already far advanced in years who have diligently and honestly contributed their share to the transforming of this once large <pb facs="5418474_9_0073.jpg" n="3"/>wilderness into a place of culture and progress. Our system and our efforts have kept pace with the rapidly moving spirit of the age. We have established new chapters for the benefit and blessing of the young generation of Germans....We Druids have erected a monument, in the form of this exalted Archdruid, to charity, brotherly love, peace,and unity--a monument that shall silently testify of our efforts and inspire younger generations to follow in our steps.....</p>
   <p>"At Salisbury, England, there still exists the colossal Stonehenge of the Druids, which some historians assert is over 25,000 years old. We can not yet comprehend how this colossal work was accomplished by the hands of men. How many storms, cyclones, and earthquakes have swept over this monument of antiquity which still exists as the ruins of a Druid Temple?</p>
   <p>"And you also, you monument of the Druids of Chicago, may you stand for centuries as a visible sign of the wisdom, the virtue, and the love of humanity in accordance with our principles, which have been written on the <pb facs="5418474_9_0074.jpg" n="4"/>banners of our order, and taught among us since time immemorial."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
