<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">Aug. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Uhlich's Orphanage Picnic.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">Aug. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">UHLICH'S ORPHANAGE PICNIC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The picnic at Odgen's Grove - a festival commemorating the 25th Anniversary of Uhlich's Orphanage - attracted many friends and admirers of the institution. The achievements and influence of this orphanage have found worthy recognition even among the non-German population, a proof that interest in its future does not wane but, on the contrary, is bound to grow.</p>
   <p>At one o'clock, headed by Mr. A. H. Lang, superintendent of the orphanage, and a brass band, a children parade starting from Burling, near Center Street, marched gayly to the grove, a festively decorated spot which soon became the scene of great merrymaking. As in the past, this year the Ladies' Club had donated tempting delicacies, which were greatly relished by the youngsters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Pastor John made a speech in which he expressed gratitude for the cooperation given the orphanage in the past, adding that the same attitude was expected to continue in the future; since the success of the institution depends on the generosity of the people. He remarked that the interest shown on this occasion was proof that cooperation was not lacking. The next speaker was General Hermann Lieb. He spoke in English, thanking the leaders of the institution for their work in behalf of the community, regardless of national origins.</p>
   <p>Some of the orphans entertained the picnickers with songs which earned them great applause.</p>
   <p>Then came a long awaited feature of the program which quickened the pulse of the youngsters - the distribution of presents. Gifts had been <pb facs="5418474_9_0322.jpg" n="3"/>selected according to individual taste, which made the children still happier. The climax of the festival was the raffling by the Ladies' Club of a velocipede, the tickets for which were eagerly and vociferously demanded by all the youngsters. The picnic ended with a repast, after which the homeward march followed.</p>
   <p>The festival, as usual, was planned by the staff of the institution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
