<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">German Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Monthly Session of the Executive Committee; Report of the Administrative Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Monthly Session Of The Executive Committee; Report Of The Administrative Council</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The monthly meeting of the Executive Committee, with president Louis Sala functioning as chairman, was held yesterday afternoon at the Kaiserhof. The session had been postponed for a week, and therefore the officials held their conference on the 17th of this month. During the proceedings, emphasis was given to the fact that several fires, which had started on the premises, were unpreventable regardless of all possible precautions. The damaged sections, -the main living quarters were not burnt,-will be reconstructed in a fire-proof manner.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Clara Rehtmeyer, secretary of the Administrative Council and president of the Women's Club, submitted the following report for the month of January:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0409.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The monthly meeting of the Administrative Council was held at the Altenheim (Home for the Aged), on Feb. 12. The accounts were thoroughly investigated; orders for supplies and bills show no errors; and we therefore recommend that the Executive Committee accept the report and make provisions for payment.</p>
   <p>The total expenditure for January, according to the report of the administrator, was $3,180.78. The Committee on Rooms reported nine deaths. During the early part of January, we had an epidemic of grippe and about eighty inmates were afflicted. It was therefore necessary to employ three additional nurses temporarily. The staff physician visited the patients daily and we feel profoundly indebted to him, as his unselfish spirit and genuine sense of duty have been the deciding factor in reducing the number of the dead.</p>
   <p>One of the inmates, Mr. Nick Mass, donated $150 to the Home. The Administrative Committee expresses its most cordial thanks for this <pb facs="5418474_9_0410.jpg" n="3"/>contribution.</p>
   <p>Fire broke out in the Hospital Building during the night of January 30 due to a defective chimney. The Forest Park and Oak Park fire department appeared promptly and extinguished it quickly. Several employees as well as the administrator and nurses quickly came to the rescue of the sick and disabled and therefore, fortunately, no lives were lost.</p>
   <p>The Council recommends that the Executive Committee express its gratitude to the many friends of the institution for their generous monthly contributions.</p>
   <p>The report was accepted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
