<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-17">Nov. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">German Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-17">Nov. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the report of the Association's benevolent activities, the last month showed an alarming recession in employment, a condition unequalled within the last four years. Indications presage the approach of a difficult period. The number of unemployed applying to the Association increased by fully one half (2,500), and that we could procure jobs for a hundred and fourteen is attributable only to the fortunate circumstance that three firms asked for ten to twelve people at a time. However, the work is only temporary.</p>
   <p>The customary factor to aggravate this serious condition manifested itself with the approach of cooler weather. The demands upon the Society's resources increased perceptibly. As soon as the winter months force the thermometer still lower, the number of impoverished families asking for aid will still be greater.</p>
   <p>As the Association's cash reserve and supply of warm clothing are exhausted, <pb facs="5418474_9_0509.jpg" n="2"/>we are compelled to ask for financial assistance and donations, such as used overcoats, clothing of all kinds, underwear, shoes, and so forth. Kindly send monetary contributions to the German Society, 160 N. Wells Street. The Society will gladly call for clothing, if notified in writing or by telephone, Randolph 4039.</p>
   <p>In October the German Society helped 44 families and 129 children; also 17 single persons, five of whom were women. It provided shelter and food to unemployed people, namely, 199 meals, and lodging for 144; it took five persons to private hospitals, eight to Cook County hospital, five to Oak Forest, one to the sanatorium for consumptives, where they were given free treatment. Medical treatment, medicine, etc., were given gratuitously to fourteen persons.</p>
   <p>The expenditures for the aforesaid purposes amounted to $704.55</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
