<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-25">Dec. 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">War on Gangsters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-25">Dec. 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">WAR ON GANGSTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago police have, of late, been using some strong tactics against gangsters at the instigation of the mayor. If they continue on the path they have set out to pursue, results should soon become tangible. Instead of negotiating with the representatives of the underworld to deal with them or to procure for them occasions to do damage with their revolvers, the police are now to shoot first as soon as the cornered gangster leaders or their associates make one suspicious move. This is the only right way to deal with these gentlemen, and it is regretable if each shot from a policeman's gun does not do its full duty on such occasions. Determined action at the right moment saves work for the police and the courts, and unnecessary expenses for the taxpayer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The police can crack down only when the mayor, the district attorney, and the judges approve their actions and lend them the support needed. As far as justice is concerned, this is self-evident. But we regret to say, as is known to Chicagoans, that this is not self-evident here. Gangsters have come out scot-free frequently enough owing to political influence, or they were given occasion to become scarce before they were taken to trial and kept away until the air became pure again. As long as such collusions persist because it is difficult to prove them in individual cases and in large numbers taken individually, all the"cracking down" by the police will do us no good in cleaning the city from crime.</p>
   <p>It is up to the citizens to insist that the officers appointed by them should once and for all take a decisive stand against crime, a stand one has a right to expect of order, of society, and of the law. Part work does no good. Work must be done here in its entire (sic) and all the organs of public welfare will have to co-operate one with the other.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The officer who in this respect is doing his work only half-heartedly or not at all should be dismissed and penalized. If he happens to be an elected officer, such as a judge for instance, impeachment procedures should be started against him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
