<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-04">Mar. 4, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">A Comparison of Benevolent Activities Among Germans and Jews.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0875</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0875.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10 (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-04">Mar. 4, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">A COMPARISON OF BENEVOLENT ACTIVITIES AMONG GERMANS AND JEWS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Sunday issue of the Chicago Herald a comparison is made of the benevolent activities of the Germans and the Jews of this city. There are 200,000 Germans back of the German Society and only 35,000 Jews support the United Hebrew Relief Association. The majority of the 200,000 Germans are well off, but a large number of the 35,000 Jews live in poverty. How do the Germans and the Jews take care of their poor? A thorough investigation of this matter disclosed the fact that the Jews take sufficient care of their poor, while the Germans do not.</p>
   <p>During the past year the German Society assisted 176 German families for which it spent $1,560.91, which is less than $10.00 per family. The United Hebrew Relief Association helped 1,224 families and spent $16,044.09 for this purpose. More than ninety per cent of these families came from Russia and Poland, but their benefactors, the Jews of Chicago, who contributed the money, were nearly all born in Germany.</p>
   <p>The German Society has about 700 members, who contribute annually between $4.00 <pb facs="5418474_9_0876.jpg" n="2"/>to $50.00. The Swiss Mutual Benefit Association furnished the largest amount, namely $200.00 due to the fact that the German Society takes care also of the Swiss. Not one of the German millionaires in Chicago gave $100.00 or more.</p>
   <p>The 200,000 Germans of Chicago, as represented by the 700 members, who are considered as the best of the total German population, contributed only $14,805.05 to the German Society, and of this amount the Society spent $13,800.00.</p>
   <p>Now let us compare this with the Jewish charitable activities, as represented by the United Hebrew Relief Association. This Association spent for relief, as mentioned before, the sum of $16,044.09, or $2,000.00 more than the German Society was able to spend for its different purposes. Thousands belong to the Jewish Association, and the example of the Sinai Congregation is evidence of their liberal contributions. Ten members of that congregation gave the total amount of $1,175.00. Of course, it is the richest of the Jewish congregations, yet others gave evidence of similar liberality.</p>
   <p>The agent of the German Society, W. C. A. Thielepape, was asked: "Why do the 200,000 Germans of Chicago contribute so little to charity for their countrymen?" <pb facs="5418474_9_0877.jpg" n="3"/>He replied with an air of indignation: "The Jews are more sensitive, and more susceptible to charity; but the Germans in Chicago are rather illiberal and every cent, destined for charity, must be wrested from them. We have in this city German millionaires who can spare $10.00 only, annually, for this Society, which is the only one assisting the needy among their own nationality. This is a disgrace for our German population, and, mind you, even these small contributions must be collected by us. We must make the rounds, and ask, and beg for the same, otherwise, we would have no means to help."</p>
   <p>If the Society has to labor under such unfavorable conditions then we can understand why it is unable to even approximately alleviate destitution prevalent among the German speaking population.</p>
   <p>It is true that the German Society has other activities, besides assisting the needy among their people. One of its chief purposes is to assist the immigrants from Germany in every possible way, and to find employment for those unemployed. But to help the needy and destitute among its own people belongs to its objectives. The Society assisted twenty-five families in the month of February, which required $105.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0878.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Jews, on the other hand, have a much better record. They assisted</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>143</cell>
     <cell>local,</cell>
     <cell>and</cell>
     <cell>20</cell>
     <cell>immigrant</cell>
     <cell>families</cell>
     <cell>in</cell>
     <cell>October</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>103</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>26</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>November</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>134</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>25</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>December</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>156</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>27</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>January</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>125</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>20</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>February</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
