<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-05">Aug. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-05">Aug. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2. The administration of the society held its meeting yesterday afternoon at its office, 49 La Salle Street under the chairmanship of Mr. George H. Rapp, vice president. At this regular monthly session the following gentlemen were present: Chas. Emmerich,....and eight others. Mr. Oscar Kuehne, the business manager of the Association, read the reports of last month. The present crisis has also affected the German Society. The requests for relief were much greater than during any July in the Association's history, likewise the demand for labor was considerably less than has ever been recorded for that month in former years. There is a considerable influx of unemployed Western laborers whose expectations do not materialize and they are generally without funds.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0844.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under these conditions they apply to us for aid or seek help from other charitable persons. Individuals and business people should be very careful before extending a helping hand, as there are many well disguised beggars, confidence-men and drunkards who use the present situation as a pretext for profitable mendicancy by pretending to be without work, food and shelter. Good farm workers always find immediate employment but those who claim to be able to do any kind of farm work but never did any, find difficulty in obtaining jobs.</p>
   <p>Aid was given to 34 families with 100 children, and to 22 single persons. Aid was extended for the first time to 17 families with 53 children and 5 single persons.</p>
   <p>The causes for these conditions are attributable to the following factors: 8 families were bereft of their supporter; 12 families became destitute <pb facs="5418474_9_0845.jpg" n="3"/>through the father's sickness or incapacity. Three families had ailing children; 6 families were deserted; 5 families were poverty stricken through unemployment.</p>
   <p>Regarding support given to the single persons: 6 were ill and incapable of earning a livelihood; 13 had no work nor funds. Three were old and decrepit.</p>
   <p>For this relief we spent $217.14 in cash and $5.94 for room and board. Employment was obtained for 217 people, whereby they saved $434 in labor agency fees. In labor matters we sent and received 436 letters and cards. The Fuller and Fuller Company and Mr. Frz. Bopp, Vice Consul, were initiated and paid the yearly dues, totaling $15.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
