<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The executive board of the German Old People's Home held its monthly meeting on December 15 at the Hotel Atlantic. Mr.[Robert G.] Scheunemann presided. The minutes of the preceding meeting were accepted as read.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Straub read the report of the administration, which was as follows: Under the chairmanship of their president, Mr. Scheunemann, the committee met on December 9 at the Home. The following ladies and gentlemen were present: Mmes. Kuehl, Juergens, Roessler, Dirks, Beiser, Swartz, and Straub; Messrs. Scheunemann, Seeler, Hann, and Brisch.</p>
   <p>The books and invoices were examined, and the latter were approved for remittance. The expenditures amounted to a total of $4,734.66. Three deaths were recorded last month: Pauline Cordes, Wilhelm Franz, and Peter Blum. New entrants: Mrs. Carrie Riedl, Mrs. Justine Lidl, Mrs. Minnie Ross, and Mr. Wm. Finck. The state of health of the inmates is good; there are no new cases of sickness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0374.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Quite a few new purchases were again necessary. The following gifts came in: Magazines from Mr. Adolph Gill, books from Mr. L. W. Kaeuffl, three crazy-quilt covers from Mrs. F. H. Arnold, fifty cans of jelly from Mr. August Taupel, and a barrel of apples and a barrel of potatoes from Mr. Ferdinand Hofz.</p>
   <p>The bathing and toilet rooms at the hospital were rebuilt and made more comfortable, and new floors were laid. In the basement of the old house a lavatory and a bath were built at a small cost.</p>
   <p>The farming land has all been ploughed and manured.</p>
   <p>It was necessary to fix the water pump, and the institution had to use city water; worn and broken parts had to be replaced by new ones, and it took a few days to do this.</p>
   <p>The male chorus of the German Baptists of Chicago gave a beautiful concert <pb facs="5418474_9_0375.jpg" n="3"/>with songs, piano and violin solos; it was, of course, welcomed with joy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wm. Klenze, chairman of the committee for admittances, recommended the following applicants for admittance: [There follows a long list of applicants.] The recommendations were accepted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
