<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-26">Dec. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">An Unnecessary Expense</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-26">Dec. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AN UNNECESSARY EXPENSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago a conference was held in Washington for the discussion of ways and means to cope effectively with crime. Much ink has been spilled over this conference. It could be seen most clearly from the various reports that the advocates of justice were no larger than the small flags of the knights of the medieval manors who took it upon themselves to exercise their profession at their own expense and peril. Here and there they gather for co-operative action, but then again drift apart and, in general, are quite jealous of their rights, thus inflicting damage upon justice rather than serving it. Facing them on the opposite side is crime, too well organized.</p>
   <p>Too much untoward treatment has been inflicted of late upon crime. Uncle Sam reached out his reliable fist and helped himself to some of the outstanding numbers without even flaring up about them (sic). It should, however, <pb facs="5418474_9_1369.jpg" n="2"/>be clearly understood that this is but a beginning, that the core of the problem has not yet been reached. Where this core is to be found was clearly demonstrated by an assistant attorney general, namely, what in this country is designated as politics. This speech gave occasion to a number of comments, mind you, nothing but comments.</p>
   <p>Now, the governor has called a conference to Springfield, next month, of all Illinois advocates of justice. In loyalty to Washington's politics, almost the same points are on the program and set for debate as were discussed the other day in the federal capital. Only one point was passed over. "Politics" and its variously indicated threats to crime is missing.</p>
   <p>It may have been political cunning not to touch on this sensitive point. Yes, it may even be in keeping with higher political wisdom to pass over these things in silence and, instead, to thresh just empty straw. This would make the subjects realize how much care is taken for their security, and how much responsibility is felt.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1370.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whole forests would have to be felled and made into paper to let all people see their ideas about "politics and crime" printed. Much more brain energy has been spent around this topic than was spent for many another invention that benefited all mankind. Stories have been uncovered that tell of the underworld with plenty of vivid and lurid details. The heroes, however, of these stories were mostly dead or those among the living whose reputation no longer could be made worse.</p>
   <p>One story even went so far that events were covertly insinuated which in their turn threw a "certain light" upon "certain persons," but never has even one person "from politics" been called by name when these gruesome stories were told. Many were the times when such persons were "exposed". As soon as the novelty evaporated, all threat was lost sight of, or was hushed up.</p>
   <p>If it is true that a large proportion of the underworld enjoys political protection, if it is true that by means of this protection back doors are <pb facs="5418474_9_1371.jpg" n="4"/>held open for criminals, if the system as a whole has its core in politics, what is the use of holding a conference? The costs will have to be borne by the taxpayers. The result will be zero, no matter how much reporting it may receive. This is no time for "whipping foam".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
