<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Give to the Utmost!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Jane Addams Describes Destitution in Germany</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GIVE TO THE UTMOST!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Jane Addams Describes Destitution in Germany</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Deutsche und Oesterreichisch-Ungarische Hilfsgesellschaft (German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society), working again for the alleviation of destitution in Germany after a two-year period of inactivity, last night again appealed to the public. The location was the crowded hall of the Chicago Lincoln Club. Charles Wacker, Dr. Frank Gunsaulus, Jane Addams, Monsignore Rempe and Harry Rubens expressed the sentiments of the occasion in eloquent terms and created a profound response in the hearts of the audience. The tense manner in which the present representatives of the Chicago German element listened to the words of that great humanitarian woman, the two clergymen, the chairman and Mr. Rubens, the spontaneous and heartfelt applause, and the eagerness with which subscription lists were signed at the end of the meeting, were unmistakable evidence that the Aid Society's appeal to fellow citizens and compatriots to give quickly at a time when action really counts <pb facs="5418474_9_0583.jpg" n="2"/>has certainly not been in vain. The success of yesterday's meeting leads us to believe that through the co-operation of the German element the Aid Society will be able to continue on an even larger scale the noble work they started at the outbreak of the war, the relief of the needy in Germany and Austria.</p>
   <p>Speaking in English, Mr. Charles Wacker, the president of the Society, opened the meeting. This language was used by all the other speakers of the evening. Dr. Gunsaulus gave the opening prayer. He spoke of the contributions of the German people to the creation of the American nation. And he spoke of the efficacy of the spirit of peace and reconciliation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wacker gave a brief outline of the history and purpose of the Society. He announced that the thirty-five thousand dollars, which remained in the treasury when the Society suspended operations, had been used to purchase <pb facs="5418474_9_0584.jpg" n="3"/>hospital supplies, codliver oil, and powdered milk for Germany. He then introduced Miss Jane Addams as the first speaker.</p>
   <p>Spontaneous applause greeted Miss Jane Addams as she made her appearance--an expression of gratitude and adoration for this truly noble American woman whose heart is full of love for all humanity.</p>
   <p>Jane Addams' message has been published in the form of a phamphlet and in part in the daily press, including the Abendpost, but here, from the lips of this American apostle, in plain language that found its way directly into the hearts, it assumed a new meaning--it be came an overwhelming appeal to the conscience of the world, of America, and above all, of German-America.</p>
   <p>The speaker, who went abroad last May and who spent three weeks in Germany last summer, talked first about her visit to the war-torn regions of Northern France and of the first undernourished children she saw in Europe--in Lille. These children are given the best of care, eat the best food, and wear warm clothing---but <pb facs="5418474_9_0585.jpg" n="4"/>German children do not.</p>
   <p>Miss Addams encountered the first German and Austrian children in Switzerland. Many families have taken these children, who are suffering from malnutrition and are in danger of contracting tuberculosis, from German and Austrian towns to give them a few weeks' rest and good, nourishing food. All these children--there were six hundred of them--were underweight, and had lost their zest for life. They were too tired and too exhausted to talk or to play, the boys even more than the girls. In Zurich, in the home of a widow of a professor, Miss Addams saw five of these young guests who had become fast friends--three Belgian girls and two Austrian children.</p>
   <p>In Switzerland there is not exactly an abundance of food. Nothing is wasted. There is neither butter nor cheese, and bread, meat, etc., have to be obtained on ration cards. Only the children can get all foods in sufficient quantities.</p>
   <p>As an example of German discipline, as Herbert Hoover has called it, the speaker <pb facs="5418474_9_0586.jpg" n="5"/>pointed out that the foodstuffs which Hoover had sent via Hamburg to Czechoslovakia and other countries had to be unloaded and handled by German fathers whose children were hungry. They did it willingly and without grumbling despite the temptation this vast supply of food must have been--so near, and yet so far.</p>
   <p>"What I saw there," said Miss Addams, "made me decide to do my utmost to have certain foodstuffs sent to Germany. The German crops will absolutely have to be supplemented by imports. When I was there during July, very little came in from abroad. Since then things have become a little better.</p>
   <p>"In a display window on the main street in Frankfort, I saw a slab of American bacon. A large crowd in front of the window marveled at this kind of food which had become a rarity."</p>
   <p>The speaker then told of the milk distribution in Berlin. Milk is scarce, not only because-many cows had to be slaughtered, but also because there is a <pb facs="5418474_9_0587.jpg" n="6"/>shortage of fodder. What is left is of poor quality, and so is the milk. Milk production has declined to one seventeenth of the prewar production. Milk ration cards are issued to mothers, sick people, and to small children, but the supply is always insufficient.</p>
   <p>In Berlin hospitals Einheitsessen (uniform meals) are served, which means that a high government official gets the same kind of food as a scrub woman. Each week a loaf of white bread has to be shared by ten patients, and a comparatively small amount of soup meat is used for twenty-two hundred patients in one particular hospital. Dried vegetables, a broth made from them, wartime bread, and so-called "marmalade" make up a hospital diet which would hardly restore the health.</p>
   <p>Professor Kayserlingk told Miss Addams that the increase of tuberculosis in Germany is alarming, and that the disease is manifesting itself in new forms as a consequence of malnutrition and lack of fats in the diet. The lack is so acute that the meager supplies are preserved in all kinds of ways. It is <pb facs="5418474_9_0588.jpg" n="7"/>even extracted from the dishwater of hotel kitchens to be used again.</p>
   <p>Outwardly Berlin looks very clean, and much the same as in former times, and only the hustle and bustle around the railroad stations has disappeared. But the destitution becomes evident when one visits the apartments of the middle class as well as the poor.</p>
   <p>In Saxony, Miss Addams found living conditions even worse than in Berlin. The Chemnitz factories have been closed because of the lack of raw materials. Long lines gather before soup kitchens. The soup is made with sauerkraut, flour, and vegetables. Each large kettle also contains a piece of fat the size of a man's fist. The children look pitiful, except those who have relatives whom they can visit in the country.</p>
   <p>Destitution is especially great among the inhabitants of the Erzgebirge district, where things have never been plentiful. With a shudder one recalls the terrible "turnip time" of 1917, when turnips were the only food obtainable.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0589.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>At that time, ten out of forty children in a village school daily regurgitated the vile food which they were given for breakfast. The digestion of the children was ruined, and many elderly people died.</p>
   <p>In some regions there is deprivation even in the homes of the wealthy. Miss Addams visited a country estate where although uniformed served the dinner, the meal was far from substantial--soup made with wartime flour, vegetables, and, an unheard of luxury, fruit and real rice! In a similar home, however, a comparatively good supper was served. In Frankfort the visitor saw many refugees from the occupied territory on the left bank of the Rhine.</p>
   <p>Miss Addams called special attention to the great need for hospital supplies, particularly rubber items. Even nipples for infants were made of paper until English women asked their Government to permit the importation of rubber nipples. Even babies wrappings were made of paper. Many sick people cannot be given adequate treatment because of the lack of necessary supplies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0590.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"Mother, is it true that there are countries where one can eat anything one wants?" a little girl asked her mother.</p>
   <p>Some doctors hope that by "overfeeding" fats the damages of malnutrition can be remedied, but others believe that the damage done to the younger generation can never be repaired.</p>
   <p>At any rate, much will depend on how much can be given and done without delay. The worst thing is that the children have to go to bed crying with hunger. That breaks the heart of many a mother who would gladly deny herself everything.</p>
   <p>In Austria, children are fed through the Hoover foundation, but they are not allowed to carry food home because there is not enough for everybody. The speaker expressed hope that in Germany, too, the school children will soon be fed. It is hoped that funds will soon be made available, and to supply this need everybody turns to America, the land of plenty.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0591.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Monsignore Rempe brought good news to the audience from Archbishop Mundelein. In referring to the eyewitness reports of the speaker, Monsignore Rempe quoted the Archbishop as declaring that all hatred and revengefulness had disappeared--or should have disappeared, anyway--and that the spirit of Christian love, the foundation of all human relations, had returned. He advised that better mutual understanding, tolerance, and the suppression of passions should be exercised to bring about a genuine reconstruction, consisting of humanitarianism and friendship, and a common aspiration to the highest ideals.</p>
   <p>Archbishop Mundelein indicated that he would gladly co-operate in destroying hatred and malice. He adhered to the principles recently promulgated by the Pope to the whole world, and to the German woman-Catholic Central Association in particular, which makes it the Catholic's duty to aid the German people. According to Archbishop Mundelein, the Catholic Church of Chicago is about to join this relief work and next week the fifty or more German Catholic parishes will start operations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0592.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>After the chairman had reported that during the last ten days $22,700 had been received, and that $2,700 had been collected to cover expenses, he urgently requested the audience to give to the best of their abilities.</p>
   <p>With a voice trembling with emotion, Mr Rubens called to the attention of the audience the hardships and suffering of the coming winter in Germany and Austria. There will be a shortage of coal and many other necessities in hospitals and homes, and in spite of that fifteen thousand dairy cows and forty million tons of coal have to be turned over to the Entente. The speaker pointed out that even if sixty million dollars were raised in America that would be less than one dollar per head for Germany's and Austria's population of seventy-two million. Unless they are assisted within a short time these poor people are doomed to perish; in such conditions a revolution borne of despair constantly threatens.</p>
   <p>The meeting adjourned after Mr. Wacker had expressed the hope that everyone would pitch in and help, and that the resultant success would do the Aid <pb facs="5418474_9_0593.jpg" n="12"/>Society honor.</p>
   <p>Although no arrangements had been made to take up a collection, many people made contributions as they left the hall. The cash and the signed pledges amounted to $26,269.25.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
