<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-02">June 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">German Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-02">June 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last annual meeting of the ladies' society of the German Home for the Aged, the president of the executive committee of the Home, Michael F. Girten, presented the following report:</p>
   <p>"The short period during which I have been in contact with the work of the gentlemen and ladies in whose hands lies the management of the German Home for the Aged has given me an insight into activities little known to many of our German fellow citizens. The work performed to render the last days of so many old people bearable is certainly an investment in values that will be corroded neither by rust nor by moths. I regret that in this year's report must be registered the death of a courageous and good man, for many years the president of our organization, Robert G. Scheunemann. All those who knew him regret his early departure, and we who were familiar with his <pb facs="5418474_9_0366.jpg" n="2"/>activities will always honor him in our memory. Then, there is the death of Mrs. Henry A. Chatroop to be mourned. She, too, was very helpful for the welfare of the Home and was for many years a member of the executive committee. May these two officers rest in peace! We all hope that many of their kind will volunteer their services for the Home.</p>
   <p>"In the course of the year we introduced an innovation which has long been desired, namely the appointment of a paid secretary for the finance committee. We have, I believe, made a good choice in Ludwig W. Kaeuffl.</p>
   <p>"The administrator's yearly report is before you, giving accurate information about the number of inmates in the Home, about innovations, new purchases, etc.</p>
   <p>"In the name of all who live in the Home, I thank all the members of the executive committee, the members of the various other committees, the Junior <pb facs="5418474_9_0367.jpg" n="3"/>Auxiliary, the dear, good ladies and gentlemen who sent yearly contributions, and all who in one way or another helped to keep up this noble work of neighborly love. May God repay you a thousandfold."</p>
   <p>The regular meeting of the ladies' organization of the German Home for the Aged will take place Tuesday, June 4, at the Home. The luncheon will begin at 12:30, the meeting at 2 P.M. Later on, Mrs. Emil Eitel will lecture on poetry and poets of modern times.</p>
   <p>The Home may be reached by the Madison Street car (to 7800 West) or by the Garfield Park elevated (to Desplaines Avenue).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
