<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Festive Benefit Ball for Altenheim</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVE BENEFIT BALL FOR ALTENHEIM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great ball for the benefit of the Altenheim was held Saturday at the fashionable Medinah Athletic Club. It was well attended, in fact, it was much better attended than might have been expected considering general business conditions. The Altenheim is popular, not only among German-Americans, but also by persons far outside their circles; therefore, entertainments in the interest of this institution may be expected to draw large crowds.</p>
   <p>Harry Soenik's famous orchestra provided the dance-provoking music, and before long the floor was filled with dancing couples. The gayety of the happy guests increased as the hours passed. Perhaps one of the greatest advantages of the Altenheim entertainments is that almost all participants know each other; a cordial lack of formality prevails as a result of this familiarity.</p>
   <p>Card tables were placed on the balcony, and guests who did not care to dance <pb facs="5418474_9_0377.jpg" n="2"/>settled there to enjoy a pleasant game of bridge or to try their skill at a crack game of skat. The ball proceeded with this merrymaking until long after midnight when most of the participants reluctantly started for home.</p>
   <p>The credit for the arrangement and success of the ball belongs to the following committees:</p>
   <p>Executive committee, Mrs. William A. Wieboldt, president; Mrs. Frederick W. Blocki, Mrs. Em. Eeitel, and Mrs. Ludwig W. Kaeuffl, vice-presidents; Elmer E. Schmus, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Board of directors, R. G. Schennemann, president; Mrs. Theodore Knehl, president for the ladies; Mrs. Henry Klaas, Mrs. John P. Straub, Mrs. Gustava Rockener, Mrs. Adolf Schmidt, Mrs. Emma Stierlen, Mrs. Henry Chatroop, Mrs. A. O. Blaich, Mrs. John Hetzel, Mrs. Anna Jurgens, Mrs. Arthur Beiser, Mrs. Gustav Meier, Mrs. Carl Roessler, Dr. Kathryn Schwartz, Mrs. Emil Dirks, <pb facs="5418474_9_0378.jpg" n="3"/>Miss Gretchen Eschenburg, Wm. A. L. Schaefer, Wm. Mannhardt, Michael Brisch, Wm. T. Klenze, Adolph Gill, Emil Seemann, Emanuel Loewenstein, Herman Hann, Paul Seeler, H. C. Timm, Henry Klaas, Ludwig W. Kaeuffl, Dr. O. R. Engelmann.</p>
   <p>Lodge committee, Mrs. Henry Klaas, Fr. and John P. Straub, Mrs. Robert Zimmermann.</p>
   <p>Committee for publications, Mrs. Gustav A. J. Meyer, Mrs. Paul Ortmann.</p>
   <p>Committee for flowers, cigars, cigarettes: Mrs. Ludwig W. Kaeuffl, Miss Wilma Hetzel, Miss Lisinka Kuehl, Mrs. J. S. O'Connell, Mrs. Adolf Schmidt Jr.</p>
   <p>Ball committee: Ludwig W. Kaeuffl, H. C. Timm, William Nehlsen, George E. Eisermann.</p>
   <p>Cards committee: Mr. and Mrs. William A. L. Schaefer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
