<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-15">May 15, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Poverty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1015</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1015.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-15">May 15, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">POVERTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A deplorable case of poverty and suffering came to the attention of Coroner Mann yesterday. He held an inquest at 110 West 14th Street, where a three-months-old child had died. The parents, Casimir Wist and his wife, arrived recently from Switzerland, and are destitute. The child was born on shipboard, contracted fever and died two days ago. The coroner found the corpse, barely clothed, lying on a table, while the brothers and sisters, as well as the children of the Reuben family, which shares the flat and which also came to America recently, played unconcernedly. The two families own one stove and no furniture. The living quarters consist of three bare rooms; everything necessary for subsistence is lacking. There is no bed, chair, or table even [sic].</p>
   <p>The oldest son of the Wists is employed as an apprentice at P. Schuettler and Company's wagon works; he is fifteen years old and earns two dollars a week. The men, Wist and Reuben, work on the railroads, but so far have <pb facs="5418474_9_1016.jpg" n="2"/>received no salaries. The children of both families, seventeen altogether, appear to be in good health and spirits, considering their circumstances. The two women do not seem to be discouraged, but nevertheless help is urgently needed. So far, both families have lived mostly on supplies which were donated, and their meals often consisted of unsalable meat, such as heart, liver and lungs. Coal also was given to them. Their first benefactor was Mr. Hartmann, who has a workshop in the vicinity; he gave them a fairly large sum of money immediately.</p>
   <p>When the German Society heard of the case, it sent its agent to investigate, and help will of course be given to the unfortunate people, and the County will also give assistance, it is hoped.</p>
   <p>However, here is a case worthy also of individual donations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
