<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-08">Nov. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-11-08">Nov. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a report submitted by Business Manager F. von Wysow to the board of directors of the German Society at their last monthly meeting, ninety-three families (including 261 children and 172 single persons, among them 26 women) were given cash relief, and 1006 meals and 129 nightly shelters were provided for unemployed and homeless people. On recommendation, and through the facilities of the Society, five persons were admitted free to hospitals, one to a sanitarium, six to county institutions--seven received free medicine and medical care, and one family was provided with coal. The cash expenditures for relief purposes were $898.64.</p>
   <p>Work was provided for 242 persons. It was noticed that unemployment had steadily increased during the last few months, and there are indications that the number of unemployed, already a staggering figure, will continue to grow. The more unemployment, the greater the destitution and misery, <pb facs="5418474_9_0721.jpg" n="2"/>and the more people will turn for aid to the German Society. This will put an extra strain on the resources of the Society. To meet this emergency in a manner worthy of the Chicago German element, the Society appeals to all charitably inclined Germans to remember their suffering German neighbors in this city, either by becoming members of the Society (minimum annual dues $5.00) or by sending in a contribution.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, the Society has turned over a substantial amount of money (from the profits of its Sixtieth Anniversary celebration at the Medinah Temple) to the German and Austro-Hungarian Relief Association for war relief purposes.</p>
   <p>With winter just around the corner, there are already requests for warm clothing, underwear, and shoes for men, women, and children. All charitable persons who can spare things like that are requested to turn them <pb facs="5418474_9_0722.jpg" n="3"/>over to the German Society, which will pick them up promptly if notified either by mail or telephone. The address is 153 North La Salle Street, telephone Main 4026.</p>
   <p>Cash contributions also may be sent there. Checks and money orders must be made out to the "German Society of Chicago".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
