<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-11-13">Nov. 13, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">General Meeting of the Aid Society for German Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-11-13">Nov. 13, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">GENERAL MEETING OF THE AID SOCIETY FOR GERMAN IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. H. Claussenius was in the chair, and Mr. C. Knobelsdorff acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>The reports of the secretary and treasurer on receipts and disbursements for the quarter ending on October 4 were adopted as read.</p>
   <p>The revision committee, consisting of Mr. C. Degenhardt and Mr. Louis Nelke, reported that Mr. C. Knobelsdorff's account of money received and paid out in connection with the Fair which was recently given by the Society, has been examined and found to be correct.</p>
   <p>According to this report, the net profit derived from the Fair amounted to $3,599.74, and was delivered to the treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1183.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was voted to invest $3,000 of the above amount in county bonds, and the secretary and treasurer were requested to carry out this resolution.</p>
   <p>Thereupon the annual election was held. Mr. Koerner (sic) and Mr. Schwarzlose (sic) were appointed to serve as election committee, and it was decided to take only one vote by ballot for all the officers to be elected, the one receiving the greatest number of votes to serve as president, the one receiving the next largest number of votes, to act as secretary, etc:</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen were then elected for the half year ending April 1,1860.</p>
   <p>President: C. Knobelsdorff, Vice-President: Doctor (sic) Fessel, Secretary: Max Koerner, Treasurer: Charles Rietz</p>
   <p>Directors for the North Side: H. Fromhold, Julius Nelke, H. Claussenius.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1184.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Directors for the South Side: G. Beuttenmueller, H. Kaestner.</p>
   <p>Directors for the West Side: Doctor Weitze, Henderis.</p>
   <p>The following were accorded a vote of thanks: Mrs.Ino Metzke, president of the Ladies Auxilliary of the Aid Society for German Immigrants, and the other members of the Auxilliary who assisted in organizing and managing the Fair;</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Koerner, Mr. Louis Nelke, and Mr. Theodor Falk for their valued advice and help; Mr. H. Claussenius retiring president, and the other officers who served the Society during the past six months.</p>
   <p>C. Knobelsdorff,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
