<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-17">Nov. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">For the War Orphans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-17">Nov. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE WAR ORPHANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Competent speakers gave a vivid description of present conditions in Germany at the Hotel La Salle last night. They told of the distress and suffering of large sections of the population, and of the evil effects these conditions will have on the children. The mass meeting was called by the Independent German-American Woman's Club, of which Mrs. Anna M. Schadler is chairman. The purpose of the meeting was to awaken public interest in behalf of the destitute German people, especially the German war orphans who are suffering acutely under present conditions.</p>
   <p>The Club had secured the well-known philanthropist, Miss Jane Adams, as speaker for the evening. She gave a comprehensive outline of conditions in the old country. As is generally known, Miss Addams has spent considerable time in Germany, having recently returned from Europe; consequently she is well aware of the conditions there. Her comments revealed that the food situation is deplorable. All over Europe there is a great shortage <pb facs="5418474_9_0578.jpg" n="2"/>of fats. Miss Addams said that in restaurants and hotels the grease is skimmed from dishwater and used for cooking purposes. The lack of fat in the diet of the German children is the reason for their undernourishment and their emaciated bodies. These conditions existed not only among the poorer sections, but throughout the entire country, the speaker explained.</p>
   <p>Mrs. J. Wilberforce Stoughton, who also has travelled thru Germany recently, was the next speaker. She is of the opinion that the English are beginning to realize that they have done irreparable damage with their hunger blockade. She spoke about the milk shortage and its horrible consequences, and about the lack of bandages which made hospital surgery a dangerous procedure. She stated that surgeons often had to use tissue paper.</p>
   <p>More speakers appealed to the spirit of charity and the sympathy of those assembled. After the speaking there was musical entertainment. The songs assembled. After the speaking there was musical entertainment. The songs offered by Miss Mae Doelling and Adolph Gill deserve special mention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
