<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-08-23">Aug. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Ball Keeps Rolling</title><title level="a" type="sub">Austrians and Hungarians Co-operate in Relief Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0738</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0738.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-08-23">Aug. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE BALL KEEPS ROLLING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Austrians and Hungarians Co-operate in Relief Work</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The officers and representatives of the Austrian and Hungarian Vereine (Associations) met last night in the La Salle Turner Hall, in order to found an Austro-Hungarian branch of the German Red Cross Society, and to establish an institution "of which he can be proud in times to come," as the chairman of the meeting, Mr. Leopold Neumann, declared in an enthusiastic address. He said the purpose of the meeting was to raise a large amount of money for the great work, and to demonstrate to the world that Austrians and Hungarians are united in this movement. Women's associations were also well represented. The minutes of the preliminary meeting of last Saturday were read by the secretary, Louis Ille, and were approved. The following organizations applied for membership: Easenburger Maennerchor (Male Chorus) Oesterreich-Ungarischer Gesangverein (Austro-Hungarian Glee Club), Stock in Eisen, Oesterreichisch-Ungerischer Krankenunterstuetzungsverein (Austro-Hungarian Sick Aid Society), Deutsch-Oesterreichischer Frauenverein (German-Austrian Women's Association), <pb facs="5418474_9_0739.jpg" n="2"/>Oesterreicher und Bayern Krankenunterstuetzungsverein (Sick Aid Society for Austrians and Bavarians), Kranken und Fortbilaungsverein der Deutsch-Ungarn (Sick Aid and Educational Advancement Society of German-Hungarians), Ungar-landischer Krankenunterstuetzungsverein (Hungarian Sick Aid Association), Deutsch-Ungarischer Arbeitermaennerchor (German-Hungarian Workingmen's Male Chorus) Lincoln Park Lodge, Tiroler and Vorlberger Verein, Banater junger Maennerchor (Young Male Chorus of Bonat), and Eisenburger Krankenunterstuetzungsverein (Eisenburg Sick Aid Association).</p>
   <p>The last-mentioned Verein announced a contribution of two hundred and fifty dollars, also another fifty dollars collected during the meeting. Collections are to be continued. The German-Hungarian Verein contributed fifty dollars and will continue collections. The Verein of Tyrol and Vorarlberg announced a contribution of one hundred dollars, the Stock im Eisen Verein announced an amount or one hundred dollars pledged, besides fifty dollars donated by members; one member <pb facs="5418474_9_0740.jpg" n="3"/>had given a ten-crown gold piece which he had just brought over from the old country. The Lincoln Lodge of the Order of Mutual Protection has called a public meeting for next Thursday evening, in Gieben's Hall, on Clybourn Avenue, for the same purpose. Everybody is invited to come. The chairman announced that the collection work was making good progress, and that various committees were to contact all well-to-do members and businessmen for contributions. Everybody is putting his whole heart and soul into it. A treasurer had to be elected who would have to put up a ten thousand dollar bond.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leopold Neumann was then unanimously elected permanent chairman, and Mr. Ille was named as secretary. Mr. Neumann expressed thanks for the honor, and promised to do his best for the good cause. When the election of a treasurer was discussed, Mr. Karl Unsorge pointed put that the Austrians and Hungarians could easily raise forty thousand dollar, although most of them belonged to the laboring class. Mr. Neumann announced that he would present the meetings with a plan whereby a large sum could be raised, a sum of which the compatriots would not have to be ashamed. With great applause, Mr. Charles Heckl was elected treasurer; <pb facs="5418474_9_0741.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Leopold, Saltiel, an Austrian, and Mr. Karl Dittinger, a Hungarian, vice-presidents; Mrs. Karoline Fischer was elected secretary of the Women's Association. Mrs. Fischer promised to do every thing she could. The presidents of all the other Vereine were elected members of the executive committee.</p>
   <p>Then all kinds of suggestions were made as to how to raise money. Mr. Neumann suggested that a tag day for the Red Cross would be a good idea, since church organizations and charitable institutions had been allowed to collect money on the streets. Even though the mayor's representative had rejected such a proposal, the mayor himself would probably give his consent. Mr. Saltiel observed that such a procedure (tag day) might violate neutrality, that it was a form of begging, and that it would cause resentment among the Slavs and other hostile elements. He believed that it was in much better taste and more dignified to collect from German fellow citizens and business friends. If that did not prove successful, they might as well close up shop. Mr. Karl Ansorge agreed with him and pointed out that a similar plan (tag day) was already under consideration by the American Red Cross. The coupon question was brought up by Mr. Andreas Kost.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0742.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Dr. A. D. Weiner thought all these suggestions impracticable. He said nobody could foretell how long this war would last, how many human lives it would cost, how many widows and orphans would become dependent on public relief. Enthusiasm may soon die down. Right now Vereine and members were falling over each other to contribute large amounts, but how long would that last? It would be better if every Verein and every member would pledge a certain monthly amount for the duration of the war. A much larger amount could be collected that way, and regular contributions would be obtained from a large number of people. This would better than to get a large amount just once; it would be better to raise six thousand dollars a month, every month, than to get fifty thousand dollars in a lump sum "If we are really sincere in our sentiments, we ought to be able to carry out this plan successfully," concluded Dr. Weiner amid great applause. The plan met with general approval. "Everybody will contribute according to his ability," said Mr. A. Havill. "The plan is good and can be carried out systematically. It should be submitted to every Verein. Whoever wants to participate can do so voluntarily," added Mr. Neumann. A Hungarian gentlemen protested violently to the idea, saying he belonged to many Vereine and could not make a monthly contribution to each one of them. He <pb facs="5418474_9_0743.jpg" n="6"/>that. The latter told of one woman who had promised to take in washing, so that she could contribute to the relief fund; other women had employed similar methods to raise money for charitable purposes. Now, money could be earned especially for this purpose. Mr. Karl Dittinger expressed his hearty approval. Everybody should do his part, and should think of the fathers and brothers who have had to leave their loved ones behind, may be never to return from the battlefields, or perhaps to be crippled for life. Harmony prevailed when the meeting as adjourned, and Mr. Neumann reminded everybody to forgot all pettiness in this critical hour. The chairman will call a conference of the executive committee within the next few days, for discussion of Dr. Weiner's and other suggestions, and to make decisions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
