<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the chairmanship of its president the German Society of Chicago held its annual general meeting yesterday afternoon. After the detailed minutes of the previous annual meeting had been read by the secretary, Mr. Rudolf Seifert, President Michael F. Girten presented his report for the year. According to the figures submitted the disbursements were considerably greater than the receipts, as has been the case ever since the outbreak of the war. Naturally, the Society was called upon to assist many Germans who have not yet become American citizens, and the sums authorized for benevolence, including Christmas gifts, totaled $8,920 during the past year. The accumulated capital was greatly decreased, owing to unusual circumstances. However, Mr. Girten expressed the hope that the German Society of Chicago would be able to continue its blessed activity, which consisted not only in rendering material aid, but also in obtaining work and giving good advice free of charge. These latter forms of activity were of great value to local German subjects.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: The paragraph omitted contains a list of those members of the Society who died during the year.]</p>
   <p>Manager F. W. Wysow reported that the German Society of Chicago had secured legal assistance through the Legal Aid Society for 209 persons; that the Society had obtained employment for 1,751 men, and that, through its ladies' department Frauenhilfe (Help for Women) eighty-seven women and girls had been placed in paying positions. The Society maintains friendly relations with the following societies and institutions: Chicago Association of Commerce, Alexian Brothers Hospital, Grant Hospital, the Society of St. Vincent DePaul, Cook County institutions, and Little Sisters of the Poor. During the past year the Society functioned as a branch of the Federal Employment Bureau, which hired Manager Wysow as head of the branch at a salary of one dollar per year.</p>
   <p>The contract which has been in force for ten years with the Schweizer Wohltaetigkeitsgesellschaft (Swiss Charitable Society) was renewed yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0656.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The election of directors resulted as follows: Messrs. M. F. Girten, Peter S. Theurer, Arnold Holinger, Albert F. Madlener and George Wegener for three years; Mr. George W. Torpe for two years; Mr. Henry Schoellkopf for one year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
