<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-13">July 13, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Surprise for the "Altenheim".</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-13">July 13, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT SURPRISE FOR THE "ALTENHEIM".</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The friendship between Carter H. Harrison and the Germans did not end with his retirement from public office, and no other nationality amongst the Chicagoans regretted the end of Mr. Carter's career as the German element did. But, that Mr. Harrison's friendship for the Germans outlived his public career was shown by his generous gift to the "Altenheim", made from the legacy of his young wife, who so unfortunately was taken by death in the prime of her life. The sum donated was $3,000. The management of the "Altenheim" and the Germans of Chicago greatly appreciate Mr. Harrison's gift. The check and the following letter were received by Mr. A. C. Hesing: "To the President and Directors of the "German Old People's Home". When the "Altenheim" was dedicated, my late beloved and I, through the kindness of the management, were enabled to assist in the pleasing ceremonies. She was touched by the courtesies then shown her, and deeply impressed by the scope of the noble charity; so much so, that she declared to me, she would some day make to the "Altenheim" a handsome donation. Summoned too early to her eternal home, she has been deprived of this pleasure <pb facs="5418474_9_0435.jpg" n="2"/>and privilege. I wish to do now in her name, what she would have liked so much to have done herself. My wife died possessed of some funds, the gift of her father Marcus C. Stearns, Esquire. These funds I have determined to give in charity, in which determination I have the hearty concurrence of my wife's father. In furtherance of this object I herewith inclose to you my check for $3,000, with which I wish to endow a fund in perpetuity to be known in your institution and on its records as "The Margarette Stearns-Harrison Fund". The principal to be invested in good securities and annual interest only to be used. While Margarette lived she made my home happy and bright. If her fund shall make the "Altenheim" a happy and bright home for some of its unfortunate occupants, the loss I have suffered by her death will be deprived of a small part of its sting. Wishing you great success in the management of your noble institution I am very respectfully Your obedient servant, Carter H. Harrison.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
