<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-24">Dec. 24, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Die Deutsche Gesellschaft</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-24">Dec. 24, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">DIE DEUTSCHE GESELLSCHAFT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Deutsche Gesellschaft (The German Society), or rather its executives, have discarded the recent plan for raising funds, since the public was not in favor of it. The Society therefore makes a general appeal and we hope that thousands of favorable answers will be received.</p>
   <p>Anyone who is able to provide an enjoyable Christmas for his own family should add to the festive spirit by thinking of the poor, and should help them by contributing as much as his resources permit.</p>
   <p>Appeal of the Deutsche Gesellschaft</p>
   <p>"Since the Chicago fire in 1871, the Deutsche Gesellschaft has found it necessary not only to help immigrants but also to give support to destitute Chicago Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"In Chicago, with its large German population, many people are urgently in need of help--particularly in the winter--but such assistance is not always obtainable from the authorities in charge of aiding the poor, nor from other social welfare societies. In all these exceptional cases the Deutsche Gesellschaft is regarded as the only welfare association for Germans, and it is expected--and rightly so--that the Society will help. And, besides, Chicago is the central point in the great railway route between the East and the West; hence many of the poorest immigrants remain here in search of help.</p>
   <p>"The Germans of Chicago have always regarded it as a humane duty to provide the Deutsche Gesellschaft with the necessary means for carrying on its philanthropic work, and undoubtedly will be generous in giving again.</p>
   <p>"The main sources of income for the Deutsche Gesellschaft were the annual fairs, balls, etc., but the work and expense which such performances entailed were far out of proportion to the proceeds derived from them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1060.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Moreover, it was always the same small number of charitable men and women who gave the necessary money to the Deutsche Gesellschaft each year, and the same humane individuals who labored so arduously to garner the contributions--while a large part of the prosperous German citizenry donated but little, or nothing whatsoever.</p>
   <p>"The Executive Board of the Deutsche Gesellschaft has therefore decided to ask all Germans to subscribe specific amounts periodically or to make voluntary contributions.</p>
   <p>"We append an estimate of our regular yearly income and expenditures, in order to show what sum will be needed for support of the poor:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>"Regular contributions per year, about</cell>
     <cell>$1,700.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest per year</cell>
     <cell>1,300.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total:</cell>
     <cell>$3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1061.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Expenditures per Year:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Salary of agents and collectors</cell>
     <cell>$1,920.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Office rent</cell>
     <cell>400.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Office expenditures, about</cell>
     <cell>580.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total:</cell>
     <cell>$2,900.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>"Sums for aid (the money for this purpose was derived from special incomes) were expended as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>In</cell>
     <cell>the</cell>
     <cell>year</cell>
     <cell>1872</cell>
     <cell>to</cell>
     <cell>1873</cell>
     <cell>$5,665.35</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>1873</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>1874</cell>
     <cell>7,991.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>1874</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>1875</cell>
     <cell>4,129.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Total:</cell>
     <cell>$17,785.69</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Thus the average yearly expenditure for aid was $5,928.33.</p>
   <p>"As the regular receipts of the Society only suffice to cover expenses, it <pb facs="5418474_9_1062.jpg" n="5"/>is obvious that $6,000 must be raised this year to provide money for aid.</p>
   <p>"The Executive Board of the Deutsche Gesellschaft therefore asks you to help us by subscribing to a regular yearly donation, which also entitles you to membership, or to give a voluntary contribution of any suitable amount.</p>
   <p>"We ask you to fill out and sign the circular we are sending you; also to give your home or business address; and then to return the circular by mail to the secretary of the Society.</p>
   <p>"In view of the philanthropic attitude of our German fellow citizens, we are confident that they will be generous, and will provide the Deutsche Gesellschaft with the necessary means for continuing its charitable activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1063.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"The Executive Board of the Deutsche Gesellschaft is as follows: George Schneider, president; H. Claussenius, vice-president; Chs. Knobelsdorff, treasurer; Directors: Adolph Schoeninger,....[nine names are listed altogether.]</p>
   <p>Max Eberhardt, secretary.</p>
   <p>Southwest Corner Randolph and Canal Streets."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
