<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-28">Jan. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">German Home for the Aged Loses Case</title><title level="a" type="sub">Legacy of Mrs. Paetzmann Awarded to Survivors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-28">Jan. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOME FOR THE AGED LOSES CASE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Legacy of Mrs. Paetzmann Awarded to Survivors</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>St. Stephen's Evangelical Lutheran Church had given Mrs. Margarete Paetzmann a promissory note for $2,000 on April 4, 1904....[Translator's note: The article states that this transaction was made during the lifetime of Mrs. Paetzmann. Since it is obvious that she could not have delivered the money, nor accepted the note, after her death, the statement was omitted.] On May 15, 1913, the seventy-six-year-old Mrs. Paetzmann applied to the Ladies' Society of the German Home For The Aged for admission to the institution, and she agreed to bequeath all her property to the Home. Thus the institution came into possession of the promissory note. But according to the agreement the Home had obligated itself to admit Mrs. Paetzmann "for one year, or, upon the successful completion of the year, for life," and she had the privilege of leaving the Home voluntarily during the first year according to the regulations of the Society, while the Society had the privilege of dismissing Mrs. Paetzmann from the Home. Should she remain in the Home for more than a <pb facs="5418474_9_0406.jpg" n="2"/>year, the agreement was to be binding for the remainder of her lifetime.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Paetzmann entered the institution on May 7, 1914, and died there on April 24, 1915, before the probationary year had elapsed. Through payments by the church the value of the promissory note had been reduced to $1,610. Now the question arose whether the Home or the administrator of Mrs. Paetzmann's estate was legally entitled to possession of the note. The church took the matter to court for decision. The Superior Court decided that the administrator of Mrs. Paetzmann's estate was entitled to possession of the promissory note, because her period of probation had not yet elapsed, and the Appellate Court upheld this decision because, according to its bylaws the Ladies' Society of the German Home For The Aged agrees to return to any inmate who leaves the Home within the probationary period any funds entrusted to its care by the inmate, after deduction of a specified amount for board and other expenses. The fact that the Society had possession of the promissory note was no proof that the Society was entitled to ownership of the note. The Appellate Court based this decision on precedent. The <pb facs="5418474_9_0407.jpg" n="3"/>Court also stated that, since the Home was a benevolent institution, every doubtful written agreement should be interpreted against it and in favor of the inmates.... [Translator's note: Subsequent paragraphs of this article relate other court procedure and are irrelevant.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
