<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-12-25">December 25, 1871</date><title level="a">[The German Relief Organization]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-12-25">December 25, 1871</date><title level="a">[THE GERMAN RELIEF ORGANIZATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of German citizens was held Thursday at the corner of Sigel and Sedgwick Streets, for the purpose of drawing attention to the faults and inadequacies existing in the relief organization for Germans of the North Side. The exceedingly numerous attendance proved the widespread dissatisfaction. The individuals who are charged by the Relief and Aid Society with the distribution of support are largely incapable of fulfilling their task.</p>
   <p>Equally ignorant of both the German language and the special situation on the North Side, they behave like uneducated beadles (Armenvogte)....</p>
   <p>The following memorial was presented to the Mayor, day before yesterday, by a deputation consisting of Anton Hottinger, Fritz Frillmann, A. Bischoff, J. Hanswirth, T. Bauer, and others.</p>
   <p>...."Under the present system of aid and support many people are receiving sustenance who are unworthy of any support. On the other hand, people get no help and no assistance who deserve it and who according to the intentions of those who donated funds for Chicago, should be helped.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1110.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as we know only those people are aided by the Relief and Aid Society who own no real estate or other means, which, even though sold at ruinous prices, could be made into money. In other words, those who were without maintenance before the fire, many of whom are indigent through their own fault, now find it only too easy to live in idleness without suffering the least return. We believe that the distribution of food stuffs, if determined by most pressing need, need, could now be restricted to a much smaller number of people, - widows, the aged, invalids.</p>
   <p>The money now so unnecessarily spent for victuals should go to buy furniture and clothes for a class that is especially numerous on the North side,- one well off before the fire and with comfortable homes. A number still have a plot or other property, but are now unable to re-establish any semblance of a household without dimishing too severely their business fund. (Betriebskapital).......</p>
   <p>The Superintendent of the 1st district should be instructed to choose his subalterns from among the inhabitants of the district. People who are acquainted with the population and its special needs. It is well known that a great number of the employees of the 1st district are inequal to their jobs. They don't understand <pb facs="5418474_9_1111.jpg" n="3"/>the languages of the aid-seekers (Germans, Scandinavians, Bohemians etc.) They have no understanding of human nature, and they cannot distinguish between those who need and deserve support and those who are so utterly unworthy, any assistance is in vain and as good as thrown away......</p>
   <p>We finally want to say that we place full confidence in the gentlemen of the Relief and Aid Society. We know they are actuated by the best intentions. If we ask the Mayor to support our demands, it is done in the hope that the "Relief and Aid Society" will give prompt and unprejudiced consideration to our petition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
