<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Ready to Help</title><title level="a" type="sub">German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society Established: Charles H. Wacker, Chairman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0774</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0774.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">READY TO HELP</title><title level="a" type="sub">German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society Established: Charles H. Wacker, Chairman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a large meeting of the representatives of the most prominent German societies, held last night in the Germania Clubhouse, it was clearly shown that the Chicago Germans are ready to do their utmost to help alleviate the inevitable suffering of their brothers in Germany, as well as in Austria-Hungary, which countries are now engaged in a bloody war. To be sure, there were some differences of opinion regarding details, but there was unanimity on the main objective, namely to establish immediately a powerful central organization consisting of the representatives of all German sections and factions, in order to collect funds for the support of all those whom the war has made eligible for relief. This is to include the care of the sick and wounded, relief for soldiers' families in distress, and adequate support of the widows and orphans of the men who sacrificed their lives on the field of honor, in defense of the fatherland. For this purpose the Deutsche und Oesterreichisch-Ungarische Hilfsgesellschaft von Chicago <pb facs="5418474_9_0775.jpg" n="2"/>[German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society of Chicago] was founded last night. It was decided to incorporate the Society immediately in Springfield, and, if necessary, to empower the business committee, which was also appointed last night, to effect a change of name, perhaps to include a reference to the Red Cross contained in the title. The purposes of the Society were briefly formulated by Paul F. Mueller as follows: To obtain funds to relieve the suffering and distress caused by the war.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened shortly after eight o'clock by Eugen Niederegger. Although he had been chosen to act only as temporary chairman, he was put in charge for the duration of the meeting, assisted by Julius Goldzier, acting as secretary. Several hundred representatives of associations and organizations of all kinds were present.</p>
   <p>Before this meeting took place, about fifty members of the Chicago branch of the German-American National Bund had held a preliminary conference at the Red Star Inn. At this meeting, a tentative list of committee members for the great movement was to be drawn up. Although the Chicago branch had <pb facs="5418474_9_0776.jpg" n="3"/>received strict instructions from the executive office in Philadelphia that all relief measures decided upon had to be carried out under the latter's supervision, and all funds collected were to be transferred to the Quaker City, the Chicago branch was persuaded, especially after the speeches of Ferdinand Walther, chairman, Paul F. Mueller, Arthur Josetti, Heinrich von Meteren, Karl Eitel, Ernst Kusswurm, George A. Schmidt, and August Lueders, to disregard their own interest and co-operate with the other committees already appointed at conferences on Monday and Tuesday. Paul H. Mueller made a motion, which was accepted, that a committee of twenty-five be appointed, drawn from the roster of committees elected on similar occasions. This list was to be submitted later at the large meeting in the Germania Clubhouse, and would serve as a nucleus for a larger committee. The idea was to let the National Bund have one-third of the [committee] membership. The list included the following names: Charles H. Wacker, chairman, Ferdinand Walther, Paul F. Mueller, George A. Schmidt, Gustav Geleng, Oscar F. Mayer, Karl Eitel, E. F. Uihlein, Arthur Josetti, Heinrich Runkel, Franz Schuetz, Horace L. Brand, Herman Paepcke, Louis Kohtz, Wilhelm Legner, August Lueders, Leopold Grand, F. W. Hess, Eugen Niederegger, H. O. Lange, Oscar Kropp, W. A. Wieboldt, <pb facs="5418474_9_0777.jpg" n="4"/>Theodor Kuehl, Fritz von Frantzius, and Dr. Huxmann. After the list was approved, the conference adjourned.</p>
   <p>Now the real business of the evening was taken up. Opinions differed sometimes about the name [of the society], about the formulation of the bylaws, and finally about the composition of the business committee. Debates on these three pertinent questions arose, in which John Koelling, Julius Goldzier, Max Wild, Theodor Kuehl, Leo Austrian, G. F. Hummel, Alfred Steffen, D. B. Brillow, Horace L. Brand, Ferdinand Walther, Arthur Hercz, Arthur Josetti, Paul F. Mueller, August Lueders, Leopold Neumann, George A. Schmidt, and Heinrich von Meteren participated.</p>
   <p>Finally it was resolved to approve the list of twenty-five names submitted by the National Bund. Following that, again after a lengthy debate, it was resolved also to approve the committee lists set up Monday night in the Germania Clubhouse, and Tuesday at the North Side Turner Hall, and to empower the associated committees to co-opt additional members which was done later by admitting all the executive officers of the Chicago branch of the <pb facs="5418474_9_0778.jpg" n="5"/>German-American National Bund and some members of the German Club. For the remainder of the evening the meeting acted as a combined committee.</p>
   <p>The actual business [executive] committee is made up as follows: president, Charles H. Wacker; vice-presidents, Ferdinand Walther, Eugen Niederegger, H. O. Lange, Heinrich Runkel, Dr. Otto Schmidt, Arthur Hercz, Frau Consul Singer, Harry Rubens, Oscar Kropp, Hermann Paepcke, Wilhelm Rothmann, and Heinrich von Meteren; treasurer, Oscar F. Mayer; secretary, Julius Goldzier.</p>
   <p>The president, the vice-presidents, the treasurer, and the secretary will confer tonight at seven o'clock in the Germania [Clubhouse].</p>
   <p>Immediately afterwards, the drive for contributions is to start. Only persons holding the proper credentials shall have the right to collect funds for the Society. Steps are to be taken immediately to incorporate the Society. Tentative plans were drawn up for a great exhibition, the net receipts from <pb facs="5418474_9_0779.jpg" n="6"/>which would augment the relief funds of the Society. Another big mass meeting was also contemplated, and the suggestion was made that the Society establish a number of places where contributions would be accepted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
