<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-10-28">October 28, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">Open Letter to the Committee of Twenty-Five.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-10-28">October 28, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN LETTER TO THE COMMITTEE OF TWENTY-FIVE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>The aim of our organization was to diminish the number of crimes in our city, and to assure the quick and certain punishment of criminals. To this end we already have agreed on the following measures:</p>
   <p>1. The improvement of our police and its numerical increase.</p>
   <p>2. A change in our Jury system which prevents the majority of the intelligent public from functioning as Jurors, and leaves, in cases of murder, the decision on punishment to the Jury.</p>
   <p>3. A change in the appeal procedure...</p>
   <p>4. Restriction of the pardoning power of the Governor.</p>
   <p>5. Changes in the criminal law concerning burglars and other <pb facs="5418474_9_1419.jpg" n="2"/>criminals.</p>
   <p>6. A grant of the County Commissioners for extradition proceedings.</p>
   <p>While we were occupied with this important reformatory work,... a new movement was started and that on the initiative of gentlemen who have found the cure for all evils to which flesh is heir, in the enforced closing of all drinking parlors from Saturday evening to Monday morning.</p>
   <p>I am firmly convinced that their attitude is impractical and not fitting, contrary to the system of good government, and injurious to the spirit of our free institutions...</p>
   <p>Your Committee possesses the confidence of the public, and has the power to prevent the laudable tendency of an important and humane part of the public to improve the social tone and to create more complete security of life and property. Protect them from being misled into the bed of fanaticism and intolerance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1420.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I therefore recommend that the Committee immediately and urgently petition the Aldermanic Council to change the Sunday law, in order to save the people the trouble, the anger, possibly the danger, of electing the new City Council, only with reference to this question.</p>
   <p>If I do not represent the views of the majority of your Committee on this question, I do not feel in my place as its Chairman, and in such a case I am presenting my resignation.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>Henry Greenebaum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
