<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-11">Sept. 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Ladies' Aid of the German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-11">Sept. 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE LADIES' AID OF THE GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ladies' Aid of the German Society held its monthly meeting yesterday. The president, Mrs. Hedwig Voss, acted as chairman. Mrs. Hirth acted as secretary pro tem, as Miss Clara Schneider was absent, having been married yesterday.</p>
   <p>The reports of the various officials were received and accepted. According to the statements compiled by the treasurer, Mrs. Marie Peipers, the summer festival netted $414.17.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Werkmeister read the monthly report, given below:</p>
   <p>"The German Society gave aid in 129 cases during the months of June, July, and August. Assistance was given to poor families and single persons as itemized: In June, $88 was paid to 35 persons or families. In July, $153 was given to <pb facs="5418474_9_1004.jpg" n="2"/>44 persons. In August, urgent cases rose to 50, and $153 was given; this, however, includes donations to people who needed continued support. Coal delivered to poor people entailed the following expenditures: June, $5; July, $4.50; August, $4.50.</p>
   <p>"For room and board for homeless persons, we spent $58.50 in June, and the same sum in August.</p>
   <p>"The total sum spent for people in need was $525.</p>
   <p>"Other donations of the German Society which were given chiefly through its agent in co-operation with other benevolent associations are not mentioned, because these items appear in the regular monthly report of the Society. But I cannot refrain from speaking of those unfortunate people who have received, or are receiving, hospital care through our intercession. These patients are given excellent care, and express gratitude whenever a member of the Ladies' <pb facs="5418474_9_1005.jpg" n="3"/>Aid calls at the hospital."</p>
   <p>A motion was made to give another Christmas festival this year for the benefit of poor children, and so Mrs. Roesch, Mrs. Molter, Mrs. Bluthartt, Mrs. Mathei, Mrs. Loeb, and Mrs. Werkmeister were appointed as a committee to plan an evening's entertainment, in order to raise sufficient funds for presents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
