<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Isolation of Mental Defectives a Necessity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Creation of Appropriate Institutions Suggested at Conference</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">ISOLATION OF MENTAL DEFECTIVES A NECESSITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Creation of Appropriate Institutions Suggested at Conference</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a conference of judges, sociologists, and criminologists, as well as psychiatrists, which took place yesterday at the criminal court, the creation of a special interning institution was suggested in which mental defectives like "Iggy" Varecha could be placed before it becomes too late, before they can do irreparable damage to society. The conference was called through the initiative of the director of the psychiatric clinic in the criminal court, Dr. Harry R. Hoffman.</p>
   <p>It was pointed out that it is desirable to create an institution after the pattern of those in New York and Massachussetts. The question as to what is to be done with mental defectives who are not insane is an acute one, for now they have to be kept in an institution for the insane.</p>
   <p>A plan for the creation of such an institution is to be submitted to the next <pb facs="5418474_9_1382.jpg" n="2"/>legislature, and it is hoped that it will pass, especially because there will be so little expense connected with it. The women's department in the Joliet prison is unoccupied at the present, since all feminine inmates have been transferred to Dwight, Illinois. The building could be adapted as an interning institution.</p>
   <p>Viewed from the standpoint of the jurist, there are scarcely any objections to be made, as the state otherwise assumes the right to isolate promptly all persons with contagious diseases, in order to separate them from other people. Finally, a compulsory psychiatric examination of all defendants about whose mental state there are doubts is advisable. It is likewise advisable to have a psychiatrist examine all convicts who are about to be paroled and whose ability to adjust themselves to society must be ascertained.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
