<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-13">Dec. 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Gala Performance on Wednesday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-13">Dec. 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE GALA PERFORMANCE ON WEDNESDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A benefit performance for the German Free Drug Dispensary will be given Wednesday at the North Side Turnhalle and all Chicago Germans who do not live too far away will be there or should be. After all, support of an institution is involved which, above any other, deserves the good will of the German public because, in proportion to its expenditures, it has been of greater usefulness and benefit than any other charitable institution.</p>
   <p>For many years German physicians here have entertained the hope that some day it may be possible to build a German hospital, a necessity which has often been apparent. Often Germans physicians have been confronted with the fact that impecunious Germans who were not conversant with the English language were either not admitted to American hospitals or, if they were accepted, could not obtain proper help, as such patients were unable to describe the symptoms of their ailments.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0249.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The fire, which curtailed the wealth of Chicago's Germans, has precluded the building of a German hospital for years to come; and many Germans have not been able to afford a doctor for the same reason. As the ever-growing demand for a German hospital became apparent, several of our most prominent German physicians, aided by wealthy Germans, opened the German-American Free Drug Dispensary at the corner of Fifth Avenue and Adams Street.</p>
   <p>These physicians have taken charge of the drug dispensary and manage it in turn, each giving a few hours each day; and thus the poor receive medical advice and the necessary medicines without incurring any expense.</p>
   <p>The institution prevented thousands of families from facing utter destitution by helping the bread winners to regain their health.</p>
   <p>Without money nothing can be achieved. Although great economy prevails at the dispensary, nevertheless large sums are spent during the year, chiefly for medicine.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0250.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A small number of Germans contribute a definite sum annually, but it is insufficient to defray expenses. The association is therefore asking the general public to give some assistance.</p>
   <p>The association feels convinced that the public would gladly contribute, but this entails the services of a collector and would be a laborious procedure.</p>
   <p>The association considers it advisable, therefore, to bring together all who might assist the cause....For this purpose a gala performance has been announced for next Wednesday at the North Side Turnhalle. The proceeds from the performance will accrue to the institution.</p>
   <p>Mr. [Alexander] Wurster's company will produce Adolph Wilbrandt's genial comedy, "Die Maler" (The Painters).</p>
   <p>The play contains very suitable parts for nearly all of the company's <pb facs="5418474_9_0251.jpg" n="4"/>more prominent members; particularly Miss Wolff, Mrs. Glaussen, and the Messrs. Donald, Mayer, and Wolkenstein.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
