<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1872-12-16">Dec. 16, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">Waldheim.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where Non-Sectarian Germans Will Rest after Life's Fitful Fever. Haas Park to Be Transformed into a Great Cemetery.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1872-12-16">Dec. 16, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">WALDHEIM.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where Non-Sectarian Germans Will Rest After Life's Fitful Fever. Haas Park To Be Transformed Into A Great Cemetery.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A week or more ago mention was made in the Times of a project to convert Haas Park into a German non-sectarian cemetery. The matter originated among the German lodges and societies, and the scheme is rapidly developing.</p>
   <p>A month or two ago, several societies held a conference over the matter and extended invitations to all other German societies and lodges in the city to meet them in council. The invitations met with a general response, and at a meeting, held a week ago, 44 societies were represented. At this meeting, a committee was appointed to consult the interest of the project and report at a subsequent meeting.</p>
   <p>It was evident from the beginning that Haas Park would be the final choice of <pb facs="5418474_9_0268.jpg" n="2"/>not only the committe, but of all those who were in one way or another interested in the matter.</p>
   <p>On yesterday afternoon another meeting was held on Clark Street, in the Odd Fellows Hall, at which delegates from about forty societies were present, including those from German Masonic lodges, Odd Fellows, Sons of Herman, Harugari, Druids, Turners, Knights of Pythias, etc. The large hall was crowded.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rose, principal of the German high school on Maxwell Street, called the meeting to order. He said they had come to deliberate upon the location of a cemetery. Mr. Van Langen, the secretary, then read the minutes of the last meeting. Upon the invitation of the chairman, a dozen delegates, appointed by their respective societies since the last meeting, handed in their names, and expressed a desire to participate in the purposes of the meeting.</p>
   <p>The Chairman then stated that they had decided to purchase Haas Park and Mr. Francis Lockner, attorney, had kindly volunteered to attend to the legal points involved in the enterprise. A Charter had been granted, and the cemetery would be known under the name of "Waldheim" (Forest Home) and they were now prepared to dispose of shares.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Several propositions were received from various parties offering tracts of land for cemetery purposes, none of which were nearer than 13 miles from the courthouse, and received little support. The sentiments seemed to prevail that the best was the cheapest. Mr. Maas, from the committee on grounds, spoke at length, and to good purpose in favor of Haas Park. The ground was more elevated than any that had been offered. Besides, it was but half the distance from the city of any other, and if desired, burial parties could proceed thither in carriages.</p>
   <p>Mr. Blaner said he had been informed that a large tract was purchasable near Calvary for about $250 per acre. One delegate seemed to doubt the statement of his brother. He knew that the trustees of Calvary had desired to purchase more land northward, but were unable to do so on account of the temperance people of Evanston, who objected to the near proximity of spirits. Still other sites were suggested, but met with little favor on account of their inaccessibility.</p>
   <p>A resolution was then adopted, instructing the committee to buy Haas Park for Waldheim Cemetery. Another resolution was adopted to proceed immediately with the disposal of shares at $15 each, the same being equivalent to one lot 9 x <pb facs="5418474_9_0270.jpg" n="4"/>18 feet in size. The cost price of Haas Park, a tract of land 140 acres in extent, will be $108,000....</p>
   <p>... The plans as now under consideration, involve a grand monument to be placed in the centre of the cemetery, and about this will be grouped the various lots of the societies proper, and it is proposed, in time to place upon each a separate monument....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
