<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1875-12-05">Dec. 5, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1875-12-05">Dec. 5, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Society held its regular monthly meeting two days ago. The agent's [representative of the Society] report for the month of November 1875 was read and accepted.</p>
   <p>"Considering the present depleted cash reserves of the Society it is a very fortunate coincidence that the winter has been mild so far; otherwise the Society would hardly have been able to do anything for destitute Germans. The favorable weather still permits building operations and that provides an income for a large number of people. This also became evident in our office, since an increase of only one hundred people [needing aid] was noted over the number of last month's applicants. In November there were 568 persons asking for assistance; in October, 468 sought help; whereas in November, 1874, 850 unemployed people called at our office.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1065.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"This year the people did not ask so much for financial aid; most of them wanted employment; there were also a large number of homeless and unemployed single people who asked for temporary shelter or railroad fare in the hope of finding jobs elsewhere.</p>
   <p>"Regarding the various impoverished and destitute immigrant families which arrived here, only a few--the most desperate cases--could be given room and board from the Society's funds; the remainder were referred to the county for the alleviation of their immediate needs.</p>
   <p>"Your agent obtained assistance from the R. and Aid Society [Translator's note: The expression is abbreviated as shown; probably "Relief and Aid Society" is meant] in the form of cash, railroad tickets, blankets, clothing, etc. It is very difficult to allocate jobs in the city; unemployed people are everywhere present in great numbers; but there are still profitable openings for farm labor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1066.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Altogether 568 persons applied at our office for aid during November, 450 men and 118 women; there were also 253 who wanted jobs. Only 26 employers called and therefore no more than 68 persons could be given employment.</p>
   <p>"Support was given by the county agent in 42 cases [and by] the Relief [and Aid Society (?)] in 28 instances; and free transportation was provided in 2 cases. Your agent succeeded in inducing various railroad companies to give reduced rates to destitute persons. The reductions sometimes amounted to one half of the regular fare and affected 16 applicants.</p>
   <p>"The German Society made small cash donations in 9 cases, and in 19 instances involving immigrants, we provided temporary funds for room and board.</p>
   <p>"Two patients were sent to the hospital and to the German Dispensary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1067.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"We received 38 letters and mailed 43.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>"Charles Endres."</p>
   <p>The report of the secretary of the German Society gives an account of receipts and expenditures for the month of November, 1875:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>"Receipts:</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Surplus from last month,</cell>
     <cell>$141.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Regular contributions,</cell>
     <cell>225.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$366.85</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>"Expenditures:</p>
   <p>Aid, salary, office expenditures, etc. $274.28.</p>
   <p>Surplus, 92.57</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1068.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>"Max Eberhardt, Secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
