<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-30">July 30, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">New Ulm</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0934</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0934.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-30">July 30, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">NEW ULM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Aid and Collection Committee met at the Sherman House yesterday forenoon. Rudolph Brand was the chairman. The various collection committees submitted their reports. A. C. Hesing [Illinois Staats-Zeitung] had received $385 [largest sum]....[various business houses contributed]. Treasurer Madlener reported that he had already sent $2,500 to New Ulm [city destroyed by a tornado], and that he would send another $1,000 in the next mail.</p>
   <p>Since several members who were appointed to the collection committee declined to serve, it became necessary to appoint the following additional committees: for furniture dealers, Mr. Woltz of Stotz and Woltz....[and eight other mercantile branches; nearly all committee members have German names].</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0935.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The assembly resolved to support the concert in every respect and also accepted with thanks the offer of L. J. Kadish to hold a swimming contest in his natatorium on the West Side, the proceeds to go to the relief fund.</p>
   <p>The Concert</p>
   <p>The committee on arrangements appointed by the Central Board of the Singers' Alliance to take charge of the details of the concert appeared in full attendance at Quincy Number Nine and elected E. G. Uihlein chairman and A. Bucher secretary and treasurer. It was reported that the various song clubs had accepted the idea with enthusiasm and would do everything to make the concert a success. After a long discussion it was decided to give the concert at McCormick's Hall because other locations would hardly provide sufficient room for the large combined chorus, and the date was set for next Friday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0936.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Gestefeld read the following letter:</p>
   <p>"To the Editor of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung:</p>
   <p>"We read in the columns of your valued paper that the singing societies of our city intend to give a concert, the proceeds of which will be given to the relief fund for the stricken people of New Ulm. We regard the idea as a manifestation of genuine humanitarianism and are heartily in favor of the proposal, but we regret that we cannot participate in the concert, and therefore we ask you kindly to add the enclosed sum, fifty dollars, as our contribution to the New Ulm fund.</p>
   <p>"Very respectfully,</p>
   <p>"The Fidelia</p>
   <p>"J. Lorenzen, secretary"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0937.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hans Balatka was requested to arrange the program; it will be published tomorrow. The combined choral numbers of the last song festival, such as "Schlachtgebet," "Mutterseelenallein", and "Braunnen Wunderbar", will be included in the program. There will be several single choral selections and also solos by Miss Hanna McCarthy and Messrs. Hugo Lindau, E. Schultze, and Leiermann and perhaps a few more. Mr. Bucher will have charge of the sale of tickets. The Following announcement was made after the session adjourned.</p>
   <p>To All the Singing Societies of Chicago</p>
   <p>The delegates of clubs affiliated with the Singers' Alliance have appointed and authorized a committee to arrange a concert [to be given] at McCormick's Hall on Friday, August 5, for the benefit of the stricken city of New Ulm, Minnesota. Participation of all the singing societies of the city is expected, and their respective directors or music committees are requested, to <pb facs="5418474_9_0938.jpg" n="5"/>see Hans Balatka not later than four o'clock on Saturday afternoon, July 30, at Quincy Number Nine, to make arrangements for appearance at the concert.</p>
   <p>The committee also appeals to the clubs to be active in selling tickets for the concert. Admission will be fifty cents. The secretaries of the various clubs are asked kindly to confer with Mr. A. Bucher, 141-143 Wabash Avenue, any time after 2 P.M. of Saturday, July 30, to obtain blocks of tickets.</p>
   <p>The Committee,</p>
   <p>E. Uihlein, chairman,</p>
   <p>A. Bucher, secretary.</p>
   <p>The Ladies</p>
   <p>The appeal to the lady members of the festival chorus brought generous response. At eight o'clock about a hundred members appeared at Brand's Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0939.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. J. P. Hand gave a short address in which he emphasized that the aid of the ladies was desired for a humane cause. He stated that all arrangements had been made to give the projected concert next Friday at McCormick's Hall for the benefit of the sufferers in New Ulm.</p>
   <p>The ladies were asked to do the principal and most difficult work,that of selling the tickets. Since 5,000 tickets were printed, the 250 members of the Ladies Festival Chorus have a job on their hands. However, the enthusiastic response with which this announcement was received leads one to believe that the ladies will try their best to prevail upon their friends and acquaintances to help along the good cause. The ladies were asked to obtain tickets from Mr. A. Bucher, 141-143 Wabash Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
