<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-02-01">Feb. 1, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting of German Ladies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-02-01">Feb. 1, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MEETING OF GERMAN LADIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In accordance with appeals which appeared in the Illinois Staats-Zeitung yesterday and the day before, a large number of German ladies met in Bryan's Hall, yesterday at 3 o'clock.</p>
   <p>Mr. Caspar Butz opened the meeting by reading the appeal and making pertinent remarks. The ladies organized by electing Mrs. Elsie Schneider chairman, and Miss Emilie Brentano secretary.</p>
   <p>On recommendation of Mrs. Julie Butz it was decided to give a fair and a ball for the benefit of sick or wounded German Union soldiers.</p>
   <p>Thereupon various committees were elected, one of them for the purpose of interviewing Mr. Bryan relative to the free use of Bryan's Hall, another to <pb facs="5418474_9_1237.jpg" n="2"/>urge ladies to make various handwork for sale at the fair, and another to solicit donations of articles (or cash) for the fair from businessmen.</p>
   <p>Next Wednesday another meeting will be held, and the time and place of the fair and the ball will be decided according to the reports of the committees.</p>
   <p>We need not impress upon those ladies who were prevented from attending yesterday's meeting that it is very desirable that they, too, participate in this charity which must be dear to the heart of every German woman, and especially that they support the fair by either making or purchasing suitable articles for donation.</p>
   <p>The German ladies having set such a fine example of loving solicitude, the German men will feel compelled to do their part in this matter. How very insignificant are the sacrifices which are asked of us, when compared with those which our brothers daily make on the battlefield for the preservation of the Union and of liberty!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1238.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We need not explain how necessary it is to support our sick or wounded soldiers. Though medical care and hospitalization for our brave fighters have been improved, there is still much to be done to make adequate the care which these unfortunate men deserve. Then too, it must be remembered that every gift and effort of love makes a good moral impression upon those soldiers who are suffering in camps or hospitals. many a soldier here on furlough has told us that such gifts, such proof of sympathy shown by fellow citizens at home have instilled in disabled fighters new courage and new desire to live, even when they were tortured by the most intense pain; and thus our gifts contribute not a little to their recuperation.</p>
   <p>Thus far we have met but very few Germans whose minds have been poisoned by the whispering of traitors. So few will fail to heed the earnest request which our loyal and zealous ladies have made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
