<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-14">October 14, 1871</date><title level="a">[The Great Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-14">October 14, 1871</date><title level="a">[THE GREAT FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federal Government is perhaps going to give five or ten million for a new Post Office, Customs Office, Tax Office etc., the State of Illinois perhaps Three and a half million. The great capitalists of the East and of Europe are going to send here millions and millions to rebuild the big stores of State Street, Lake Street, Wabash Avenue, Washington, Madison, and Monroe Streets. But from what shall North Clark, Division, Sedgwick Street, Clybourne and North Avenue be reconstructed, and all the numberless side streets of the North Side? Even if the rich Stewart throws ten millions into Chicago - who is going to help the burnt out German, Irish and Scandinavian workers back to their feet?... American Germans are accustomed to fill the alms plates, not to hold them out. However, if it has to be done, it should be done without false shame. And it has to be done! - The quiet earnest, yes even the cheerfulness with which thousands of Germans talk about the loss of all their worldly possessions should not deceive anybody. In very, very many cases there is despair behind the mask of equanimity. To banish this despair, to revive hope, is the task of all Germans, who feel as Germans. If in a case like this the old Fatherland betrays its children, or tries to quiet them with beggarly alms, then the number of those who will be ashamed to have been born as Germans will grow by the tens of thousands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
