<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-01-24">Jan. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">German Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-01-24">Jan. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual report of the president of the German Hospital Society contains the following statistics:</p>
   <p>During the last year 569 patients were taken in by the German Hospital at Larrabee Street, sixty-one more than the previous year (284 males, 285 females); seventy-six of the patients were brought in by the police (twenty-seven accidents, two on whom murderous attacks had been made, thirteen suicide cases, six sick persons, three fighters, twenty-four of a longer illness); only nine of these cases were fatal.</p>
   <p>Four hundred seventy four persons have been dismissed by the hospital, of whom 315 were cured, 141 convalescent, eighteen incurable; fifty-three patients died in the hospital. Forty-two patients were in the hospital at the end of the year (twenty-six men, fourteen women, two children). Three hundred eighty persons of the coming-in patients were Germans; 152 Americans (of which 105 were German-Americans), one Swiss, two Swedes, one Norwegian, five Danes, <pb facs="5418474_9_0190.jpg" n="2"/>twelve British, eight Irish, two Scots, ten Austrians, one Italian, one French, six Canadians, seven Hungarians, one Bohemian, one Pole, two Russians, two Luxemburgers, and three Greeks. One hundred ninety four of the patients paid the full fee, 247 only part of it, 128 no fee at all. The takings of the hospital were $20,686.86; the expenses were $19,023.71.</p>
   <p>The membership in the beginning of the year was 758. Seven of them died, thirty-two left and thirty-four reduced their contributions. Two hundred defaulted with their contributions. There were twelve new members with contributions of $465. Eight old members increased their contributions with $60. The amount for nursing the 569 patients was $17.326 per month at an average against $1,383.71 in the previous year. This makes $1 a day for each patient.</p>
   <p>In the free clinic of the hospital, during the year, 3,400 persons found advice and support, of which 2.068 have been treated medically and 1,350 surgical.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0191.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The house physicians were Dr. A. Belitz, Dr. G. B. Gottschalk, Dr. H. Haifelden, Dr. Frager, Dr. Goldspohn, and Dr. Bernaner as members of the surgical staff and Dr. Hessert, Dr. Freer, and Dr. T. R. Welkev as members of the medical staff.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
