<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-04-06">April 6, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0902</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0902.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-04-06">April 6, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the general meeting yesterday the following reports were received: The Treasurer reported that the sum taken in by the Society during the past year amounted to $6,977 on payments of loans, $6,424.54 on contributions, $673.60 interest and $1,119.90 additional payments of the Women's Society; adding the sum of $81.99 present in the cash register at the beginning of the financial year, makes a net total of $13,477.03. The outstanding claims amount to $9,800.00. The expenditures for the year were $12,564.72, of which $2,039.59 were spent on relief, $6,950.83 is invested capital and $3,574.32 for salaries, rent, etc. According to this report the Society disposes of a surplus of $912.51. This, together with the afore-mentioned outstanding claims, and property representing a value of $5,000.00, amounts to $15,702.31, the Society's total fortune. The President's annual report told further that the Society's membership increased from 602 to 731, with an increased annual contribution from $3,563.00 to $4,835.00. The immigration was heavier during last year than ever before, the total figure reaching 712,542 of which 229,986 were German immigrants, the majority of the last mentioned group has chosen the Western States as their domicile. Chicago was the destination of 226,000 immigrants, almost one third of the total number. The immigration officials are working under the supervision of the Federal Government which is of great advantage to the immigrants. We express our gratitude to the railroad companies for their willing cooperation. We also commend the employment offices <pb facs="5418474_9_0903.jpg" n="2"/>for their good work. Of the 15,706 persons looking for employment, 5,067 were placed. -The City Council has been appealed to for an ordinance by which, operating an employment bureau would depend on the Mayor's consent and therefore, would be under police supervision. This request has been complied with for the benefit of the immigrants. The Society has been asked to help 23,452 persons (20,216 males, 3,136 females). Relief and advice was given 3,887 exceeding the list of the previous year by 873.</p>
   <p>Complying with the request of the German Society, the County agent helped 678 and the Relief and Aid Society, 302 persons. Medical treatment was received by 116, another 156 have been referred to hospitals and 38 received medicines free.</p>
   <p>The financial status of the Society is, as pointed out by the treasurer, satisfactory. A building for permanent occupation by the German Society has not been found so far. The following men then were elected directors: Messrs. Jacob Beiersdorf, William O. Hettich, Max Eberhardt, Conrad L. Niehoff, Louis Wampold, Henry W. Hill, F. Madlener, Edward G. Uehlein, George H. Rapp, Carl Moll, William Vocke, William Swissler, Louis Borlin, John Feldkamp and Richard Schicle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
