<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-04">December 4, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">The German Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0971</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0971.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-04">December 4, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon the administration of the German Club held their regular meeting, President Beiersdorff was Chairman and Secretary Eberhardt took down the minutes. Treasurer Christop made his report on the finances of the Association which was accepted. On account of the severe cold of last month, the number of the needy increased considerably. More than 306 applications partly for financial assistance, payments for rent, coal, groceries, clothing, sleeping accommodations, etc. have been received. Especially among the newly immigrated foreigners were many needy Germans, Poles and Bohemians. Twenty nine immigrants have been supplied with means to continue their journey. Also twenty one needy families livingin Chicago received assistance and thirty four families received means to leave Chicago ( they probably have been transported for $1.00 to St. Louis, the cheapest method to get rid of the petitioners forever.) The locality of the Club had been beseiged by friendless persons, especially during the cold season, by day and night but on account of the poor financial condition only 58 of the needy could be taken care of. Totally, according to the report of the agent, ten invalids have been sent to the hospitals and twenty six received free medicine. The cash balance of the society has been reduced with $412.80 by giving support to 692 persons. The Society has resolved to alter its mode of propoganda and in place <pb facs="5418474_9_0972.jpg" n="2"/>of arranging entertainments, dances, concerts, etc. it will organize a membership drive among the Germans of Chicago in the interest of the needy and suffering. It is anticipated that immigration will continue to increase and the means of the society are much too small, to satisfy all demands made.</p>
   <p>Therefore the necessity has arisen, to get a larger membership. The Chairman also asked the gentlemen of the publicity Committee to do their very best in this respect. The following gentlemen have been accepted as new members.</p>
   <p>G. Gregory, F. C. Lentz, H. Bockener, Louis Brenell, John Feldkampf, Fred Frendenberg, Otto Dehling, and William Bettinghausen. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
