<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-09-05">September 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">German Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-09-05">September 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the trustees of the German Society, the management reported on the activities of the last three months (June, July, and August). It gives us a definite picture of the praise-worthy actions of one of the oldest benevolent societies in Chicago, and proves how, in these great and exciting times, the demands which are placed upon the society are greater than ever.</p>
   <p>In the above mentioned period of time, 237 families with 637 children have received cash relief; 424 single persons, among them 27 women, idle and without shelter, have received 5,112 meals and 589 nights' lodgings, against 1,688 meals and 202 nights' lodgings in the corresponding months of last year.</p>
   <p>Through recommendation of the society, 19 persons have been admitted to hospitals free of charge; 16 persons to various county institutions; and 14 persons have received medical attention and medicine, free of charge.</p>
   <p>The expenses for relief amounted to $2,650.25. For 868 persons employment was secured; most of these people being sent to the rural districts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0693.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In comparison to the stationary number of unemployed since the beginning of the war, only with small exceptions, the offer of work has steadily decreased, therefore the necessity for distribution of a greater number of meals and nights' lodgings is explained. The conditions form an exact measure of improvement or deterioration, by the increase or decrease of persons applying for work, meals, or shelter, and are still more vividly illuminated if the first eight months of the past year and this year compared.</p>
   <p>From January 1, until August 31, 1914, 4,696 meals and 624 nights' lodgings were supplied, while in the same period of this year, 19,218 meals and 950 nights' lodgings were given. Cash relief for the first eight months of 1914 amounted to $5,922.32, while cash relief in the same period of 1915 amounted to $8,558.06.</p>
   <p>Considering such numbers, which are such mute and yet deliberate proof, and with the sad certainty of conditions becoming worse during the winter months, the society begs all charitably inclined persons for money donations, or for yearly membership to the amount of $10.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
