<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-18">Jan. 18, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">German Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Report of Yesterday's Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-18">Jan. 18, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Report of Yesterday's Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the general meeting of the German Hospital yesterday evening, the following directors, whose terms had already expired, were re-elected for another three-year period: Judge Theodore Brentano, John C. Burmeister, George Schneider, and Charles Emmerich. President John Miller acted as chairman.</p>
   <p>The detailed annual report of President Miller shows that the German Hospital is in an excellent condition; it acquires an ever growing clientele among the wealthier classes, which provides a better income.</p>
   <p>During the past fiscal year, 680 patients were treated, viz., 270 men, 410 women, and 36 children (sic). Among these, 591 were cured and discharged; 53 died, and on January 1, 1901, only 36 remained in the <pb facs="5418474_9_0170.jpg" n="2"/>hospital. The 680 patients represented 297 Germans, 283 German-Americans, 8 Swiss, and 12 Austrians. [This accounts for only 600 persons. The other 80 presumably were Americans, since the report mentions 680 patients. Trans.]</p>
   <p>The income, according to the treasurer Charles Emmerich, was $34,728.86; the total expenditures were $34,197.80. On January 1, 1901, there was a balance of 531.06. The annual contributions of the members amounted to $3,890; i.e., $500 less than last year. Donations reached a total of $5,474.96, about $2,000 more than in the year 1899, and hospital fees provided an income of $21,504.07. This represents an increase of $2,800 over last year. Among the donations, the following are listed: $2,000 from the German-American Charity Association, and $500 from Mr. Jacob Huber. The evening entertainment of Uhlich's Orphan Home, given for the benefit of the hospital, produced $390.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0171.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The directorate had resolved to raise $10,000 to diminish its indebtedness, and thus far it has been successful in raising $5,000, part in pledges and part in cash.</p>
   <p>The training school for nurses, which is a very important adjunct to the institution, is thriving and enjoys an excellent reputation. The nurses who attain proficiency in their calling, both theoretical and practical, are very much in demand to take charge of patients in private homes.</p>
   <p>During the previous year, 28 nurses applied for acceptance but only 17 matriculated. At the end of the year, the school's standing is as follows: 6 nurses are in the second year and 25 in the third year class.</p>
   <p>The Hospital Messenger brought a surplus of $315.42.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0172.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the annual report, President John Miller also expresses his thanks to all supporters and donors, as well as to the German Press, for their good will.</p>
   <p>The following lines represent a chronological record of the hospital since August, 1884, date in which it was founded: In the year 1884, 25 patients were registered; in 1885, 87; in 1886, 71; in 1887, 103; in 1882, 228; in 1889, 376; in 1890, 550; in 1891, 714; in 1892, 741; in 1893, 660; in 1894, 508; in 1895, 569; in 1896,582; in 1897, 650; in 1898, 733; in 1899, 766; and in 1900, 680. A total of 8,048 patients treated since the institution's inception.</p>
   <p>The directorate will announce an election within the near future. The following persons are also officials aside of those previously mentioned:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0173.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>John Miller, Edward G. Uihlein, Otto C. Butz, Hermann Paepke, Louis Lutz, and Erich Gerstenberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
