<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-03">Apr. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-03">Apr. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The release of the Germans interned and imprisoned in the United States is imminent.</p>
   <p>According to all reports received, they are in urgent need of all kinds of clothing, such as suits, shoes, underwear, shirts, etc.</p>
   <p>Through the co-operation of friends we were able to purchase suits of first class material and workmanship for $12.50 apiece.</p>
   <p>Special collections have made it possible to place one thousand of these suits at the disposal of German marine officers and sailors who will be set free. Suits are also to be provided for another thousand marine officers and sailors who are now confined at Fort Oglethorpe, for about fifteen hundred officers and crew members of former German warships who are imprisoned at Fort McPherson, and also for several hundred interned civilians who are to be deported to Germany. The necessary funds to purchase the suits must be raised soon. The cost of about <pb facs="5418474_9_0651.jpg" n="2"/>three thousand suits and other clothing is estimated at fifty thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The Welfare Committee is acting by permission of the State Department, has a general license from the War Trade Board and the War Department to send consignments to the various camps, and earnestly requests help and contributions, so that the war prisoners and interned who are to be deported to Germany may be equipped in time. And for an additional thousand interned German civilians who are to be released soon we will have to have one thousand used suits and overcoats.</p>
   <p>Money in the form of checks (made payable to Adolf Kuttroff, Chairman) should be sent to us at 24 North Moore Street, New York City.</p>
   <p>"A dollar today is worth ten tommorrow."</p>
   <p>Welfare Committee For Prisoners Of War.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
