<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Get Busy!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Collections for the Relief of Distress Show Generosity of the Schwabenverein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-13">Aug. 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S GET BUSY!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Collections for the Relief of Distress Show Generosity of the Schwabenverein</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The collections for the Deutsche und Oesterreichisch-Ungarische Hilfsgesellschaft (German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society) of Chicago are in full swing. The purpose is to bring relief to those whom the war has caused to suffer. The Abendpost, too, has been authorized to accept contributions for the good cause, and can boast of gratifying results. This afternoon, the finance committee, under the chairmanship of Karl Eitel, will meet to work out the details. It is probable that in addition to the workers who were furnished with collection blanks by the various Vereine, a number of places will be authorized to accept contributions. The names and locations of these places will probably be published tomorrow. The names and contributions of the individual donors will also be published, and this publication will serve as a receipt.</p>
   <p>Karl Eitel, chairman of the finance committee, has appointed the following <pb facs="5418474_9_0758.jpg" n="2"/>members for his committee, which is to consist of fifteen gentlemen: August Blum, Julius Kessler, Arthur Josetti, Harris W. Huehl, Peter Theurer, Dr. O. S. D. Schmidt, A. Uhrlaub, L. Guentzel, and Rudolph Brandt. [Translator's note: only nine names are given.]</p>
   <p>The executive committee of the Aid Society, consisting of the president, the vice-presidents, the secretary, and the treasurer, met yesterday afternoon at five o'clock for a secret session. After the reading of the minutes of Saturday's session, and the appointing of the special committees, the following appeal was issued to the German element of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Appeal to the Masses!</p>
   <p>"War has broken out and is claiming its toll. Countless sacrifices are being made daily and hourly in countries from which we originated. We cannot stop the slaughter; we can only hope that it will be of short duration, and that the peoples of Europe will soon again enjoy the blessings of peace.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0759.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"It is a tragedy that in our age of progress, war, with all its horrors, has become a fact. But that does not serve as an excuse for us who far away from the theater of war to stand idly by and shirk the duties which the times have imposed upon us.</p>
   <p>"Where there is war there are wounds. To heal these is our sacred duty. Where there is war there is also want and suffering. To alleviate this want, to relieve this misery, and to act as comforters and good samaritans is the obligation of those who live far away from the war area. Our motives should be charity and love of neighbor.</p>
   <p>"Inspired by these motives, the Deutsche und Oesterreichisch-Ungarische Hilfsgesellschaft has been organized. It is our intention to use all the available means at our command to lighten the burden of war.</p>
   <p>"While under the neutrality laws we must be careful not to give assistance to the armies of the belligerents; it is our right, nevertheless, to help the <pb facs="5418474_9_0760.jpg" n="4"/>wounded and to give our sympathies and active assistance to the widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>"The territories of the countries and the masses of the population which are affected by the war are so tremendous that great sums of money are required if we desire to discharge adequately our duty toward our bloodbrothers.</p>
   <p>"Trusting that we will have your friendly co-operation, we are asking everybody to join in the great work we have set out to tackle. Our movement is not one of a few individuals, but a mass movement. We do not appeal to a handful of people, but to all our German brothers whose homeland is either Germany or Austria.</p>
   <p>"You must show that your hearts beat for your brethren across the seas. Germans, Austrians, and Hungarians over here stand united in this work of love, just as they are united in defense and attack on the other side of the ocean."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0761.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It was then decided that the treasurer, Oskar F. Mayer, should place a bond of fifty thousand dollars. Issuance of blank collection lists is to be closely checked to avoid errors. Every list bears a number, and the name of the person to whom it was issued is to be recorded by a collection official. It was announced that four gentlemen had already pledged amounts of two thousand, five hundred, and three thousand dollars. The names of the generous donors, however, were temporarily withheld in order to avoid possible errors in the lists of official receipts which are to be published later. It was also resolved to hold a meeting of all the committees next Wednesday night in the upper clubrooms of the Bismarck Hotel.</p>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting in the Green Mill Gardens, the Erholung Club (Recreation Club) decided to turn over five hundred dollars to the Red Cross. According to the president, Mrs. Ida Schrader, this contribution is to be increased if it is found that more funds are required.</p>
   <p>The Schwabenverein, true to its tradition, always among the first to relieve <pb facs="5418474_9_0762.jpg" n="6"/>suffering and distress, and aware of its duties as the largest German Verein during this world crisis of the German cause, held a memorable meeting in the North Side Turner Hall, and resolutions were made which are indeed a credit to this organization.</p>
   <p>President Fritz Hess opened the meeting and pointed out its purpose: namely, to find ways and means to assist the fighting German brothers and their dependents. After he had explained the causes of the World War in an interesting manner, Secretary Heinrich Hieber read four recommendations of the executive committee. The first one suggested that the sum of one thousand dollars be given to the relief fund of the Deutsche und Oesterreichisch-Ungarische Hilfsgesellschaft, and that later a portion of the proceeds of the Cannstatter Volksfest (annual Swabian festival; Cannstatt is a locality in Germany) be used for the same purpose.</p>
   <p>During the ensuing discussion, however, it became apparent that the members did not care to bother with trifles, and when Mr. Karl Haerting pointed out <pb facs="5418474_9_0763.jpg" n="7"/>that a Verein which could spare fifteen thousand dollars for a monument was well in the position to spend more than one thousand dollars for the victims of the greatest German war, applause was heard which proved the sincerity and interest of the German element.</p>
   <p>"We would be willing to give our last drop of blood for our countrymen," said Mr. Haerting, "but since we can't do that, we want to give at least every cent we can spare. I move that all proceeds from the Cannstatter Volksfest be turned over to the relief fund."</p>
   <p>With rousing applause the motion was adopted unanimously.</p>
   <p>The next recommendation of the executive committee, that the entire amount be turned over to the treasurer of the Deutsch-Amerikanische National-Bund, was also adopted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ansorge's plan, to erect a sales tent at the Volksfest at his expense for <pb facs="5418474_9_0764.jpg" n="8"/>the benefit of the relief fund, was also approved. If the expenses should run too high, the Verein would assume a share.</p>
   <p>The last recommendation of the executive committee was in regard to the certified collection blanks issued by the National Bund and on which individual donors may register their pledges. Two of these lists had been sent to Mr. Hess, and in no time five hundred dollars was pledged by the audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. August Lueders called the attention of the meeting to the Irish picnic next Saturday in Brand's Park. The purpose of the picnic is to aid the Irish countrymen who are fighting for their existence across the seas. Mr. Lueders announced that the Irish had invited the Germans and that as an expression of their sympathy with Germany they intended to raise a German flag. Together with the Irish, the Germans could make a protest against the closing of the German radio stations [Translator's note: Transatlantic transmitters probably] located on American soil. The Irish had already offered their co-operation, and therefore Mr. Lueders suggested that the Schwabenverein appear in <pb facs="5418474_9_0765.jpg" n="9"/>a body at the Irish picnic and protest against the silencing of the German wireless stations.</p>
   <p>Both motions were adopted, The protest against cutting off communications between Germany and America will be carefully worked out. As far as the Irish picnic is concerned, as many members as possible should participate. The entire executive committee will be there.</p>
   <p>During the discussion it was also revealed that nobody would have to drink California or Ohio wine at the Cannstatter Volksfest, for twenty-five barrels of imported wine has been procured for the guests. Then there was the question of whether it was fitting and proper to hold festivals during these grave times, but it was decided that an affair like the Cannstatter Volksfest, for which preparations had been made so long in advance, could not be cancelled upon so short a notice, even though such amusements are untimely.</p>
   <p>With a vote of confidence to the executive committee whose business administration <pb facs="5418474_9_0766.jpg" n="10"/>during the past was lauded, and with an expression of unlimited confidence in its efficient handling of the great problems of the future, the meeting adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
