<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Relief Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">Every German's Sacred Duty to do His Part</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-20">Aug. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE RELIEF WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">Every German's Sacred Duty to do His Part</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of Germans, Austrians, and Hungarians are now shedding their blood on the battlefields of Europe, and many of them will worry about their loved ones at home, whom they left without a provider when the war drums called them to the colors. Whole trainloads of wounded will leave the war zones for home after the great battles, and the care of these wounded and the relief of distress among the destitute families of the soldiers will cost many millions. Their compatriots living abroad have the sacred duty of taking part in this relief work, and of contributing, without exception and to the best of their abilities, to the relief fund which will be turned over to the Red Cross. Any gift, no matter how small, is welcome; the pennies from a child's savings bank as much as the check of the businessman or the donation of the workingman. Every cent will help to alleviate pain, to dry tears. And if the men now go through hell and death learn that their blood brothers across the great pond have not forsaken them, but stand by them loyally and effectively, their <pb facs="5418474_9_0752.jpg" n="2"/>courage will be steeled for the horrible struggle ahead. The Abendpost, which has been authorized by the German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society to accept contributions, asks its readers to open their hearts and their purses, and either take their donations to the Abendpost office or mail them in. The money will then be forwarded to Mr. Oskar F. Mayer, treasurer of the Aid Society. The amounts received will be published daily in the local columns of the Abendpost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
