<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Fest in the Interest of German Winter Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL FEST IN THE INTEREST OF GERMAN WINTER RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An evening for the benefit of local winter relief for Germans arranged last Saturday in the De Paul Auditorium by the organized German Societies of Greater Chicago was in every way successful.</p>
   <p>The number of people in the audience was quite satisfactory, and good music was provided by Hennecke's orchestra; entertainment of every description, as well as first class food, contributed to the pleasure of the evening.</p>
   <p>A special attraction was the great winter procession in which about a hundred persons participated, and for which Mrs. Mathesius prepared the pretty costumes. Furthermore, there were dances by Dorothy Mathesius, Ruth Hergert, and Erna Schweizer and "Schuhplattler" performances [tap dances] by the gay Holzhacker Buam (woodchopper boys).</p>
   <p>Among those present were the German consul general, Dr. Jaeger, district <pb facs="5418474_9_0478.jpg" n="2"/>leader Fritz Gissibl from the bund of the Friends of New Germany, vice-president William Joern from the German-American citizens bund, and other notable persons. Addresses were given by the chairman of the organization Georg Joesten, and by Herr Arthur Koegel about the Dawa (German American Winter Relief). At the head of the fest committee was President Georg Joesten, Fest President Fred Lindner, and Treasurer Theo Jung.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday a large number of guests gathered at the well-known family restaurant of Von Thenen, Western Avenue and Roscoe Street. They came to listen to the music of the artists' quartet and orchestra of the Friends of New Germany, and to enjoy their coffee and cake and other refreshments.</p>
   <p>The hours went by much too quickly, owing to the lively conversation and light music, and at parting one could often hear "Auf wiedersehen next Sunday!"</p>
   <p>These concerts, as reported elsewhere, take place every Sunday afternoon, beginning at 3 P.M. Admission is free. All Germans are cordially invited.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
