<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-19">May 19, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Society of German Old People's Home Extremely Active</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Report Submitted by Frieda Schmidt, President of Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-19">May 19, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S SOCIETY OF GERMAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME EXTREMELY ACTIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Report Submitted by Frieda Schmidt, President of Home</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the general meeting of the Women's Society of the German Old People's Home, in Forest Park, the annual report was submitted by Mrs. Schmidt, president of the Society. The text of the report was as follows:</p>
   <p>"As you all are aware, one-half of a century has elapsed since the founding of this home for the aged. The financial report, which you will hear about from the proper officials, shows that the German Old People's Home operates on a sound basis, although the capital is insufficient to render the institution self-supporting.</p>
   <p>"This Home depends to a large extent upon charitable donations; it therefore seems quite appropriate to remind the friends of this Home to extend financial assistance to this worthy cause, thus helping to bring security to those whose <pb facs="5418474_9_0380.jpg" n="2"/>advanced years prompted them to seek the hospitality of this institution."</p>
   <p>The proceeds of a card party held last July, when the fiscal year was inaugurated, yielded the sum of $548.90.</p>
   <p>Splendid work was also done by the Women's Sewing Circle associated with the institution. The articles produced by their talented fingers were exhibited and sold during the last week of October, 1928 at the Webster Hotel. Thus the sum of $3,548.88 was realized toward the maintenance of the Home.</p>
   <p>The charity ball held at the Belden-Stratford Hotel on the first of December yielded the net proceeds of $3,658.25, as a result of the extraordinary efforts of Mrs. Henry Klaas, who met with splendid success in selling tickets for the entertainment.</p>
   <p>The fifty-first anniversary of the founding of the German Old People's Home. was celebrated at a luncheon held on April 21 at the Webster Hotel. Doctor <pb facs="5418474_9_0381.jpg" n="3"/>Ludwig Mueller, the German exchange professor at Northwestern University, delivered the principal address.</p>
   <p>According to an announcement made by Mrs.Klaas, the list of life-members of the institution has been increased by eight new names. On the other hand, the Home suffered the loss of two of its founders, Mrs. Marie Mann and Mrs. Gesine Rapp, who with nine other associates of this organization were taken by death. Tribute was then paid to the memory of these departed members.</p>
   <p>Only twenty-one new members have affiliated themselves with the organization - in sharp contrast to the number that joined during the previous year. The list of members of the organization now contains 516 names.</p>
   <p>The Home was also the recipient of two five-hundred dollar legacies: one from Mrs. Magdalena Schmelzer, the other from Mr. Edward Schoellkopf. Furthermore, Mrs. Marie Lefens' generous gift of five-thousand dollars was used, as she instructed, to increase the endowment fund. The Wieboldt Foundation also made a contribution of five-hundred dollars to this charitable institution. Donations <pb facs="5418474_9_0382.jpg" n="4"/>were also received from the following persons: William Mannhardt, $150; Mr. Horney, $50; Mrs. B. Schulz $50; Miss Poyrne, $20; and Mrs. Ida Marshall, $10. In addition, the profits derived from the showing of the motion-picture "The S. S. Emden," amounting to $117.58, was also presented to the institution. And finally, Christmas gifts totaling $415 concluded the list of donations.</p>
   <p>"To all who have contributed toward the success of this association," [said Mrs. Schmidt,] "I express my deepest gratitude - especially to the officials of the organization and the members of the various committees.</p>
   <p>"In conclusion, I wish to express the great appreciation felt by this association to the Men's Executive Committee, which has at all times given us its splendid co-operation."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
