<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-12">Jan. 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">German Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Transactions During the Recent Session of This Benevolent Institution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-12">Jan. 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Transactions During the Recent Session of This Benevolent Institution</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The January session of the board of directors of the German Home for the Aged was held at the Schiller Hall on Thursday evening, with Jacob Heissler, president, functioning as chairman.</p>
   <p>Mr. Eberhardt, chairman of the Acceptance Committee, submitted the application of Mrs. Johanna Burkheim, 4811 Langley Avenue. She is 87 years old and lived in Cook County during the last twelve years. Mr. Gustav Rupprecht was accepted on trial for a year, and Mr. Charles Robertus will remain permanently.</p>
   <p>According to the report, the Administrative Committee is organized as follows: Julius Rosenthal, chairman; Mrs. Maria Werkmeister, secretary. Kitchen committee: Mrs. L. Lackner, Mrs. S. Heissler, and Mrs. M. Muehlhaus. [Other committees are listed, such as laundry, rooms, garden, finance. Transl.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0418.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Bills amounting to $994.94 were ordered to be paid; receipts amounted to $67.21.</p>
   <p>Health conditions at the Home are somewhat threatening at present, and several cases of influenza have been registered. Mrs. Marie Raible, who had been ailing for many years, died on December 24, and Heinrich Hannah departed to the Great Beyond, on January 6. Two new inmates have been accepted, Nicolaus Richter and Heinrich Aula.</p>
   <p>The Administrative Committee noted that the discontinuance of local trains proved to be a distinct disadvantage to the institution; the distance becomes more inconvenient now than formerly, and a telephone is, therefore, of vital necessity. In view of these findings, the members resolved to recommend its installation, and they suggested that Mr. Heissler communicate with the Telephone Company. The water supply question also came under consideration, and it was shown that the present cylinder [verbatim] is entirely too small, that a larger cylinder and gasoline engine will save considerable money now paid for water tax. The <pb facs="5418474_9_0419.jpg" n="3"/>executives asked Mr. Heissler to investigate the problem.</p>
   <p>Thanks were expressed to the following donors: Heissler and Junge, for bread; Fleischmann for, yeast; the Tosetti Brewing Co., Schoenhofen Brewing Co., Henn and Gabler, Anheuser Busch, Manhattan, Wacker and Birk, Blatz, Pabst, and Independent Brewing Co., for beer.</p>
   <p>Announcements of future activities: Euchre party, with valuable prizes, next Saturday, January 26, 2 P.M., at Schiller Hall. The ladies hope that members and friends will appear in large numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
