<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-02-27">Feb. 27, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0815</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0815.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-02-27">Feb. 27, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This society held its annual meeting yesterday at the Association's headquarters, 50 N. La Salle Street, which was attended by the entire staff. After the president, Mr. Brentano, explained the purpose of the meeting, he proceeded with the following report. At the end of last year this Association had a membership of 549, thirty-two of whom were new members. This is a sadly small number, if we take into consideration the large German population of Chicago, which exceeds 500,000. Contributions received from our members totalled $3,230.38....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0816.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A correct statement of the number of immigrants who remained in Chicago cannot be given, but it is certain that the number exceeds that of the previous year. The number fitted for factory work was largest. The next largest group was composed of people seeking employment in the business world. The number of agricultural laborers, however, was surprisingly small. During the past year 3,850 employers and 3475 employees were successfully served without any charge through the medium of our agency. The German Society expressed its deep appreciation to the German-American Charity Association for the donation of $400.00. They also expressed their gratitude to the Bureau of Justice, the German and the Alexian Brothers' hospitals, the varuous railroad companies, and to the representatives of the North German Lloyd, and the Chicago Relief and Aid Society. This Society also expressed its appreciation for the services rendered by the German newspapers of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0817.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The resignation of six directors was announced. A committee for the nomination of new directors was appointed with the result, that the election of candidates for that office fell upon the following: E.G. Halle, Alexander Klappenbach, E. Mannhardt, E. Wm. Kalb, Gustav E. Fischer and Adolph Georg. They were elected unanimously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
