<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-05-10">May 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Evangelical Deaconess Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-05-10">May 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">EVANGELICAL DEACONESS SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As previously often reported, a Deaconess Society has been formed here, whose aim is to build a hospital, furthermore to train deaconesses after the German model. The society acquired about six months ago, five building lots, to which it added a sixth, so that it possesses now a building lot, totaling 125 by 150 feet. Its situation is favorable for a hospital. Near a large thoroughfare (Halsted Street) the noise made by cars cannot be heard by the patients, on the other hand Garfield Boulevard is near by, and Sherman Park is also inviting to the patients. The building lots are on 54th Place and Morgan Street. This property which represents a value of $7,500.00 and is almost fully paid for, belongs to the Deaconess society. The place upon which the hospital will be erected exists already. The plans have also been submitted by the architects, and all that is necessary is the erection of the building. Gifts of love enabled the purchase of the lots, and such gifts shall also be the means for the erection of the building. Naturally, it will be necessary to knock on many doors, before the necessary amount can be raised. The directors found in Pastor Tillmann the right man, who gladly made collections for the cause. Besides, 2 pupils of Elmhurst's seminary have been won, who, during the summer vacations, will collect in the city and the country gifts for the hospital. The names of the young men <pb facs="5418474_9_0162.jpg" n="2"/>will be made known shortly, and they will receive credentials, so that they should be able to identy themselves. The Deaconess Society has already 350 members. Annual dues are $2.00. Whoever wants to join this society, should send his yearly dues to Rev. G. Koch, 646 W. 62nd Street, from whom they will receive receipt, by laws, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
