<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-03-30">Mar. 30, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">50Th Jubilee of the Altenheim.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-03-30">Mar. 30, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">50TH JUBILEE OF THE ALTENHEIM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 50th Jubilee of the Altenheim began with an excellent luncheon. This was followed by an instrumental and singing program which was greatly appreciated by the 300 guests. The festival took place in the Webster Hotel yesterday afternoon, and was under the supervision of Mrs. Adolf Schmidt, its president.</p>
   <p>At her side were, as honorary guests and representatives of the German government, Dr. Hugo F. Simon and his wife. The hall itself was decorated with beautiful flowers, and in front of the president's chair sparkled in large golden ciphers, the number "50." Everybody was in a lively mood.</p>
   <p>With well chosen words, the president greeted those present and introduced the three surviving founders of the Altenheim, Mrs. Mary Mauer, Mrs. Gesina Rapp and Mrs. Gustava Rockener. After a beautiful prologue, recited by Mrs. Sophie Listemann, the Consul General took the word and held the festival speech in a humorous vein.</p>
   <p>He remembered the sacrifices of the women during the last 50 years, since the <pb facs="5418474_9_0384.jpg" n="2"/>founding of the Altenheim. In simple words, he described the sacrifices of the first active president of the Altenheim Women's Society, Mrs. Marie Werkmeister, and spoke of German love and kindred feelings, which enabled the institution to grow. He spoke of woman's superiority over man, when it comes to lending a helping hand, because the man, on account of his duties is unable to devote his time to such acts of love as the Altenheim requires.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
