<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-29">Nov. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Are Vigilance Committees Necessary?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-29">Nov. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ARE VIGILANCE COMMITTEES NECESSARY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Has it become necessary in Chicago to organize vigilance committees? Thinking about the many unusual crimes which have been committed in Chicago during recent days and weeks, one is compelled to ask the above question. Masked men stage their hold-ups in our suburbs in broad daylight. They force people, at the point of a gun to turn over cash and valuables, irrespective of sex or age. Almost in the heart of the city a gang of masked robbers enters shops and stores with brazen audacity, hold up guests and customers, and recklessly kill those who dare to interfere or oppose. Day and night we have with us the pickpockets, and highwaymen, and mysterious nightly burglaries, robberies and murder.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1399.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A real flood of crimes has come upon us. Our police appear to be unable even to catch one of these criminals; it seems to be helpless and perplexed.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the police department with its chiefs, its inspectors, its captains and its lieutenants are not to blame; nevertheless, their competence is questionable, and so much so, that we must repeat the former question: "Has it become necessary to organize vigilance societies in Chicago?"</p>
   <p>The answer is, yes! The present deplorable conditions must not continue. Our envious and jealous friends in New York, St. Louis, and in Europe will readily exploit the situation, and portray the dangers, to which visitors at the World's Fair will expose themselves. They will describe very vividly how the streets in Chicago swarm with robbers, and how wise it is to prepare for death before entering one of the saloons. The good reputation of Chicago will suffer seriously, if these conditions continue to exist.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1400.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the police force does not bestir itself, then there will be an urgent necessity to organize vigilance committees, which will drive the criminals from the city, and the corrupt elements from the police force.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
