<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-04">Oct. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-04">Oct. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The executive board of the German Society held its semiannual meeting yesterday. Georg Schneider, president of the Society, acted as chairman.</p>
   <p>After reading the minutes and attending to routine matters, Mrs. M. Werkmeister and Messrs. J. Beiersdorff and Arthur Erbe were named as members of the entertainment committee.</p>
   <p>After reading the agent's report for September, the meeting adjourned. [Translator's note: The agent is in charge of the Society's welfare work, distribution of funds, etc.].</p>
   <p>The Report</p>
   <p>The records show that immigration was fairly large last month. Figures for <pb facs="5418474_9_1001.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago show that 2,200 people came to the city, but the majority will go to farms in the West, Northwest and the Territories. All nationalities were represented. There were about 400 Germans; 500 Russians, mostly well-to-do Mennonites; 500 Norwegians, Swedes, Danes, and Belgians; 200 Austrians, Bohemians, and Hungarians; 300 English, Scotch, and Irish; 150 Italians; 100 Swiss and French; and about 50 from Schleswig-Holstein.</p>
   <p>Altogether 828 people called at our office, 664 men and 164 women.</p>
   <p>During the past month, 67 employers came to our employment bureau, and we were able to place 208 people out of 378.</p>
   <p>Advice and help was given in 187 cases.</p>
   <p>We had 170 applicants asking for money and, upon investigation, we gave cash to 40 persons whom we considered deserving. According to our figures, 50 persons <pb facs="5418474_9_1002.jpg" n="3"/>wanted free or partially paid railroad fare. Free medical aid was sought by 6 people; and they were also given medicine free of charge. Room and board were provided in 52 instances. We referred 42 cases to the county.</p>
   <p>Our total expenditures for aid, etc., amounted to $302.80 during the month of September.</p>
   <p>A case involving lost baggage, which we traced and located, was also recorded.</p>
   <p>Very respectfully,</p>
   <p>Charles Endres,</p>
   <p>Agent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
