<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-10-08">Oct. 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-10-08">Oct. 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's regular monthly session of the German Society the following persons were present besides chairman Beiersdorff and Secretary Eberhardt: Mrs. Weakmeister and Messrs. Madlener, Hill, Hettich, Erbe, Berg, Uihlein, and Biroth.</p>
   <p>Carl Moll tendered his resignation because he did not approve of Agent Ender's conduct. The resignation was not accepted because the affair was not considered of sufficient importance.....[Translator's note: Details are given but are omitted in the translation because it was simply an altercation.] The monthly report of the agent follows.</p>
   <p>According to estimates 18,000 immigrants arrived in Chicago by rail in the month of September, or an average of 600 per day. All European nations were represented. Swedes, Norwegians, and Danes were still most numerous. About four fifths of these continued their journey after a short stay. With few <pb facs="5418474_9_0911.jpg" n="2"/>exceptions they were farm workers and laborers and had little money.</p>
   <p>In the last month 1492 persons called at our office, an average of 57 daily. There were 1239 men and boys and 253 women and girls. The following vocations were represented: laborers 785, druggists 6, bakers 33, butchers 5, brewery workers 6, miners 3, bookbinders 6, printers 2, building carpenters 25, dyers 5, gardeners 9, goldsmiths 4, hatters 1, engineers 4, clerks 88, coopers 6, waiters 2, teachers 9, millers 10, bricklayers 7, painters 6, machinists 43, stonecutters 3, tailors 3, blacksmiths 7, typesetters 11, shoemakers 55, saddlers 2, locksmiths 52, cabinetmakers 24, paperhangers 1, potters 2, wheelwrights 4, total men 1239 [Translator's note: I can find only 1229 according to the figures given]; total women 253, grand total 1492.</p>
   <p>All together 164 employers called this month; last month, 144. We had 11 reports of lost baggage and took action in the matter and succeeded in locating the articles in 7 cases. We had 276 requests for aid and gave assistance to 31. Our total expenditures for aid, etc., amounted to $238.80.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0912.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following gentlemen became members: M. J. Stallus, Louis Koerner, Harold Zimmermann, Eduard Hoffmann, Charles Kaltenbach, Wartmann Brothers, Gerhard Soeffker, Louis Klinckerfues, M. Wassermann, J. J. Jung, and C. Cunon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
