<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1894-03-26">March 26th, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Ignorance and Crime.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1894-03-26">March 26th, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">IGNORANCE AND CRIME.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Various Aid Societies and noted Philanthropists joined hands lately with the goal of diminishing crime, which from their standpoint is caused mainly by the ignorance of the poorer classes.</p>
   <p>We cannot agree completely with the opinion of these Societies, which are representing more or less the one sided mental attitude of our wealthy classes, which always liked to name education and knowledge as the cause and reason of their earthly wealth. We have written before on this subject and never shall miss the opportunity to enlighten the public, whenever misleading theories are reaching our ears.</p>
   <p>Crime is caused, as a rule, by poverty in homelife and morbid surroundings during the childhood days and later life. These underlying-crime-breeding conditions can be remedied by more ample work opportunities at decent wages and equivalent labor protection laws, which above guarantee the safety of the American home and growing children, mentally and morally. An educational program will be of course helpful to guide our youth along, in order to become useful members of our community, if under all circumstances a friendly labor policy has been followed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1397.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ignorance by itself never will be a driving force towards crime and education never will be an unfailing preventative of crime, which can be diminished to a certain extent, but never will be exterminated completely, as long as Science has no control or opportunity to heal inherited or incidentally contracted defects of the human brain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
