<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-10-09">Oct. 9, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">September Report of the Agent of the Aid Society for German Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-10-09">Oct. 9, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">SEPTEMBER REPORT OF THE AGENT OF THE AID SOCIETY FOR GERMAN IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Requests for employment</cell>
     <cell>290</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured employment for</cell>
     <cell>85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters received</cell>
     <cell>48</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters written</cell>
     <cell>55</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located baggage for</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured support through County Agent for</cell>
     <cell>20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured admission to County Hospital and Poorhouse for</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured railroad tickets through County Agent for</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Aided 30 families with $1,295 of the Society's funds.</p>
   <p>Filed one complaint with the Police Court and two complaints before a Justice of the Peace.</p>
   <p>Collected $25 in claims for J. G. Gerber from Castle Gardens of New York.</p>
   <p>In my monthly report for August, I recommended that the Immigration Board <pb facs="5418474_9_1186.jpg" n="2"/>at Castle Gardens, New York, abolish the immigrant trains designed to protect immigrants during the journey from their point of landing to their destination, but my recommendation has not been adopted.</p>
   <p>The employes of the New York railroads, which have leased Castle Gardens from the Board of Immigration, cheat immigrants in various ways. When exchanging the foreign money of immigrants for American money, railroad agents fail to pay the full current exchange value. Often these agents overcharge immigrants for tickets; they charge them the price of second-class tickets, but give them tickets that are accepted only on immigrant trains. It also frequently happens that agents direct immigrants on roundabout routes, and thus force them to spend more time and money than is necessary to get to their destination. Again, agents habitually charge immigrants for excess baggage without issuing a proper receipt, thus forcing the immigrants to pay twice for transportation over some parts of the trip. In many cases, agents also fail to issue receipts for immigrant <pb facs="5418474_9_1187.jpg" n="3"/>freight, causing many delays and difficulties [Translator's note: The rest of this article has been clipped out of the newspaper.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
