<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-05">Jan. 5, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">German Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Statement of Activities During December 1900 and Last Quarter of Past Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-05">Jan. 5, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Statement of Activities During December 1900 and Last Quarter of Past Year</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The administration of the German Society held a regular session yesterday under the leadership of its president, Theo. Brentano.</p>
   <p>Charles Spaeth, business manager, submitted his report for December. During the month, 148 applications for assistance were filed and 143 were considered. Support was given to 93 families with 278 children, and to 50 single persons. This entailed an expenditure of $466.17. In fifteen cases room and board were paid; thirteen tons of coal were distributed among twenty-five parties; shoes were provided in ten cases.</p>
   <p>Membership dues amounted to $125. Mr. Max joined the society, paying <pb facs="5418474_9_0808.jpg" n="2"/>$5 for a one-year membership.</p>
   <p>Employment was found for 234 persons. We received requests from employers for 246 men. We received 258 communications and mailed 263 letters and cards in connection with our employment activities.</p>
   <p>During the last three months, October to December 1900, the German Society helped 195 families and 557 children, and 107 single persons. We supplied 21 pairs of shoes, 46 half-ton loads of coal, paid room and board in 27 cases. Our expense was $1,037.84. Membership contributions during the same period were $706.</p>
   <p>During the last quarter we obtained employment for 864 persons; 831 communications comprising requests for jobs and offers from employers were received, and our list shows that we mailed 933 letters and cards.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0809.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As a result of the many unfortunate strikes which affected certain classes of workers, increased requests were made to our society during this quarter.</p>
   <p>In order to enable us to continue the humanitarian work of allaying suffering among German families, and even enlarging the scope of our endeavors, we urgently implore all financially able German compatriots in Chicago to become affiliated with our organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
