<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-06">Dec. 6, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Uhlich's Orphanage No Better Than Baby Farms.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-06">Dec. 6, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">UHLICH'S ORPHANAGE NO BETTER THAN BABY FARMS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The flight of 11-year old Alfred Bloch from the German-Evangelical Uhlich's Orphanage has disclosed more new facts about the mis-management of this institution.</p>
   <p>If the statements are true which neighbors of this institution and the poor orphans living there, are making - one must admit that this German-Evangelical charitable institution is comparable to the ill famed European baby farms so far as the cruel treatment of the unlucky little ones is concerned.</p>
   <p>The neighbors of the institution complain in unison that the children are being mistreated by the superintendent, Mauermann. Many stated that they had seen children between four and five years of age beaten and thrown on the ground of the garden by a brutal attendant, for the most trifling reasons.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mauermann himself uses a scourge and also a knotted rope to chastise the wards. Almost all of the children of this institution have marks on their faces and bodies as a result of this inhuman physical punishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0333.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not satisfied with that, Mr. Mauermann also lets the children entrusted to him go hungry, as they themselves relate. There is always some reason found for punishing a child for irregularities and in this case it is the result of Mr. Mauermann's economy, which allows his cash register to accumulate profits.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Bradford, principal of the Arnold School across the street where all the children attend classes, verified these statements and said that she had for a long time had the intention of informing the Humane Society about the mismanagement of this institution, endowed and founded by the millionaire, Uhlich, and now under the supervision of a board of directors composed of German-Evangelical pastors of the North Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
