<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-29">Dec. 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Demonstration in Behalf of the Suffering People in Ireland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-29">Dec. 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">DEMONSTRATION IN BEHALF OF THE SUFFERING PEOPLE IN IRELAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Men, women, and children responded to the appeal of the Socialists and staged an overflow protest meeting at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle (Forward Turner Hall) in behalf of the suffering peasants in Ireland. Every available seat was taken, and the gallery was crowded. About a dozen prominent Socialists sat on the stage. On opposite sides of them were the Union Jack and the Socialist banner bearing the words, "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity".</p>
   <p>Nearly all who were present wore their union badges and almost every trade was represented.....[Translator's note: All non-German items are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Paul Grottkau was the only one who spoke in German and he addressed the crowd as follows: "Ireland's history is an uninterrupted record of distress, which can, possibly, only be compared to the tribulations of Poland. England's greatest <pb facs="5418474_9_0978.jpg" n="2"/>disgrace is the subjugation of Ireland, where the people are kept at a low level, physically and mentally, while poverty and superstition aid in intensifying the condition. Their distress is unbearable now, and their call for aid has reached distant lands. The demonstration today is an expression of our sympathy for these oppressed people.</p>
   <p>"What are the Irish demanding? A reduction in land rents and that the government divide the land, so that everyone may own a home. However, I consider this parceling system, this division of land, a retrogressive measure, as is proven by French history. Land is state property, and the principle must prevail that the interests of the state, and of society, are superior to the special interests of the individual.</p>
   <p>"Wherever and whenever states were formed, states maintained the right of expropriation. In the course of time property rights gained importance and this manifested itself in the accumulation of large land holdings. A few prominent individuals acquired huge tracts of land and called themselves 'lords'. Let us <pb facs="5418474_9_0979.jpg" n="3"/>now consider the parceling system: France showed what a calamity this land-dividing-scheme proved to be and how it affected the farmer. He is not able to rise and throw off that yoke of slavery, the mortgage, regardless of incessant labors."</p>
   <p>The speaker then compared Irish and French laborers, and added that whiskey and Christianity were the curse of the Irish workers and farmers. "But now," he continued, "their distress is unbearable and they call for help! Now the clergy declares: 'You must own your home, we must revert to the land parceling system.' But this method will bring the same results; a few rich people will become the owners of land. The earth has passed its stage of primeval fertility, we have no more virgin soil, and when the small renter cannot meet the mortgage payments, then the creditors come and acquire the property. As matters are constituted at present, the Irish must demand that the few land sharks return their holdings to the commonwealth, so that all the farmers can cultivate the soil, improve it, apply modern methods, and fertilize the ground to make it productive <pb facs="5418474_9_0980.jpg" n="4"/>again. The Irish people should not be led astray by the clergy, but should think only of progress, of civilization. The object of this meeting is to inculcate the right ideas and to help the Irish in their efforts. But, if all endeavors prove futile, then let them take recourse to the sword and all liberal-minded people will join them in the name of humanity and justice."</p>
   <p>Chairman Meier announced that the committee would take up a collection now for the oppressed Irish people.....</p>
   <p>While the collection was progressing Bawler read excerpts from Irish history during the last three hundred years....a fearful picture of English tyranny and exploitation.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
