<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-06-02">June 2, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A Word about the German Societies and Their Activities</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Submitted)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-06-02">June 2, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD ABOUT THE GERMAN SOCIETIES AND THEIR ACTIVITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Submitted)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A man of discernment and good judgment who spends an hour in an office where German immigrants are given advice, information, and all conceivable assistance, will fully comprehend the exacting business to which the gentlemen have dedicated themselves.</p>
   <p>Anyone who has never had an opportunity to see the activity of such a German Society at close range (I am speaking at the moment of the German Society of Chicago, although others may have more or less similar obligations) will not be able to understand what a wide range of services the gentlemen perform for immigrants.</p>
   <p>They deal mostly with the lower strata of the German population, which <pb facs="5418474_9_1073.jpg" n="2"/>increases the difficulties of their labor, and, because of the great numbers of immigrants arriving, money and other types of resources are insufficient to provide everyone with the assistance which he feels he should have, but nevertheless one can only express the highest praise for the friendly politeness shown and the readiness to be of service.</p>
   <p>How many thousands of immigrants have found a berth shortly after landing because of the efforts of this or that German Society? How many thousands have been given financial assistance and have been saved from a death of starvation by the intervention of the Society?</p>
   <p>But how few there are, who ever thought of returning the money and advances after succeeding and enjoying better circumstances! Indeed, there are only a handful who really prove grateful and make restitution, and in this way take thought of other unfortunates who are now facing the same conditions which once confronted them!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1074.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We often talk of social problems when we have time. Why not remember those who minister to German immigrants?...</p>
   <p>If ever an institution deserves recognition for its accomplishments in the field of social service, our German Societies certainly should receive it....[Translator's note: The editor added a postscript concurring in the opinion of the contributor and, as it represents virtually a repetition of the article, it has not been translated.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
