<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-01-03">Jan. 3, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">Report of Manager of German Home for Needy, 140 South Union Street (December, 1873)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-01-03">Jan. 3, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF MANAGER OF GERMAN HOME FOR NEEDY, 140 SOUTH UNION STREET (DECEMBER, 1873)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, December 31, 1873 there are 63 persons in the German Home for Needy. During the entire month only 310 persons were admitted to the institution. They received board and lodging. The aggregate time that they spent at the institution was 980 days. Accordingly, the average number of persons who received aid daily was 35.</p>
   <p>Following is a list of inmates classified according to their occupation or profession: 14 cabinetmakers, 104 laborers, 10 bookbinders, 3 printers, 1 cork cutter, 2 blacksmiths, 1 typesetter, 2 tinners, 9 cooks, 5 coopers, 3 locksmiths, 6 farmers, 3 weavers, 3 moulders, 3 upholsterers, 1 metal winder, 4 tailors, 8 bakers, 2 mechanical draftsmen, 4 stewards, 2 coppersmiths, 3 butchers, 7 engineers, 8 artists, 18 bartenders, 1 stoneworker, 4 sailors, 2 cab drivers, 2 cigarmakers, 3 journalists, 5 tanners, 1 Doctor of Philosophy, 3 masons, 3 millers, 2 pharmacists, 1 music teacher, 37 salesmen, 1 clerk, <pb facs="5418474_9_1091.jpg" n="2"/>1 milliner, 1 barber, 1 cobbler, 1 gardener.</p>
   <p>During the past month only one woman was an inmate of the Home, and she remained only three days.</p>
   <p>We received gratis the following furniture, furnishings, and utensils: 32 bedsteads, 23 mattresses, 16 pillows, 28 woolen blankets, 15 quilts, 18 towels, 5 heaters, 2 stoves, 8 tables, 72 chairs, many dishes, and all the kitchen utensils needed at present.</p>
   <p>The institution can give shelter to 300 persons, but until recently we had sleeping quarters for only 75 persons.</p>
   <p>By order of the German Society of Chicago we purchased a closed grocery wagon and a harness for $70, and Dr. Stromberg presented the Home with a horse.</p>
   <p>The outfit will be used to haul meat, bread, and other donated articles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Since the value of the provisions on hand in the institution at present is only about $300, an employee will call at the various places of business to solicit meat, groceries, bread, vegetables, clothing, shoes, coal, etc.</p>
   <p>The donors will record their gifts in a subscription book which the driver of the wagon must present.</p>
   <p>The drug department of the institution is under the supervision of Mr. Emil Dietzsch and his assistant, Mr. M. Muffat, and is well supplied. One hundred and sixty-three prescriptions were compounded for indigent sick people during the month of December. The institution fills only those prescriptions which are written by licensed and competent physicians.</p>
   <p>Cleanliness is evident in all departments, and all work is done by inmates. The latter receive a meal of bread and coffee in the morning, and in the evening soup and meat is served, and vegetables, when they are available.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1093.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Strict rules of hygiene are observed at the Home. Every person is bathed and otherwise thoroughly cleansed upon admission, and if the Home was supplied with clothing to replace dirty garments we could prevent infestation by vermin.</p>
   <p>By order of the German Society of Chicago homeless people will be admitted for only three days, and after that time they must file application for readmission.</p>
   <p>The manager has been authorized to act as special policeman for the institution, and with the assistance of a city policeman who is stationed at the institution from 4 to 10 p. m., he is able to enforce all rules.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>A. L. Forker, Manager,</p>
   <p>C. Knobelsdorff, Chairman of the Executive Board,</p>
   <p>George Schneider, President,</p>
   <p>The German Society of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
