<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-12">Mar. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[How Are German-Americans to Send Aid to Suffering Germany?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-12">Mar. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[HOW ARE GERMAN-AMERICANS TO SEND AID TO SUFFERING GERMANY?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It gives me great satisfaction to learn from Mr. C. A. Koenig's answer to the very timely and appropriate question of Mr. Blumenstengler, that there are still some among the local Germans who are willing to give aid to their needy and suffering fellow men in the old country. I hope that the amount of help will correspond with Mr. Koenig's estimate. I myself doubt it, unless the conscience of local Germans is sufficiently aroused by propaganda and an organization is established to conduct the work efficiently.</p>
   <p>The Friends of German Democracy could serve as a nucleus of such an organization. Owing to their past activity, their loyalty to the United States would not be doubted; and then--some will not like to hear it, but it must be said--they themselves are, to a certain extent, responsible for the present plight of the German nation. They strove to overthrow the Imperial <pb facs="5418474_9_0653.jpg" n="2"/>Government of Germany. Although they undoubtedly did not intend to, yet they did step beyond their object, and helped to bring unutterable misery, misery unparalleled in the history of the human race, upon the people of Germany. Evidently Mr. Koenig considers it to be only natural that the Society of the Friends of German Democracy now has simply gone to sleep. But if anyone has fallen into the water because of my negligence, then I must do something entirely different from going to sleep. The Society ought to make it its new object to alleviate the misery in Germany, and do everything possible to attain this object. Germany needs help now, since its supplies of food, clothing, etc., will soon be exhausted. It cannot exist on promises of future help. It is true that it will be difficult to begin this charitable work at once; but since a state of war with Germany now exists only in name, the difficulties can be only of a technical nature; and the Society of the Friends of German Democracy, if anyone, should be able to remove all difficulties. At all events, it is well worth trying.</p>
   <p>Very respectfully,</p>
   <p>Dr. I.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
