<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Time Has Come</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0594</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0594.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE TIME HAS COME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Mother, is it true that there are countries where children can eat as much as they want?"</p>
   <p>Last night in the Chicago Lincoln Club, during a description of distress in Germany, Miss Jane Addams told an audience that an eight-year-old German child had asked that question, but she did not tell us what the answer was, nor what her own reaction had been. Nor were we told just what impression this childish question made on her audience--what thoughts, emotions, or decisions were prompted by it. But we do know, just the same. Every mother knows, every father knows; in fact, every human being with a sympathetic heart should know. Only a quick comparison of the profound distress in Germany with the still relatively abundant way of living over here--a little shame and remorse--and the decision is made: to give, to help as much as possible!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0595.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The amount that was spontaneously given or subscribed to last night--no arrangements had been made for the acceptance of contributions and pledges--is only a small fraction of the sum which is going to be given by those who had the privilege of listening to Miss Addams and Monsignore Rempe. The amount of money which the many warm-hearted German-Americans and German sympathizers would willingly give can hardly be overestimated.</p>
   <p>The willingness to give is there. The time has come for the harvest, the harvest of dollars from a well-fed Chicago and America to restore the health and strength and to preserve the lives of thousands of starving German and Austrian children, to give these children, who have had to go hungry as long as they can remember, an opportunity to eat their fill so that they can believe that during all those years there really were countries where "children could (always) eat as much as they liked".</p>
   <p>Now to reap the harvest, quickly to gather the quarters and dollars, singly <pb facs="5418474_9_0596.jpg" n="3"/>and by the thousands, and to put them to work for the noble purpose of relieving distress in Germany--this must be done at once! And the job has to be done thoroughly. Who does it or how it is done makes little difference, as long as it is done well, so that every dollar fully benefits those in need.</p>
   <p>The Deutsch-Amerikanische Hilfsgesellschaft (German-American Aid Society) is active and operating favorably, and so are the Austro-Hungarian Aid Society and the German Children's Shoe Relief Fund. In addition, the "old" German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society has resumed its activities and the beginning is auspicious. All these organizations are working toward the same objective, and success for each individual organization means success for the good cause, and therefore success for all. "Competition is the life of trade," as the saying goes. In charity, too, competition may be an incentive and may heighten success. "To march in separate columns and to defeat the enemy together," was supposed to be the formula of the great military strategist Moltke. Since we all--all Americans of German descent--have the same goal, a separate route may also be of value to our cause. But this will only be true providing we march under the same high command of friendly understanding and intelligent <pb facs="5418474_9_0597.jpg" n="4"/>co-operation, to guarantee our mutual support, and to avoid waste of energy.</p>
   <p>The time is here. The chances are excellent. Great success is possible. Those who have organized the various aid societies or who have been put in charge by their trusting fellow citizens are also responsible for the success. It is their duty to conduct and to organize the movement in such a way that the success will be as great as we anticipate. They will have to confer and agree upon ways and means which will satisfy the demands of the general public--demands that personal interests must not play a part, and demands for proof that every dollar is used efficiently, quickly, and exclusively for the benefit of those for whom it is intended.</p>
   <p>It may be difficult to establish such an organization. But the intention to do so is sincere--it has to be in view of the objective to be attained--and the job will be done. In the meantime--it may be a few days, even weeks before the organization gets going--everybody should send his contribution to the society which he prefers. After all it makes little difference to which <pb facs="5418474_9_0598.jpg" n="5"/>organization the money is donated. They are all equally trustworthy; the important issue is that the contributions come in quickly and in generous amounts!</p>
   <p>One dollar given now is worth one hundred given next April or May.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
