<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-21">Jan. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-21">Jan. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The horrible war was ended. Erich, a Rhenish man, an electrician by occupation, had served his fatherland, had fought for years in the trenches, and had been wounded twice. Broken in body and spirit, he still had the courage to marry, after a year. He and his wife Eugenie could help his parents on their small farm, as well as could be done under the trials and strains resulting from the collapse of Germany. Immediately after the birth of their first child, Ursula, in 1920, the family council decided that the young couple should seek a better life in America, as soon as they could save the necessary means.</p>
   <p>Despite great privations, they finally amassed sufficient funds, and with Ursula and Hildegard, who was born in May, 1922, they landed in Chicago in 1925. Fortunately, Erich found work with the Western Electric Company, through the German Society of Chicago. Apparently things were going well. Erich thanked the Society for assisting him in finding permanent employment <pb facs="5418474_9_0480.jpg" n="2"/>and then nothing was heard from him until the Ladies' Aid Society of Saint Paul's Evangelical Church, Fullerton Avenue and Orchard Street, notified the Society that a family living at 3008 North Oakley Avenue was in great need.</p>
   <p>Investigation by the German Society revealed that it was Erich's family, which, had been increased by the birth of another daughter, who was born in May, 1926. Erich, who had worked uninterruptedly, had incurred a disease of the lungs during the last part of 1926, could work only part of the time, and he was permitted to do so because he was very efficient in his trade. However, in January, weakness forced him to stop working. His savings, and the money which his wife, Eugenie, received for doing "odd jobs" while Erich took care of the children, enabled Eugenie, who also was in poor health to provide for the family. When she could earn no more money, the situation became acute. By accident, the Ladies' Aid Society heard of the plight of the family, which was too proud to ask for help, although it was close to death by starvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0481.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Since September, 1927, the German Society contributed $15.00 each month toward the support of the family, had Erich examined at the Chicago Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium, and, when he was declared to be tubercular, provided home treatment for him. When the parents of the couple offered to care for the family, but could not pay for its passage to Germany, or even a part of the cost of transportation, the Society tried to persuade the Government to deport the family. The attempt failed, because Erich and his family had been declared healthy when they arrived in this country, and deportation would be possible only if the American Embassy in Berlin would furnish a written declaration by the German Bureau of Emigration stating that the husband of the family had shown traces of lung trouble when he emigrated. Fortunately, that could be done. A few months prior to his emigration, Erich had been treated at the Berlin Charite for the effects of a gas attack, but had failed to mention this fact in his application to emigrate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0482.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>By the middle of October, matters had progressed to such an extent that the United States authorities could inform Erich that he could leave this country early in November, however, the Government declared that transportation charges would have to be paid for the children who were born in America--and there were two of them, one having been born in September, 1929 while negotiations were going on. What could be done? These two children, American citizens, would either have to be separated from their parents and placed in some local institution, or their fare would have to be paid. Mr. A. C. Schmidt persuaded the Hamburg-American Line to grant a very low rate of fare, and the German Society of Chicago paid one half of the amount, while the other half was furnished by the Immigrants' Protective Association.</p>
   <p>This is but one of many difficult cases in which the German Society has succeeded in assisting a family in need. Now, needy families have no access to such help, because the Society can care only for the severest cases, since its funds are nearly depleted. For this reason, the Society continually asks charitably minded people for financial support. The Abendpost, 225 West <pb facs="5418474_9_0483.jpg" n="5"/>Washington Street, and the Society, 160 North Wells Street, will gratefully receive contributions. Old clothing, too, will be gladly called for. Please write us, or phone Randolph 4037.</p>
   <p>The employment office of the Society received fewer applications for work during November and December, since many of the unemployed applied at the Civil Works Administration. Several of them received employment, but they must wait for their pay. The number of those who were put to work by this national agency was quite large when compared with the number of applicants. One hundred fourteen persons were furnished with employment by our Society. Eighty-five families, in which there were 153 children, received support, seven persons were admitted to private hospitals, eight to the county hospital, two to Oak Forest, one to the "Little Sisters of the Poor," and nine were given free medical attention, medicine, etc., through the offices of the German Society, which spent $780 for these benevolent purposes.</p>
   <p>We thank all donors who responded to our written plea for money at Christmas.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0484.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Unfortunately, only $470.90 was received, and $61.00 of that amount was contributed at the office of the Abendpost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
