<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-12-18">Dec. 18, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Aid Society for German Immigrants</title><title level="a" type="sub">November, 1867</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-12-18">Dec. 18, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE AID SOCIETY FOR GERMAN IMMIGRANTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">November, 1867</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Requests for employment</cell>
     <cell>355</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured employment for</cell>
     <cell>105</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters received</cell>
     <cell>46</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters written</cell>
     <cell>51</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located baggage for</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Families aided by appealing to county agent</cell>
     <cell>22</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured admission to county hospital or county poorhouse for</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured railroad tickets through county agent for</cell>
     <cell>5</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Families aided by expending $114.47 of the Society's funds</cell>
     <cell>30</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Complaints entered with the Immigration Commission in New York</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Complaints filed with the police at Liverpool</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>[Translator's note: The next few paragraphs are omitted in translation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They describe the evils to which immigrants are subject after landing in New York--a topic which has been amply discussed in many of the Society's reports of earlier date.]</p>
   <p>The Bureau of Immigration has heeded public opinion, and has ordered the dismissal of all railroad agents at Castle Gardens who are guilty of fraudulent practices.</p>
   <p>This procedure has now been approved by the courts, which decided that it is the duty of the Bureau to protect immigrants upon landing, that the Bureau has the authority that is necessary to perform this duty, and that nobody could justly demand that the Bureau tolerate certain agents (whose honesty is questionable) at Castle Gardens.</p>
   <p>Thus an important issue has been decided, and we hope that the Bureau of Immigration will not refuse to assume full responsibility for the protection and assistance of all immigrants, not only during the time they must spend <pb facs="5418474_9_1177.jpg" n="3"/>at Castle Gardens, but until they have arrived at their destination in whatever state they intend to settle.</p>
   <p>The time when immigrants could be exploited or robbed is past. As soon as immigrants set foot on American soil they should be treated as American citizens. To that end, repeated requests have been made to the Bureau of Immigration that it institute and enforce the following measures:</p>
   <p>1) Abolish immigrant trains and give all immigrants second class passage on regular express trains.</p>
   <p>2) Make the New York railroad companies which have contracted for the transportation of immigrants responsible for the prompt delivery of immigrants' baggage, and require that the roads engage, at their own expense, and agent recommended by the Bureau of Immigration, an agent who speaks both English and German, and who shall have the duty of providing immigrants with the advice and protection that are necessary for a safe journey to their <pb facs="5418474_9_1178.jpg" n="4"/>ultimate destination.</p>
   <p>3) Insist that railroad employees remain within the bounds of their duty. They should not be permitted to exchange moneys. The Bureau should engage and pay a special man to make such transactions.</p>
   <p>Only such railroads, or railroad agents, as are willing to submit to strict supervision by the Bureau of Immigration should be permitted to operate in Castle Gardens.</p>
   <p>The Bureau of Immigration is now in a position to prescribe to the railroads the conditions under which they may continue to transport immigrants.</p>
   <p>However, not only immigrants who maintain Castle Gardens through payment of poll tax, but also American citizens have the right to demand that a thorough reform in the administration of Castle Gardens be effected immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1179.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On October 24, Mr. Murray, an agent of the New York Central Railroad, collected $22.75 from Mr. H. J. Schultz as a charge for excess weight on four pieces of baggage to be forwarded from New York to Fulton, Iowa, but did not note receipt of payment of that amount on the ticket. Arriving in Chicago on October 29, Mr. Schultz was forced to pay an additional $8.75 on excess baggage, for carrying it from Chicago to Fulton, Iowa.</p>
   <p>At Mr. Schultz's request, I wrote to the Bureau of Immigration, asking that they prevail upon Mr. Murray to refund the excess charges, and was informed that I would have to send a receipt for the payment made to the agent at Chicago.</p>
   <p>Ernst J. Knobelsdorff</p>
   <p>Agent</p>
   <p>Uhlich's Block, Room 20</p>
   <p>The above report was read to the board of directors today, and was approved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1180.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>C. Knobelsdorff, President,</p>
   <p>Max Koerner, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
