<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-14">Dec. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Little Prospect for Success</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-14">Dec. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">LITTLE PROSPECT FOR SUCCESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference for combatting professional crime has adjourned. Many speeches were made and many resolutions passed, but it may be said right now that the tangible results will be quite small indeed. The attorney general ordered the department of justice to institute a sort of clearing house to gather information about professional criminals and turn it over to the proper authorities. This is an innovation which will undoubtedly turn out to be a valuable weapon in the war against crime.</p>
   <p>Then, the traffic in firearms was discussed, and suggestions were heard to surrender the munitions business into the hands of the government. This would, of course, necessitate the passing of a pertinent law. Then, a group of policeman would be trained by the department of justice to hunt criminals.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1253.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The discussion then passed on to the subject of dishonest lawyers, who function as aids and abettors of criminals.</p>
   <p>It is conceivable, and it was to be expected, that the conference would be quite strongly influenced by the events that took place during the hunt for Dillinger and his pals. And so, many a forceful little word was spoken to the effect that policemen and detectives should shoot down, without any ado, professional criminals, and not attempt to arrest them. The thinking person will object to that; but crime will not be effectively fought in this manner.</p>
   <p>The number of desperate criminals, ready at any time to commit murder, is relatively low. It appears to be much larger than it actually is, because the press always prints full reports of their exploits. If all these murdering knaves were shot down, the professional group of criminals, as far as numbers are concerned, would be diminished by a small fraction only. The difficulties as they actually occur are to be looked for elsewhere in this war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1254.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>J. Edgar Hoover, the chief of the detective branch in the department of justice, in his speech advocated the separation of crime from politics. The former secretary of state, Henry J. Stimson, called on judges and attorneys to join in the battle against crime. In these two remarks (sic) lies the key to victory in this war. The police know the professional criminals quite well, and arrest them on every possible occasion. Before, however, they are brought to headquarters, there is already an attorney waiting with a habeas corpus injunction effecting their release.</p>
   <p>One of the worst causes of professional crime lies in the abuse of bail and habeas corpus privileges. If the state's attorney succeeds in getting an indictment from the grand jury, then immediately the abuse of postponement sets in. In some cases, political influence has a hand; in others, the judges simply stick to the law, which permits the defendant too many privileges. If all goes well, the trial comes, and then, perhaps, the sentence. With this, the gruesome act is not yet closed, however, for at this time the many legal loopholes begin enabling the lawyers to appeal their cases, or to</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
