<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-31">Aug. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Untimely Decision</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-31">Aug. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">UNTIMELY DECISION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plan of the Dawes commission has been accepted by the German government, but it is untimely to expect that everything in Germany is "now as of yore." Many months will pass, before its influence will become apparent in the German economic system. We must help the sufferers during the interim. Unemployment and disaster affect the entire German nation. Therefore, continue sending good, fresh, nutricious, strengthening American food to your loved ones, as heretofore.</p>
   <p>The packages of the Central Committee contain carefully selected food stuffs, with the idea in mind to supply products which, due to <pb facs="5418474_9_0531.jpg" n="2"/>their excellence, will bring undernourished bodies quickly to normal. Our packages contain the best food obtainable in the land and are therefore highly welcomed by Germany's unfortunates.</p>
   <p>Those without relatives requiring help in Germany, should donate the cost of a package to the Central Committee for the sake of the destitute in general.</p>
   <p>Packages "A" and "L" will be delivered to the addressee home free of charge. Packages "B," "C," "D," "E," "F," "G," "H," "I," "K," "M," "O," "P," and "R," free to the nearest railroad freight station where addressee lives. In Vienna packages will be delivered free to the warehouses, but in all other parts of Austria, delivery will be free to the depot nearest destination. We guarantee delivery <pb facs="5418474_9_0532.jpg" n="3"/>of every package. Central Committee, Inc. For the Relief of Distress in Germany and Austria. Food Package Department, 247 East 41st Street (Suite 72), New York, N.Y. Orders may be given to the American Welfare Association, 128 North La Salle Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Package "A." Delivered in Germany $4.75; in Austria $6.50. 1 can corned beef, 1 can roast beef, 1 can salmon, 2 cans sliced bacon, 2 cans beef lard, 2 cans baked beans, 1 doz. broth cubes, 2 cans raspberries, strawberries or apricot marmalade, 2 cans condensed milk with sugar, 2 cans evaporated milk without sugar.</p>
   <p>Package "B." Delivered in Germany, $16.50; in Austria $19. [Same items, larger quantities, plus 3 cans ox tail soup, 3 cans Mulligatawney soup, 3 cans vegetable soup.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0533.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Packet "C." Delivered in Germany, $8.25; in Austria $12. 241/2 1bs. wheat flour, 10 1bs. rice, 10 1bs. sugar, 5 1bs.macaroni, 2 1bs. groats, 2 1bs. starch, 2 1bs. sweet chocolate, 2 1bs. coffee, 1 1b. cocoa, 1 1b. tea, 1/4 1b. cinnamon, 1/4 1b. pepper.</p>
   <p>Package "D." Delivered in Germany $6.50; in Austria $9. 48 cans evaporated milk without sugar.</p>
   <p>Package "E." Delivered in Germany $8.10; in Austria $11. 48 cans condensed milk with sugar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
