<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-24">July 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">American Welfare Association for German Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-24">July 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN WELFARE ASSOCIATION FOR GERMAN CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The office of the American Welfare Association will be closed after two o'clock in the afternoon during the hot months of July and August. Therefore, we ask all who intend to send an order for provisions to the proverty-stricken in Germany, to call in the forenoon or send the request by mail, enclosing a personal check.</p>
   <p>The chief of the Registration Office in Dresden-Neustadt confirms the dire distress of the persons herein named and urgently implores some benevolently minded persons to come to their rescue.</p>
   <p>The Liebner family, in Wilschdorf, consisting of three children of compulsory school age and three younger ones, is in utter destitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0537.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The father works only two days a week; the mother is slightly feebleminded. There is no bedding, no underwear, no stockings; only shoes in a sad state of repair. The smallest child is so weak as to require hospital care, but there are no funds for that.</p>
   <p>Miss M., in Klotzsche, has no income whatsoever. Being self-conscious, she cannot face strangers. Great distress.</p>
   <p>Mrs. F., a widow, in Klotzsche, makes her living by renting small rooms. She has two daughters, but it is impossible to find employment. They do house-work but cannot earn enough to buy food. Dire want prevails.</p>
   <p>The family R, in Ottendorf-Okrilla. The father suffers from a serious heart ailment. Of the five children, three are of school age. A seventeen-year-old son and a daughter of fifteen are unemployed. No <pb facs="5418474_9_0538.jpg" n="3"/>linen nor clothing.</p>
   <p>Mrs. and Miss R., in Koetzschenbroda, live only from homework, which provides insufficient funds. Mrs. R. is seventy-four years old and sick, and requires the constant attendance of her daughter. Miss R. suffers from malnutrition; she embroiders all day but earns only enough for bread.</p>
   <p>Two spinister sisters, the Misses K., in Niederloessnitz, both over seventy, manage a rooming house and sold all spare furniture, can not pay the last gas bill; have neither coal nor potatoes.</p>
   <p>Mrs. S., in Koetzschenbroda, and her constantly ailing daughter, have neither coal nor potatoes. Face starvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0539.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Miss D., same locality, above seventy, single, tried to earn a little money by picking berries, but her swollen legs make that impossible.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. M., in Oberloessnitz, an old, childless couple, have neither coal nor potatoes. Mrs. M. is almost blind. Great proverty is to be found here.</p>
   <p>Mrs. E., in Koetzschenbroda, has four children, ranging in ages from nine years to six months. The husband was committed to an insane asylum recently. Because of her many small children, she cannot leave home and work elsewhere. Receives some money from the poor fund, which is not enough for the bare necessities of life. Even bread and potatoes are mostly lacking; the children have no shoes.</p>
   <p>The American Welfare Association, 128 North La Salle Street, Room 47, Telephone Franklin 0339, beseeches you: Help us to give some <pb facs="5418474_9_0540.jpg" n="5"/>support to these unfortunates! The donations may also be sent to Amtshauptmann Dr. Guehery, Dresden-Neustadt, Gross Meissner Str. 15.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
