<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-19">Dec. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal for the Red Cross.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-19">Dec. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL FOR THE RED CROSS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judges George Kersten, Theodore Brentano, Charles M. Foell and Oscar Hebel have issued the following appeal, in regard to the campaign for increasing the membership of the Red Cross Society. The Red Cross is an organization, at the head of which stands the president of the United States, and its management is in the hands of persons, whom he appoints. Their financial statements are examined by officers of our army, and the vouchers so far prove, that the interest on the fund pays the expenses of management, so that fully 100 percent of the fund is used for the purpose for which it is intended.</p>
   <p>The Red Cross does not care for our soldiers in the field only, but also for the families they have left behind. It not only alleviates sickness, need, and hunger here, but also helps the unfortunates over there. Its application is manifold and extends over the whole world. It is one of the world's great organizations for the benefit of humanity, which is acknowledged by all civilized nations of the world.</p>
   <p>We therefore feel, that every American citizen, no matter of what descent should welcome the opportunity to help with this noble work, and through it to show his patriotism and gratefulness to this country of his choice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0666.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this reason, we ask all our fellow citizens to work hand in hand, so that the membership for which the President asks, 15,000,000, should be reached by Christmas. The reports of persons, who in all sections of the city go from house to house, in order to get new members for the Red Cross, have been received at headquarters scantily. This must be attributed to the plan of campaign, which placed the responsibility for the result upon the volunteer workers in the individual districts. In most cases such a worker has to visit only twenty-five houses, with the instruction to win all persons living there for the Red Cross. The reports received, so far, show, that this plan promises to be a positive success and that the total number hoped for will be reached by Christmas Eve.</p>
   <p>In order to promote the Red Cross campaign there will be held a number of neighborhood meetings, every evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
