<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-05-03">May 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">German Society Their Activities in April, Voluntary Contributions Requested.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-05-03">May 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SOCIETY THEIR ACTIVITIES IN APRIL, VOLUNTARY CONTRIBUTIONS REQUESTED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Charles Spaeth, Manager of the German Society of Chicago, reported at the last monthly meetings of the administration-board, about the activity of the society in the month of April, as follows: Assistance received by 168 families with 390 children and 107 single persons. $840.00 were spent for this purpose. In 246 cases board and lodging were granted, employment was secured for 355 persons, of which 250 were placed with farmers. $462.00 were received from members. 22 joined as new members, with a total contribution of $150.00 amd 16 members raised their yearly contribution from $5 to $10. The distress among the laboring population of Chicago, has, in spite of the increased spring activity of the building trade, not much improved, and the demands on the German Society are just as large as before. The cash assistance of last month, exceeded those of April of last year by $520.00, and the membership contributions by almost double, so it seems inevitable, not to touch the capital. The directors and the special committee <pb facs="5418474_9_0800.jpg" n="2"/>for acquiring new members are doing their best to increase the membership, and have, so far acquired about seventy new members, but all this is not sufficient, to meet the demands. The German Society repeatedly appeals to the Germans in Chicago, for co-operation in this noble work of philanthropy and begs for energetic financial assistance from all citizens. The German Society requests all Germans of Chicago, to remit volunteer contributions directly to the Society, 61 La Salle Street.</p>
   <p>They will be gratefully received and used for relief of really suffering, deserving countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
