<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-11">Apr. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Solidarity Is Accentuated between Doctor Bundesen and Doctor Schmidt</title><title level="a" type="sub">Coroner Announces His Resignation as Member of the Chicago Medical Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-14">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-11">Apr. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">SOLIDARITY IS ACCENTUATED BETWEEN DOCTOR BUNDESEN AND DOCTOR SCHMIDT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Coroner Announces His Resignation as Member of The Chicago Medical Association</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hostile attitude shown toward Dr. Louis Ernst Schmidt, the widely known physician and philanthropist, by the Chicago Medical Association has stirred the citizens of Chicago beyond words, and has had immediate consequences of an unpleasant nature.</p>
   <p>As a direct result of the irrevocable decision of the organization Doctor Hermann N. Bundesen, Coroner, and former Health Commissioner, has declared himself on common grounds with Doctor Schmidt, and has therefore chosen to withdraw as a member of the Association.</p>
   <p>Doctor Schmidt's humanitarianism has been profoundly appreciated by Doctor Bundesen, who, in a letter to the Medical Association, revealed the reasons <pb facs="5418474_9_0138.jpg" n="2"/>for his resignation. Therein he denounces the disproportionately high medical cost for the family whose income varies between $1,500 and $5,000 annually. "However," he said, "the clinical charges of hospitals, sanitariums, laboratories, etc. are high in comparison to the physician's fees. Thus, illness must be looked upon as a luxury, too costly for the middle class. However, if sickness does occur, the only alternative would be to ask for credit and to incur debts. But this is not the American way; the American people do not choose to beg."</p>
   <p>Continuing, Doctor Bundesen referred to Dr. M. L. Harris, president of the American Medical Association, the central organization for local medical associations, as having been the originator of the plan for more and bigger hospitals and clinics, the benefit of which should adhere to the citizen regardless of his or her station in life. He has submitted that plan to the Chicago Medical Association.</p>
   <p>As a member of the Supervisory Committee of the Illinois Social Hygiene <pb facs="5418474_9_0139.jpg" n="3"/>League, Doctor Bundesen has repelled all attacks made upon Doctor Schmidt, whom he regards as a man of high ideals, honored throughout the world in professional circles.</p>
   <p>Expressing profound regret over the whole unfortunate affair, the former Commissioner of Health condemned the act of the Medical Association, adding that he no longer could remain a member of that organization. However, in the interests of mankind, he looked forward to the time when the Medical Association would recognize its gross mistake and then take steps to correct it.</p>
   <p>The Rosenwald Foundation, as well as the University of Chicago and various other polyclinics, which were also under the attack of the Medical Association, has, through its manager, Mr. Edward N. Hurley, energetically condemned the stand taken by that organization. Moreover, he has announced that these institutions will continue the benevolent work, regardless of the attacks to which they are subjected by that corporation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0140.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Charles Mayo, director of the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn., expressed his sympathy with Doctor Schmidt, using, however, extreme caution so as not to incur the enmity of the Medical Association.</p>
   <p>Doctor Schmidt, in the meantime, has chosen not to make his future plans known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
