<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-23">Dec. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Resolutions with No Sounding Board</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-23">Dec. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTIONS WITH NO SOUNDING BOARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the conference called by the attorney general for the deliberation on better methods for combating crime, the intimation was made, among other things, to exercise greater caution in conditionally releasing convicts. The proposal was made that the names of all persons should be made public who advocate the release of prisoners from penitentiaries before their term expires, so as to give them a greater sense of responsibility. Today many go too far in their petitions for parole, without having any knowledge about the prisoner and his criminal act. They do this usually just to please a third person, frequently a politician who exercises his influence because he is under some obligation to the prisoner or his family or to one of his good friends, and also because he expects certain services from the parolee or the circle of his friends. There are many shyster lawyers, and even <pb facs="5418474_9_1373.jpg" n="2"/>officers of the court, who pave the way for such people because such work is lucrative to them. In many instances neither police authorities nor the persons interested in the prisoner are notified that a petition for parole has been entered. They at times do not even receive notice that the prisoner has been set free, and instances have been known where the police apprehended such parolees while again engaged in wrong-doing without knowing that political or other influences had succeeded in setting him free.</p>
   <p>Another proposition was that a conditional release be given only in such cases in which a gainful occupation could be found for the prisoner and besides, a strict supervision of the parolee be assured. Any encroachment upon the parole regulations must immediately result in the unconditional revocation of his parole and recommitment into an institution. The same should happen in case a parolee should prove himself unworthy, in one way or another, of the privileges accorded him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1374.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These propositions were agreed upon by the conference in the shape of a few resolutions. Attorney General Homer S. Cummings is quite right when he states that the people may have many or few crimes in the land, just as they wish it. As long as the public submits in all tranquility to be damaged in body or property by persons who have escaped from a penitentiary because of scandalous relations between politics and underworld, just so long even the best-intentioned resolutions will avail them nothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
