<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-12-07">Dec. 7, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-12-07">Dec. 7, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is the annual report of the President of the German Society, William Vocke: "It is a pleasant mission of mine to report the last year as one of the most successful years the society has had. There was a marked increase in membership. The interest in the organization by the German people of Chicago has become more acute. The financial support, extended to our clients, has been more generous and the financial status of the German Society is much more satisfactory now than ever before. The activity of this society's employment agency did not change during the past year, although the anarchistic disturbances of recent years prejudiced the American employer against German labor. They prefer Scandinavian and Irish workingmen, in spite of the fact, that the Germans are generally regarded as the cleverest and the most diligent amongst laborers. Fortunately this prejudice is confined to the city only, for the American farmers still look for help among the Germans, whom they consider most conscientious and expert workers and appreciate their knowledge acquired in the old country. Financial assistance was extended to 246 families and to 221 single persons, which amounted to $1,595.95. The German Society supervises a $13,000 fund and aside from that, the society owns a piece of real estate property valued at $4,000.00, besides the sum of $1,362.85 in the cash register January 1st, 1887.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0886.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The executor for the late Mrs. Louis Hesing handed, according to the will of the deceased, the sum of $500.00 to the treasurer of our society. This donation deserved a special mention, as it is the first large gift since the existence of the society. In tribute to the donor, the managing council of the German Society decided to add this gift to the already established fund and listed it as the Luise Hesing Fund, the interest of which should be used for beneficiary funds. The festival at the Turner Hall, April 17th, for the benefit of this society netted us $727.07. During the year ending November 30th, 1886, 111,696 immigrants arrived in Chicago; 41,635 of whom were Germans, many of them seeking the aid of this society. The German Society, in existence for thirty four years, never felt the need for the erection of a home for immigrants more than it does now, and we call on our compatriots to help and support us in this endeavor. We express our deep appreciation to the Alexandrian Brothers Hospital, Michael Reese Hospital, and the German Hospital, for their kind co-operation."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
