<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-03">Aug. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II F (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-03">Aug. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following real-estate transfers, amounting to $1,000 or more, have been officially recorded:</p>
   <p>Mary Garrity to Carl Steinbach: Addison Street, southwest corner of Lincoln Street, north front, 48 1/2 by 124 feet. Price, $3,200.</p>
   <p>T. C. Schaffner to Peter J. Claussen: Alta Vista Terrace, 26 feet north of Grace Street, 24 by 140 feet. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>James Waters et. al. to Charles O. Lippert: North Ashland Avenue, 150 feet north of Waveland Avenue, east front, 25 by 124 feet. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>Lizette Mueller to Ludwig D. Janz: Bradley Place, 92 feet west of Lincoln Street, north front, 30 by 124 feet. Price, $6,700.</p>
   <p>Julia Kopf to Jakob G. Kiesgen: North Hermitage Avenue, southeast corner of <pb facs="5418474_9_1573.jpg" n="2"/>Grace Street, west front, 49 by 108 feet. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Agatha Liebig to Elizabeth Hodes: Paulina Street, 141 feet south of Addison Street, west front, 25 by 125 feet. Price, $5,900.</p>
   <p>L. N. Daleiden to August H. Ludwig: Racine Avenue, 120 feet south of Barry Avenue, east front, 24 by 125 feet. Price, $3,900.</p>
   <p>Sophie Gehrs. to Sophie L. Gehrs: Wellington Avenue, 50 feet east of Herndon Street, south front, 25 by 124 feet. Price, $3,200.</p>
   <p>Charles Stogren to Henry Marmann: West Cuyler Avenue, 272 feet east of North 53rd [Avenue], north front, 30 by 125 feet. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <p>William Hellmuth to Felix Kuberski: Quinn Street, 500 feet south of West 29th Street, east front, 25 by 115 feet. Price, $2,300.</p>
   <p>Francis C. Daily et. al. to Charles Sorge: Wentworth Avenue, 100 feet south of <pb facs="5418474_9_1574.jpg" n="3"/>31st Street, west front, 25 by 120 feet. Price, $5,740.</p>
   <p>Arthur Melker to Jozef Bodizniak: Coles Avenue, 223 feet north of 82nd Street, north front, 25 by 125 feet. Price, $1,625.</p>
   <p>Charles M. Bruff to Rudolph Kaufmann: Coles Avenue, 387 feet north of Cheltenham Place, west front, 75 by 190 feet. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Mary W. A. Lesch to Luther G. Bass: Jefferson Avenue, 50 feet south of 52nd Street, west front, 25 by 120 feet. Price, $3,700.</p>
   <p>Richard B. Messner to Maria Hammel: Prairie Avenue, 198 feet north of 73rd Street, east front, 662/3 by 159 feet. Price, $1,300.</p>
   <p>David Smith to Adolf R. Soderbeck: Saginaw Avenue, 97 feet south of 78th Street, west front, 331/3 by 159 feet. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <p>Georg Rosen to Solomon S. Graff: Ashland Avenue, 147 feet north of 66th Street, <pb facs="5418474_9_1575.jpg" n="4"/>east front, 156 by 123 feet, and other property. Price, $7,500.</p>
   <p>Peter Donahue to John Teschler: West 66th Place, 136 feet east of South 40th Avenue, north front, 116 by 124 feet. Price, $1,850.</p>
   <p>John H. Bach to Frank Kossowski: Julian Street, 269 feet west of Ashland Avenue, south front, 24 by 100 feet. Price, $2,875.</p>
   <p>John Rossbach to Lafayette Hopkins: State Street, 105 feet north of Attrill Street, southwest front, 44 by 200 feet. Price, $1,500.</p>
   <p>Pauline Wagner to Walentu Gusek: West 19th Street, 150 feet west of Oakley Avenue, south front, 25 by 125 feet. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>Louis Bucholtz to Hyman Brown: Hastings Street, southeast corner of Laflin Street, north front, 46 by 124 feet. Price, $9,000.</p>
   <p>Louise D. Kulb to Louis Herring: West 21st Street, 312 feet west of Hoyne <pb facs="5418474_9_1576.jpg" n="5"/>Avenue, north front, 24 by 125 feet. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Maurice Flynn to Nathan Alters: Spaulding Avenue, 225 feet south of 15th Street, west front, 25 by 125 feet. Price, $8,150.</p>
   <p>Max E. Weinstock to Ida Privulsky: Douglas Boulevard, 106 feet west of Lawn-dale Avenue, south front, 25 by 150 feet. Price, $10,000.</p>
   <p>Ernst Adler to Michael Jochimiec: 15th Street, 168 feet east of Wood Street, south front, 24 by 124 feet. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Anton Heil to Stanislaus Preisler: West 20th Place, 75 feet east of Fisk Street, south front, 25 by 100 feet. Price, $3,175.</p>
   <p>Harris Wolf to Isador Feierstein: Washburn Avenue, 240 feet east of Paulina Street, north front, 24 by 125 feet. Price, $4,600.</p>
   <p>John Boland to Joseph Cali: Townsend Street, 156 feet north of Hobbie Street, <pb facs="5418474_9_1577.jpg" n="6"/>east front, 52 by 100 feet. Price, $11,000.</p>
   <p>Joseph T. Tenesse to Matthew Neumayer: Cornelia Avenue, 225 feet east of Lincoln Avenue, south front, 18 by 124 feet. Price, $3,050.</p>
   <p>Thomas Town to Magdaline Niehaus: Edgewater Avenue, 400 feet west of Southport Avenue, south front, 50 by 114 feet. Price, $9,100.</p>
   <p>Charles Wehrheim to Charles Hallmann: Gordon Avenue, 204 feet west of Southport Avenue, south front, 50 by 125 feet. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>Joseph S. Durand to Robert Hankel: Paulina Street, 266 feet south of Addison Street, west front, 30 by 125 feet. Price, $3,400.</p>
   <p>Charles Lenz to Georg Lipper: Eastwood Avenue, 239 feet west of Campbell Avenue, north front, 30 by 120 feet. Price, $4,900.</p>
   <p>August H. Spiering to Max Moeckel: 45th Court, 50 feet north of Cornelia Avenue, <pb facs="5418474_9_1578.jpg" n="7"/>west front, 37 1/2 by 126 feet. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>Georg J. Handtmann to Jan Vittel: West 13th Place, 225 feet west of Union Street, south front, 241 by 10 feet [sic]. Price, $4,375.</p>
   <p>August Koenig to Marie Morarer: Ruble Street, 152 feet north of 18th Street, south front, 25 by 100 feet. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>Ernst Quastenberg to Walenty Gruszcynsky: West 22nd Place, 381 feet east of Marshall Boulevard, south front, 24 by 124 feet. Price, $3,050.</p>
   <p>Katherina Tauber to Herman Loges: Leamington Avenue, 92 feet south of Ohio Street, east front, 27 by 125 feet. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Frank B. Reed to Henry Drossel: Huron Street, 151 feet east of Lavergne Avenue, north front, 31 by 120 feet. Price, $5,700.</p>
   <p>Henry W. Austin to George Siegmund: Lexington Street, 169 feet east of Central Avenue, north front, 54 by 124 feet. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1579.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>John P. Boesen to Edward Wareham: West 21st Place, 165 feet east of Lockwood Avenue, south front, 25 by 124 feet. Price, $2,600.</p>
   <p>Bernhardt Wilhelm to Catherine Loughey: West Eastwood Avenue, 269 feet east of Albany Avenue, south front, 30 by 136 feet, Price, $5,700.</p>
   <p>Charles Pearson to Samuel Ahrens: Montrose Avenue, southwest corner of North 49th Avenue, north front, 50 by 129 feet. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Oscar Heinemann to Chicago Savings Bank and Trust Company: Armitage Avenue, southwest corner of Fairfield Avenue, north front, 99 by 119 feet. Price, $70,000.</p>
   <p>Adolf Christensen to Otto Christensen: Humboldt Boulevard, 90 feet south of Cortland Street, west front, 30 by 152 feet. Price, $5,200.</p>
   <p>Hermann Brand to Crillie Steppner: LeMoyne Street, northwest corner of Spaulding Avenue, south front, 50 by 124 feet. Price, $22,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1580.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Bethel Evangelical Lutheran Church to the West Side Hungarian Reformed Church: Carroll Avenue, 341 feet east of 44th Avenue, 50 feet to the alley. Price, $2,400.</p>
   <p>Charles Moriarity to Frank Liess: 61st Street, southeast corner of Laflin Street, north front, 95 by 125 feet. Price, $4,500.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
