<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-06">Apr. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Widow Wants Husband's Murderer Executed Life Imprisonment Is Much Too Good for Him, Says Mrs. Fuchs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_1290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_1290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-06">Apr. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">WIDOW WANTS HUSBAND'S MURDERER EXECUTED Life Imprisonment Is Much Too Good For Him, Says Mrs. Fuchs</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"If I only had the opportunity, I would do away with him. He murdered my husband in cold blood and ought to expiate for his crime with his own life".</p>
   <p>With these words, Mrs. Wilhelmine Fuchs answered today to the question asked her by the superior judge of the criminal court, Thomas Lynch. His question was whether she would be satisfied if the 31-year-old Everett Jackson Giese pleaded guilty and was sentenced to life imprisonment.</p>
   <p>On January 13, Giese attacked her husband, William Fuchs, a butcher, in his store at 3535 North Racine Avenue and shot him dead when the latter attempted to resist robbery. The hoodlum then fled in an automobile, but in his haste he lost his hat, which was to be his undoing. He set out in search of the hat, and dared to come to the vicinity of where he had committed the murder. There he fell into the arms of one of the many policemen who had been summoned <pb facs="5418474_9_1291.jpg" n="2"/>in the meantime.</p>
   <p>Giese fought with distinction in the world war. He was wounded and on a few occasions he was stunned by poisonous gases. His defenders, the lawyers Milton D. and W. W. Smith, are of the opinion that their client's nerves, owing to drum and artillery fire, have suffered considerably, and that the accused is not responsible for that reason. Giese was ready to plead guilty of murder and to go to prison for life, But his attorneys would not permit it, following the widow's plea for the death penalty. They are convinced that their client is not normal mentally, and want to try to save him from heavy punishment by means of an insanity procedure. Judge Lynch granted a postponement of the trial until April 26, to give the attorneys a chance to summon a number of witnesses whom they want to question.</p>
   <p>Giese had come in conflict with the law once before. Several years ago he was sentenced to prison in Ohio for housebreaking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
