<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-20">Dec. 20, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">German Womens Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_9_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_9_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-20">Dec. 20, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN WOMENS CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>M. Klare's hall N. Clark St., Tuesday, Dec. 28 a distribution of Xmas gifts for poor children by the German Women's Club, will take place. The children will first be treated with coffee and cakes. Guests to this public charity enterprise can take part in the food for 25 cents. It is more than desirable, that visitors bring along a quantity of different kinds of foods, to add to the insufficient supplies of the women's club.</p>
   <p>We have repeatedly protested against these publicity making charities, where the principal object is show, but to our regret without success. the gifts really do not come from the German Women's club, who only take the credit at the expense of others. Instead of the rich ladies dipping into their own pockets, they prefer to ask the Press, favorable to their undertaking, for support; clothes dealers, toy, and book shops are pressed till the necessary supply of secondhand merchandise is together. If this is still insufficient, a few musicians and artists are chosen, who will be flattered and persuaded to give their services free <pb facs="5418474_9_0970.jpg" n="2"/>for the good cause. The visitors will have to pay an entrance fee and the German Womens Club get the laurels. With the satisfaction of having a share in the gratifying tears of the child, who has been fed and given presents, the lady of the Club goes to bed, pleased that her own purse is still intact and they act according to the words of God: "The left hand does not know, what the right one is doing."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
