<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-04">Nov. 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Escapes the Republican Landslide</title><title level="a" type="sub">Our Countryman, Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, Re-elected</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0866.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-04">Nov. 4, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ESCAPES THE REPUBLICAN LANDSLIDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Our Countryman, Congressman Adolph J. Sabath, Re-elected</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although at the last election Republican candidates for presidential, state, and county offices were given a great majority of votes in all of the Chicago wards, nevertheless three Democratic candidates escaped the Republican landslide. Two of them were elected in districts preponderantly inhabited by Czechoslovaks, that is, the Fourth and Fifth Congressional Districts. The men elected were the present Congressmen John W. Rainey and Adolph J. Sabath.</p>
   <p>In our state and in the United States in general, with the probable exception of the solidly Democratic South, there were very few Democrats who escaped the astonishing Republican victory. One of these few Democrats who are elected is Congressman Adolph J. Sabath. Yesterday it was reported that even he may be defeated, but his friends were hopeful and, when the final report came in, they rejoiced in the knowledge that his victory was assured. The <pb facs="5418478_8_0867.jpg" n="2"/>final report shows that Congressman Sabath received 13,307 votes, while his opponent, Mr. Gartenstein, received 12,706 votes, which gives our Congressman a majority of 601 votes. This, of course, is not as large a majority as voters of the Fifth Congressional District usually give to Congressman Sabath, but considering that every Democratic candidate was buried under the Republican landslide, the victory of our Congressman is that much more remarkable. It is proof of the general confidence he enjoys among citizens, which not even the general desire to elect Harding as our president could destroy.</p>
   <p>It is apparent that a great number of voters did not split the ballot, did not take into consideration the individual candidates, but voted a straight Republican ticket; and as a result, even such an excellent candidate as Congressman James McAndrews was defeated by a great majority. But Mr. Sabath was supported by many citizens who, recognizing his meritorious work during the long term of his congressional activities, re-elected him.</p>
   <p>Congressman Sabath was elected the first time as a member of the Sixtieth</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
