<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-14">March 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The New Immigration Law.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-14">March 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW IMMIGRATION LAW.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.4 - The new immigration bill, about which there has been so much debate in both houses of Congress, is now about three-quarters complete. The remainder will probably be finished by the next session of Congress. The entire matter could have been settled before now had it not been for the fight on some parts of the bill. The Senate at the last moment mitigated some of the most severe restrictions of the bill and the joint committee approved these changes. However, a decision on the entire matter could not be arrived at and it was necessary to set it aside for the future. Several of the original strict provisions of the bill were left in it by both Houses of Congress. These are concerned chiefly with the return of persons afflicted with epilepsy or insanity, also those, who entered the country in an unlawful manner, and anarchists. In the case of the former, it is ordered that they may be deported if it is proven they were afflicted within five years previous to their arrival here the same may be done with immigrants who within two years after arrival become dependent upon the public welfare. This two year period also applies to anarchists and all newcomers who during <pb facs="5418478_8_0100.jpg" n="2"/>that period advocate the overthrow of the government by force or the assassination of public officials.</p>
   <p>The provisions given here are the strictest of the new immigration bill. Otherwise there are included in the bill various provisions which will only be of benefit to the immigrant, because the jurisdiction of the immigration inquisitors of Ellis Island, whose administration especially of late has become so famous, will be limited. The Commissioner of Immigration in New York City did not wait for the new law to become effective, but introduced various reforms for the benefit of immigrants, who in the future will not be subject to the good will of any case. It was high time, that something of the kind happened, for it was simply scandalous the way the poor immigrant was handled. In the future it will not be possible to send anyone back to where they came from, except for good reasons. Should a three member committee decide on deportation of the immigrant, he can appeal to the Appellate Department of the Immigration Commission on the Island, and should its decision be unfavorable the immigrant may appeal to Washington. In that manner it is expected that the rejected immigrant will receive justice. This is the most <pb facs="5418478_8_0101.jpg" n="3"/>important change which was made in behalf of immigrants. Also there were several minor changes made for the improvement of the present system on the Island, and more are to follow. What has finally been accomplished, insofar as immigrants are concerned, is that they will be treated with more justice in the future and only those will be deported who cannot be permitted to enter under any consideration according to the Immigration Laws.</p>
   <p>On the whole conditions on the Island should be much better in the future. However, it was really time something was done in regards to improving existing conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
