<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-31">Mar. 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Vladislav Florjansky.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-31">Mar. 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">MR. VLADISLAV FLORJANSKY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2, col. 3.. During his tour of the United States this noted Bohemian operatic tenor honored us by stopping in Chicago. Mr. V. Florjansky is a former director of several European operas, gaining most of his fame in Prague, Czechoslovakia. In Prague he had the reputation of an excellent operatic singer. He has a large repertoire, consisting of about seventy operas. His ability was soon recognized by the largest opera houses of Europe which offered him attractive contracts, but Mr. V. Florjansky always gave preference to his own people.</p>
   <p>Now we find this artist on a concert tour of America. On his way to Chicago he has given Bohemian concerts in New York, Baltimore, Pittsburg, Cleveland, Buffalo, Detroit, Cedar Rapids and many other eastern cities. His concerts were so well liked in these cities that he had to promise to repeat them on his way back east.</p>
   <p>Mr. V. Florjansky is accompanied by Mr. F. Veselsky, a young but very accomplished pianist. Mr. F. Veselsky is a student of the Prague Conservatory and also studied piano in Vienna under the guidance of Professor Gruenfeld. Although he is young he has already gained fame during his tour of Czechoslovakia and England. Now he and Mr. V. Florjansky are rapidly winning acclaim for <pb facs="5418478_8_0808.jpg" n="2"/>their concerts in America.</p>
   <p>These two Bohemian artists will give their Chicago concert on April 7, 1907, at the Czechoslovak-American Hall. It is expected that every Chicago Bohemian will take the opportunity to hear these celebrated artists, especially the chance to hear the wonderful voice of Mr. V. Florjansky. The best way to show our gratitude would be to fill the hall to capacity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
