<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-22">Jan. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">New Attack of Foes of Immigration Repulsed</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada and Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar Join in Protest against Bill Giving European Governments Control of Immigration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-22">Jan. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NEW ATTACK OF FOES OF IMMIGRATION REPULSED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada and Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar Join in Protest against Bill Giving European Governments Control of Immigration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the efforts of Senators LaFollette, O'Gorman, Stone, and others, the so-called "conference bill," which is a compromise between the Senate and the House on the Burnett-Dillingham Bill aimed at the restriction of immigration, was defeated in Washington last Monday. The bill has been returned to conference because of the Senate's protest against the article concerning the immigrant's good reputation.</p>
   <p>The adoption of this article would have made it necessary for immigrants from countries where certificates of good repute are issued to emigrants to present their certificates upon arrival in America. Apparently, this article was directed against members of such societies as the Black Hand and Camorra <pb facs="5418478_8_0041.jpg" n="2"/>but it would soon have become a welcome means to all European governments desirous to gain control over their emigrants. In Austria, for instance, where it is a crime to evade military service by emigrating from the country, all that would be necessary to prevent young men from emigrating to the United States, would be to pass a law providing for the issuance of certificates of good repute. Obviously, because a certificate of good repute would not be issued to a political criminal, this bill would have provided the Austrian government with a powerful weapon, and made of the American Government an efficient police force for Austria.</p>
   <p>This inhuman, un-American bill, which would, in effect, completely stop emigration from Russia by giving the Czar's government complete control thereof, has stirred all who have a sense of right and justice. The senators from states with a large population of immigrants have therefore received a great number of telegrams urging them to prevent the passing of the bill.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0042.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) has sent to both Senator Cullom of Illinois and Senator LaFollette of Wisconsin the following telegram: "The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) urgently requests you to do all that is in your power to prevent the passage of the vicious conference bill on immigration. The bill is un-American, it has no good purpose, and is aimed at aiding certain European countries in the suppression of their subjects.</p>
   <p>"E. St. Vraz, President"</p>
   <p>Another telegram sent to both of these senators reads: "Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (the Bohemian-American Press Bureau) requests you to oppose vigorously conference bill article requiring the presentation of certificates of good repute. Its passage would endanger the liberty of American people. We protest most emphatically against such laws and shall appreciate your intervention.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0043.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"J. F. Stepina, President"</p>
   <p>As we said before, it was only because of the article on the certificates that the bill was defeated. Both organizations will express their thanks to those senators who voted against the bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
