<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-05">May 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Ceskoslovenska Americka Obchodni Vyprava En Route to Zechoslovakia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-05">May 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKOSLOVENSKA AMERICKA OBCHODNI VYPRAVA EN ROUTE TO ZECHOSLOVAKIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The nucleus of the Ceskoslovenska Americka Obchodni Vyprava (Czechoslovak-American Commercial Expedition) left Chicago yesterday at 10 P. M. from Dearborn Station. It consisted of more than two hundred individuals. The local Ceskoslovenska Obchodni Komora (Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce) sent its delegates to the railroad station to bid them adieu.</p>
   <p>Among those who accompanied the group of men, who left for the old homeland, were Reverend Dr. Vaclav Vanek, (who is the secretary of the Expedition), Mr. V. L. Rezabek, and Mr. Karel Vesely. The train which carried the members of the Expedition was tastefully decorated with American and Czechoslovak flags.....Among those who came to bid bon voyage to the departing countrymen was the local Czechoslovak consul, Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, and several members of the consular staff.....The expedition will arrive in <pb facs="5418478_8_0168.jpg" n="2"/>Prague on May 18, 1922. Many prominent American Czechoslovaks are among those who left here, and their names are already well known in Czechoslovakia, that is, from the time of our liberating movement. All of them, however, are plain citizens, hearty people, good patriots, and, as we are wont to call them here, "self-made men". Most of them by their abilities, their industry, and economy have achieved their successes in life, and despite the fact that they look forward to the moment when they will again look upon their native land, now liberated and independent, they would rather forego all official welcome and the elaborate amenities associated with it. After all, they go to inspect and to study industrial and commercial concerns, spas, country estates, etc., and do not have any desire to look at the bunting with which the buildings in Prague will be adorned. Their idea is to enter into commercial agreements and to invest their money in some profitable enterprise either on their own account or on behalf of their business friends at home in America. The purpose of many of these men is to make business contacts, and their long experience leads them to believe that they can establish a lively trade between their old homeland and their <pb facs="5418478_8_0169.jpg" n="3"/>new one. Some of them intend even to remain in Czechoslovakia should conditions make it profitable, and to purchase properties there.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow we shall publish a complete list of the members of the Expedition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
