<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-02">June 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Our "Neutral" Youth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-02">June 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OUR "NEUTRAL" YOUTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The other day, at the meeting called by the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) in the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Hall, we saw very many of our men and women, young and old; but our youth, the young people born in this country, appeared to be missing. Those who were present were almost entirely our immigrants; some of them may have been here for very many years, but nevertheless they were born and at least partly reared in the old country.</p>
   <p>The indifference of our youth, the children of Bohemian parents, is all the more discouraging and regrettable because we see German and Polish youths and others born here forming one front with the immigrants of their various races. Our young men have even been heard to say such things as:</p>
   <p>"I am an American; I am a neutral. What do I care about the independence of <pb facs="5418478_8_0569.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemia?" Sentences in quotes are in English in the original.]</p>
   <p>Such language used by a young man reared by a Bohemian mother is bound to hurt. It is not worthy of an American or of a Bohemian. Everybody who claims to be a good American should burn with the love of liberty, should defend liberty not only here in America but everywhere, else, should do all he can to help secure liberty for other nations, and should be an enemy of tyrants and oppressors, no matter where they may be. But first of all, he should help to secure liberty for the nation whose son he is, the nation to which his parents were or are native. Would such a "neutral" not be proud to say that he is derived of a free nation instead of admitting, as he now must do, that the country in which his parents were cradled is subject to foreign rule. If such "neutrals" are impervious to the appeal of anything idealistic, they should at least have sufficient personal pride, enough egotism, to feel that they ought to help in the liberation of Bohemia, if for no other reason than their own personal gratification.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
