<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Protagonist of Personal Liberty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0901</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0901.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A PROTAGONIST OF PERSONAL LIBERTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of our outstanding workers in the political field is Mr. John Toman, alderman of the Thirty-fourth Ward, whose interests he is representing with pronounced success for the third time. His right to the title of "outstanding worker" is derived not only from activities in the city hall and within his ward, but also from the fearless manner in which he has always defended the right to personal liberty against the attacks that are made by prohibitionist elements. There has not been one single attack launched against personal liberty, and the saloon business in particular, without Toman's instantly countering it with a telling blow which invariable stultifies the designs of the "drys". The followers of the unsound reforms know this well; they cannot help remembering it--but so do Toman's many friends.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Toman's reliability and efficiency have been given recognition by the city <pb facs="5418478_8_0902.jpg" n="2"/>hall. He was appointed member of the license committee, the committees on schools, gas, oil, electricity, transportation, and finance. In 1914 he became a member of the committee which decides upon the appointment of committees.</p>
   <p>In these various capacities the alderman never missed the opportunity to oppose measures by which generally undesirable obligations would have been shoved upon the shoulders of his own ward. There is a typical case which is still vivid in the memory of many. In that instance the Thirty-fourth Ward was to be blessed with an incinerating plant. It cost Alderman Toman and the followers of his party extreme efforts to have that plan changed. Another time Mr. Toman had to exert his utmost influence to prevent the building of an annex for smallpox patients to the hospital in his ward. A new building was erected, not in his ward, but in a more suitable location.</p>
   <p>Wherever there is anything to be gained for his ward, Mr. Toman is in the foreground. The remarkable improvement in the street lighting of his ward is due to his work. He is particularly watchful now, while the proposal for a new <pb facs="5418478_8_0903.jpg" n="3"/>schoolhouse is at issue. He is ever ready for action. This was demonstrated recently by the construction of the Herzel School on 15th Street and Lawndale Avenue, and the school on 18th Street and Keeler Avenue which is to be built soon. Small parks and playgrounds adjacent to schools in his ward were laid out chiefly through his influence. When he began his first term there was only one playgroung in his ward; several have been installed since.</p>
   <p>Alderman Toman set as a goal for himself the improvement of the pavements on 22nd Street and on Crawford Avenue. He carried out this plan just as he did others for better transportation, sewers, and small bridges. He saved money for the taxpapers by insisting upon a twenty-five per cent rebate on taxes which were paid immediately.</p>
   <p>An account of Alderman Toman's activities and achievements would be incomplete without an outline of his personal characteristics. He is always willing to help without asking many questions. At the same time he is vigorous and knows how to attain his aims.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0904.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is hardly one person in the city hall, whether in the council or offices, who would not consider Alderman Toman a friend, even though political or private opinions may differ. The alderman is of diplomatic timber. He knows how to win his point--sometimes by a sharp word--but he also knows how to soothe the ire of the recipient of the blow, and thus establish amicable relations again. A timely, good-natured joke, applied then and there is the medium. This trait of character is conspicuous in his private life also, and has won him innumerable friends.</p>
   <p>Mr. Toman was born in 1876 in Cerhonice, near the town of Pisek, Bohemia. He came to the United States with his parents when he was only six years of age.</p>
   <p>The family settled in a predominantly Czech district along De Koven Street, and the children went to school there. After graduation, young Toman began to work in a printer's shop. Soon he found a better position in the Chicago Public Library. That was in the year 1890, and he remained there fully twenty-two years, when his many friends urged him to seek the nomination for <pb facs="5418478_8_0905.jpg" n="5"/>the office of alderman. He became a candidate, was elected in the Thirty-fourth Ward, and immediately began to do what few aldermen are wont to do, i. e., familiarize himself with the conditions of his office and the agenda pertaining thereto. In fair recognition and appreciation of his zeal, the voters re-elected him for a second term with an astonishing majority. The number of votes cast for Toman for the third term reached a sum unparalleled in the history of municipal elections.</p>
   <p>The alderman shares his successes with his friends and his family. He devotes his leisure time to his wife, Mrs. Bertha Toman, Andrew, a son, and Irene and Lucille, daughters. They all live at 4141 West 21st Place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
