<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-08">Jan. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An American Commercial Expedition</title><title level="a" type="sub">Join This Expedition as Soon as Possible</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-08">Jan. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN AMERICAN COMMERCIAL EXPEDITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Join This Expedition As Soon As Possible</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee of the American Commercial Expedition held a meeting on December 5 under the chairmanship of Jan K. Valha in the restaurant of A. Schnabl on West 26th Street. The secretary read a list of many new participants. The second-class cabins having two bunks have almost all been reserved. Those who wish to take part in this expedition should communicate as soon as possible with the undersigned. Let it be remembered that this venture is an American Commercial Expedition, the prime intent of which is the establishment of commercial, industrial, and agricultural contacts with Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <p>The steamship "George Washington," which will transport the members of the Expedition, will leave New York on May 6 and will go to Bremen. The committee could secure only two hundred and fifty second-class cabins.....The down payment on such a cabin is twenty-five dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the meeting of the committee, a letter was read from the Svaz Hotelieru v Republice Ceskoslovenske (Hotel Owners' Union of the Czechoslovak Republic), which is located in Prague. This organization, which assumes all responsibility for the quartering of the members of the expedition, will do so not only in Prague proper, but also in the provinces. First-class hotels will make a charge of thirty to thirty-five Czechoslovakian crowns per room having one bed, while the charge in second-grade hotels will be from sixteen to twenty-two crowns. The Prazska Uverni Banka (Prague Credit Bank) writes that it will be glad to supply any kind of information to all those who would like to establish a business relationship. Other groups and organizations in Prague will show similar consideration to the members of the Expedition.</p>
   <p>The first stop of our party will be New York, then Bremen, and then Prague. From Bremen to Prague there will be a special train.....The committee consists of the following trustworthy gentlemen: Messrs. John K. Valha, president; Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary; Josef Dusek, treasurer; Anton J. Cermak, <pb facs="5418478_8_0196.jpg" n="3"/>who is in charge of special trains; Vaclav L. Rezabek, representative of the press committee; and Karel Vesely, who has the responsibility of dealing with the commercial and agricultural organizations of Czechoslovakia. All requests should be accompanied by checks or money orders made out to Joseph Dusek, treasurer, and should be mailed to Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary, 2324 South Central Park Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
