<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-20">July 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Conference of American Czechoslovakians and the Officials of the Czechoslovakian Government at Prague</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-20">July 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A CONFERENCE OF AMERICAN CZECHOSLOVAKIANS AND THE OFFICIALS OF THE CZECHOSLOVAKIAN GOVERNMENT AT PRAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: This meeting, which took place in the offices of the Narodni Rada Ceskoslovenska (Czechoslovakian national council) on Masarykovo Nabrezi (Masaryk's Quay) in Prague on Wednesday, July 5, 1922, consisted of Czech leaders from the various cities of the United States; among them were several representatives from Chicago. The underlying idea was the stabilization of the then newly formed republic, particularly its economic life and its relations to the United States, especially as regards commerce and industry. Since most of the material refers to matters not directly bearing upon the life and activities of the Chicago Czechs, only one or two passages are translated here which reflect the attitudes of the economic and social leaders of the Czechs of Chicago. Thus Mr. John A. Sokol, who is a successful wholesale tea and coffee merchant here, said:]</p>
   <p>"The economic question is basic for the republic [of Czechoslovakia]. We have worked for four years, but the results are meager. What is needed is a greater <pb facs="5418478_8_0140.jpg" n="2"/>confidence on the part of America in the ability of the Czech businessmen to meet their contracts. This is of utmost importance. Your people are good and honest, but when some of them attempted to launch enterprises they encountered obstacles which were put in their path by their own government. We Americans are always ready to work for an ideal, but when we see these political (governmental) hindrances, we stop. In the future, America will be the only country which can be considered dependable. She will be your best friend politically, as well as economically. Show us that you are serious; it all depends on you..... [First of all] develop your sample rooms in which your goods are to be exhibited. These rooms can be located in one building, and can be rented by the merchants and industrialists for a whole year. Also you need modern hotels here. The future of the Czechoslovakian republic will depend on the confidence of the foreign countries."</p>
   <p>Mr. Karel Vesely, a Chicago attorney, and another member of the delegation, thought that Czechoslovakia had made a mistake by instituting laws which are alien to Czechoslovakian culture. "This should be changed. You ought to enact <pb facs="5418478_8_0141.jpg" n="3"/>laws which would make it possible for American businessmen to obtain import and export permits. This is a governmental function, but instead, you have invested certain individuals with the authority to regulate trade....."</p>
   <p>Reverend Vaclav Vanek, referring to the critical opinions of some of the members of the delegation, said: "We are in a family circle here, and, therefore, in spite of the criticisms, good will must prevail. We must consider the effects of the foreign yoke which exerted its pressure upon [Czechoslovakia] for three hundred years."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Mr. Bohus Hak, a delegate of the Chicago Sokols, Mr. Vladimir Geringer, son of the publisher of the Chicago Svornost, were also speakers in this political and economic symposium. The article is two columns long.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
