<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To Bohemian Nationals in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO BOHEMIAN NATIONALS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) of Chicago is addressing an appeal for help to similar organizations in other American cities, and to all Bohemians, which does not need to be and which must not be explicit. An esteemed Bohemian leader, whose name is known to three men only in our organization but for whose absolute honesty and sincerity the Sdruzeni offers every assurance, asks for $10,000 for political action in behalf of the Bohemian cause in Europe. It will be impossible to publish any report on the use of the money, but an accounting will be made after the war. This is very little, but, just the same, it is all the information we are in a position to give to our public at this time. Any additional information would damage gravely the entire action and the man who is undertaking it. All of you who can help and are in favor of helping the old country in any political action its accredited representative and spokesman is about to undertake should do so soon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0628.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We publish here the first contributions received for this purpose: Mr. J. F. Stepina, Chicago, $500; the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), $500; Dr. B. D. Simunek, $100. All contributions will be publicly acknowledged by the Sdruzeni once a week. In order to avoid any possible confusion as to whether the donations are for relief purposes or for the aforesaid action, all moneys donated for the latter purpose should be sent to our president, Dr. L. J. Fisher, 2533 South Central Park Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. All pertinent correspondence should be addressed to Dr. J. E. S. Vojan, 2004 South Albany Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>In this cause, not words but deeds talk! Let us remember the words of Thomas Paine in his introduction to the Crisis: "These are the times that try men's souls!" Let us remember the immense amounts of money donated by American Irishmen for their fight for Home Rule!</p>
   <p>For the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, Dr. L. J. Fisher, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
