<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-29">Aug. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Daily Journal about the Bohemians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-29">Aug. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO DAILY JOURNAL ABOUT THE BOHEMIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The resolution and clear manifestation of the Bohemian point of view of the relationship of the Bohemian nation to the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy made public in its English text as reprinted in yesterday's issue of our paper has, quite naturally, aroused attention also in the English language papers, and the Chicago Daily Journal devotes an editorial to it. We are not among those who are elated about any and everything an American newspaper prints about the Bohemians. Much of it is erroneous, based on ignorance and, sometimes, bias. But the remarks of the Chicago Daily Journal are so pertinent and flattering that we feel we should make them known to our readers.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Journal, a publication favorable to Slavic ambitions, deals with the mentioned proclamation in an article entitled, "Bohemians for America and against Austria". The article outlines the standpoint of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) and continues as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0527.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"This proclamation should serve as an example to all American citizens of foreign extraction. We do not care to have here any hyphenated patriots. We do not want any double allegiance. We require loyalty of that kind which is manifested by these 'Americans of Bohemian origin' who have for the United States a loyalty pure and sincere, devoid of any moral taint and spiritual restraint. The Bohemians have merited an expression of thanks,and the confidence of every American".</p>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Tribune writes in a similar vein, stressing the fact that the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni has thrown out the hyphen of the "Bohemian-American" by declaring that we are loyal to the United States only.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
