<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-28">June 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Yugoslavs for Their Homeland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-28">June 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE YUGOSLAVS FOR THEIR HOMELAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a fact that the world war has disclosed our weaknesses, our weak points, when it caused us to be confronted with such problems as we never have dreamed of being called upon to solve, and for the solution of which we have not dared to hope. From the life in our microcosm we have been thrown into a world current of great political conceptions, and it is up to us to show what we can do, and to show it on this colossus of a world arena. We Bohemians have always been expected to take the lead in any movement, and to find the best way toward the realization of those ideals for which our ancestors have never hesitated to put their lives at stake. This expectation is the result of our magnificent history of deeds that had been causing upheavals throughout Europe. The reputation gained for us by our ancestors still exists among the peoples of the world, but are we worthy of it? Viktor Dyk [a contemporary poet of repute] points out in a recent poem published in the "Lidove Noviny" [People's News, a daily published in Brno, Moravia] that we are wavering, biding our time and waiting to see on which side fortune will smile in order to give it our sympathies, to <pb facs="5418478_8_0557.jpg" n="2"/>align ourselves with it. All this in spite of the fact that the trend of our history clearly points out the direction of the road we should take in the European confusion. That road is straight, independent, drawn by a clean character and selected by a warm heart, devoid of pose and theatrical effects, simple in its principle, unassailable because protected by an impregnable wall built by its fundamental truthfulness and honesty.</p>
   <p>During the more recent years we have been guilty of abandoning this road in many instances for the lure of some side road, and always paying very dearly for every one of such opportunistic steps. We are in a similar situation now. Our position of leadership among the Slavic nations is, though we may not care to see it or admit it, in considerable danger. A number of facts supporting this statement may be found. Just recently the Jugoslavs issued a manifesto to the British Parliament signed by the president of the national assembly of Dalmatia, former Mayor of the City of Split (Spalato) and member of the Austrian Diet, Dr. A. Trumbic, the president of the Yugoslav Committee of Chicago, Dr. Biankini....[here follow some twenty names of prominent Yugoslav leaders in Austria-Hungary].....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0558.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The names of these prominent Croatians, Slovenes, and Serbs prove clearly that there is a united national will among the Yugoslavs, that they stand in a solid mass behind their demands, and the manifesto shows that these demands are not only of the most serious, far-reaching character, but also that they are presented to the British people and their Parliament with a definiteness and self-assurance permitting of one, and only one, single interpretation. Of course, the manifesto defines very clearly the status of Yugoslavs in Austria. The preparation of it is a matter of great political importance, and since it is the first of its kind issued by Austrian Slavs, it has made a deep impression in European political and diplomatic circles, and it has the advantage that it will be the first to be considered when the time for it comes. Whatever comes after it runs the danger of appearing to be an invitation.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The text of the Yugoslav manifesto is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Would that we could present to the world something of a similar nature, <pb facs="5418478_8_0559.jpg" n="4"/>something definite, stating exactly our position and our plans for the future, and--find our leaders, both here and abroad--ready to sign the document, come what may.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
