<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-05-08">May 8, 1880</date><title level="a">Let Us Help Ourselves</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-05-08">May 8, 1880</date><title level="a">LET US HELP OURSELVES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is considerable talk in public about the collection of donations for the establishment of a National Theatre in Prague. It is hoped that some contribution will be sent from Chicago, but before any start is made to collect funds for this purpose, it is unavoidably necessary, as we said more than a week ago, and which becomes more urgent day by day, that we take every cent, every dollar, which it is possible to collect from our charitable donors, for the benefit of our countrymen arriving here continuously from our native land moving to America to make homes here for themselves and their children, which, in their native land, they were unable to accomplish because of the government and bad times.</p>
   <p>At the present time, every cent so graciously contributed should be used only for the help of those hundreds of our countrymen who passed through Chicago each week toward the west. It would be a sin to divert this money toward any other purpose, no matter how worthy, while we see these hundreds of our countrymen at the railroad depots each week, unfamiliar with the language, robbed of all their means, wornout groaning with hunger; and thirsting for every bit of sincere advice and for all help no matter how small.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0110.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Any one who has visited the railroad depot just once, when a train of immigrants arrived and has met his country men there, men, women and children, who following our example, are coming to build for themselves a more dignified life in this land of freedom, has seen their troubles, has seen how they are swindled, robbed and oppressed in spite of all efforts of the city police and railroad officials, will not harden his heart toward these unfortunates and will admit that all other cultural purposes must wait until this condition is remedied.</p>
   <p>We called attention, to this matter publicly last week, to the Bohemian Ticket Agents who sell railroad and steamship tickets to the people, thereby deriving a profit and a living; they are citizens: J.B. Belohradsky, Vaclav Kaspar, Fr. Novak, Aug. Geringer and V. Fiala. It should be their chief concern to see that some sort of aid is provided and steps taken to provide some kind of organization for the benefit of immigrants to Chicago. They make a profit from this, their interests and gain are first. Thus far not one of them has signified that he would take any step in this matter.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0111.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We know of no other method whereby this much-needed organization can be realized, except that the above-named citizens should meet, dedicating one whole evening for the purpose of consulting and taking the necessary steps among the lodges and citizens of our city. Or must we wait until the summer's sultry days have passed, until it begins to snow, until several thousand Bohemians have passed through Chicago are cursing the city and all its inhabitants, because at no other point in their journey did they meet with any injustice or robbery except here, (as is pointed out in the previous paragraphs)? Shall we wait, as so often happens in national undertakings, until Bohemians stop arriving, and arrive with the cross after the funeral?</p>
   <p>In the name of several Bohemian citizens who have many times gone to the railroad depots and convinced themselves of the suffering and need for some kind of aid for Bohemian immigrants, and in the name of our national honor, the love toward our brother countrymen felt by our Bohemian fellow citizens, we call once more for the cooperation of all our countrymen, and we urgently beg that the above named citizens, the ticket agents, whom it concerns most, should not delay, but that they meet and decide as to what in their opinion would be the proper procedure.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0112.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let us show our countrymen, that there are in Chicago Bohemians, and to be sure Bohemians who are not denationalized, but with a warm heart and with the good old Bohemian spirit, which seeks to help those brothers in distress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
