<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-01-17">Jan. 17, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Big Loss in Carl Jonas' Death</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-01-17">Jan. 17, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">BIG LOSS IN CARL JONAS' DEATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian community in the U.S. has suffered a great and unredeemable loss in its national and political life.</p>
   <p>With the death of Carl Jonas, the Bohemian-American community lost its first tutor and protector, its national idealist, and instructor. Since 1863, when he was 23 years of age, he had offered all his energy, ability, and life to the cause of awakening and exciting the Bohemian-American people to honest workmanship and education.</p>
   <p>Overworked, he lost the fight with life as the American consul in Crefeld, where he represented his American countrymen.</p>
   <p>Carl Jonas was known and honored by every Bohemian in America during the last 33 years because he was always active as reporter, editor, and manager of the publications Slavie, Zwon, Prorok and American.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0981.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>His main works are a Bohemian-English vocabulary, "A Woman in a Human Community," "Austro-American Pacts and Conventions," "American Law" (3 editions), "Bohemian Interpretations for Americans.</p>
   <p>He also studied law, political science, and economy. He created the Bohemian colony in Kaledonia, near Racine, Wis.</p>
   <p>A republican until 1872, he was entirely absorbed with the creation of his big Bohemian colony in Kaledonia.</p>
   <p>Beloved, eloquent, his advice was always appreciated and approved even by the old settlers in his new colony.</p>
   <p>In 1872, Carl Jonas became a democrat, taking part in the state's democratic events and gaining prominence and influence among older politicans.</p>
   <p>Nobody could state that he was a professional politician acting for his own <pb facs="5418478_8_0982.jpg" n="3"/>profit,--honestly or dishonestly. He never soiled his honor for political reasons and kept all promises to friends and political opponents.</p>
   <p>Married to Christine Kozicka, daughter of a Racine farmer, he left 4 children, all married and in the United States.</p>
   <p>A freethinker from his youngest years, he never believed in the dominating power of priesthood or nomility over the population. The activity of his whole life was concentrated in that direction. The memory of Carl Jonas should never be forgotten.</p>
   <p>He was buried in Prague, Bohemia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
