<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Ceske Narodni Sdrruzeni V Americe</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-04">Oct. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CESKE NARODNI SDRRUZENI V AMERICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The warlike events in Europe seem to be reaching the end of the first chapter of the great drama that is shaking the very foundations of the old Continent. The closer we get to the solutions of the complicated questions behind this struggle, the more imminent becomes the necessity of approaching with due seriousness the problem of the future of the Bohemian Crown Lands in the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy. Under the influence of such considerations, the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni V Americe (Bohemian National Alliance in America), comprising the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), and the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian-Slavonic Auxiliary Committee), with all its allied organizations, held its last meeting under the chairmanship of Dr. Fisher in the premises of the Vojta Naprstek School last night.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On behalf of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar, its secretary reported on the work done by this body. He pointed out the memorandum which the Kancelar prepared for the members of the Belgian delegation. This memorandum was prepared and printed with particular care and presented to the Belgian guests by a deputation which had a long conversation with the Belgians and gained from them a most favorable impression about their opinion of the prospects of the Bohemian nation after the war. He also discussed in detail the long memorandum that is being prepared at this time and which, according to recently formulated plans, will be presented to all influential bodies and individuals within the reach of the Kancelar. The memorandum will be translated into several languages. The preparation of documentary material illustrative of the attitude of the American press toward various Slavic and Bohemian questions is now nearing its completion. Simultaneously the editorial work on the text of several respective proclamations is being done. The Kancelar has also drafted an article concerning the principal facts behind the Bohemian problem as a part of an action which will be continued. The <pb facs="5418478_8_0701.jpg" n="3"/>reporter called attention to Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal's lecture on the Bohemian question which will be held in the Chicago Press Club on October 14, and will no doubt receive the deserved attention of the representatives of the American press.</p>
   <p>Secretary Melichar of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni outlined a program of organization according to which the various auxiliary bodies would be consolidated into one body, with the provision that each individual body would have complete liberty in arranging for their solicitation of funds. President Dr. Fisher regretted that so far it has been impossible to form a united front of all Bohemian-America in its actions, and said that "it is a matter of principal interest and prestige of all our organizations to become united in the present political action".</p>
   <p>The chairman of the Cesko-Americky Pomocny Vybor, Mr. James F. Stepina, said, in reporting on that body's work, that he had received a communication from <pb facs="5418478_8_0702.jpg" n="4"/>the Cesko-Americky Vybor (Bohemian-American Committee) of New York, showing that that body, too, sees that an absolutely unified action is a matter of necessity. This announcement was received with great interest and satisfaction by all those present. He also reported that the Vybor had decided to give help to the Bohemians in Paris.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. St. Vraz outlined the program of his coming lecture tour through Bohemian communities in America. His lectures will include information concerning the present state of affairs in the old country. Mr. Vraz will also arrange a festival for the benefit of the two funds that are now being created.</p>
   <p>Finally, the meeting adopted Mr. R. J. Psenka's suggestion to prepare artistic Obetiny [oblations: plural of Obetina--an article of almost any description sold for the benefit of some special purpose and usually made specially for that purpose] in co-operation with the Umelecky Klub (Artistic Club).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
