<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-24">Jan, 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs and Slovaks Give Thanks to the Allies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-24">Jan, 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS AND SLOVAKS GIVE THANKS TO THE ALLIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Ustredni Vybor Ceskeho Narodniho Sdruzeni," (Central Committee of the Czech National Association) in accordance with a resolution passed in the mass-meeting held in Chicago by the association, sent the prime minister of each of the four allied powers a telegram of thanks for their decision by which the liberation of the smaller Slavic nations from their present rulers has been made one of the prime conditions for the conclusion of peace with the Central powers.</p>
   <p>Aristide Briand, premier of France, was addressed as follows: "The Czecho-Slovak citizens of the great trans-Atlantic sister republic, numbering more than one million souls, are thanking you, as the representative of the glorious French nation. Five hundred years ago, we were allies of France. Prague learned from France. The Czechs fought for France. The Czech parliament protested against <pb facs="5418478_8_0475.jpg" n="2"/>the annexation of French provinces in 1871. Czech volunteers are shedding their blood on the battlefields of the Champaigne for the common cause. We love free France who fights for freedom; we love France, the great democratic republic. Love for France spells love for mankind itself. Glory to France, the land of heroes, that guides mankind towards a happier future!"</p>
   <p>To Premier David Lloyd George: "Great Britain, great in her history, and still greater in her future, has joined her allies in their demand for freedom of the small nations. Three hundred years ago, an English princess was our Queen. Today, our people are united with England by strong social ties of the struggle for justice and against violence. Great Britain, led by your energy and your genius, will save the future of Europe and of mankind. Today, when the Allies proclaimed the future liberation of the Czechs and Slovaks, one million <pb facs="5418478_8_0476.jpg" n="3"/>Czechs of America manifest deepest gratitude and joy. The brotherhood of the human race, founded upon equal rights for nations, large or small, will survive the ages. Ten million Czechs and Slovaks all over the world wholeheartedly wish the best of success to England, the protector of small nations."</p>
   <p>To Prince Galicin, premier of Russia: "The voice of holy Russia reached the Czechs in America demanding, in accord with her Allies, the freedom of the Czech and the Slovak nations. More than one million of American Czechs and Slovaks owe gratitude to you, the head of the government of His Majesty. Glory to the Czar, the liberator! May the great Russian people prosper as the beacon light of all Slavs, leading them into battle for justice and the rights of the oppressed brethren!"</p>
   <p>Premier Paolo Roselli of Italy: "Today, when the Czechs and Slovaks <pb facs="5418478_8_0477.jpg" n="4"/>celebrate the proclamation of the liberation in sight for their native lands, the Czechs in America request you to accept our thanks and ardent well wishes that Italy may progress from victory to victory over our common enemy. Not until the nations oppressed by Austria are free will it be possible to establish a reign of freedom and justice in Europe."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
