<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-28">Aug. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To All Good American Bohemians</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni [Bohemian National Alliance])</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-28">Aug. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL GOOD AMERICAN BOHEMIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni [Bohemian National Alliance])</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian cause has received a warm reception in the British press. A number of friends of the Bohemian nation are now informing the British public of the general situation and the demands of the Bohemian nation, and are preparing British public opinion for the time when the Bohemian question will come to the stage of diplomatic negotiation. Today it is quite safe to say, with satisfaction, that the Bohemian question will not disappear from the European international forum, and that it has reached an all-European importance. To be sure, Bohemian contacts with other nations have been growing during recent decades, but these were economic and cultural contacts, not political ones. In international politics, the leaders of the Bohemian nation have always been most careful. However, the Bohemian question is receiving attention on its own account and merits. Former Bohemian contacts with the outside were always of the most innocent nature <pb facs="5418478_8_0529.jpg" n="2"/>because the foreign, and particularly British, public had no deep understanding of the Bohemian cause. Even several months after the outbreak of the war, there was no idea among the Allies of solving the Central European problem by partitioning Austria and giving her component nations independence. In the course of the developments brought about by the war it has become apparent that the expected revolution in Austria will never take place--because it would obviously be suicidal for Austria's non-German nations--and those who had been friends of the Bohemian nation before the war were becoming interested, through the work of Bohemian organizations outside the country, in the solution of the Austrian problem in the only just and proper manner, that is, by liberation of Austria's components. The fact that this solution has never entered the minds of British and French diplomats before is easy to explain. Before the war it would have been considered, by the French and British, as a direct offense to try to secure any kind of action for the political independence of our nation, because the preservation, and even strengthening, of Austria--for the balance of power with the growing importance of Germany <pb facs="5418478_8_0530.jpg" n="3"/>and Russia--was considered by them a European necessity. And let us not forget that our modern Palacky [Translator's note: important Bohemian historian of the first part of nineteenth century], Professor Ernest Denis, our greatest friend, has voiced his agreement with Palacky's now discredited opinion, that Austria has its mission and Bohemians have a mission in Austria.</p>
   <p>But the war of aggression which Austria started, and subsequent developments in the Austrian Monarchy in the direction of complete subservience to Berlin with future annexation of Hapsburg lands to Germany--a plan with which Austrian Germans now dare to face openly the impotent government--have completely changed the basic opinion concerning Austria's raison d' etre. And now, Denis, as well as W. Steed, the great British journalist, who is extremely well-informed concerning Austria's conditions, and who even during this war was in favor of Austria's preservation, providing it would completely shake the influence of Berlin, are the most ardent partisans of an independent Bohemian state. With these there are any number of friends who refused to be deceived (as were even many overseas Bohemians) by the <pb facs="5418478_8_0531.jpg" n="4"/>seeming indifference of the Bohemian nation.</p>
   <p>The French and the British press more and more frequently print articles about our demands. In addition to papers mentioned on other occasions there are now three new ones which justify our hope for the final victory of our cause. Even in the pessimistic atmosphere of the present Russian retreat it is impossible to deny that the Bohemian cause, regardless of developments on the battlefields, is gaining general support, and will gain more in the time of the final decisive victory. And this victory will be due, as articles in many French and British papers prove, partly to the co-operation of overseas Bohemians and their organizations.</p>
   <p>Here we are giving in translation three such documents, three examples of the method by which the British public is being informed concerning the situation of the Bohemian nation. In the Spectator, a very influential and popular London weekly, in the issue of July 10, there is an article entitled "Austria-Hungary is falling apart"....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0532.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: The article which follows is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Thus goes the article in the Spectator, a publication which is very close to the highest political personages in the British Empire. How encouraging and gratifying to all good Bohemian hearts should such words of a serious British publication be! What a different, much deeper conception of true work for the Bohemian cause it inspires! The same paper has, in the July 24 issue, an article by our well-known friend, R. J. Kelly, entitled "Bohemia and the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy".</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The article which follows is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>This statement by a great Irish friend of the Bohemian nation makes all argument unnecessary and serves the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni as a competent recognition of its work which now is achieving decided successes on both sides of the Atlantic Ocean. But it is to be desired that the Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_8_0533.jpg" n="6"/>emigrants should always bear in mind the words of three of their august predecessors: Komensky (Johannes Amos Comenius), Vojta Naprstek [Translator's note: an early and most prominent Bohemian immigrant in America] and finally, also, the scion of the old noble family of the Counts Vratislav of Mitrovic. Komensky: "I believe that thou wilst resume the management of thy own affairs, oh Bohemian nation!" Naprstek: "'No oceans can separate those who are one in heart' should be the motto of our days." The last of the trio, A. H. Vratislav, should be our example in spreading overseas the knowledge of Bohemian matters. Let us quote from the Spectator one of the foremost British journalists, James Baker, who accompanies an original article about the family of the Counts Vratislav of Mitrovic by the following explanation:</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The article which follows is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Since, then, the English press now writes so convincingly and so hopefully about the Bohemian cause and the future independence of the Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_8_0534.jpg" n="7"/>nation, should it not be the duty of every one of us to exert all our efforts toward the liberation of our native country?</p>
   <p>Let Bohemian America talk with conviction equal to that of our British friends overseas, members of another nation, but men who have an understanding of the rights of the Bohemian nation and of a healthy development in free, liberated Bohemian-Slavonic lands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
