<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-28">Nov. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Changes in the Organization of Paris Bohemians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0653</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0653.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-28">Nov. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CHANGES IN THE ORGANIZATION OF PARIS BOHEMIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mail reaching us yesterday from Paris brought an interesting letter from the Committee of the Bohemian Colony and Volunteers of Paris which shows that the original committee Has dissolved and that at present, the club is going through a crisis; that the paper Na Zdar! (To Success!), which was profusely quoted by certain Bohemian newspapers in Chicago, is not an official publication with the right to speak on behalf of Paris Bohemians, but rather a private enterprise which is being published for profit. Our readers will get a clear idea about the whole situation from reading the letter in its entirety:</p>
   <p>"Paris, November 12, 1914.</p>
   <p>"Dear Countrymen: In the general confusion of the first days of mobilization, the Bohemian colony in Paris charged a number of countrymen with the responsibility of protecting its rights and securing permission for its members to <pb facs="5418478_8_0654.jpg" n="2"/>remain in Paris.</p>
   <p>"The mandate of this committee was of a temporary, provisional character. Now that some of its members have enlisted in the French Army, some have left Paris, and Members Hoffman-Kratky, Novak, and Bilek have resigned, and the committee is unable to function, a pleuary meeting of the whole colony was called for November 10 at which a new, definite set of officers was elected.</p>
   <p>These officers have been elected from among those of our countrymen who are noted for their patriotism, unselfishness, and willingness to work hard. Their names are a guarantee that they will bring the work which the colony has agreed upon to do to a successful conclusion.</p>
   <p>"In apprising you of this change, we wish to call your attention to the fact that this definite, permanent committee only has the right to represent our local colony and the Bohemian volunteers and to protect the political and <pb facs="5418478_8_0655.jpg" n="3"/>economic interests of the Bohemian nation.</p>
   <p>"We also call your attention to the fact that the newspaper Na Zdar! is not the official organ of our colony--that it is rather a private enterprise of Mr. Hoffman-Kratky who, having resigned from the committee, has lost his right to represent our local group.</p>
   <p>"We are, with cordial greetings, the Vybor Ceske Kolonie a Ceskych Dobrovolniku v Parizi (Committee of the Bohemian Colony and Bohemian Volunteers of Paris).</p>
   <p>"J. Capek, president; P. Svoboda, vice-president; Ant. Vesely, Vilous Crkal, Rudolf Kepl, secretaries."</p>
   <p>[A French postscript is added to the letter giving the names, addresses, and official titles of this new permanent committee.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
