<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-14">Apr. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Brilliant Example of a Remarkable Career</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-14">Apr. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BRILLIANT EXAMPLE OF A REMARKABLE CAREER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In today's issue, we offer a biographical sketch of the life of our young fellow-countryman of whom the Czech settlement may justly feel proud. He is Mr. Otto Kerner, outstanding Chicago lawyer, popular alderman of the Twelfth Ward, and lately, master in chancery in the circuit court of Cook County. His life is one chain of unqualified successes, which appear the more significant upon consideration of the fact that they came through his own assiduousness, energy, and perseverance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kerner was born on February 22, 1884, in the heart of our Czech Plzen (Pilsen) district. His birthplace was the community of Eighteenth and Fisk Streets. His father, Charles, was one of the oldest and highly esteemed settlers of the neighborhood, and his mother, Josephine, was well-known too, and befriended many people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0911.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After having gone through public school, Mr. Kerner worked in the office of the late Alderman Joseph F. Kohout, then as a clerk in the office of Edw. J. Novak, lawyer, where the foundations for his vocation were laid. He replenished his knowledge in night schools and after careful preparation, began to continue his studies in the law school of Lake Forest University, from which he graduated in June 1905 with the highest average. He became connected with the law firm, Novak and Pollack, with whom he remained until 1909. He then entered into partnership with De Witt C. Jones, and has been active as a lawyer up to the present. Mr. Jones, his partner, is the oldest among the lawyers of Cook Country, and also one of the, most active, notwithstanding his age of seventy-nine, and an excellent advocate. He has brought tears to the eyes of many a juror. He effectively helped build up the repute of the firm Kerner &amp; Jones as one signally successful before the courts.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kerner became a figure in public life at an early date, though it is <pb facs="5418478_8_0912.jpg" n="3"/>meet to acknowledge that he obviously never craved for a public office. His first step into the political sphere was his acceptance of an appointment to the office of assistant city prosecutor tendered to him by Mayor Carter H. Harrison. He remained there from 1911 until 1913. In the latter year, he was elected alderman of the Twelfth Ward.  December 1916 brought his appointment as master in chancery, assigned to Judge Honore's Court.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kerner is member of the city council, having been re-elected with a great majority this year. His exprience gained for him the chairmanship of the judiciary and of the finance committees.He is also a member of the committee on compensation, which decided he amounts paid by the great corporations and utilities for the franchises and privileges granted by the city. The proposed law prescribing fenders for freight automobiles is his creation. It was taken into court by opposing corporations to test its constititionality. If passed, <pb facs="5418478_8_0913.jpg" n="4"/>it will prevent many automobile accidents Ald. Kerner's father fell victim to an accident caused by a heavy truck.</p>
   <p>Ald. Kerner gave innumerable proofs that he takes an intense and sincere interest in the welfare of the people.</p>
   <p>In 1907, he married Miss Rose D. Chmelik. They have two sons and one daughter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
