<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-18">Dec. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Brittain Is in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0752</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0752.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-18">Dec. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">MR. BRITTAIN IS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Brittain, the American Consul in Prague, is in Chicago these days. This is an occasion for our representative and prominent men to do all they can to show Mr. Brittain our appreciation for everything he has done for our nation in general and for American Bohemians in particular during his work as United States Consul in the heart of Bohemia. We are calling especially on those of our countrymen who are acquainted with Mr. Brittain's activities; who dealt with him during their visits to Bohemia and learned to value him not only as an extremely able American representative, but also as a willing helper in any matter when he is asked for assistance; an ardent friend of the Bohemian nation whose desires and aims he well understands and supports whenever he can. The constant attacks directed against him by the Germans in Prague are his best recommendation to every Bohemian.</p>
   <p>American visitors to the last Sokol Slet (Mass Convention) will never forget <pb facs="5418478_8_0753.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Brittain's enthusiastic work for the Slet and for American Sokols. Many weeks after the Slet he was still finding pleasure in showing his callers the pictures of the Slet printed in Leslie's Weekly and the articles about the Slet that had appeared in other American publications. It is up to us to be grateful to such American friends and to appreciate their work properly. We should consider it our duty to show Mr. Brittain our feelings not only on the occasion of his visit, but also when the Democratic administration comes to Washington. That will be the time to show our appreciation not only by words, but also by deeds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
