<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-30">Dec. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">For Czechoslovak Independence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-30">Dec. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FOR CZECHOSLOVAK INDEPENDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is true that Czechoslovak independence has not yet been officially proclaimed. Nevertheless, that independence is assured, if we do our duty to our own nation and to the Allies. Of what does that duty consist? It means maintaining voluntary but rigid discipline. A sense of that duty is the guide for those who strive for moral and rational perfection. It can be understood by those who are capable of responding to a suggestion from their organization. One of our duties is to pay our national head tax. Only people who are spiritually dead and who are void of self-consciousness will consider their nation a beggar for alms.</p>
   <p>One of our foremost duties is certainly military organization. Every nation that wants liberty must fight for it and pay the price in blood. After centuries, we can again shoulder arms under our own flag.</p>
   <p>A nation that ventures upon revolution and wants to be considered a sovereign <pb facs="5418478_8_0425.jpg" n="2"/>state must create a regular army of its own, in order to prove that it is vital and mature enough to merit the right of self-determination.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak National Council has been empowered to organize a military force, with the consent and express will of our nation. Our nation is united in the old homeland and beyond its borders. The Czechoslovak National Council began its highly responsible task by proclaiming a general mobilization of the Czechoslovaks. Everyone who calls himself a real man must respond!</p>
   <p>It is easy to forget the hardships of a few months. But the shame of treason committed against one's people will haunt one's posterity like a curse.</p>
   <p>We must not fight anonymously in the various armies of the Allies. We should fight alongside them, as a compact military unit and under our own command! This will mean to us an open recognition of our right to our demands.</p>
   <p>If our nation did not rise in its full strength, that would be tantamount to branding its forehead with the sign of inferiority and cowardice! Its very <pb facs="5418478_8_0426.jpg" n="3"/>fate for centuries is in the balance. Therefore, every man to the front! Let women take the place of men, and children work at home!</p>
   <p>Every honest patriot belongs to the nation in the first, and to the family in the second place. If he becomes one of our soldiers, he will be under the protection of the French Republic and will enjoy the same privileges as the soldiers of the French army enjoy. In order that he may not lose his spirits in worrying about the needs of his people at home, his family is assured of support. Besides this, our Auxiliary will also attend to soldiers' families.</p>
   <p>Those who win liberty for our nation will have a voice in its organization. The nation will not only chronicle the names of its faithful sons, but it will also take care of them.</p>
   <p>Those desiring more detailed information about the Czechoslovak Army in France are referred to the Czechoslovak Committee 3743, W. 26th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
