<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Czechoslovak Review</title>,
            <date when="1922-03">Mar., 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Vaclav Vanek, D.D.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0852</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0852.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>,
<date when="1922-03">Mar., 1922</date>.
<title level="a">VACLAV VANEK, D.D.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the best known and best liked and at the same time the most democratic of Bohemian divines in America is the Reverend Vaclav Vanek. It may truly be said of him that he has hosts of friends and not a single enemy. This may be explained by the fact that he has helped, literally, thousands of countrymen throughout his eventful career.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vanek was born at Domazlice, Bohemia, May 31, 1862. Domazlice is on the Bavarian frontier and the Bohemians living in that district are known as the Chods and have been distinguished for centuries by their peculiar dialect and picturesque costumes, as well as their hard heads. Of course, Mr. Vanek, in spite of his mild character and big heart, has much of the stubbornness of the Chods and he possesses in a large measure their love for Bohemia and its language.</p>
   <p>In the ancient royal City of Domazlice there is a "gymnasium", school of eight <pb facs="5418478_8_0853.jpg" n="2"/>years' course - graduates being admitted to sophomore grade in college - to which the burghers and wealthy farmers from the surrounding country send their boys to go through eight years of Latin and Greek and to prepare for the Prague University. The father of Vaclav was a railroad man with a none-too-generous salary. In order that the young student might complete his eight years' course, he was forced to tutor students less gifted than himself. Upon graduation he set out for Prague where he tried to make up his mind as to what vocation he would select for his life's work. Thus he spent two years in the school of theology and two years in the school of law. During all this time it was only with difficulty that he kept his young appetite satisfied. About this time relatives settled in Chicago, Illinois, and wrote to young Vanek about the great opportunities in America. So, in 1887, he packed is worldly possessions in a suitacase and set out for the United States, where upon his arrival he went to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Like a great many other young Bohemians who came to this country with unfinished university education, he found a living as a reporter on the Chicagske Listy, a daily. The editor and proprietor of the publication was a very talented man <pb facs="5418478_8_0854.jpg" n="3"/>with an unfortunate liking for liquor. While his paper was popular, the editor, true to the traditions of the "Fourth Estate," never had any money. On Saturday nights he paid his reporters $5.00 and told them the balance of their stipend would be credited to them on his books.</p>
   <p>Dr. Vanek was a good journalist, and is one to this day. The smell of printer's ink is still sweeter to him than the perfumes of the Orient. It was while working on the Chicagske Listy that he discovered that the ministry was his true vocation. He enrolled for a theological course at Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois. In 1892, he became pastor of Jan Hus Church, Sawyer Avenue, corner 24th street, Chicago. The church edifice standing now on this corner is the result of his efforts. It was during the panic of 1893, and subsequently, that Dr. Vanek was afforded an opportunity to prove his love for the poor. During this disastrous period he was the instrument by which whole blocks of Bohemian immigrants, all out of work and without money, got enough to eat and to keep alive.</p>
   <p>While still working on the Chicagske Listy and studying at Northwestern University, Mr. Vanek married, in 1899, Miss Mary Riha, who has been a faithful <pb facs="5418478_8_0855.jpg" n="4"/>and untiring helper to him ever since. They have six children.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vanek should have never left Chicago. But a call came to him in 1894 from the Bohemian Presbyterian Church of Baltimore, Maryland, which he accepted. Church buildings seem to he his specialty. When he came to Baltimore he found a congregation but no church. Being a new man in the city it took him four years to collect enough money to erect a church on the corner of Ashland Avenue and Washington street, Baltimore. During those years he was also editor and publisher of a weekly religious paper called the Kednota, still remembered as the best Bohemian religious in America. He continued publication until 1899, when his growing family made it impossible any longer to put a large part of his slender pastor's salary into the insufficiently supported weekly.</p>
   <p>As a part of his work as a pastor in Baltimore, Mr. Vanek visited the Locust Point Pier, No. 9, at which docked the weekly ships from Bremen with Bohemian immigrants. Here he made many friends who scattered all over the country, but who still remember Mr. Vanek as the man who gave them the first assistance and advice when they stepped on American soil. From this work grew the <pb facs="5418478_8_0856.jpg" n="5"/>"Immigrant Home", opened in 1906, at the corner of Broadway and Madison streets, where thousands were sheltered and aided in finding work. Charity and social welfare were always two of Mr. Vanek's strong points. During the Summer he maintained a resort for the children of the congested district of northeastern Baltimore. "Dingley Bell" farm is remembered with much pleasure by the now young men and women who, as youngsters, spent the hot months of the Summer in Fallston, Maryland. Then for the workers in Curtis Bay, Maryland, he secured an old schoolhouse which he turned into a settlement.</p>
   <p>Far beyond Baltimore his fame spread during those years and in 1909 he was called back to Chicago to undertake religious work among the large number of Bohemians in that city. Under his leadership was erected the "Bohemian Settlement House" on Racine Avenue at a cost of $40,000, and in the following year the Hubbard Memorial Bohemian Presbyterian Church on Lawndale Avenue, of which he is now pastor, was opened.</p>
   <p>In 1915, Dubuque (Iowa) University conferred upon the Reverend Vanek, the honorary degree of Doctor of Divinity in recognition of his work among the <pb facs="5418478_8_0857.jpg" n="6"/>people. Three times he has been a delegate to the Presbyterian General Assembly.</p>
   <p>Dr. Vanek never considered his pastoral duties confined to preaching and visiting the members of his congregation. He, in a true sense and with out the accompanying blare of trumpets, is a minister to the poor. For twelve years he has been secretary of the "Bohemian Charitable Association", one of the greatest of all Bohemian institutions in the United States. During the World War he was secretary and chief executive worker of all the Chicago war charities. Incidentally he enjoys the distinction of marrying more couples than any other minister in Chicago.</p>
   <p>After a lapse of seventeen years Dr. and Mrs. Vanek are going to revisit Bohemia. Unless he had something to do on the trip he would not enjoy it, so they elected him secretary of the "Bohemian Businessmen's Tour" which is sponsored by Chicago. He will receive a hearty welcome in Prague for he is looked upon as one of the Protestant leaders in America and as the greatest charitable worker among our people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0858.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Though he has been soliciting aid for his many charities for many years, he is reputed to have never been turned down by any of the business men whom he has approached for help, be he Catholic, Protestant, or Jew. Everybody in Chicago loves Dr. Vanek for his sterling qualities and big heart. While sixty years old, his step is firm and his mind and body active. He visits his "Congregation", conglomerate at best, with the same spirit and enthusiasm he possessed thirty years ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
