<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-02">May 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czech People of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">For a Festive Reception of Masaryk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-02">May 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECH PEOPLE OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">For a Festive Reception of Masaryk</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, delegates of all Czech organizations of Chicago, gathered in a meeting called by the Czech National Alliance for April 30 in the hall of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, in which we joyfully resolved to arrange for a triumphant reception for the greatest man of our nation, our "Daddy" Masaryk.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday afternoon, shortly before 2 P.M., a train will arrive at the Northwestern Station, bringing to us a group of men. Among them will be our leader, whom we are going to welcome by an overwhelmingly enthusiastic manifestation of love and pride. Czech Chicago is going to demonstrate how deep-rooted is its love and devotedness for the tortured Czech nation. Let us welcome T. G. Masaryk again, after his many years of absence from Chicago, and let the world know how we prize those who are dearest to us.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0408.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He will come among us as the chief of the Czechoslovak Army--an army which has already earned the admiration of the world, and is going to win still more glory. He was known to us in former years when he was among us, a dear old friend whose heart and beautiful soul we have long since learned to love.</p>
   <p>Czech children, Sokols, women, and organizations, workmen, and all others of you who sent us to that meeting at Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Hall, all you Czechoslovaks, hear ye:</p>
   <p>The time being too short, we have not been able to address ourselves to our community except in this way. We are confident, however, that our Czech and Slovak people will come in tens of thousands, and that the afternoon of next Sunday will be one never to be forgotten.</p>
   <p>We request all participants to provide themselves with small American flags.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0409.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Sokols are expected to appear in their attire, just as will the organizations of our butchers. All flags carried in the parade should be preferably American flags. All information on arrangements will be published in our dailies. Places will be accurately designated, so that every group will know where to take its stand. Professor Masaryk will ride through Madison Street, then on Michigan Boulevard to the Blackstone Hotel. Every organization will form a group about its own leader. Only functionaries of large bodies will form a separate group which will greet Professor Masaryk at the entrance to the railroad station; they will wear special sashes.</p>
   <p>We entreat all of you to help give our leader a royal welcome.</p>
   <p>Chicago, May 1, 1918.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: A list of the organizations is omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
