<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-05-31">May 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">To Lighten the Immigrants Burden.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-05-31">May 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">TO LIGHTEN THE IMMIGRANTS BURDEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4--Innumerable men, women and children are leaving the shores of the other continent every year in search of a new homeland. Not many years ago, America was considered by the Czechs as a kind of Promised Land; nowadays, however, the influx of Slavonic peoples into America has taken such proportions that some Americans are becoming afraid.</p>
   <p>Fifty years ago the trip over the sea used to cost a terrible amount of money, and took several weeks, aye, several months; and those aboard a wind-jammer were exposed to the danger of stranding on foreign shores.</p>
   <p>Nowadays, choice meals and splendid entertainment await them on sea for the short time of one week's crossing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The low cost of traveling may be considered as one of the reasons for the onrush of immigrants from our old country. Yet, there is another cause that prompts the Czech immigrant to take precipitate action. It is the misleading information about the economic and social conditions of this country, by which the people of the old country are inveigled into taking the deciding steps. The number of immigrants would be much smaller if those desirous to leave had had honest reports about their future abode.</p>
   <p>The conditions in this country are unduly extolled in the old country; they are never pictured in their true light. Often we meet with Czech countrymen of ours who seem to be in a terrible predicament.</p>
   <p>We hear laments about the vicissitudes of life, the ingratitude of the world, and the misery to be endured in this country, all of which, brings misfortune instead of happiness to so many families.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We hear complaints directed against a mode of living repulsive to our element, and against conventions thoroughly disliked by our kind. We know from our own experience many Czechs who owned not inconsiderable property, and who allowed themselves to be beguiled by misrepresentation, sold out, and left their native land with high expectations of a hospitable reception by rich America. What a disappointment is in store for many of them! What privations they have to endure before they become used to the customs of the country; before they find a proper outlet for their energies, and the kind of work to employ their knowledge or skill, and before they are able to provide for their families!</p>
   <p>If the immigrant happens to be past a certain age it is often extremely difficult for him to find and hold a position, for he has no knowledge of the language and is unacquainted with the methods and systems which govern American industry and commerce.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0093.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The younger man or girl are in a more advantageous position as they assimilate quicker and are swifter at work, where the elderly person is bound to lag. We are unable to offer any remedy against these conditions which will continue as long as our people in the old country are a prey to dishonest traveling agents who lure them from a secure existence into misfortune.</p>
   <p>The conditions in our country are not, of course, so lamentable as to justify an all around complaint; they are, in fact very gratifying for many, though they rarely prove to be as represented by irresponsible persons who cajole the emigrant in the old country into the momentous decision of abandoning hearth and home.</p>
   <p>But even for young people there also exists the possibility of having to undergo the ordeal of misery.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0094.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The more mature man, ordinarily having more judgement, is more easily satisfied with what the country offers to him, whereas young people do not, as a rule, befriend themselves with their surroundings, though later, when finally accustomed, they, categorically declare they would not return to the old country even if someone paid for the voyage when they become prosperous, they exaggerate their praise of the opportunities in America.</p>
   <p>Such people are the true counterpart of the unsuccessful ones who know no better than to heap abuse upon everything American, hardly conscious of what they are saying. We are ready to admit that the situation of many an immigrant is nothing short of critical, but as the workingman is at liberty to quit and look for a different occupation, the immigrant, similarly, can leave these shores and return to the old country; his financial status, however may not allow him to do this, and so he settles down, grumbling, resigned to his fate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0095.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We sincerely regret all this, but most of us, after all, had to undergo various hardships and struggles for our existence, before we could safely cast anchor on these shores. And we rejoice, nevertheless, when we see new immigrants arriving from the old country, although we fear that in a short time many of them will be lost to our nation, instead of seeing them united in one mighty organization working for the common interest of their nationality as other nationalities do. The life of many Czech immigrants is burdensome, true enough, but the fault lies with us who do not support sufficiently the social unification of the newly arrived, which would certainly greatly improve their living conditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
