<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-10">Mar. 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Frantisek Fiser, Bohemian-American, Journalist, Author, and Distinguished Amateur Actor, Died Early Yesterday Morning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-10">Mar. 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MR. FRANTISEK FISER, BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN, JOURNALIST, AUTHOR, AND DISTINGUISHED AMATEUR ACTOR, DIED EARLY YESTERDAY MORNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The none-too-large community of Bohemian-American journalists and authors was again bereft of one of its members by death. Frantisek Fiser is no more. He died shortly before five o'clock yesterday morning. He died peacefully, quietly, being spared the painful struggle with death. He had been ill for several months, but had not given up hope of becoming well again. Likewise, his wife, Marie, and his children, Oldrich and bessie, were also convinced their beloved husband and father would recuperate, and be active again. However, fate decided otherwise, and Frantisek Fiser, to the great sorrow of his dear ones, and the great loss to Bohemian-American literature, did not recover. About three weeks ago, he was injured by a street care at 22nd Street and Kedzie Avenue, and there is no doubt that this injury, if not the direct cause of his death, hastened it. It is certain that before he met with the accident, he was recovering from his illness, and gaining strength, and had every reason to look forward to an early recovery. However, since the fateful day when he was dragged almost half a block by the <pb facs="5418478_8_0956.jpg" n="2"/>street car, his condition grew steadily worse, and even though at times he seemed to be improving as was the case the day before his death, Frantisek Fiser was nearing the end. He has finished suffering, and has ended fighting. Yes, it can be said of him that he ended the fight and died like a soldier on the field of battle.</p>
   <p>We do not have many Bohemian men of letters in America, and of those, Frantisek Fiser was one of the best. In so far as original work was concerned, he wrote miniature stories mostly. Some of these we reprinted in our calendar. It was in these little stories, written in simple, understandable words, that Fiser's talent was best shown. Being an educated man, a graduate of the higher gymnasium in Kralovy Hradec, and an expert of the Czech language, he always endeavored honorably so that his works would influence others, and he was remarkably successful.</p>
   <p>In so far as larger works are concerned, he is known through a great many translations, all of which were very successful and sought after by all readers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As an editor, he was a valuable force in any editorial room, and because of his clever pan and fine composition, he was never in want of a place.</p>
   <p>He came to America in 1888, and shortly after his arrival, accepted a position on the editorial staff of the Cechoslovan, a Catholic weekly published at that time by Victor <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>eclik. Resigning from this position after a time, he traveled with his family to Omaha, and joined the staff of Osveta. But he longed for Chicago, and returned here taking a position on our staff. From there, he went to Nared. when the newspaper Jednota was founded, he became its editor. After the failure of that publication, he went to Cedar Rapids, where he published the Ceska Lipa. Later, he was a member of the editorial staff of the Lidovy Noviny, and of Svornost. Some time ago, he went to Milwaukee and joined the staff of Domacnost. He again returned to Chicago. However, he did not work for any newspaper after that, but devoted himself to literature exclusively.</p>
   <p>Frantisek Fiser will be remembered not only as a journalist and writer <pb facs="5418478_8_0958.jpg" n="4"/>but also as a distinguished amateur actor. Those old lovers of the amateur theatre, wherever it still flourished, remember Frantisek Fiser well. Yes indeed, it is hardly possible to forget some of his roles, whether they be of a serious or comic character, which he portrayed on the stage. Let us recollect only his "Valenta" in "Palicov dceri," (The charcoal-burner's daughter) in which role he had no peer. The stage brought Fiser just as many friends as his activity as a journalist and writer; ala however, both brought only friendship and moral recognition. Otherwise, he had to struggle hard for an existence, and had to exert all his forces if he wished to have his family lack nothing.</p>
   <p>Of his ardent love for the homeland and for all things Bohemian, we have innumerable examples at hand. His library, of the choicest Bohemian works, speaks for all of these. It was nothing strange for Frantisek Fiser to use the last penny, if necessary, to acquire some Bohemian book.</p>
   <p>Frantisek Fiser was born in Studenec v Podkronosy, and was forty-seven years old at his death. As has been said, he came to America in 1888, <pb facs="5418478_8_0959.jpg" n="5"/>accompanied by his wife. At that time, he became a member of St. Vaclav Society No. 65, First Catholic Central Union, and later, a member of the dramatic club, "Jablonsky."</p>
   <p>His funeral will be held Sunday morning at 9 o'clock from his former residence at 5050 South St. Louis Avenue, then to the Church of the Bohemian blessed Agnes, and from there to the Bohemian National Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
