<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-18">June 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Contingent of the Bohemian-American Commercial Delegation Visits President Masaryk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-18">June 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CONTINGENT OF THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN COMMERCIAL DELEGATION VISITS PRESIDENT MASARYK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, three column-fifth of a page, view of eight members of the Chicago delegation grouped around Dr. Masaryk; another half-tone, three column-three-sevenths of a page, view of a letter head with the President's castle at Lany and below it the signatures of the President and the Chicago men as follows: T. G. Masaryk, Dr. Alice G. Masaryk, Colonel Victor Hoppe, The Reverend Vaclav Vanek, John A. Sokol, Charles Vesely, Joseph Dusek, Vaclav L. Rezabek, Frantisek Zajicek, Bohus Hak, Frantisek J. Maly, Franta Marik, John Pecha, Dr. O. S. Pavlik, Anton J. Zahrobsky, J. F. Stepina, Emil Tuma; Mesdames Eugenie Patterson, and Rella Hoppe.]</p>
   <p>Last Friday we received another communication from our friends who, as members of the Ceskoslovensko-Americka Obchodni Vyprava (Czechoslovak-American Commercial Delegation) are now probably in Prague. The letter--and it was a voluminous one--was mailed to us by the Reverend Vaclav Vanek. The letter, which <pb facs="5418478_8_0143.jpg" n="2"/>bore the post date of May 29, 1922, enclosed several pictures of which we reproduce two. The Chicago delegation made a trip to Lany, the summer residence of President Masaryk, and the upper picture will show the members of that group. [Translator's note: Omitted in translation are the names of members of the Chicago delegation previously reported in the description of the second half-tone.] Among other things which the Reverend Vaclav Vanek, who is the secretary of the Delegation, wrote was that the visit was facilitated by Captain Emil Tuma.....</p>
   <p>On this occasion the Reverend Vaclav Vanek addressed the President as follows: "Mr. President! Since the day when your republic of Czechoslovakia was born, we, the Czechoslovaks of America,have honored two George Washingtons, fathers of their [respective] countries: One is buried at Mount Vernon in Virginia, not far from the capital city of the United States--Washington; the other resides in our dear and now liberated mother city of Prague. I am not going to tire you with a long speech. You know yourself how much we all love you. Your name is a mighty one which was and is able to call us out of our graves, <pb facs="5418478_8_0144.jpg" n="3"/>graves of indifference and half-measures. I beg you to hold your protecting hand over our young nation, and especially to give succor to the poor and the wretched. We stand behind you as one man. All you need to do is to say the word and no sacrifice will be too difficult for us."</p>
   <p>The speaker then introduced the members of the delegation. The President thanked the speaker briefly, and, after shaking hands with everyone, invited the delegation to a luncheon which was waiting.</p>
   <p>The luncheon consisted of rissole fried a la Pompadour, roast goose, new potatoes, cucumber salad, asparagus, holland sauce, fresh strawberry ice cream fruits, coffee, wines of all varieties, cigars, cigarettes, etc. Every member of the delegation had a place especially assigned to him, with a place card bearing the President's crest and the name of the invited person.....</p>
   <p>After luncheon was over the President and the delegates repaired to the smaller audience hall where, over cups of black coffee, the President entertained his <pb facs="5418478_8_0145.jpg" n="4"/>visitors and where the list of names of all the guests was signed by him. The wife of the President made her appearance among us at this time and remained for about thirty minutes.</p>
   <p>In a very simple manner she said: "I wish to introduce myself; I am Mrs. Masaryk".....</p>
   <p>The sojourn at the President's castle at Lany was considered most enjoyable by all the delegates.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
