<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-19">May 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">To the Sokol Slet</title><title level="a" type="sub">A List of Participants Who Have Made Application to Join This Year's Excursion to the Old Homeland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-19">May 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE SOKOL SLET</title><title level="a" type="sub">A List Of Participants Who Have Made Application To Join This Year's Excursion To The Old Homeland</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Extensive preparations are being made in all Bohemian-American communities for this year's excursion to Bohemia for the Sokol Slet (Gymnastic Festival). Everything indicates that this will be the biggest joint visit to the old homeland ever undertaken by Bohemian-Americans. From all directions come reports of the large numbers of countrymen who will join the excursion. These, added to those who have already left, will swell the representation of Bohemian-America during the festive Sokol Days in Prague. It is impossible to correctly estimate the number of excursionists; however, according to the lists which we have received from F. Skala &amp; Company of Chicago and Brodsky &amp; Sovak of New York, the number of participants will be unexpectedly large. Both of these firms have been accepting applications from individuals who will depart on June 11 from New York, with the Sokol delegation, on board <pb facs="5418478_8_0770.jpg" n="2"/>the steamship New Amsterdam. However, these are far from all of the excursionists; for both firms have sent large numbers of other countrymen who, although they are not accompanying the excursion proper, are travelling to Prague for the same purpose--to visit the old homeland and to take part in the Sokol Slet.....</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The article carries two columns of names of individuals participating in the excursion.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
