<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-12">June 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Czech-Americans: a Statement by the President of the Czech National Alliance in Regard to Mr. Dyrych, and in Answer to the Article by Mr. Karel Horky</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-12">June 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO CZECH-AMERICANS: A STATEMENT BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE IN REGARD TO MR. DYRYCH, AND IN ANSWER TO THE ARTICLE BY MR. KAREL HORKY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"During the three years while I was President of the Czech National Alliance, I always endeavored to give preference to our dear cause and to avoid dissension. It was, this I know, polemics, which became the calamity of Czech America, poisoned public life, and sapped the strength of the Czech-American branch.....</p>
   <p>"I regret that it is my duty to make a declaration to those who knew the difficult start of the activities of the Czech National Alliance long before the beneficent hand of Thomas G. Masaryk was felt.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0457.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Czech America must be given a clear view of the Dyrych affair. Mr. Horky writes about America as if he stood with his back to it; I am writing these lines face to face with Czech America because I use no lies.</p>
   <p>"It is not true that the expulsion of Dyrych was made under the influence of Dr. Eduard Benes. I have not exchanged one single word with Benes during my entire activity in the Czech National Alliance. It was T. G. Masaryk who informed me about the fatal doings of Dyrych. From that information I am submitting to Czech America terrible accusations, for the truth of which I assume full responsibility. I say this:</p>
   <p>"While in France and in Russia Mr. Dyrych committed such terrible deeds that they threatened to destroy completely what Masaryk has built up during three years. I was horrified by this information, yet took cognizance of them without taking action; for I felt that it did not behoove me to mix with European affairs. When, however, Dyrych made attempts--and I have proof for that--to lead Czech America away from Masaryk and to demoralize our <pb facs="5418478_8_0458.jpg" n="3"/>movement, I wrote to Masaryk:</p>
   <p>'America, to the last Czech, stands behind you in whatever you plan to do in the Dyrych affair for the exoneration of our dear old homeland.' Not long after this I received the news from Masarvk, then in London, England--and not from Benes--that Dyrych was expelled from the Czech National Council. While reading the letter, I felt distinctly the pains that the dear old Council must have suffered before deciding on such steps. The reasons for the expulsion are given in the letter, but they are of such nature that I simply loath to put them down in writing. However, I am willing, just as Mr. Horky is, to reveal the reasons to an assembly of honest and judicious people.....</p>
   <p>I feel it below my dignity to expatiate on other naive contentions in Mr. Horky's pamphlet. Therefore, I shall not answer his statement that our central organization gave orders to throw stones at Dyrych; also, that Masaryk takes English money, for everyone knows from where the money for the professors of King [or King's?] College comes. I shall likewise not answer the question of <pb facs="5418478_8_0459.jpg" n="4"/>money sent from our headquarters to Europe, because it is I who am mailing it through the American State bank to Professor Masaryk, and to him alone--and Czech America is sure to have faith in Masaryk. I won't answer Horky's attacks against the secretary-general, Dr. Eduard Benes. Horky attacked him because the former did not dare attack Masaryk's very person before all Czech America, in spite of the great relish--one can scent this from the pamphlet--with which he would have done so.</p>
   <p>We all are willing to appear before the court of our nation and give an account of our work. There is where Dyrych will have to appear and where Horky will be brought; he, the man who has soiled his literary shield by writing the pamphlet. Before a court such as this the affair will be tried.</p>
   <p>The Czech National Alliance, the pride of the Czech people in America, must not suffer, and neither must the unfortunate people who cry for liberation in the old homeland. We joyfully accept the leadership of the Czech National Council, just as the Czechs in Russia have done. We have achieved great victories under the banner of T. G. Masaryk, and we intend to follow it toward <pb facs="5418478_8_0460.jpg" n="5"/>further future successes.</p>
   <p>(Signed) "Dr. Ludvik J. Fisher President of the Czech National Alliance in America."</p>
   <p>There follows a postscript with a solemn promise by Dr. L. J. Fisher to pursue faithfully his national duties as president of the Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
