<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-31">Mar. 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Jan G. Masaryk at the University of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-31">Mar. 31, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">JAN G. MASARYK AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jan G. Masaryk, Czechoslovakian minister to the United States, was the guest of the University of Chicago, yesterday afternoon. The University of Chicago is the famous educational institution where his renowned father, Thomas G. Masaryk, conducted a series of lectures, about fourteen years ago, while visiting the United States. At 4 P. M., in the university auditorium, Kandel Hall, at 57th Street and University Avenue, many people had assembled. Among those present were members of the university's faculty, students, and also many representatives of the Czechoslovakian people. When our dear guest appeared on the speaker's platform, he was greeted by enthusiastic applause. His speech, in which he discussed the actual conditions in Czechoslovakia, created a deep impression. In addition to him, representatives of the university spoke, expressing their sympathy with the Czechoslovakian people and their President. The meeting lasted until late in the evening and was a <pb facs="5418478_8_0230.jpg" n="2"/>success in every respect. Among the large assemblage we noticed Professor Kasparek, who has just returned from Siberia where he had been sent by the Czechoslovakian government on an important mission.</p>
   <p>Jan G. Masaryk at The Board of Trade</p>
   <p>At noon time today, a reception will be held in the Hotel Lasalle in honor of Jan G. Masaryk, Czechoslovakian Minister to the United States, whose residence is in Washington, D. C. The reception has been arranged by the Chicago Board of Trade, with which the Czechoslovak Board of Trade of America and the Czechoslovak Board of Trade of Chicago are affiliated. The following countrymen are on the arrangements committee: John A. Cervenka, John A. Sokol, Karel V. Janovsky, Frank G. Hajicek, James F. Stepina, and many others. On this occasion, our distinguished guest will speak on the subject, "The New Europe and Its Possibilities".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
