<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-15">May 15, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Big Protest Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-15">May 15, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A BIG PROTEST MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have already announced, the United States Senate passed one of the most drastic bills ever directed against immigrants, whereby the immigration law is to be made especially severe. The bill was introduced by Senator Root, and is now in the hands of the Congressional committee, by which it could easily be adopted. All southerners on the committee are obstinate enemies of immigrants, especially the socialist immigrants, and all of them will vote in favor of the bill. Protesting against this bill, in the same measure as the immigrant elements of all nationalities, are reasonable and prudent Americans.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) thus far has taken every step possible in opposition to this bill. A letter has been sent to the chairman of the Congressional committee, Congressman Fitzgerald of New York, who sent a very favorable reply to Prof. J. J. Zmrhal. The Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) also is doing its share in opposing this legislation. At a special meeting held last <pb facs="5418478_8_0053.jpg" n="2"/>Monday, in Libuse hall, by the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada, a resolutions committee was elected for the purpose of drafting a resolution committee was elected for the purpose of drafting a resolution protesting the proposed legislation, in the name of all Bohemians of Chicago. In Chicago there have been held several protest meetings which were participated in by representatives of all nationalities, and in which there was expressed an emphatic protest against such drastic enactments--an outgrowth of outlived know-nothingism. Such protest meetings have been held in Cleveland, Baltimore, New York, Philadelphia, Boston and Pittsburgh. Appeals have been sent to both Houses of Congress and to the President.</p>
   <p>The bill provides for the surrender, at the request of any government, of all political offenders who by word or letter have transgressed against their government; indeed, even those are to be surrendered who only inspired any such acts.</p>
   <p>Thus would be surrendered into the hands of governments, on request, every minor offender who had written a sharp article in opposition to a despotic government, or against government politics and a rotten system, or who might <pb facs="5418478_8_0054.jpg" n="3"/>advise anyone else to do so. Such a law is in the highest degree damnable in such a constitutional republic as is the United States, and must never come into effect; and it will not, if all nationalities take the proper steps in opposing it. Therefore it is our duty to rise as one man to oppose it, to do everything in our power, and to give a helping hand to the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada and the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday evening, a meeting will be held in the Auditorium, to which will come representatives of all nationalities for the purpose of adopting an emphatic protest, and to warn Congress against such errors as are a disgrace for a democratic state. It is therefore our duty to attend this meeting in as large numbers as possible, and we hope that our countrymen will not allow this invitation to remain unheeded. This meeting was called by the Immigrants Protective League, and participating will be distinguished leading citizens of the city and state. Nationally popular speakers have also been invited, such as W. J. Bryan, W. Wilson and former president T. Roosevelt, all of whom are opposed to the proposed legislation.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
