<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Two Guests</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR TWO GUESTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two highly esteemed men have arrived among us. Tonight they will be welcomed at the auditorium of Sokol Chicago. The meeting will be an occasion on which Czechoslovaks of Chicago will express their gratitude to France, our great sister republic.</p>
   <p>Our guests were sent to us by our brothers who now fight for our cause in Russia. They are representatives of the Russian branch of the Czechoslovak National Council. They are among us at the very moment when we are gaining a great diplomatic advantage in the recognition of our Czechoslovak Army in France as a compact military unit. This army guarantees the recognition of our right to an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>We want to proclaim openly our everlasting gratitude to France. We want to join <pb facs="5418478_8_0430.jpg" n="2"/>our guests in doing this. We want, at the same time, to promise our young Czechoslovak brothers fighting in Russia that we will co-operate and help them in the fight for the liberation of the Czechoslovak nation!</p>
   <p>Tonight, then, all Czechs and Slovaks, male or female, ought to be in the hall of Sokol Chicago! Let our dear guests, after their long journey from Siberia across the Pacific Ocean to America, be welcome again upon Czechoslovak ground! Let us great them wholeheartedly and with brotherly love! They have come to work among us, to awaken our feelings in a decisive moment, and to encourage us. We are to testify to the old Czech proverb that "What is united by hearts cannot be separated even by the ocean!"</p>
   <p>We are a virile part of the great patriotic movement of our nation, which is a great nation through the sacrifices of its sons and daughters in Czechoslovak lands and in Russia. Our sons and daughters who have given their blood and their <pb facs="5418478_8_0431.jpg" n="3"/>lives to save the Czechoslovak nation from destruction have given our nation hope for the future.</p>
   <p>Let us welcome those who represent both the ex-prisoners and the contributors of vast sums of money for our patriotic aims, while they themselves were in desperate circumstances. Those men and women paid the national tax joyfully and proudly with their blood and with their lives.</p>
   <p>All of you should welcome our brothers from far-away Russia today. All Czechoslovak volunteers are to assemble at the home of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs. From there the parade will proceed to the home of Sokol Chicago, South Kedzie Avenue near 23rd Street.</p>
   <p>Yesterday we had the pleasure of receiving the two guests at our offices. Zdenek Firlinger, captain on the staff of the Czechoslovak Army, and Editor Jan Jancek were introduced by Mr. Kubec, chairman of the Czechoslovak Committee on <pb facs="5418478_8_0432.jpg" n="4"/>Military Affairs, and by Mr. Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary of the Czech National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Captain Firlinger has a pleasant approach, and the bearing of a young warrior. Seven medals won for bravery adorn his chest. He will instantly arrest anyone's attention. It is obvious that he has experienced the severe discipline of war, and that he has attained his distinguished position by courage, intelligence, and extraordinary talent for the science of warfare. He was born in Olomouc, Moravia.....</p>
   <p>Our other guest, Jan Jancek, editor and writer, was born in Ruzomberk, Slovakia, and is a member of the branch of the Czechoslovak Council with headquarters in Russia.....</p>
   <p>All of us, Czechs and Slovaks, are expected to be at Sokol Chicago tonight. Welcome to our guests! </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
