<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE CZECHOSLOVAK CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ceskoslovenska Obchodni Komora, (Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce) of Chicago was founded to carry out the noble aim of cultivating mutual relations between commercial and industrial concerns in the old homeland and those of this country, through the medium of the Obchodni A Zivnostenska Komora v Praze (Chamber of Commerce and Industry of Prague) and various other chambers of Czechoslovakia. Among the members of this Czech Chicago institution there are a great many Czech businessmen. The Komora has already accomplished a great deal of meritable work, and deserves to be known better by everyone. To make this possible, but also to celebrate the happy return of all our Chicago countrymen who visited the old homeland this summer, the Komora has arranged a reception to be held on October 18....in the Pilsen Park pavilion, West 26th Street and Albany Avenue.</p>
   <p>The supper will be served by the ladies at 7 P.M. The names of these ladies are <pb facs="5418478_8_0132.jpg" n="2"/>a sufficient guarantee that the supper will be a first-class affair. After supper there will be an interesting program in which some of our foremost artists will participate, as for instance the well-known violinist, Mr. Jiri Hrusa, and the concert singer, Mrs. Marie Schnabl. There will be Antes, of Domazlice, and Miss Anna Lukes, of Prague. The Ludvikovo Divadlo (Frank Ludvik Dramatic Association) has augmented the program with a comic duet. There will be some speeches, each lasting about five minutes, by the representatives of the Komora and the returned members of the two expeditions to Czechoslovakia. Dancing will begin at 10 P.M.</p>
   <p>The admission, including supper, is $1.50. The tickets have already been mailed out, but additional ones may be obtained from the following: Mr. L. Solar, treasurer of the committee, 3215 West 26th Street; Mr. A. Schnabl, West 26th Street and Trumbull Avenue; and Mr. K. V. Janovsky, West 51st and Robey Streets. It is advisable that everyone secure his tickets at once, for the entertainment committee must know in advance how many places should be reserved for the supper. The committee....consists of Messrs. Karel V.Janovsky, <pb facs="5418478_8_0133.jpg" n="3"/>John A. Cervenka, Anton J. Cermak, J. A. Sokol, J. M. Kotek, Frank G. Hajicek, Louis Jalovec, Louis Solar, A. Laadt, William Hnatek, Josef Citta, I. F. Zetek, Sam Strobl, Rudolf Liska, and Mesdames A. Schnabl, Anna Zarobsky, Jennie Sistek, Emma Nikodem, Katerina Novy, Marie Hnatek, Josefina Beranek, and several others. It is up to every participant of either expedition to see to it that all tickets for the reception are sold. Let us all give a helping hand to the hard working committee so that this entertainment will meet with complete success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
