<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-30">Apr. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian-Slovak Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Korrespondencni Kancelar Svazu Cesko-Americkych Zurnalistu [Correspondence Bureau of the Association of Bohemian-American Journalists])</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-30">Apr. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN-SLOVAK QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Korrespondencni Kancelar Svazu Cesko-Americkych Zurnalistu [Correspondence Bureau of the Association of Bohemian-American Journalists])</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is certainly a most encouraging sign that Bohemian-Slovak unity is gaining understanding both in the Bohemian and in the Slovak public, and there is every indication that the Bohemian-Slovak question will be successfully solved shortly after the war. As a proof we submit an article from the Slovensky Dennik appearing in Budapest. It was published in the issue of March 28 and sent to us with a request that we disseminate it most intensively. We are glad to do this, and are forwarding the copies of the article particularly to the Slovak papers with whom we deal, knowing that other Slovak papers will publish it with an indication of its source:</p>
   <p>"The Slovak Question"</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0577.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Prague March 28--After the outbreak of the world war all activity in Hungary's internal politics stopped. There were no more articles discussing the Slavic nations of the Monarcky, and even the inter-Slavic relations between Austro-Hungarian Slavs have lost the interest of the readers. But the problems involved in these relations have remained unsolved.</p>
   <p>"Of course, we have been somewhat afraid to write what we have thought--there was the censorship. But perhaps we were more afraid than we should have been. Now all fear of censorship is waning, and the discussions of domestic political problems are engaged in freely. The great masses of our nation are coming to the conclusion that we shall not be annihilated by the war, that our cause has the best possible chance of success, and that our most daring hopes are not unjustified. And our thinking people, men who have been systematically working on their pet ideas, are now returning to them, and speak about autonomy, about the death of the denationalizing chauvinism, etc.</p>
   <p>"Now we wish to point out one thing. Our brother [that is, Bohemian] press <pb facs="5418478_8_0578.jpg" n="3"/>and public opinion over the River of Morava are growing very favorable to us. The love for the Slovaks and the understanding for Slovak affairs is increasing. The Slovak language has been put on the same level with the Bohemian. All Bohemian papers are printing Slovak articles. If I could explain all this more in detail and more thoroughly, and tell what a change there has been in the hearts and minds of our Bohemian conationals, the pessimists among us would be surprised, and our doubting Thomases would acquire faith. All Bohemian newspapers deal with Slovakia: [Article lists names of ten of the most important dailies, several weeklies, and some monthly magazines appearing in Bohemia and Moravia.] If they had enough Slovak editors and writers, no issue of a Bohemian paper or magazine would be without a Slovak article or a Slovak column. But unfortunately we have to admit that there are no Slovak authors; there is no intensive political and cultural life in Slovakia, and therefore there is nothing to write about, and nobody to write about it.</p>
   <p>"Over across the Morava, a great deal is being written about us. Perhaps not <pb facs="5418478_8_0579.jpg" n="4"/>all is original, not all quite true. But that does not matter. Many prominent writers now study the Slovak question. Soon we shall have many who will be helping us in our work, therefore many who will be helping us in our struggle. The war will speed up the emergence, if not the solution of our problems, both literary and cultural. But even so, we have decided to be optimistic, although we fail to do so clearly in many respects. The present war is based on co-operation of several powers on each side, and on the concentration of their efforts. Let us try and solve our Slovak question on the same principle; let us concentrate our effort too; let us be optimistic that it will be salved in the proper way."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The quoted article is in the Slovak, not Bohemian, language.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
