<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-04">May 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">We Are Austrians!</title><title level="a" type="sub">The United States Census Report Does Not Recognize Bohemians(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-04">May 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">WE ARE AUSTRIANS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">The United States Census Report Does Not Recognize Bohemians(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Eagerly we have waited almost two years for the report of the Government Census Bureau as to the result of the last general enumeration in order that we might learn therefrom how much we have increased in numerical strength here in Chicago and in the United States in general. But now the Census Bureau has grievously disappointed us! The Bureau has just recently published the results of the census for the State of Illinois, and in this report there is not the slightest mention of Bohemians. Slavonic immigrants are listed only according to the empires from which they came: Bohemians as Austrians, Slovenes as Austrians, Slovaks and Croations as Hungarians, Poles as Germans, Austrians, or Russians. To perpetrate an even worse injustice against the Slavs, the report differentiates between English Canadians and French Canadians; it shows how many immigrants are here from <pb facs="5418478_8_0064.jpg" n="2"/>Ireland, Scotland, and Wales--that is, from countries having even less political independence than Croatia or Bohemia.</p>
   <p>The method of enumeration used by the Census Bureau must be protested by all Slavs. Another report may be issued later which will show the number of immigrants of each nationality, but why are the Irish and Scots enumerated according to one rule in this report and the Slavs according to another?</p>
   <p>On the basis of these census reports, the local German newspapers arrive at their own conclusions and estimate the number of Germans in Chicago and in Illinois according to the figures given in the report. The census figures indicate that 133,201 residents in Chicago were born in Austria. The German newspapers claim that the majority of these are Germans. We think that the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) and the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) should see <pb facs="5418478_8_0065.jpg" n="3"/>to it that a report in which Bohemians and all other Slavs are correctly listed is published as soon as possible. During the census every Bohemian said he was born in Bohemia, not in Austria. Why, then, is Bohemia not even mentioned in the report issued by the Census Bureau? Why is only Austria listed?</p>
   <p>On the basis of the figures given in the census report, the Abendpost, in its issue of yesterday, deduced how powerful an element the Germans in this city and country are. This German paper figures that since 181,987 local residents were born in Germany, they are all Germans, and that the majority of the 133,201 born in Austria are also Germans. In this way it arrives at the joyful conclusion (for Germans) that the German element here is not diminishing, but on the contrary, is increasing.</p>
   <p>All this, as though it did not know that among the immigrants from Germany are listed many thousands of Poles who fled from the land of their birth before German cultural activities, and that very few immigrants come from <pb facs="5418478_8_0066.jpg" n="4"/>the old Austrian lands which are predominantly German, and when they do come they are Bohemians and Croatians from Vienna and Slovenes from Styria. Germans get along quite well in Austria. They are favored nationally and economically and have no reasons for migrating to America.</p>
   <p>In conclusion we introduce some of the figures of the census report which were most interesting to us. Chicago residents born in Austria number 133,201; Bulgaria, 321; French Canada, 4,633; Canada, 26,232; Denmark, 11,466; England, 27,890; France, 3,030; Germany, 181,987; Greece, 6,601; Holland, 9,632; Hungary, 27,497; Ireland, 65,922; Italy, 45,111; Norway, 24,170; Rumania, 3,344; Russia, 122,035; Scotland, 10,303; Serbia, 395; Sweden, 63,035; Switzerland, 3,493; Wales, 1,818.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
