<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-08-06">Aug. 6, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0983</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0983.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-08-06">Aug. 6, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An opportunity presented itself yesterday to the Bohemian population of this city to express their sincere gratitude and sympathy towards one of their eminent and well-known countrymen, the Rev. Joseph Molitor, who celebrated his 25th anniversary as a priest. His life presents, indeed, a part of the history of the development of Bohemian colonization in the United States.</p>
   <p>His arrival in Chicago in 1866 was of far-reaching importance to the development of Bohemian activity and Catholic religion locally as well as in the whole west. Sensing the truth that the school is the most effective means and its results most lasting for the cultivation and maintenance of desirable national characteristics and customs, he devoted to this branch of education of his countrymen his undivided attention and activity.</p>
   <p>As president of the Bohemian Literary Club of America he found ways and <pb facs="5418478_8_0984.jpg" n="2"/>means to have schoolbooks printed in the Bohemian language and to have children make use of them, thereby promoting their mental development. Since the Bohemian population increased steadily in this city, his activities along these lines were very successful. In 1866 only one Bohemian Catholic Church existed in this city, namely the Wenzel-Church, whose pastor is still Rev. Molitor; but today there are seven churches among a population of 75,000 people, in which services are held in the mother tongue; the children being taught same in their parochial schools.</p>
   <p>In view of these facts it was a well-deserved tribute of gratitude which was yesterday rendered to the honorable jubilee-celebrant. Not only Bohemian and Polish, German churches of this city sent their delegates to the festival, but they also came from Detroit, St. Louis, Cleveland, Milwaukee, etc.</p>
   <p>The sermon for the occasion was delivered by J. Kosidelka of Cleveland, who expressed with eloquent words what the audience felt toward the <pb facs="5418478_8_0985.jpg" n="3"/>guest of honor.</p>
   <p>After the church services a banquet was held in the school-house in which a considerable number of clergmen participated. The honored priest received toasts in seven different languages. Nearly all persons who come from the Slavonic countries of Austria-Hungary are able to speak the German language.</p>
   <p>The impressive celebration closed last night with a dramatic and musical performance before a large audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
