<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Great Moments for Czechoslovaks</title><title level="a" type="sub">T. G. Masaryk, Our Great Leader, Addresses the American Public</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-09">Oct. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT MOMENTS FOR CZECHOSLOVAKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">T. G. Masaryk, Our Great Leader, Addresses the American Public</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In reporting yesterday on the arrival of our great leader, Professor Thomas G. Masaryk, we pointed out that the English language local press is devoting more attention to this event than it did even when members of reigning houses visited our shores. In commenting on this fact, we declared that the regard shown for Professor Masaryk reflects, in a way, on our nation, and fills us with pride. But we are ever so pleased at the prominence given to our leader's visit, because he justly deserves it, and we concluded that Professor Masaryk's visit here is bound to become a period of spontaneous magnificence.</p>
   <p>Our prediction proved correct. The scenes of yesterday's celebration will surely not fade from the memory of our leader, and will remain in the recollection of all the participants, including the representatives of <pb facs="5418478_8_0289.jpg" n="2"/>foreign nations. The manifestations of love and reverence were certainly a surprise to him. With all his magnificent mental qualities and his personal significance, he has retained the mien of the plain man. He is unassuming, even shy, especially when appearing before large audiences. He rids himself of this bashfulness when he delves into the meaning of the cause for which he is battling, and for which he is ready to make any sacrifice, even that of his own life--he would not feel it too heavy upon his shoulders as long as it was dedicated to his principles. When he touches upon such sacrifice, his eyes begin to radiate his intrinsic determination and undauntedness, captivating every one in the audience.</p>
   <p>Officials of our local, county, State, and Federal governments, and throngs of Czechoslovaks, together with representatives of other nationalities, were assembled at the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad station when the train with Professor Masaryk aboard arrived at 9:00 A.M. yesterday. Among them were the arrangements committee, composed of the following members of the Czech National Alliance: Messrs. J. F. Stopina, F. G. Hajicek, Reverend V. Vanek, <pb facs="5418478_8_0290.jpg" n="3"/>Professor J. J. Zmrhal, Dr. L. Fisher, Dr. Pecival, Messrs. Vojta Benes, Lajers, and Lonek. The executive committees of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics and the Slovak League appeared in full strength. Among many Czechoslovak leaders we mention Congressman A. J. Sabath, Anton J. Cermak, and J. A. Cervenka.</p>
   <p>The train had scarcely come to a stop when members of the reception committee boarded the car in which Professor Masaryk was riding with his personal secretary, Mr. J. Cisar. Miss Olga Masaryk, a daughter, had not come along as her health is none too good. After a few words were exchanged with members of the committee, Professor Masaryk was photographed with members of the Czechoslovak Army, and also with Czech and American delegations. A brief interview was granted the press, and the party drove to the Blackstone hotel where our guest is stopping. After another few words for the press, everybody retired to let him enjoy a well-deserved rest. His secretary and two detectives remained.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0291.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Professor Masaryk and Dr. Hinko Hinkovic spoke in support of the Fourth Liberty Loan at a meeting in Power's Theater. Hinkovic, is a parliamentarian, representing Southern Slavs of Austria.....</p>
   <p>Professor Masaryk declared that while he was introduced as a professor and soldier, he wants to adhere to his capacity as a soldier, and as such, he must say that it is the duty of all American citizens to stand behind the Government and the President. This can be done by purchasing Liberty Loan bonds to the utmost of their capacity. In return they will receive a fair rate of interest for their investment.</p>
   <p>Speaking of the Czechoslovak Army, Professor Masaryk remarked tersely that he admired its soldiers for the fact that although they shed their blood and endured great hardships, they were content with wages of only 17 rubles [about $8.50] per month. They did not, as a matter of fact, receive their money until they arrived in Vladivostok, Siberia. These soldiers have, however, also made other heavy sacrifices.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0292.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When they got their money, totaling several hundred thousand dollars, they returned about seventy-five per cent of it to their commanders, for use in the movement for the liberation of the old motherland. This gift from the soldiers helped defray expenses for administration, propaganda, diplomatic representation, etc. The speaker emphasized that he did not obtain this information from personal observation, but from the admiring account by an officer of the Japanese Army, a sober and critical observer.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hinkovic followed as a speaker....advocating most earnestly a vigorous support of the Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>The band from the Great Lakes Naval Training Station played during intermissions. First Lieutenant Holy of the Czechoslovak Army was presented by Mr. Merrick, chairman of the meeting; he refrained, however, from addressing the throng, although he was enthusiastically received, which reception was meant, of course, for the commander in chief and the entire Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0293.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Both professor Masaryk and Dr. Hinkovic spoke on the outlook of the war in general. They agreed that although Bulgaria is eliminated from the scene of war, the struggle is by no means at an end. In Austria, the tool of Germany, the situation is the worst. Austria promises reforms which would, however, mean merely another form of oppression of small nations.... For the establishment of a permanent peace, it is necessary to down the German Government and dismember Austria altogether....The Austrian bridge must be destroyed, by means of a bulwark, an independent Czechoslovak state, created between Germany and the East, and a similar rampart in the South, i.e., a Yugoslovak republic.</p>
   <p>In the evening manifestation, which took place in the Auditorium Theater, the atmosphere was surcharged with an enthusiasm that has not been witnessed since the famous French Marshal Joffre with other members of the French mission was welcomed there. Czechoslovak, Allied and American flags were in abundance. A pleasant surprise was given by the presence of Italian soldiers--mountaineers--and a band from a Sardinian regiment. They were led by Italian officers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0294.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The latter were seated upon the platform, which was crowded with American and Czechoslovak guests, singers, the arrangements committee for the celebration, and speakers, [The centennial anniversary of the entry of the State of Illinois into the Union was the subject of the celebration.]</p>
   <p>The moment Professor Masaryk entered, the multitude burst into deafening applause and acclaim. Everybody rose. When this demonstration, which lasted a long time, had finally subsided, and all were in their places, the opening of this memorable manifestation took place.</p>
   <p>Three military bands alternated in playing the American, French, and Italian anthems, while the Italian soldiers stood guard of honor with rifles and bayonets presented. The Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (United Singers), under the direction of Mr. J. Houdek, sang "Kde Domov Muj" (Where my homeland is....), Czech national anthem. The audience rose in solemn attention and was visibly moved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0295.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Mr. Samuel Insull, head of the State Council of Defence, after stating the purpose of the celebration, called attention to the progress the State of Illinois has made since one hundred years ago, when it was taken into the Union. He continued in speaking of the Yugoslavs and Czechoslovaks, whom he showered with praise, and finally introduced Professor Masaryk.</p>
   <p>The guest of honor thanked Mr. Insull for the invitation to speak on this occasion, and chose "The Democracy of War" for the subject of his address. He first gave a definition, calling it the most ideal brotherhood, contrasting it with the autocracy of Austria and Germany. This gave the autocratic rulers the advantage and prestige of being designated by the church as rulers by divine right. Against this system the Allies pit democracy, so that this World War is, in essence, nothing else but a battle between German and American principles. American democracy is shown in the Declaration of Independence, which presents the best definition of democracy. This conception was grasped perfectly by the great Lincoln, <pb facs="5418478_8_0296.jpg" n="9"/>and is sustained by Wilson now, who promotes the principle of the liberation of mankind. President Wilson sets forth the actual quality of the nations, none of whom can be forced to live under a government that it does not want.</p>
   <p>Professor Masaryk also dwelt upon the conception of nationalism, which he declares, really does not interfere with social reforms, and should not be regarded in the same light as chauvinism. He mentioned Austria as an illustration. Much fighting is done there, all of it on the basis of nationalism. The small nations in Austria are proving, with nationalism as a background, that no nation can be termed small if it has enough strong adherents who know what to do.</p>
   <p>Masaryk also put the question, for what purpose do the Allies prosecute this war? For democracy and equal rights of nations. The fight is carried on for Belgium, Northern France, Alsace-Lorraine, Serbia, subjugated Poland, Bohemia, etc. The Czechs are fighting for the liberty for which <pb facs="5418478_8_0297.jpg" n="10"/>they have been fighting for centuries, and which was dear to their hearts long before America was discovered. Present American principles were in the hearts of the Czechs long before that time.</p>
   <p>The speaker pointed to Komensky, who also was a protagonist of democracy. He declared that he stands up for the Czechoslovak Army because it protests against autocracy not by words only, but by deeds as well. He thanked the American people for the sympathy shown for the oppressed nations. With an apology to others, Masaryk addressed the Czechoslovaks in the native tongue, reiterating that American principles are Czech principles which are shown in the best light here. He set forth the actions of the Czechoslovak soldiers in Russia, for whom death upon the battlefield amounts almost to a religious rite for the sake of the motherland and liberty. Not diplomats, but Czechoslovak soldiers were those who filled America with enthusiasm, and finally won the recognition of the entire world. The speaker closed with words in the English language, asking the audience to rise in <pb facs="5418478_8_0298.jpg" n="11"/>honor of those who have given their lives upon the battlefield, not only for our own liberty but also for that of future generations.</p>
   <p>The singers presented a choral, after which Professor J. J. Zmrhal read a message from the Czechoslovaks to the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>This closed the manifestation, which won new and favorable commendation for the Czechoslovaks. This was due to the efforts of our undaunted leader, Professor Masaryk.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
