<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-03-03">Mar. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Liberty at Their Meetings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-03-03">Mar. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERTY AT THEIR MEETINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, February 28th, the branch of the Croatian Unity "Matija Gubec" gave a public lecture entitled "Friends and Enemies of the Croatian People". The lecturer was Dr. Biankini. The lecturer requested all present to register as members of the branch, because it it sad - as he said - that in such a great Croatian settlement as Chicago, there are only twenty-five members.</p>
   <p>Of course anyone who registers as a member has to pay one dollar, otherwise he cannot become a soldier for the national cause.</p>
   <p>Ten munnutes were given to registration. Eleven registered. Then the lecture began. We bring just some excerpts from Dr. Biankini's lecture:</p>
   <p>"England went to war to defend international law and justice. If God grants it, Russia will occupy Constantinople. After the Allies are <pb facs="5418478_8_0625.jpg" n="2"/>victorious all Slavic nations will be united and form a Federative Union."</p>
   <p>"Russia is," said Dr. Biankini, "in social matters more perfect than any one civilized state."</p>
   <p>"In Russia public opinion was for war. Conservatives and liberals united for the defense of little Serbia."</p>
   <p>"The war is now between Germanism and Slavism. If there ever was, now is the time to unite and to shout, that other nations may know what we want."</p>
   <p>The lecturer proceeded in this tone glorifying Russia and abusing Austria.</p>
   <p>Of course, nobody knows what is meant by "liberation by Russia" and "unification of all Slavic nations."</p>
   <p>It seems the imagination of some people penetrated into special worlds, <pb facs="5418478_8_0626.jpg" n="3"/>which enables them to look upon Russia as a liberator.</p>
   <p>Russia is not willing to give freedom to anybody in her own lands how could she give it to others. In these dreams, just remember the Polish nation to see the "brotherly" love of Russia. Dr. Biankini accentuated that, at the meeting as the people may hear from every one of those present. But when Mr. Mijo Trcak wanted to tell his opinion, he was forbidden to talk because he is not a members that means he did not pay one dollar. At that meeting the right to speak cost a dollar. This method prevents anyone from contradicting those who pay a dollar. They are unanimous from the start.</p>
   <p>There was a commottion in the hall when Mr. Trcak was forbidden to speak.</p>
   <p>It seems that certain gentlemen fear freedom of speech, the more so when that furnishes the possibility that someone could be able to name and uncover the arch onemies of the Croatian nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
