<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-01">Oct. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas Gifts for Soldiers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-01">Oct. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS GIFTS FOR SOLDIERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czech and Slovak women: Our glorious Czechoslovak army in Siberia is daily surprising the entire world with its deeds of valor. It battles for our freedom, the independence of Czecho-slovak lands, and the creation of an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>Many of them, fathers of families, have been enduring the harsh life of a soldier for four years, submitting to sufferings and want, concomitant with warfare. They endure all of this for our sake, and for the security of our future.</p>
   <p>Christmas is approaching! Though used to the hardships of a soldier's life, our plucky boys will be in the snowbound Siberian plains, far from human dwellings and from their loved ones, without a thing to show that they are remembered by their folks at home or friends in their homeland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0302.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everyone will have thoughts of the relatives and friends whom he has had to leave behind. This will surely mean a sad Christmas for your lonely soldier!</p>
   <p>But lo and behold! He is not forsaken yet. There is the Czechoslovak woman from America to offer him a gift, with sincere, sisterly feeling. She does it with heartfelt words of friendship, encouragement, and hope.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Auxiliary of America, in agreement with military authorities, has decided to appeal to Czechoslovak women of America requesting everyone of them to prepare a gift for a soldier of the Czechoslovak army, so that our boys may, at least, be partly recompensed for the separation from their loved ones, and know that their brothers and sisters are trying hard to ease their burden.</p>
   <p>It was decided to ask our women to have 100,000 small bags ready by Thanks-giving Day. The gifts contained in them should be accompanied by a friendly letter. All satchels are to be uniform in size and pattern. They will be <pb facs="5418478_8_0303.jpg" n="3"/>forwarded early enough to arrive on Christmas Day.</p>
   <p>We hope there is not a single Czechoslovak woman in the United States who will not do her bit. Just think of how overjoyed your soldier boy will be when he receives your parcel, when he will be handling and fondling the things you sent, and when he will be reading and repeating the friendly words you wrote in the letter to him.</p>
   <p>About the satchel: Its shape can be seen in any substation of the Auxiliary of Czechoslovak women in the United States, where samples are on exhibition. We recommend the following articles as most fitting to be sent: towel, rubbing bag, handkerchief, shaving soap, washing and laundry soap, razor, toothbrush, tooth paste, writing paper and envelopes, pencil, knife, pipe, scissors, thread, pins, buttons, comb, shoelaces, tobacco, cigars, cigarettes, notebook, chocolate tablets, etc. The letter with the name of the lady should be enclosed.</p>
   <p>About 100,000 satchels will have to be prepared to accommodate all our soldiers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0304.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We will, therefore, need an effective organization. November 28 is the last day for receiving gifts, otherwise our gift may not arrive in time. Every Auxiliary office will have its allotment of work. The Czechoslovak National Council, 436 West 23rd Street, New York, will act as supreme supervisor of the entire activity.</p>
   <p>Some suggestions: Our women will be approached by our press. They are, however, expected to begin on their own account, and prepare a satchel in advance. Use good materials for the gifts which you intend to put into the satchel. In New York, and presumably in other cities also, there will be special depots where goods of the best quality can be bought in wholesale lots.</p>
   <p>The New York division of the women's Auxiliary is scheduled to furnish 15,000 satchels. Each district will be apportioned a certain number of satchels to furnish. We are certain that our women will do everything in their power to provide everyone of our soldiers with a satchel.</p>
   <p>For the auxiliary committee of the Czechoslovak National Council in New York--Mrs. L. Motak, Ethel J. Cabik.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
