<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-22">Oct. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">For a Czech Day in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-22">Oct. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FOR A CZECH DAY IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Tribune has not, until recently, paid the attention to Czechoslovak affairs that they truly deserve; the attention given to them by other local newspapers, and indeed by some of the foremost publications in the United States. Yesterday, however, the Tribune printed an editorial entitled, "A Bohemian Day," which takes a very sympathetic attitude to our cause:</p>
   <p>"The Tribune suggests that a day be designated on which greetings may be extended to the new Czechoslovak sister republic. No people deserve full independence more than the Czechoslovaks. Their heroism and devotedness to liberty, as well as their high level of intelligence, are a guarantee for their future progress."</p>
   <p>This simple and terse article is a manifestation of admiration, coming from the most exclusive strata of the American people, for the undaunted, heroic Czechoslovak nation. It must have made the heart of every sincere Czechoslovak throb <pb facs="5418478_8_0264.jpg" n="2"/>with joy, and awaken the wish that the Tribune's suggestion become a reality in the near future. We do not doubt for one moment that this wish will come true.</p>
   <p>We should like, at the same time, to call the attention of readers of the Denni Hlasatel to the rapid approach of a day of high significance for us. This will be the day of the [Czech] National Tax levy, as designated by the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, our two foremost national organizations. It will be held Thanksgiving Day, November 28, 1918.</p>
   <p>On that day, authorized representatives of the two organizations will call on every Czech and Slovak in the United States and Canada. They will appeal to your Czech national sentiment, to your heart, to your devotedness to the cause of liberty, and to your willingness to sacrifice. Receive them, therefore, as they truly deserve. They come in the name of our suffering nation, and <pb facs="5418478_8_0265.jpg" n="3"/>of its better future.  The first beams are now penetrating the horizon, which till now has been obscured.</p>
   <p>Let there be not one Czech who would so forget himself and his nation as to refuse to help! That would mean undying shame for his name. The rich people should contribute in proportion to their resources. Those in poorer circumstances should contribute at least one dollar to the National Tax. There are one million Czechs in the United States and Canada. They should donate one million dollars to their motherland which is now celebrating its rebirth and its glorious victory, which guarantee a better and happier future. Our people are engaged in a terrible struggle against terrorism and starvation. Our boys on the Russian front died, and are dying, for the liberty of their homeland. Our blood was shed on the battlefields of the Italian front, and our Czechoslovak Army in France is ready to shed its blood for liberty. We also have duties to fulfill. We have to accomplish something here that will be helpful to the ultimate liberation of our beloved homeland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0266.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Although liberty for the Czech nation is guaranteed, it has not yet become a fact. More sacrifices are needed, and our people must not weaken while making them. Money is needed constantly, and more may yet be needed, particularly for the fund for our political activities. That money, which was issued to Professor T. G. Masaryk by the United States Government, was not destined for our political fund, but for the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>More money was later issued to Professor Masaryk by the American Government, making in all the sum of $8,000,000 for the Czechoslovak Army. The sum of $5,000,000 was placed at his disposal as leader of our people, and is to be used for foreign business. War materials and other supplies are being purchased with the money issued for the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to contribute to this fund which is so important to us--the fund for political propaganda. It is for this fund that the National Tax will be levied on the Czechoslovak people in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0267.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>How to increase this fund has often been the subject of our speculation. This inspiration came from Eastern publications, i.e., from a proclamation by C. B. Wilson, mayor of Bridgeport, Connecticut. He depicted the sufferings of the Czechoslovak people under the tyranny of the Central powers, which lasted for centuries. He pointed out that the Czechoslovaks play an important part in the World War, and that one of the results of this struggle will be the liberation of that nation. He designated the week of September 16 to 21 as the week for a collection, the proceeds of which went to help the Czechoslovak cause. The quota set for this drive was $50,000. It was oversubscribed by $10,000. What the people of Bridgeport can do should be easily accomplished by the people of Chicago. A tag day could be held. The permit would be given by the State Council of Defense. The suggestion should be made by the city council. It should not come from Czechoslovak aldermen. The latter should do the preparatory work. American ladies who have acquaintance with the Council of Defense and the American Protective League might be requested to conduct the tag day activity. The collection would be handed to Professor Masaryk as a gift of American Chicago to the just and great cause of the Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0268.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This tag day might be extended to include all the states of the Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
