<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-22">Sept. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the Czechoslovak Auxiliary Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-22">Sept. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CZECHOSLOVAK AUXILIARY COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Numerous communications were received at last night's meeting in the hall of the Pilsen (Plzensky) Sokol. They all expressed gratitude for the beneficial work done by the Czechoslovak Auxiliary Committee for the relief of our soldiers and their families. These letters also contained words of encouragement for the continuation of that body's activities. The distribution of military forces over various fronts has brought about a division of work in the committee. In this way it becomes more evident where the burden of the relief work will fall. The committee also makes every effort to help our boys in the American Army, those in prison camps, and those unfortunates about whom the American Red Cross has sent us reports. In addition, there are many of our refugees who are in dire need of help. One cable from Vladivostok, Siberia, states that there are 20,000 refugees, among them 4,000 Czechoslovak children. Besides these, a Czechoslovak army is encamped there. To these, first of all, our help had to be extended. There are also wounded or sick soldiers of our own and Allied armies, and many from Tokio and Shanghai.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0310.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First information on these conditions came to the committee from Washington, and now Professor T. G. Masaryk is sending an appeal for aid. Physicians and nurses are needed. New York's Czech Auxiliary Committee is speedily organizing medical forces. It has placed forty women in hospitals for training, and many others are volunteering for service. Some are from Chicago and eight physicians from the Czech branch of the American Red Cross are also there.</p>
   <p>A very interesting communication has arrived from Paris, France. Sincere gratitude is expressed in it by the Czechoslovak colony, for the help extended by our committee to the sick and wounded Czechoslovak legionnaires, and to widows and orphans as well. This letter is to be published verbatim as a document of the committee's activities which started at the very beginning of the war, and are carried on under the sponsorship of the Czech National Alliance. The work is divided so that activities will neither impede each other nor overlap.</p>
   <p>Our work is to continue, and will have thorough supervision. An ambulance has been bought by us, and will be delivered to our soldiers in Vladivostok, Siberia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0311.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another ambulance may be bought for France and Italy, so that the great humanitarian institution, the American Red Cross, can see proof of our good will and readiness to sacrifice. If we wish to have the Red Cross help our soldiers, in one or another army, we have to show that we appreciate their help and are grateful for it.</p>
   <p>We are also in receipt of a report from the command at the Serbian front. It came from Saloniki, Greece, and states that the American Red Cross has helped the Serbian Red Cross by donating $50,000. This benefited a great many Czechoslovak soldiers, some of whom had been taken prisoner from the Austrian Army, while others had deserted. All of them offered to serve in the Allied armies. About 300 of them, under the command of Major Konrad, joined the Czechoslovak Army on the Italian front, while another 300, under Lieutenant Krystof, were sent to Cognac, France, to join the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>From the same source came thanks for books, magazines, and newspapers, provided mainly by the ladies' section of our committee. They are being sent by Brother <pb facs="5418478_8_0312.jpg" n="4"/>Vokral, secretary, and also by members of the Beseda Fric [another Auxiliary association in Chicago]. The parcels are sent to individuals in the various military camps here and across the ocean. Our boys in Vladivostok are receiving their gifts from us through the good offices of the French consul there.</p>
   <p>Some of the packages containing underwear, books, etc., did not arrive until a year after their mailing. Many sick prisoners who were in Serbia, but are in France now, were affected by this. Some of the largest boxes did not arrive at all. Evidently the ship had been torpedoed. This did not deter the committee from continuing their aid. Packages are arriving in good condition, as proved by acknowledgments of receipts and by letters of thanks.</p>
   <p>All our subcommittees should begin to prepare for Christmas and provide supplies of tobacco and other gifts. The Czech National Alliance and the Auxiliary are going to have conferences with the branches in Cleveland, Ohio. Mr. Stepina, who is heading the movement, has been presented by our ladies with an artistically embroidered pillow with an American emblem, as a token of appreciation, and <pb facs="5418478_8_0313.jpg" n="5"/>also of encouragement for the hard task which he has undertaken. Delegates for the Cleveland conference have already been appointed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
