<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-31">July 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Hlasatel Investigates Sensational Rumor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-31">July 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HLASATEL INVESTIGATES SENSATIONAL RUMOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, we printed a news item, which stated that Miss Milada Jarusek of New York city had been sentenced to death in Vienna, Austria, having been charged with espionage. The New York Tribune, in yesterday's issue gave further details. It said, "When Miss Jarusek was sent to Austria by the Czech National Alliance, she traveled on the same ship with Count Bernstorff, formerly German ambassador to the United States. As a governess in Count Seckendorff's family, she had made the acquaintance of Bernstorff and some other prominent Germans. She had won their confidence. For this reason the Czech National Alliance decided to send her to Austria on the same ship with Bernstorff; there she was to investigate the attitude of the Czechs, and their representatives in parliament, to the proclamation of an 'Independent State of Czechoslovakian lands'."</p>
   <p>Information to this effect was supplied to the New York Tribune, the newspaper says, by Milada Jarusek's brother, who is none other than <pb facs="5418478_8_0370.jpg" n="2"/>Slavomir Kratochvil, whose real name is Slavomir Jarusek, who still lives in New York. He further stated to the Tribune that he had received news from his sister from Halifax, to the effect that Bernstorff was pessimistic in his attitude toward the war, and hoped for a peace with the United States through the mediation of Denmark. Before this, however, she had told him of a conversation which she had overheard, wherein Bernstorff predicted the full success of the German U-boat warfare.</p>
   <p>This was the Tribune's story. Another item is printed in yesterday's issue of the Evening American; the story is by the New York correspondent, and states that the New York Czechs and Slovaks are very much disturbed over the report that Miss Jarusek has been sentenced to death for espionage in her native land. This shows that Austrian spies are working in New York and deceived Miss Jarusek, after having suspected her brother for several months. The New York Czechs and Slovaks, so the report states, will have to take some steps in the matter immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0371.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Denni Hlasatel, in search of authoritative information, went to the Czech National Alliance, whose headquarters are in Chicago, and questioned Mr. Vojta Benes, school teacher, organizer of the Czech National Alliance, and, at present, also its secretary. We were greatly surprised to learn that the Czech National Alliance has never had any contact with Miss Jarusek, such as would have been necessary in a matter of such significance. He does not know the girl, and no one in Chicago does either. All Mr. Benes can remember is that the afore-mentioned Slavomir Kratochvil once asked him in New York to help his sister find a job. Just what kind of a job the girl wanted to get through the mediation of her brother, Mr. Benes cannot recall.</p>
   <p>This sudden turn in the aspect of the affair compels the Hlasatel to view the authenticity of the reports with the utmost reserve, and with an attitude of watchful waiting for further developments. Realizing the full significance of the matter, we investigated, as was our duty, for the sake of our readers, in order to let them know what the National Alliance itself had to say.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
