<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-27">Dec. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Truth about Conditions in Bohemia and in Prague</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Call to Bohemian-Americans for Help (From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-27">Dec. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRUTH ABOUT CONDITIONS IN BOHEMIA AND IN PRAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Call to Bohemian-Americans for Help (From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The news about conditions in the Bohemian lands has afforded us a very incomplete picture of the true situation. Recently we witnessed the dissemination of news of such a fantastic nature that it led Bohemian America to the most erroneous conclusions and generated a multiplicity of false combinations and suppositions. This uncertainty was not, we are sure, of any benefit to the cause which is so dear and sacred to us all; but we are just as certain that it has not for a minute deprived us of our faith in our nation's firm and confident facing of its future. We never believed the reports which were calculated to show the Bohemian nation as uniformly loyal to Austria, and we shall never believe any of the Austrian official <pb facs="5418478_8_0633.jpg" n="2"/>press bureau's reports of manifestations of Austrian loyalty in Prague.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, we have anxiously awaited the first news from the old country that would tell us more than the Prague newspapers or the insipid, colorless letters that have been reaching us here--news that would enable us to fathom the import of history-making events whose scene is laid in the old country.</p>
   <p>We have to admit that it was quite impossible to contact our friends in Bohemia during the very first period of the war, and that it is still rather difficult. But the fact remains that we have now received the first detailed and reliable reports about the spirit prevailing in Bohemia and about events of the last few months of this hapless year.</p>
   <p>That news is of such importance that it would be read by all of the <pb facs="5418478_8_0634.jpg" n="3"/>Bohemian-American people and the appeal for help which it contains should deeply stir the hearts of all of us.</p>
   <p>This news was sent to Editor Joseph Tvrzicky for the proposed newspaper, Ceska Amerika (Bohemian America) and forwarded to the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) for publication, together with other valuable information and letters. All this will be published in the near future.</p>
   <p>Prague, November 15, 1914.</p>
   <p>"I should be writing a very, very long letter if I tried to tell you all that is going on in Bohemia--all that has been happening here from the beginning of the war; what is being born; what is smoldering; and what is <pb facs="5418478_8_0635.jpg" n="4"/>being prepared; what our political leaders are thinking about; what the hearts of the hundreds of thousands of our soldiers beat for, soldiers who go to death for the sake of liberty.....</p>
   <p>"No doubt our dear Bohemia is again a country in which the lava of historical events is boiling under an artificial, calm surface. The hearts of the people are filled with the highest achievement of civilization: Liberty. They all sense that what has been hidden for centuries in the most intimate hopes and desires and memories of the Bohemian people and its best men is bound to push through--now or nevermore--in the form of a gorgeous blossom of a new life, life born of soil soaked in blood; that it is bound to materialize in a glorious call of the true, proud, and free humanity, which is our historical heritage.</p>
   <p>"Our dear overseas countrymen! We know that you are working for your <pb facs="5418478_8_0636.jpg" n="5"/>native country, that your ties of love, hope, and devotion with your native country have perhaps never been as strong as they are now! Keep on, persevere, work for all you are worth. The victory of your native country will be your own victory! Let the whole world see that we deserve liberty, that we know how to achieve it by love, by work, by struggle. Do not lose confidence in your country and your people abroad! Do not be misled by our calm, because it is a calm before the storm, the calm of a powerful hero who has been ambushed and fettered, but who now gathers breath and flexes his muscles for the decisive effort that will make him free.</p>
   <p>"I do not have to repeat the denial of all the fantastic news about bloody riots in Prague, about the ruins of the St. Guy Cathedral, the National Museum, of all the historical landmarks. They are as false as the report that Klofac [National Socialist party leader and deputy], Kramar [Young Bohemian party leader and deputy], Masaryk [Realist Party leader and deputy], and others have been shot....."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0637.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>[There follow two columns describing the baiting of Bohemians in Prague by Germans and Jews, attempts at provoking them to rioting, false manifestations of Bohemian loyalty put up by German students and Jewish store employees, etc. Also there is a true story of two battalions of the Infantry Regiment No. 28 which was being recruited from Prague and which did riot, in fact, threatening to shoot their officers when the battalions were being entrained for the front.]</p>
   <p>"It is a great fight, our dear countrymen in America, and we can hardly expect to achieve a complete victory without your help....."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
