<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-29">Mar. 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Appointed as Principal of a School.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-29">Mar. 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN APPOINTED AS PRINCIPAL OF A SCHOOL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2, col. 3.. The school board has appointed a Bohemian, Dr. K. J. Lunak to the position of principal of the Goodrich Public School, located at Jefferson and 14th Streets. His appointment will become effective at the start of next week. It will be of interest to Bohemians of Chicago to know that Dr. K. J. Lunak attained this high ranking position through his ambition to better his social standing and the perseverance to reach his goal.</p>
   <p>He is the son of J. V. Lunak,who is the secretary of the grand lodge of C. S. P. S., a Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Society in St. Louis, a well known national Bohemian organization. Dr. K. J. Lunak was educated in a public school in Cleveland, Ohio, later moving to Kewaunee, Wisconsin, where he attended a public high school. He then taught in the public school of that town for several years, but the longing for better education brought him to Oshkosh, Wisconsin, where he studied at the normal college. He was an outstanding student there, making it possible to complete his course in less time than it usually requires.</p>
   <p>He then returned to Kewaunee, Wisconsin, to teach in a high school and in a <pb facs="5418478_8_0964.jpg" n="2"/>short time was appointed its principal. However, he longed for a big city like Chicago, so he came here and took the examination for principals of public schools. Of the 122 candidates who participated in the examination, five were passed as having the necessary qualifications. Dr. K. J. Lunak was one of those five, rating third among them.</p>
   <p>In his spare time he studied to be a doctor and passed his studies successfully. He will be indeed a valuable asset to the public school system of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
