<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-07">Feb. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Hlasatel and Sabath Prevent Deportation </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-07">Feb. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">HLASATEL AND SABATH PREVENT DEPORTATION </title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 3--Our fellow-countrymen Joseph Ocenasek was to be deported yesterday. He had come from Bohemia to Join his relatives in Racine, Wisconsin, but was detained on Ellis Island by the immigration authorities. They decided to deport him for two reasons: first, a somewhat abnormal eye, and second, lack of the required funds. But Ocenasek is a trained machinist and in perfect condition for work, so that there is no probability that he will become a public charge.</p>
   <p>He has received permission to remain through the efforts of Congressman, Adolph J. Sabath, and his relatives are spared the trouble of taking further steps to effect his release.</p>
   <p>To bring his case to a happy conclusion, however, it will be necessary for some one to extend to him pecuniary assistance so as to enable him to produce the amount required by law. He must also present a sworn statement by responsible people, such as his relatives, guaranteeing to support him in case he should fail to do so himself. This affidavit must be sent to Ellis Island.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The immigrant in question has a good friend in Racine, Mr. Frank Proska, who upon learning of his plight instantly sent a telegram to Washington, offering to shoulder all responsibilities. Our immigration authorities, who have become rather haughty of late, completely ignored the communication, and the deportation of Ocenasek was imminent. Proska thereupon addressed himself to the Denni Hlasatel, and our management promptly wired to Congressman Sabath, then in Washington, whose firm intervention caused the authorities to change their attitude and saved Ocenasek in the nick of time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
