<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Voice of Warning from Bohemia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A VOICE OF WARNING FROM BOHEMIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day before yesterday, our banker, Mr. James F. Stepina, received a card from a prominent political leader in Bohemia about whom a great deal has been written not only here, but also in the old country. The card contains a few words which Bohemian America should bear in mind in all its undertakings.</p>
   <p>This leader expressed to Mr. Stepina in private the wish that Bohemian America would avoid all hasty actions in these unsettled times and refrain from any possibility of incriminating certain personages in the old country by mentioning their names in the press us being connected with any undertaking or any organization in America. We added that hasty action is more likely to damage than to improve the situation in the old country. He advises extreme sagacity and caution, because every, even the least conspicuous, movement finds its way from Bohemian America to the old country and <pb facs="5418478_8_0696.jpg" n="2"/>could have most catastrophic results, not for American Bohemians, but for all the Bohemians in Austria, especially, however, for its leaders.</p>
   <p>We have not read the whole card. Only a part of its contents has been intimated to us by Mr. Stepina, who has asked us to keep it to ourselves. But just because we are so concerned in preventing anything that could affect the conditions in the old country in a detrimental way, we have decided to publish at least the gist of what we have been told, knowing that Mr. Stepina will not mind, because he himself shares the same aim as we do.</p>
   <p>All we care about is that the best possible conditions prevail in the old country, and that we help the old country as much as we can. Therefore, we believe that utmost perspicacity and deliberation must be the principal features of any action we may wish to undertake.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0697.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For the time being, we should do nothing else but convince the old country that we Bohemians stand behind it financially, that we are with the people in the old country heart and soul, and that we are ready to dig deep into our pocketbooks in order to give assistance where assistance is needed. And such aid is needed now throughout the Bohemian lands, where misery, hunger, and despair lurk behind the doors in order to get into their grasping claws those in particular them husbands, sons, or fathers, dead of wounded in the war, have left helpless......</p>
   <p>Therefore, let us keep on collecting and be proud of doing our patriotic duty. Much, very such money will be needed. But let this be all we care about. Everything else should be left to these who are more competent and better authorized to act, are intimately acquainted with local conditions and requirements. There are leaders both in the old country and here who know what is and what will be their duty. Let us and not bother about them; <pb facs="5418478_8_0698.jpg" n="4"/>let us leave then alone, because otherwise we may cause damage; we could damage great nation is the all country which are its only hope, only protection, only refuge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
