<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-04">Nov. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"Liberty of Europe Imperfect Without Czechoslovak Independence"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-04">Nov. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">"LIBERTY OF EUROPE IMPERFECT WITHOUT CZECHOSLOVAK INDEPENDENCE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Journal pays more attention to our national affairs than any other paper in our city. In last night's issue it printed an editorial about the recent events in the Austrian parliament concerning the latest report of a German-Austrian victory in Italy, which was received by the Czech representatives with deadly silence.</p>
   <p>The article in the Journal states that the news about the occurrence came by wire from Switzerland. The telegrams stated that the first official news of the victory was presented to the members of the parliament, who were invited to show their elation. The German members did, but the Czechs and Slovaks remained silent. Few of the others responded, for three-fifths of the population hates its German-Hungarian rulers. Despite this fact, the Journal points out, the feeling of the Czechoslovaks has never before been exhibited so openly and daringly. Their courage and political maturity have made them a mighty unit with which it will be advisable to reckon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0445.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Europe will be neither united nor safe if Czechoslovakia does not win its independence. Thus the editorial concludes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
