<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Letter from Bohemia to Our Friends and Enemies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0656</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0656.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKY POMOCNY VYBOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Letter from Bohemia to Our Friends and Enemies</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of all our intensive informative work, many of our countrymen are not sufficiently aware of the great task which the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor (Bohemian Slavonic Auxiliary Committee) has undertaken, and toward which it is and will be working with great diligence. This fact is evident from replies we have been receiving from various societies, lodges, and associations to our letters requesting their financial and moral support. We are therefore, again publishing information that will, we hope, make our aims and objectives clear.</p>
   <p>Money collected by the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor is destined to help the Bohemian nation in these difficult times--specifically, to alloy the misery and need which is already apparent in Bohemia, need and misery which will become appalling later on when present stocks and supplies are exhausted. As Bohemians, and as men and humans, we have a sacred duty to help our kin. If any one of us <pb facs="5418478_8_0657.jpg" n="2"/>is helping his own relatives, that fact does not liberate him from the duty of helping the whole nation and the masses of those who have nobody to take care of them, our co-patriots in the old country who may be in the greatest need now, and whose distress will certainly be more pronounced in the near future. To care just for oneself and one's own family and own relatives is nothing but selfishness and shows an utter lack of national feeling.</p>
   <p>Even if it may be impossible for us to give a great deal to our country in these bad times, it must be expected that everybody will give at least something, no matter how little it may be. Every society, lodge, association, club, and every individual should prove by at least a small donation that there is compassion and charity, love and patriotism in his heart.</p>
   <p>The money should be sent to the American State Bank, 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago. The bank keeps minute track of all our money, and one of its officers, Mr. O. Vasak, is our treasurer. Each donor is given an individual receipt for <pb facs="5418478_8_0658.jpg" n="3"/>his contribution, and once a week the donations are publicly receipted in the newspapers. If any name has been inadvertently omitted from these public receipts, please let us know by post card, and we shall be glad to rectify the error. The bank pays interest on the money we deposit. No salaries or expenses are being paid from this sum except current bills for postage, printing, and such necessary expenditures which the actual work in our office requires. Therefore, all the money collected will be turned over to the purpose for which it was donated. Every Bohemian has the right to look over our books during the bank's business hours.</p>
   <p>Dr. Josef Scheiner, president of the Ceska Obec Sokolska (Bohemian Sokol Community) informs us by letter that he will be glad to help us in distributing the money. He thanks us on behalf of the Bohemian nation, and especially appreciates the fact that the Bohemians of America are showing their love for their home country now during more critical days than we ever could have dreamed of before. He has great faith and we hope with him that our countrymen here will not <pb facs="5418478_8_0659.jpg" n="4"/>disappoint his and our expectations.</p>
   <p>For the Cesko-Slovansky Pomocny Vybor, J. V. Nigrin, secretary; James F. Stepina, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
