<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-19">Apr. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Karel V. Janovsky Upbuilds Czech Settlement.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-19">Apr. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">KAREL V. JANOVSKY UPBUILDS CZECH SETTLEMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The district of Town of Lake, densely populated with Czechs, owes its rapid development to several men, among whom is one of the best-liked and hard-working men. In business he is scrupulously honest. He is Karel V. Janovsky.</p>
   <p>His endeavor has not only placed him among the first men in his district, but also in the business and social world of our city.</p>
   <p>Mr. Janovsky was born on January 27, 1876, in Blatna, Bohemia. He went to school in his native town, and at the age of thirteen emigrated from Bohemia to follow his elder brother who had settled in Chicago, and took quarters in the district of Town of Lake. He first worked in some industrial plants, and in 1891 worked as a typesetter for the Chicagske Listy Chicago Newspaper]. After its downfall, he opened a printing shop with <pb facs="5418478_8_0891.jpg" n="2"/>his brother, Bohumil. He conducted the business with a short interruption until the War between Spain and the United States started. In this struggle, Karel V. Janovsky enlisted in the ranks of Uncle Sam. In those times, he became very well known to many of our readers who anticipated with much interest his desccriptive articles sent regularly from Key West to the Denni Hlasatel. He returned to Chicago at the close of the War, and engaged in studies in the Athaenia, and in a Y. M. C. A. law course.</p>
   <p>Mr. Janovsky married Miss Mary T. Kleker. His activities at that time included regular reporting for the Denni Hlasatel. His enterprise prompted him to add to his business an office of notary public and real estate affairs. His honesty and efficiency raised his standing as a man of business to a high level. He has been heading his real estate office up to the present at 1642 West Forty-Seventh Street, this location will be changed shortly to 1957 West Fifty-first Street. His residence is 5043 <pb facs="5418478_8_0892.jpg" n="3"/>South Western Boulevard, where he lives in happy wedlock with his wife. His aged, but still lively father, Mr. Vaclav Janovsky, also lives with him.</p>
   <p>The development of the Town of Lake district he managed to achieve by means of five sub-divisions which he sold to his fellow-countrymen, all of whom are still residing there, most of them fairly prosperous.</p>
   <p>Mr. Janovsky soon recognized the important part which the Czech-American Aid Societies played in the national and economic life of the settlers. He not only became an ardent worker for them, but he founded two, and in one of these he held the office of secretary for a long time. Credit is due him in the growth of the settlement, for he never skimped with his valuable advice which he gave gratis. Many a poor and helpless family can bear out this assertion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0893.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>No wonder Mr. Janovsky's popularity is growing by leaps and bounds when one considers that he has given so much of his time to social and national organizations. Today, there is hardly one of them of which he is not a member, and of which he has not been an officer at one time or the other. He had been a vice-president in the Bohemian Charitable Association, of the Old People's Home, and the Orphanage. He also became a member of the Sokol at the time of the world's Fair, and an extremely active one, at that.</p>
   <p>It is meet to mention that Mr. Janovsky has been taking a lively part in political life and that he has everywhere shown himself a protagonist of the right of personal liberty, of American principles, and a staunch adherent of Czech national interests.</p>
   <p>The vicissitudes of life have not always had roses in store for Mr. Janovsky. He struggled bravely against adversities and won out, thereby <pb facs="5418478_8_0894.jpg" n="5"/>giving a concrete example to our adolescents who ought to make his ideals their own: righteousness and the joy which comes with work for the interests of mankind, and of one's nationality, in particular.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
