<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-20">Jan. 20, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Oldest Living Person in Chicago Is a Czech</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-20">Jan. 20, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLDEST LIVING PERSON IN CHICAGO IS A CZECH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Anna Burian, living at 4948 South Seeley Avenue, according to the results thus far of the census taken by the United States government, is the oldest living person in Chicago. This grand old lady asserts that she is 103 years old. John J. Gaynor, director of the census in the district of Chicago, announced yesterday that according to the previous results of the census, Mrs. Burian is the oldest person thus far reported. Mrs. Burian lives with her nephew, Mr. Vaclav Lhotak. The census collector, who registered this oldest person in our city is Mrs. Minnie Slesinger.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Burian stated that she was born in Bohemia in 1816, and immigrated to the United States in 1875. This, repeatedly, is a proof, "how sound the Bohemian root is." Mrs. Burian, in fact, is almost 104 years old, because around Easter holidays she will complete that year, and is strongly convinced that this will not be her last birthday celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0871.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For forty years, she had lived with her husband, and during the last forty years, she has been a widow. She enjoys good health, all the senses serve her well, except her eyesight, which is growing weak. She is the mother of six children. Mrs. Burian, like almost all elderly women born in the old country, indulges in drinking beer moderately, and cannot understand why this privilege has been forbidden by the prohibition act. </p>
   <p>Mrs. Burian is an argent reader of the Bohemian newspapers, and follows very closely all the public questions which are to be settled. She is also convinced that women should not mingle in politics, but should devote all of their time to their homes and families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
