<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-30">July 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Distinguished Guests</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-30">July 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DISTINGUISHED GUESTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Garden City was host to a distinguished guest yesterday. Colonel Vladimir Hurban of the Czechoslovakian Army stopped in Chicago for a few hours, on his way from Vladivostok, Siberia, to Washington, D. C., to deliver his report on the situation to Professor Thomas G. Masaryk. The visitor comes from our Czechoslovakian Army, to which the world press refers as "the marvel of history," which rescued the city of Vladivostok, and itself, in self-defense, from the claws of Bolshevism.....Colonel Hurban came from San Francisco accompanied only by two aides. He was not expected here, not even in the headquarters of the Czech National Alliance, where he called shortly after twelve noon. The officials made all possible, albeit hurried arrangements to insure a dignified welcome for the Colonel from the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League. Their representatives, and those of the press, gathered quickly to hear the Colonel's account of his adventures and experiences--as much as he deemed fit to disclose. Our guest is tall and wiry. His features do not show any signs of the strain and hardships he has <pb facs="5418478_8_0373.jpg" n="2"/>had to endure.</p>
   <p>Colonel Hurban handed each of those present a document stating the purpose of his mission in Washington. We had to content ourselves with what this document contained, but we were told a few very interesting things during the conversation.</p>
   <p>The Colonel declared that he himself no longer has any military distinction whatsoever because the part of the Czechoslovakian Army that is now in Vladivostok, is about to go to France, there to join the other part of the Czechoslovakian Army. He is simply going to join the others, if necessary as an ordinary private..... The Czechoslovakian Army in Siberia hopes to get to France via the United States. There are about 15,000 men. They feel confident that on their way through the States, they will find Czechs in America doing their sacred duty toward the motherland.</p>
   <p>The Colonel spoke very little of himself. A smile crept upon his lips, however, <pb facs="5418478_8_0374.jpg" n="3"/>when he told of half a dozen San Francisco newspapers, each of which had written about him. They came out with an elaborate personal interview supposedly granted by him the day before. He himself had gone to bed immediately after his arrival. His aides slept in his room. These interviews allegedly granted by him were nothing but pure fiction.</p>
   <p>The Colonel left Chicago at 4:30 P.M. Many prominent Czech leaders of Chicago went to the depot with him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
