<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czechoslovak People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECHOSLOVAK PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hearts of the Czechoslovak people of this country are filled with joy today. We stand before the flag of this glorious Republic in deep emotion, bowing our heads in deepest reverence and love for our President, Woodrow Wilson.</p>
   <p>The Government, through Secretary of State R. E. Lansing, has proclaimed the independence of the land of our fathers. It recognized the Czechoslovak National Council as the provisional government of Czechoslovak lands and gave the proclamation into the hands of our beloved leader, the venerable Professor T. G. Masaryk.</p>
   <p>We are hailing, in this glorious, historical action, the greatest day for Czechoslovak-Americans in the history of this Republic. Our eyes are filled with tears, and our tongue does not find words suitable to express the deep <pb facs="5418478_8_0344.jpg" n="2"/>feeling that surges through our hearts.</p>
   <p>From the grave of the past there rises the newly born Czechoslovak nation from which we came; the nation of our forefathers who peered into the future for fully three hundred years visioning, but vainly expecting--liberation.</p>
   <p>After days of utter oblivion, after years of want and shame, after centuries of suffering and misery, the hour of liberation is approaching. The words of our great Jan Amos Komensky, which reverberate over our lands like the peal of a bell, are coming true: "I too believe in the Lord, and that after the storms of ill will, brought upon our heads by our sins, are over, thou wilt again rule thy own destinies, Oh my Czech people!"</p>
   <p>Our land will be free again. We have worked for four years for the nation from which we came. We followed Thomas G. Masaryk, whose name is dear to us, and will be still dearer to the coming generations of our nation. We followed his footsteps over broad unplowed acres into which he sank his shovel plow. In <pb facs="5418478_8_0345.jpg" n="3"/>sweat and white heat, in hope and despair, that is how we staggered through grievous days. But our love of freedom could not be shaken, and neither could our firm belief that the day would come for which we had been waiting--the day of liberation and victory.</p>
   <p>That day has come, for America, which is our homeland, has done what it could not have failed to do: It drew the sword--justly--for the freedom of the oppressed nations, and, therefore, also for our own nation. We were not disappointed in placing trust in America, just as the democratic world will not be disappointed by its president--Woodrow Wilson.</p>
   <p>America is our fatherland. Reiterate your vow on July 4--repeat the pledge we gave to the flag of this Republic. Let us promise to devote our work to her, make sacrifices for her, and give her everything we possess. Whenever she calls on us, the Czechoslovak people will rally under her banner, determined to make sacrifices--and she is worthy of them.</p>
   <p>Czechoslovak people: May all Czechoslovak hearts be aglow with the purest joy <pb facs="5418478_8_0346.jpg" n="4"/>over this solemn recognition, and jubilate all over this Republic. Let the American people see the gratitude which fills your hearts by gathering in large camps and meetings next Wednesday. This should be observed wherever Czechoslovaks live.</p>
   <p>We greet the leader of the Czechoslovak nation, T. G. Masaryk, commander of our heroic Czechoslovak army. We pledge our loyal support in this hard task, till the end of the troublesome days.</p>
   <p>We believe more than ever before in a victory for the Czechoslovak nation. Fate does not want the Czechoslovak people, or its future generations, to perish.</p>
   <p>Liberty for the Czechoslovak people grows out of humiliation and oppression, starvation and blood, sacrifices by Czechoslovak sons, who suffered on the banks of the Vltava and the Vah and died on the banks of the Marne, in Poland, on the plains of Siberia, in the snow-covered Alps--out of a sea of tears and sacred hopes, which fortified the Czechoslovak people in the immense struggle <pb facs="5418478_8_0347.jpg" n="5"/>of mankind--out of love for their motherland shown by children of America--out of the glorious strength of Thomas Garrigue Masaryk and his faithful co-workers, out of the Czechoslovak soil, soaked with the tears and the blood of our forebears and consecrated with their ashes--out of the whispering and rustling of the woods and orchards,--out of the deep mysteries which lie in the streams of our old homeland,--out of songs and the truth and our rights for which the sons of America, too, are shedding their blood.</p>
   <p>Czechoslovak America, devoted to truth, faithful to the Stars and Stripes, loyal to its president, Woodrow Wilson, greets today a new and bright future for the Czechoslovak State.</p>
   <p>Bohemian National Alliance:</p>
   <p>Dr. L. J. Fisher, chairman.</p>
   <p>Vojta Benes, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0348.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Reverend Ino Kestl, chairman.</p>
   <p>Fr. Sindelar, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
