<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The American-Czechoslovak Commercial Expedition to Czechoslovakia</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three-column-eighth of a page, picture of the committee of the expedition.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN-CZECHOSLOVAK COMMERCIAL EXPEDITION TO CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three-column-eighth of a page, picture of the committee of the expedition.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American-Czechoslovak commercial expedition to Czechoslovakia will leave Chicago one week from next Thursday, that is, on May 4, 1922 at 10 P. M.  The expedition will leave from the Dearborn Station by a special train of the Wabash Railroad Company. There will be about 260 participants who will wish to visit their liberated homeland, to visit the places of their birth, and to view the historical places of Czechoslovakia. Some of them will wish to establish business relations with that country. A preponderant number of them are American citizens. These will leave by a special train as indicated above. The aliens will have to leave a day earlier, and will be accompanied by several members of the committee who will facilitate their arrival in New York, and their embarkation. The members of the expedition who are citizens of the <pb facs="5418478_8_0174.jpg" n="2"/>United States will arrive in Hoboken, New Jersey on Saturday May 6, 1922, and since they will arrive at an early hour they will be permitted to remain in their Pullman cars until 7 A. M. They will then repair to the dock and embark on the steamship "George Washington".</p>
   <p>The "George Washington" will weigh anchor at noon, and will probably arrive in Bremen on May 16, 1922. The expedition will depart from Bremen on the following day and arrive in Prague on May 18. A performance of Bedrick Smetana's Bartared Bride" will be given in the Narodni Divadlo (National Theater on Saturday, May 20. Those who signified their intention to attend the opera and to reserve their rooms in the hotels at Prague, will be taken care of accordingly as indicated on the circular sent to them by the secretary of the expedition. Those who have not yet done so, are asked to signify their intention at once, otherwise they would have to attend to their reservations personally.</p>
   <p>The committee has thus far projected only one joint trip to Plzen (Pilsen) and to Domazlice and Sumava (Bohemian forest). After this trip the members of the <pb facs="5418478_8_0175.jpg" n="3"/>expedition will disband, but meet again in Prague on the Fourth of July to attend a celebration of the American Independence which will most probably take place on Zofin [an island on the river Moldan.] It is expected that about one thousand Americans, who at this time reside in Czechoslovakia, will attend this celebration. After the celebration we have been invited to visit the birthplace of Janzizka at Trocnov, and the oriental fair at Bratislava, Slovakia. The fair will last from July 9 to 16, 1922. While in the town of Bratislava we shall have a good opportunity to see the natural beauties of Slovakia and to establish business relations with the Republic. All this shall be decided by us on board the ship at a meeting of the participants of the expedition.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Government; the Czechoslovak Ambassador at Washington, Dr. Stepanek; the Chicago Consul, Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka; and the New York Consul General, Dr. Prusik have willingly co-operated with the committee of the expedition. The ministry for foreign affairs of the Republic of Czechoslovakia informed the committee that the ministry of finance [treasury <pb facs="5418478_8_0176.jpg" n="4"/>department] is willing to waive any customs inspection of the larger baggage belonging to the members of the expedition; this will be inspected after their arrival in Prague. All hand baggage will, however, be examined at the border. The ministry of foreign affairs asked us not to take too many hand bags along [to avoid delays at the border].</p>
   <p>The committee consists of the following: Mr. John K. Valha, president; Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary; Mr. Josef Dusek, treasurer; Mr. Anton J. Cermak, committeeman in charge of special trains; Mr. Vaclav L. Rerabek, committeeman in charge of the press; Mr. Karel Vesely, committeeman in charge of the establishing of commercial and industrial relations in Czechoslovakia; Mr. Frank J. Skala, general representative of the steamship company. [Translator's note: The names and addresses of the members of the expedition is omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
