<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-16">Feb. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Appreciate the Friendly American Attitude</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-16">Feb. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S APPRECIATE THE FRIENDLY AMERICAN ATTITUDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tens of thousands of copies of newspapers printed in the English language are sold in the Czech districts of Chicago. Not every reader is wont to observe how these papers view our cause, our efforts toward the liberation of our old homeland. Some of the papers, on the whole, which are friendly toward the Czechs, informed us that they could not give special attention to a fraction of the populace of Chicago if they cannot see signs of special interest in the articles written for that fraction. The fault lies with our people who do not sufficiently patronize the papers friendly toward us, but buy copy of papers of decidedly Teutonic leaning; they do so because of habit. But now we have to see to it that the papers our people read shall be informed about our aims.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From the very beginning of the war it was the Chicago Daily Journal which, aside from the Herald, was most friendly toward us. Lately, it hardly missed an opportunity to proclaim its sympathy for our cause. This should suffice to the Czechs and Slovaks to support that paper in every way.</p>
   <p>Letters of appreciation of articles printed in the English press should always be accompanied by requests for other items of a similar trend. This sort of patriotic detail work will help to acquaint the American public with our aims. The Bohemian Review, a monthly, which interprets our wishes in the English language, should also be supported, and find its way into the libraries not only of Chicago, but the suburbs. There is no obstacle in the way of information about our cause. Let's go ahead!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
