<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-11">Feb. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Gift of Honor to President Masaryk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-11">Feb. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">GIFT OF HONOR TO PRESIDENT MASARYK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The significant day of March 7 is near; when the Czechoslovaks in our old country and in all parts of the world will celebrate the seventieth birthday of the first President of the Czechoslovak Republic: Thomas G. Masaryk one of those few men to whom the Czechoslovak nation will be indebted for what they have done for the liberation of the Czechoslovak nation during the great World War. The Czechoslovaks in the United States will also pay their tribute and recognition to this great son of our nation and therefore a collection was started, for the gift of honor which will be given to him at his birthday celebration, to be used by him for charitable purposes wherever it is most needed. It is a known fact that most of those who worked and financially supported our struggle for liberation are exhausted, but by keeping our word of honor we shall endure to the end, and we shall not yield until the situation in our old country will be such, that they will not have to depend on our help anymore. The Czechoslovaks <pb facs="5418478_8_0254.jpg" n="2"/>in the United States, who supported so freely the cause of the liberation of their old country, will not fail now when it [money] is needed the most, in order to aid the poor and suffering children. All the collections and contributions should be sent to the district committees of the Czechoslovak National Alliance or directly to the headquarters, which will present the total collected amount as a gift of honor to Professor Thomas G. Masaryk on his seventieth birthday celebration.</p>
   <p>For the Czechoslovak National Alliance,</p>
   <p>Signed: Dr. J. P. Pecival, president.</p>
   <p>Joseph Paskovsky, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
