<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-09-22">Sept. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Recognition of a Bohemian.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-09-22">Sept. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">RECOGNITION OF A BOHEMIAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Josef F. Lunak, 658 Loomis St., Appointed Professor of Practical Dentistry.</p>
   <p>It is with pleasure that everyone receives the report that one of our countrymen has been honered by being called to act as a Professor of Dentistry at Northwestern University.</p>
   <p>Dr. Josef F. Lunak was appointed Professor of Dentistry at a meeting of the Directors of Northwestern University Dental School last week. He will take up his duties immediately as the study of dentistry commenced at the University this week. The appointment is extraordinary, for the reason that Dr. Lunak did not seek it. It was offered to him by the Directors.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lunak was a distinguished student at this institution, and it was, therefore, for his earnest industry that he was given the greatest recognition possible that the University could bestow on one of its students, which is to be appointed valedictorian of his class. This unusual recognition of the youthful Bohemian is now further advanced by his appointment to the faculty.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0970.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Josef F. Lunak was born in Cleveland in 1878, and his appointment is all the more extraordinary because of his youth. Even in the first year of his studies at the University, attention was directed towards him, and he was soon recognized as the leader of his class, which class elected him to membership in the fraternal society, Psi Omega.</p>
   <p>So far as we know, he is the first Bohemian in Chicago to be so honored. The news of his elevation will be welcomed by all his friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
