<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-12">Apr. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet to Honor Charles J. Vopicka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-12">Apr. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET TO HONOR CHARLES J. VOPICKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A galaxy of prominent men and women gathered in the halls of the Ceska Beseda, Douglas Boulevard and Lawndale Avenue, to welcome Charles J. Vopicka, United States minister in the Balkan states, who has returned to Chicago lately. In his capacity, Mr. Vopicka had the opportunity of observing the horrors of War. It was with great difficulty that he was able to secure passage to the shores of this country, for which he felt a mighty longing. In the circle of the Beseda, he has always been one of the most active members.</p>
   <p>The hall of the Beseda was crowded with friends, and patriotic airs were played by the orchestra of Mr. Cerny.</p>
   <p>Among those present were: former Governor Dunne, Judge Karel of Milwaukee, Msgr. Francis Bobal, Doctor Ludwig J. Fisher, president of <pb facs="5418478_8_0896.jpg" n="2"/>the Bohemian National Alliance, Professor Bohumil Simek of the Iowa State university; and Mr. J. M. Triner acted as toastmaster.</p>
   <p>After the official welcome, Mr. Vopicka spoke words of thanks, then related some of his experiences on the Balkan peninsula, and told how he strove to alleviate the sufferings of the people caused by the War.</p>
   <p>There was a program filled by renditions of pieces of high artistic quality, and our best artists took part. Among them: Mrs. Marenka Geringer, singer, Mrs. Alva Messenger, harpist, Mr. George Hrusa, violin virtuoso, and Mr. Hugo Castl, singer. Sundry numbers for the orchestra were played under Mr. Cerny's direction. Several men, prominent in Chicago life, had been invited, but were detained by various duties. Congressman A. J. Sabath because of the necessity of his presence in Washington, Senator James Hamilton Lewis for the same reason, Mayor William <pb facs="5418478_8_0897.jpg" n="3"/>Hale Thompson, on account of pressing business in his office; State's Attorney Maclay Hoyne was sick in bed. All of these sent telegrams of hearty welcome and sincere regrets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
