<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-29">July 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Strong Oppostion against Mr. Vopicka</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0943</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0943.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-29">July 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">STRONG OPPOSTION AGAINST MR. VOPICKA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the New York Evening world an article has been published discussing the difficulty which Secretary of State Bryan is experiencing with the candidacy of Mr. Charles J. Vopicka for the position of United States envoy to the Balkans. True friends and sincere supporters of temperance are sending Mr. Bryan letters and telegrams expressing their disappointment and surprise in learning that he wants to appoint a brewer to such a high office. His grape-juice politics is in that way put to quite a test. The Anti-Saloon League of Illinois started a campaign against Mr. Vopicka's nomination and is urging the Leagues in other states to do the same. The League's national headquarters in Washington and a number of other temperance bodies have also taken up the fight.</p>
   <p>In speaking of the matter, Senator James H. Lewis of Illinois declared that <pb facs="5418478_8_0944.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Vopicka had been highly recommended for the office and that his friends expect that his name will soon be sent into the Senate. Senator Lewis understands that while Mr. Vopicka is the chairman of the board of one of Chicago's largest brewing companies, he does not drink even his own beer and does not permit anything but soft drinks to be served in his home. Recently Mr. Vopicka was helping the dry forces to obtain the passage of a law establishing a minimum distance between a saloon and a church or school.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vopicka is a model citizen, highly educated and cultured, speaks five languages, and has traveled widely. Brewing is a recognized business, and it would be illogical for Secretary Bryan to stop the candidacy of an able man just because he is a brewer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
