<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-29">Sept. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Present War and Bohemian Crown Lands</title><title level="a" type="sub">From the Cesko-America Tiskova Kancelar [Bohemian-American Press Bureau]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-29">Sept. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESENT WAR AND BOHEMIAN CROWN LANDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">From the Cesko-America Tiskova Kancelar [Bohemian-American Press Bureau]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Austro-Hungarian Monarchy is undoubtedly facing critical times. Because of all that the Monarchy has perpetrated against the Bohemian nation, it seems that we should remain indifferent to its plight, but the destiny of Bohemia is closely tied up with that of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy by historical, legal, and political bonds. It is necessary to bear this circumstance firmly in mind, for it is as timely as the warning given to the Austrian statesmen by Dr. Reiger at the legislative assembly held at Komeriz in 1846: "The gallows, gentlemen, is not the right kind of a prop for a disintegrating monarchy." [Dr. Reiger was the recognized leader of Bohemian politics from 1860 to 1890; he was head of the Staroceska Strana (Old Bohemian party), which was loyal to the Austrian constitution and for some forty years the dominant Bohemian political party.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0705.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If Austria, in these history-making times, is relying upon its greater physical strength, and that seems to be the case according to the news reaching us here, it would be only a confirmation of the fact that it has neither learned nor forgotten anything from its history. With the Bohemian nation it is different. History has taught Bohemia, and it has been a most painful lesson: that it cannot be certain of free development of all its intellectual, cultural, and economic elements as long as it is not the master of its own destiny in its own lands.</p>
   <p>The history of the most recent years shows how the Austrian governments, and the Emperor himself, have in many instances misused the trust of the Bohemian nation, a nation whose proven loyalty to the dynasty and to its "wider homeland" is called forth whenever the existence of the Monarchy is in danger. It also shows how they are in the habit of readily forgetting their promises and obligations as soon as the danger is averted by the good graces of the loyal and unselfish Bohemian nation, and the government is secure again.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0706.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Old Bohemian party, which built up its political program on the principles of Frantisek Palacky [first modern historian and political leader of the Bohemian nation], was trying to secure, by passive opposition and through personal contacts, the independence of Bohemian lands as early as 1860. When, in the 90's, the Mladoceska Strana (Young Bohemian party), which was originally a democratic peoples' party, took over the political leadership, it stated in its platform that "the foremost requirements of the nation are autonomy and equal rights, political rights included." In 1900 the political party of Realists was founded. It adopted as its first aim, "independence based on the Bohemian nation's natural rights which substantiate the historical rights, and the acquisition of full freedom and protection of thoughts and speech, religion, arts and press, assembly and congregation".</p>
   <p>Under the influence of the principles of the Realist party, Socialistic ideas and to some extent, spontaneously, the radical Progressive party and the radical Home Rule party came into being in 1897. Their political programs contained the postulate to "change the centralistic Austria into a federation of nations, <pb facs="5418478_8_0707.jpg" n="4"/>and create in the Bohemian lands a Bohemian state as a member of the federation". Special-interest parties, such as the Social Democratic, National Socialist, and Agrarian, also dealt with this question very thoroughly. The Social Democrats agreed in their 1901 convention to "fight the 'bureau-cratic-centralistic government' and remodel Austria into a democratic federation". The National Socialist party grew up exclusively on its program of home rule which attracted to it many partisans, especially among artisans and small businessmen. The exclusively self-interest Agrarian party has also in its program the independence of Bohemian lands framed in general along the lines of the parties adopting the political program of Palacky.</p>
   <p>All this shows that our old country's independence has been a longed-for postulate of all Bohemian political parties for many decades, and the history of our old country's political struggle has proved that the Bohemian nation has always been ready to bring any sacrifice, no matter how great, in order to realize this political dream. It can therefore be seen that the Austrian <pb facs="5418478_8_0708.jpg" n="5"/>government not only does not know, but also--at least in principle--does not recognize as justified this postulate of all Bohemian political parties. This it admits whenever Damocles' sword hangs over Austria. To prove this, it is not necessary to go as far back as 1848; it is enough to recall the events of 1860.</p>
   <p>In that year, the enlarged imperial diet in Vienna recognized the historical rights of the several lands, as well as equal rights and autonomy of the several national elements. Thus foundation was being given for Austria's federalization. But as soon as Austria's conditions were somewhat improving, our old country again suffered under the visitation of centralism and Germanization as is apparent in the so-called "February Constitution" adopted in 1861, and which was centralistic throughout. When, in 1867, the Bohemian parliament protested against the abrogation of its privileges by the Vienna government, it was simply dissolved.</p>
   <p>The present Emperor has issued manifestoes to the Bohemian nation in which he <pb facs="5418478_8_0709.jpg" n="6"/>recognized the rights of the Bohemian crown lands and expressed his willingness to give these rights a solemn confirmation by coronation, but this, so far, he has not done....The various successive Austrian governments have been well aware of the fact that the only foundation of the Austrian Monarchy's existence is the Bohemian crown lands. But they not only have done nothing to fortify this foundation of the Monarchy, but even worked systematically toward the enslavement of the population of these lands, following the idea that Austria must remain as strongly German and centralistic as possible because, while now only an inferior ally of Germany, it would never forget what it was to Germany prior to the battle of Hradec Kralove. To the idea of the former German Holy Roman Empire, it has finally sacrificed both its own existence and the happiness of its peoples, because it was being ruled by governments which--with very few exceptions or short duration--have never grasped Austria's natural mission and, having always been in direct emotional and intellectual conflict with a large (two-thirds) majority of the population, they have been pampering the non-Slavic political parties, the minority, to <pb facs="5418478_8_0710.jpg" n="7"/>the detriment of the other parties and nations of the Monarchy.</p>
   <p>These German bureaucratic governments of Austria bear also the full responsibility for the present war in Europe, for they have been following imperialistic ideas for decades, thus spreading disquiet and nervousness into the European concert of powers. The Bohemian nation, whose love of peace is proved by history takes part--although a passive one--in today's European drama only because of an irresistible force of circumstances. It is for this reason that its almost one-million-strong American branch has taken upon itself to be the spokesman of the whole nation. This it does principally in the interest of a permanent European peace, because it is a certainty that peace will prevail as soon as each nation in Central Europe will be assured of its freedom--its unhampered progress based on the principle of justice and equal rights for all. The overlordship of the pugnacious German minority over the peace-loving Slavic majority will cease and peace, the attribute of all Slavic races, and especially of the Bohemians, will prevail.</p>
   <p>Note: If we do not want to live in anxiety over the future of our old <pb facs="5418478_8_0711.jpg" n="8"/>country, let us not forget to make frequent contributions to our political fund. This fund will be used to finance important steps leading to our dear old country's independence. Send your contributions--the sooner the better--marked" for the political fund" to the treasurer of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni in America, Mr. F. J. Stepina, 1825 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
