<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Straz Osvojenych Has a Petition Which Is to Be Presented to Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">STRAZ OSVOJENYCH HAS A PETITION WHICH IS TO BE PRESENTED TO CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Straz Osvojenych [The Guard of Enlightened Peoples] held its annual meeting last evening. After the members had attended to the current business of the evening and to the election of officers, a very interesting motion was presented and carried.</p>
   <p>In the transaction of the current business more than a hundred letters were read announcing the names of delegates to the Straz Osvojenych for the year.</p>
   <p>At this meeting nearly all last year's officers were re-elected. The following are the officers: chairman, Vojtech Cada; secretary, Mr. Soukup; financial secretary, Mr. Vaclav Janda; treasurer, Richard Mejdrich. Dr. Iska was re-elected trustee.</p>
   <p>It was Dr. Iska who made a motion just before the close of the meeting, the <pb facs="5418478_8_0479.jpg" n="2"/>sense of which was that the Straz Osvojenych shall present a petition in resolution form to the Congress of the United States urging the Congress to request the delegates selected five years ago to the International Parliamentary Union and to request the European countries as well and the other civilized nations to take into consideration the interests of the smaller European countries and to respect these interests when new conditions have to be met after the war.</p>
   <p>In this petition which the Straz Osvojenych is to send to Congress attention is especially to be directed to the position of the Czech nation, and emphasis will be placed upon the fact that the desires of the smaller nations can best be fulfilled by an international congress of delegates of all the nations interested, which will give to the smaller nations a chance to make known their desires and their earnest endeavors to free themselves of their oppressors. These smaller nations would hardly get a fair representation at a peace conference.</p>
   <p>In the opinion of Dr. Iska, the sponsor of the motion, this contemplated peace <pb facs="5418478_8_0480.jpg" n="3"/>conference would decide to act in a matter so momentous as the freedom of smaller nations in Europe, or at least to grant to these nations autonomy.</p>
   <p>Dr. Iska's motion was referred to the organization committee, which holds its meeting next Monday, and at that meeting he will without delay make his motion and see to it that it is carried, and that the document is sent to Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
