<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An Expedition to the Old Country!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXPEDITION TO THE OLD COUNTRY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The committee of the Czechoslovak Catholics for the furtherance and cultivation of contacts among Catholics in foreign countries, which was organized last year as a part of the Rada Ceskoslovenskych Katoliku v Praze (Czechoslovak Catholic Council of Prague), prompted by brotherly love, gratitude, and respect for their ardent and self-sacrificing brothers in far-away America, sends its warm greetings to the projected expedition of our American brothers to the old country, which is to take place this summer.</p>
   <p>"The committee greeted with great enthusiasm the proclamation of the executive committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of the Bohemian Catholics of America), which was published in the Hlidka (Sentinel), volume II, number 2, and steps were taken immediately to make your proposed expedition a success. We assure you that we shall be happy to serve the members of your expedition as guides and hosts; we shall also prepare an itinerary for a trip through Bohemia, Moravia, and Slovakia; and there <pb facs="5418478_8_0192.jpg" n="2"/>will also be celebrations in your honor.</p>
   <p>"If last year's expeditions of the French and Belgian Catholics were warmly received by us, you must realize how much more we shall endeavor to show our gratitude to our beloved brother Czechs of America, knowing full well what they have accomplished for the cause of Catholicism.</p>
   <p>"I am empowered by the committee to offer you our most sincere and friendly aid. To this end we have already communicated with our centers in Moravia and Slovakia to work out an exact itinerary. So, please have no worries about these detailed arrangements. Our only ardent wish is that a great many of you will come to see us.</p>
   <p>"Asking you to transmit to the executive committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku and to all the brothers associated with it my warmest wishes, I am,</p>
   <p>"Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>"Dr. Josef Hanus, Metropolitan Canon and Chairman of the Committee."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0193.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every one who desires to take part in the expedition of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku and the Katolicky Sokol, and expedition which will leave on May 13 via the steamship "Rotterdam," should send his application, together with a deposit, not later than the end of February. It would be wise to do this as early as possible, because cabins and berths are reserved in the order in which they are selected by the first comers. Judging by the number of orders already received, the expedition promises to be a very large one--in fact, one of the best we have had so far. Our special prices for cabins in the second class is $130 and $132.50, depending upon the location of the cabin. The deposit for such a cabin is $25, to which must be added $5 for expenses.</p>
   <p>Every detail of the expedition will be carefully worked out, and the committee is laboring tirelessly to insure its success. Send the money for reservations to the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, 3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois. Our Chicago countrymen may obtain information directly from the offices of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, and they can leave their deposits there any day between 9 A. M. and 8 P. M. This will be a convenience for those who work late.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
