<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">Apr. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Conditions in Serbia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-04">Apr. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CONDITIONS IN SERBIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sir Thomas Lipton, who traveled through Serbia to learn about conditions prevailing there, describes his experiences in words that make the blood freeze in any reader's veins. According to his words, Serbia is one huge open-air hospital in which the sick have no bed, linen, and frequently even no straw or hay to lie upon, and they seldom have even the care of a physician.</p>
   <p>"I have found," says Mr. Lipton, "people on highways and field lanes who were too weak to crawl to a hospital. These were being picked up and loaded into farm wagons pulled by oxen. Frequently, the wife and children were prodding the oxen while the husband was raving with fever inside the wagon. There are hardly enough healthy people left to dig graves for the <pb facs="5418478_8_0584.jpg" n="2"/>dead whose bodies lie unburied in cemeteries. The situation is completely out of the control of authorities. There is a crying, desperate need of medical supplies, tents, hospitals, physicians, nurses, modern equipment, and clothes with which to replace the dirty rags, full of vermin, that spread typhoid germs."</p>
   <p>Concerning the hospital in Dzevdzelia (Djevdjelia)--where our Dr. Guca became ill and his wife suffered a fatal illness--Mr. Lipton has the following to say: "The place is a village in a wild, uncultivated country, and the hospital is established in a former tobacco factory belonging at one time to Abdul Hamid. Sick men lie here in clothes in which they lived for months in the trenches, filthy and crawling with vermin, suffering with typhus, typhoid fever, dysentery, and smallpox---Austrian prisoners of war play the role of nurses. The stench all this exudes is impossible to describe."</p>
   <p>What Mr. Lipton says about the Serbs will be of interest also: "There is <pb facs="5418478_8_0585.jpg" n="3"/>not a braver nation in the whole world. You never hear a word of complaint from them. One of the reasons for the rapid spreading of diseases is the black army bread which is issued to the sick and the remnants of which are gathered up in the hospitals by peddlers and sold to people who have nothing else to eat. The streets are swept and hospitals cleaned by Austrian prisoners of war whose numbers are rapidly decreasing, the prisoners dying of typhus and other diseases."</p>
   <p>Now, please let our readers realize that these "Austrian prisoners" are mostly Bohemians of whom there are close to fifty thousand in Serbia, and that these brothers of ours, our blood and the flower of our nation, live there in rags, filthy with vermin from which they suffer unspeakable torture and which carry dangerous contagious diseases. Bearing this in mind, you will understand the urgency of the cablegram requesting American Bohemians to collect and send good clothes, linen, and foot wear to Serbia. This is not only a matter of comfort, cleanliness, modesty, or protection against cold, but a matter of <pb facs="5418478_8_0586.jpg" n="4"/>life and death--life and death of Bohemian people.</p>
   <p>Articles for Bohemian prisoners of war in Serbia may be deposited with the following countrymen who have agreed to collect them:.....[seven names are given]. We shall greatly appreciate hearing from additional countrymen who will volunteer in this service. Whoever has a friend in Serbia or a relative who is a prisoner of war may put his name on the package or bundle, and the Serbian Red Cross will make an effort to deliver the package to the addressee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
