<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Reward Offered to Clear Status of Dr. Iska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0881</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0881.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">REWARD OFFERED TO CLEAR STATUS OF DR. ISKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An old and persistent bit of gossip has been making the rounds through all the Czech-American settlements in these critical times. In this gossip it is hinted that Dr. Fr. Iska, president of and speaker for the Czech Freethinkers' Community in Chicago, is a traitor to the old Czech homeland. They say that he took money for services rendered to the Austrian Government to the detriment of the old homeland. Among patriotic people such practices, of course, would degrade him to the level of the scum of society and make it impossible for him to stand before Freethinking workers.</p>
   <p>Pressure was exacted upon the Freethinkers' Community to have him ousted from its midst. The latter, however, waited until the charges could be substantiated. The Czech public here expected proof to be furnished soon after the accusations had been made. This proof of Dr. Iska's action has not been furnished as yet. Not even the courts, to which this affair had been carried, were able to establish facts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0882.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Freethinkers' Community in Chicago suffers great harm as a result of these accusations, for it is being looked down upon as the protector of a traitor to our old homeland.</p>
   <p>In its annual meeting held on December 2, the Freethinkers' Community resolved to take steps for the acceleration of the investigation and definitely to establish the truth or the baselessness of the charges raised against Dr. Iska. To this end an amount of one thousand dollars was deposited in the W. Kaspar State Bank, to be paid to whoever furnishes irrefutable evidence for the charge that Dr. Iska accepted payments from the Austrian Government for services performed for it in America for said emoluments.</p>
   <p>If this fact cannot be established, the reward of one thousand dollars will be paid to the person who can put the Freethinkers' Community upon the trail of the one who sent the information about the charges to the Providence Journal (which published the accusations before the Chicago dailies).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0883.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Freethinkers' Community believes that by heading in this direction it will discharge itself of its obligation to the Czech public and still not feel guilty of harboring in its midst any traitors to the old homeland. It wants to be guided by justice, well aware of the established rule that no court can pronounce a party guilty before guilt has been established beyond reasonable doubt.</p>
   <p>The Freethinkers' Community takes a humanitarian attitude, one based on justice. As long as incriminating evidence is not established or the informant identified, the Community will stand behind Dr. Iska, deem him worthy of being president and speaker for the Czech Freethinkers' Community, and recognize his qualification for a top place in the ranks of Freethinker workers.</p>
   <p>When the accused is proved guilty, the Community will do its duty and will not suffer the culprit to remain under its roof any longer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0884.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Freethinkers' Community promises strictest privacy for any communication that may establish facts in either direction. For the Freethinkers' Community in Chicago, Illinois: Joseph Uejno, Jos. Schroeter, Martin Nosek, Fr. Strunc, V. K. Soukup, J. Cizek-members of the committee on resolutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
