<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-04-18">Apr. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">In Honor of Professor T. C. Masaryk's Sixtieth Birthday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0797</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0797.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-04-18">Apr. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">IN HONOR OF PROFESSOR T. C. MASARYK'S SIXTIETH BIRTHDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2, Col.3--Sixty years has elapsed since the day Professor T. G. Masaryk was born, in a little community of Moravia.</p>
   <p>The greater part of his life he had been confronted with tremendous struggles to protect his thoughts and ideas and in many instances, forced to disagree with his own friends even perhaps making enemies of them, because he could see no worthwhile reason of their disagrements with him.</p>
   <p>In Czechoslovakia, on the evening of his birthday, his friends, including many of his former enemies, held a party in his honor. They know now, that he is a great man, who is not afraid to follow his own proven ideas, whether it concerns politics or religion, and they acknowledge his ability to be leader of men.</p>
   <p>Professor Masatyk is not a stranger in America. He has married an American woman and has many personal friends here, some of whom are his former students It is for this reason that we celebrated and honored this great Bohemian man.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0798.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Bohemian people of Chicago held a meeting in his honor, last evening at the Park of Svat. Cecha. (now known under the name of Dvorak Park). Several prominent speakers present, spoke of professor Masaryk's achievements and of his successful progress in life, in general. Miss Jane Addams who was to preside at this meeting was unable to do so, because of sudden illness, but was represented by Miss M. McDowell who is also well-known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
