<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to Our Readers Who Have Not Yet Done Their Duty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO OUR READERS WHO HAVE NOT YET DONE THEIR DUTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new year is approaching. The events of the past twelve months make us hopeful that the new year will bring us better luck than the old. Many a change will take place. We are determined to make up for our neglect. Our conscience tells us to do our duty both to our native Czech land and to those who are battling for its liberty.</p>
   <p>We wonder whether or not we shall forget our patriotic organization, the Czech National Alliance. We ponder whether we shall hesitate to send in our dues, which are only a dollar, or shall pay more, according to our circumstances.</p>
   <p>Countless numbers of our fellow citizens have been giving this their attention for fully three years. Has any one of us neglected his patriotic duty, during the past three years? Has he forgotten to join the ranks of the thousands of willing workers and contributors in the Czech patriotic movement? These workers were motivated by a sense of duty that could not be made non-existent <pb facs="5418478_8_0428.jpg" n="2"/>by its neglect.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of our Czech-American boys have already left for Europe to join the ever-increasing ranks of the Czechoslovak Army. This unit is a guarantee that the Czechoslovaks and their land shall not be forgotten at the peace conference and that this people shall, in fact, be remembered as long as this world exists!</p>
   <p>Not everyone follows the example set by patriotic workers; not everyone becomes inspired with a manly determination; and not everyone heeds the call to the ranks of the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <p>Some may not heed the call to become volunteers. However, there is no reason for their disregard of our appeal to them to join the serried ranks of the Czech National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Who prefers to be called a "slacker"? Send in your dues today!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
