<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovaks Thank America</title><title level="a" type="sub">In the Name of their Brothers and Sisters across the Ocean, and on their Own Account, they Herald a New and Bright Future for the Czechoslovak State</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAKS THANK AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">In the Name of their Brothers and Sisters across the Ocean, and on their Own Account, they Herald a New and Bright Future for the Czechoslovak State</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovaks of America express their ardent gratitude to President Wilson, who showed himself to be a true friend to the oppressed nations; also, to the leader of the Czechoslovak nation--Thomas G. Masaryk, and finally to the undaunted Czechoslovak army. [A picture, four columns wide and half a page high, shows a Czechoslovak warrior at the side of President Wilson.]</p>
   <p>This picture is the work of our highly esteemed friend, O. Valasek, whose artistic cartoons are known to the Czech people of America through American publications. The Austro-Hungarian and the Prussian eagles have waged a ghastly war for the domination of Central Europe, and the entire world. They are coveting the Slavonic nations of Russia and the Balkans. But the <pb facs="5418478_8_0350.jpg" n="2"/>Czechoslovaks are barring their way. The Czechoslovak army is defending Russia and Siberia. The Czechoslovak state, formed as a result of this war, stands on the borders of Germany, raising high the emblem of its ideals and its strength to prevent the Prussian eagle from invading Balkan lands. The two-headed Austro-Hungarian eagle lies dead, slain in a combat which it had provoked. The swords of the Czechoslovak heroes have destroyed that geographic conception called Austria-Hungary.</p>
   <p>In the solemn manifesto of September 3, 1918, President Wilson recognizes the independence of the young Czechoslovak state, thereby inducting it into the community of free nations. He stands behind one of the small nations of Europe with his great moral and physical power, he the liberator, to whom the Czechoslovak people turn today filled with hope, and with feelings of deepest gratitude.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
