<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Expedition to the Old Homeland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_8_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXPEDITION TO THE OLD HOMELAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We hereby call the attention of members of our national organizations, the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), the Slovenska Liga (Slovak League), and the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) to the fact that there are only ninety-five reservations to be had for our expedition to our homeland. The interest in the expedition is great, and applications are coming in from almost every state in the Union, as well as from Canada. Therefore, those who intend to go should send in their applications as soon as possible before it is too late.</p>
   <p>The expedition will sail from New York on Saturday, June 4, on the steamship "Nieuw Amsterdam" to Boulogne-sur-Mer, from there it will proceed by rail to Paris. In Paris, two days will be devoted to sight-seeing, and the expedition will then go directly to Prague, Czechoslovakia. The regular price for a second class cabin is $145; the war tax and transportation from harbor to Paris is included in this fee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_8_0204.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The expedition committee, which is getting all possible help from the government of the Czechoslovak Republic, has taken care of everything in order to make this trip a pleasant one. A special Czechoslovakian train will meet the members of the expedition in Paris. All housing arrangements in Prague will be taken care of, as well as customs inspections at the border. The American correspondence bureau in Prague, together with the officials of the government, is already engaged in making preparations for the members of the expedition. The expedition committee will furnish all information concerning baggage, accommodations, taxes, passports, circulars, etc. Preliminary information is already being published from time to time in the monthly organ of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe, the Poselstvi.</p>
   <p>Applications are being handled by the expedition committee at the office of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni. It is necessary to present a membership verification card from one of the above-mentioned national organizations with the application, together with a fifty-dollar deposit for each reservation. Out-of-town applications may be sent to the following address: The Czechoslovak <pb facs="5418478_8_0205.jpg" n="3"/>National Alliance, Expedition Committee, 3734 West 26th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
