<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-22">Jan. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Orphanage Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Meeting--Report from Building Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-22">Jan. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN ORPHANAGE SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Meeting--Report from Building Committee</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The building committee....met at the home of Reverend Harrisville on February 10, 1908, for organization....At the meeting plans were presented, drawn by various architects, and after the committee had studied the plans, the one submitted by Architect Sorensen was accepted as the most practical and as the one that would most nearly meet the requirements. The secretary was requested to have the architect make certain changes in the plans and supply specifications so that bids could be obtained from builders.</p>
   <p>On April 2, there was a joint meeting of the finance committee and the building committee at the home of Mr. O. H. Haugan. Ten of the committee members were present together with Mr. H. A. Haugan and the architect, <pb facs="5423969_3_1588.jpg" n="2"/>Charles Sorensen. Estimates were presented for a building in accordance with Mr. Sorensen's plans, to cost between $32,000 and $35,000. After considerable discussion it was unanimously decided to recommend to the Orphanage Society to erect new buildings in conformity with the plans with such minor changes as the Society might find desirable, and that the work of construction should not be started until $10,000 had been secured for the building fund. These plans and proposals were placed before the Society at the quarterly meeting in April....They were unanimously adopted with the reservation that the upper story was not to be finished until the number of children at the Orphanage should make it necessary.</p>
   <p>The building committee again met on April 27, at the home of Mr. Sorensen. All the members were present. The vacancy caused by the death of the chairman, Mr. S. T. Gundersen, was filled when the president of the Society named Mr. C. L. Ibsen as chairman. Mr. Ibsen was unanimously chosen chairman of the committee. The architect's plans were studied in detail and a few changes and improvements proposed. It was also decided to invite <pb facs="5423969_3_1589.jpg" n="3"/>the ladies who were members of the board of directors to meet at the office of the architect to inspect the plans.</p>
   <p>Since that date the committee has not met since the financial committee has not reported having secured the required $10,000. The plans, however, are perfected so that bids may be had and work started at a month's notice. Since prices of material and work vary it would be of no use to ask for bids until such time as it had been made certain that the work could be started; the contractors are unwilling to make bids to be in effect far into the future. The plans are placed before the annual meeting for inspection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
