<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-22">Jan. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Home Finding Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-22">Jan. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN HOME FINDING SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Home Finding Society held its annual meeting at St. John's Norwegian Lutheran Church last Wednesday evening. About sixty members were present. The meeting was opened with prayer by Reverend Bergesen.</p>
   <p>The president gave his report as follows:</p>
   <p>There have been thirty-three children at the Society's home; nine have been placed in homes; seven had been accepted at the Home temporarily because their parents were ill; nineteen are still at the Home. Of these, ten will be placed in homes as soon as papers can be put in order.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1580.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are invariably more offers of homes than there are children to place; it is therefore easy to find good homes for the little ones. In regard to several of those who have offered their homes to children, with right of full inheritance, the ministers to whose congregations they belong state that these people who want children are Christians, kind, and well off, even rich--childless people who are missing the joy of having children in their homes.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that more members be won for the Home Finding Society so that it may not be necessary to hold bazaars,etc., in the future. The Society is the only one among Norwegians--perhaps among Scandinavians--with the purpose of placing orphans in private homes. This method is recommended by President Roosevelt as the best solution of the problem of the orphans.</p>
   <p>The membership has been nearly doubled during the year. New members have joined both from Chicago and from the country. The annual report for this <pb facs="5423969_3_1581.jpg" n="3"/>year will be printed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peter Johnson stated that the large accession of new members from the Church of Our Savior (Lutheran) chiefly is due to the branch which members of the Society, belonging also to that church, have organized. The Home Finding Society decided to form branches in all the congregations which have members who belong to the Society.</p>
   <p>The treasurer's report showed that current expenses at the Home were as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Household expenses</cell>
     <cell>$538.81</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Heat and light</cell>
     <cell>157.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Reparations, furnishings, taxes</cell>
     <cell>584.98</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest</cell>
     <cell>134.58</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Wages</cell>
     <cell>279.58</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Other expenses</cell>
     <cell>90.74</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>The income was</cell>
     <cell>$2,642.21</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
