<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-01">Apr. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1380</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1380.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-01">Apr. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee has been appointed to revise the statutes of the Tabitha Society. This is an important task weighted with responsibilities. One of the tasks of the committee is to determine and define the principles upon which the Society was founded and the promises made in that connection. The basis for the collection of funds for the establishment of a hospital was the clearly expressed promise that the institution was to be completely neutral in regard to denominational matters. Since the Norwegians are divided into many religious groups, it would not have been possible to bring about co-operation on any other basis. Such was the situation at the time of building the hospital, and conditions have not changed since.</p>
   <p>However, a large number of the Norwegians in Chicago have somehow gained the conviction that the Tabitha Hospital belongs, in a manner, to a certain religious sect. Even the board of directors has given strength to this <pb facs="5423969_3_1381.jpg" n="2"/>conviction. The attitude of the board has been uncertain and wavering and in several ways in direct contradiction to the unequivocal priniciples and pledges. These facts have prevented the hospital from gaining such general support from our people as it otherwise would have obtained.</p>
   <p>The task and the duty of the committee for revision of the statutes of the Tabitha Society is to correct the situation here referred to. The public expects statutes of a type to make the hospital that which it was intended to be originally; the public expects the hospital to be freed definitely from domination by any church or denomination; that it be made completely neutral so that all Norwegians may be able to feel at home in the institution. If the hospital is to attain this characteristic, there can be no official priest or minister connected with the place and no official hour of worship. Everybody must have the same rights as in his or her own home to seek spiritual advice and consolation according to personal desires. The meetings of the Society ought not to be held in churches, and festivals or fairs held by the Society must be devoid of church influence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1382.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this manner the hospital may gain the desired general acclaim of our people. This is a necessary condition for its development and growth.</p>
   <p>The work of the committee is being watched intently by our people, and it is hoped that the confidence and trust placed in the committee will not be betrayed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
