<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-20">Nov. 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Singing Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert Last Sunday Very Successful</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-20">Nov. 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN SINGING SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert Last Sunday Very Successful</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual concert of the Norwegian Singing Society held last Sunday evening at Wicker Park Hall, was most successful in every way. All day Sunday the rain poured down, and it was almost impossible to pass at street crossings without getting wet feet. In spite of this, more than one thousand people assembled to enjoy the concert.</p>
   <p>Professor J. W. Colberg's orchestra opened the program with an overture by Verdi, and this number, as well as "Variations on Norwegian Folk Melodies," arranged by Mr. Colberg, received much applause.</p>
   <p>Violinist Nels Halter played the "Fifth Concerto" by De Beriot and the "Zigeunerweisen" by Sarosate, accompanied at the piano by Miss Christine Anderson.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nels Halter has appeared before the public a number of times, invariably showing that he is capable of handling his instrument, and on this occasion <pb facs="5423969_3_0047.jpg" n="2"/>he once more proved his ability as a violinist....He was strongly applauded.... A pupil of Mme. De Marion, Miss Pearl Burmeister, appeared for the first time in this Scandinavian neighborhood. She sang, "Dream of Love" by Grieg, and "Forbidden Music" by Gastaldon. She was accompanied at the piano by Mme. De Marion. Miss Burmeister took the public by storm; she has a high, clear, pleasing soprano voice and was repeatedly called before the curtain by the enthusiastic audience. She was also presented with two bouquets of roses.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Singing Society sang excellently...and received vigorous applause after each number.</p>
   <p>Mr. C. L. Hansen, the well-known first tenor of the Society....was enthusiastically applauded.</p>
   <p>It was evident that the Norwegian Singing Society had not been indolent under their new leader; all the numbers presented were executed in a masterly manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0048.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The director, Mr. Christian Nilsson, showed that his method of leadership differed somewhat from that of the other song leaders in that he puts greater emotional force in the transition from pianissimo to fortissimo; this proved an advantage in the numbers presented. After his own composition had been played he was given an ovation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
