<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-24">June 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Edison Park Orphans Tackle Big Job]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-24">June 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[EDISON PARK ORPHANS TACKLE BIG JOB]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.7...Scandia's inquiry as to the progress of the proposed gardens for children of the Edison Park Orphanage has brought out information and detail that is surprising. We will neither attempt to give a complete detailed description of this project nor a full report of what has been accomplished to date, but one or two phases will give one an idea of the magnitude of the job Miss Sevros has single handedly undertaken</p>
   <p>To start at the beginning, every inch of the ground, intended for the children garden plots, had to be measured, plowed or spaded, raked and marked for beds. The proper seeds must be understandingly chosen and planted. Thorough experience, constant vigilence and unlimited patience are required to see that all children follow instruction to the most minute detail. Miss Sevros not only explains how each step is to be taken, but why something must be done just so and just when.</p>
   <p>An idea of the actual work, patience and knowledge required can be organized by following the preparation of two-thousand strawberry plants for planting. A third <pb facs="5423969_3_1525.jpg" n="2"/>of the roots had to be cut way so fresh roots could develope that would supply the plants with moisture and every bud and flower must be nipped off to insure sturdiness and bearing. A hundred grape vines had to be pruned and five-hundred tomato plants had to be temporarily set in flower pots, later to be transplanted to the garden bed. Every item to be raised by the embryo gardeners required patient and accurate preparatory handling.</p>
   <p>To instill the idea of how, why when and where in the unsimilar minds of so large a group of children requires thorough knowledge, training, tact; patience and even a generous portion of psychology. Miss Servos possesses a generous amount of all these qualifications and visitors are loud in their praises of her personality and its effect on the children with whom she works.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
