<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Book Survey</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Inquiry into the Nature of Peace and the Terms of its Perpetuation. by Thorstein Veblen</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BOOK SURVEY</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Inquiry into the Nature of Peace and the Terms of its Perpetuation. By Thorstein Veblen</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our renowned compatriot Thorstein Veblen has presented us with a substantial,thoughtful book to which I wish to direct the attention of the readers of this paper. The book treats of the greatest question and one which at the present time will catch the public interest. It is hardly presumptuous to prophesy that the book will win the greatest attention in wide circles.</p>
   <p>Through three works issued earlier, Professor Veblen has proven himself an independent, original thinker who does not just follow the beaten track in his field. His "Theory of the Leisure Class" in one group gave him an enviable position in the field of economics. In his two later books, "The Instinct of Workmanship <pb facs="5423969_3_0363.jpg" n="2"/>and the State of the Industrial Arts," and "Imperial Germany and the Industrial Revolution," he followed up the victory he had won. And the near future will hardly witness an exposition of the cause of peace, that will be more inclusive or more profound than the book which I am discussing.</p>
   <p>In regard to the method and objective of the book, a quotation of the preface given there will serve. Having quoted Kant's renowned treatise, "Fum ewigen Frieden," which claims that a lasting peace will come some day because nature itself seems to be moving in that direction, he continues: "The quest of perpetual peace at large is no less a paramount and intrinsic human duty than it was, not is it at all certain that its final accomplishment is nearer. But the question of its pursuit and of the conditions to be met in seeking this goal lies in a different shape today; and it is this question that concerns the inquiry which is here undertaken..........What, if anything, is there in the present situation that visibly makes for a realization of <pb facs="5423969_3_0364.jpg" n="3"/>these necessary terms within a calculable future? And what are the consequences presumably due to follow in the nearer future from the installation of such a peace at large? And the answer to these questions is here sought not in terms of what ought dutifully to be done toward the desired consummation, but rather in terms of those known factors of human behavior that can be shown by analysis of experience to control the conduct of nations in conjectures of this kind."</p>
   <p>There are seven chapters in the book.</p>
   <p>In the first is discussed the problem of the state in its relation toward war and peace.</p>
   <p>Chapter two, treats of the nature and the application of patriotism.</p>
   <p>Chapter three,deals with the conditions for lasting peace. Lasting peace is probable <pb facs="5423969_3_0365.jpg" n="4"/>only if aggressive states made harmless through the introduction of democratic government - unless submission to their over-lordship be preferred. This latter possibility is treated in.</p>
   <p>Chapter four, painting the conditions consequent on such peace, with biting irony.</p>
   <p>Chapter five, takes up for consideration the question of peace and neutrality. Will it be possible to internationalize certain national prerogatives such as protective tariff, commercial navy, colonies, or even those accepted privileges inherent in citizenship - matters which under the rules of today may easily draw nations into the maelstrom of war.</p>
   <p>Chapter Six, deals with the problem of elimination of the unfit. Lasting peace presupposes the abolition of imperialism in government, the doing away with all the implements or arrangements for war, the nullification of all national debts, the confiscation of such industries and resources as have made war possible. All this to <pb facs="5423969_3_0366.jpg" n="5"/>be taken care of by a league of neutral states with an international police force strong enough to take action against possible rebellious states.</p>
   <p>In chapter seven, "Peace and the Price System" the author, finally, gives an interesting exposition of the probable development, industrial and cultural, under the projected eternal peace among the nation.</p>
   <p>The whole bank is permeated by a spirit of liberalism and democracy. It is a book which ought to be read by the thoughtful of all classes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
