<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1890-11-20">Nov. 20, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A Proposition</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Directors of the World's Columbian Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1890-11-20">Nov. 20, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A PROPOSITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">To The Directors of the World's Columbian Exposition</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The undersigned hereby offers for sale a whole outfit of a Lappish family from the North of Norway. Said outfit consists of tents, household furniture, and utensils of every description; a Lappish sleigh and other vehicles, a saddle for reindeer, hunting and fishing equipment, bedclothing and wearing apparel of reindeer skins, both for men and women--in short, all articles used by a Lappish family, both in and out-of-doors, tending to illustrate the life and manners of this interesting nomadic race. I will agree to deliver the whole collection free of expense in Chicago, and place in proper shape for exhibition in the place which may be assigned for it, for the sum of three thousand ($3,000) dollars.</p>
   <p>Such a collection, representing this primative northern mode of life, cannot fail to be of great interest to observers in this age of advanced civilization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You may be assured that a Lappish camp at the Chicago Exposition would hold its own as our attraction, and receive merited attention and approval. It would also contribute its share in making the Fair as comprehensive and universal as possible.</p>
   <p>At the same time, I offer to exhibit a collection from the hunting grounds of Spitzbergen and the polar regions, consisting of trapping outfits, utensils, hides of polar animals, teeth, heads, etc., of such animals. To this collection also belongs a number of interesting objects from the Samoieds, illustrating the home industry of this peculiar Nomad tribe of the far North. I will also deliver this collection and place it in position at the Exposition for the sum of one thousand ($1,000) dollars, but this price only in case the above named Lappish camp is desired.</p>
   <p>A part of the Lappish camp was exhibited at the Fair in Tromso (Norway) and received a medal there.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Awaiting your answer to the above proposition at your earliest convenience, I remain your obedient servant,</p>
   <p>William Kjellman.</p>
   <p>The above letter was received by the Editor of Skandinaven a short time ago, with the request that we bring the proposition before the proper authorities. It is a matter with which we have no personal acquaintance, and in which we have no interest, except the desire to do anything we can to make the World's Columbian Exposition as attractive and as truly cosmopolitan as possible.</p>
   <p>It is our opinion that few exhibits of the out-of-the-way Races of the world as they exist would be more attractive, or more instructive than the one under consideration, and that if such exhibits are to be part of the great World's Fair--as they doubtless are--it would be incomplete without a Lappish camp like the one described here.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0313.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The directors of the Exposition can get the address of the person offering the exhibit from the Skandinaven, and can communicate with him at their convenience.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the directors will pardon us for taking the liberty at this time of reminding them that a collection from the national Swedish Museum of Antiquities was the feature of the late Exposition at Paris, which attracted much attention. The Northern peoples have very faithfully gathered and preserved the relics of their past, both in Norway and Denmark, as well as in Sweden. They are a very complete and attractive collections of national antiquities. If a judicious selection from these museums could be exhibited at the Chicago Exposition, it would not only be of great service to our own scholars and antiquaries, but to those of every country. But what perhaps would be of more practical and immediate interest to the board of directors is the great value such collections would have as a means of attracting every class of visitor from the nationalities which are so numerously represented in our city and in the whole Northwest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0314.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We are not familiar with the conditions on which the above mentioned collection from Sweden were secured for the Paris Exposition, nor do we know how readily the Northern governments would consent to the transportation of such valuable scientific treasures across the ocean, but we have no doubt that they would yield to any reasonable demands for the sake of both science and the success of the great Exposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
