<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1915-04-28">Apr. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-04-28">Apr. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN BUILDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An appeal came to us some time ago to assist in the erection of a Norwegian building at the San Francisco Exposition. At first it appeared to us that we were not particularly concerned with this matter, but further consideration showed the situation to be as follows:</p>
   <p>The Swedes, Danes, and nearly all other small as well as great nations, have erected buildings at the Fair and have made provisions for the reception of their people at the Exposition, but the Norwegians looked in vain for a building over which was hoisted the flag of their fatherland. As was done by those governments in connection with the Swedish and Danish buildings, Norway signified her willingness to contribute one half toward the erection and maintenance of a suitable building if the Norwegians here would contribute the other half. The proposition was reasonable and the question presented was whether we should raise the money necessary--some $40,000,--or whether we should endure the <pb facs="5423969_3_0233.jpg" n="2"/>humiliation of being less patriotic than the other two groups of Scandinavian people.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that the Norwegian Lutheran Synod meets at the Fair and that the Norwegian Sangerfest [Singer Festival] will be held there, and in view of the further fact that June 7 has been designated "Norway Day" on the official Exposition program, it was particularly humiliating to think that we should not even have a flag pole from which to unfold the colors of old Norway.</p>
   <p>Considering these facts, we decided to help. The building is erected and paid for. A number of men have contributed from $25 to $100 each, but no general canvas has been made for we have been unwilling to incur expenses that would reduce the contributions made. We have decided instead to make an appeal to our people throughout America for a helping hand. Join us if <pb facs="5423969_3_0234.jpg" n="3"/>you can. Send contributions to Theodore Wold, Federal Reserve Bank, Minneapolis, Minnesota, or Skandinaven, Chicago, Illinois. We might suggest that contributions from $2 to $25 would be entirely acceptable and proper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
