<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-21">Dec. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Tabitha Hospital Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-21">Dec. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE TABITHA HOSPITAL SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The nominations committee, which named candidates for election at the last annual meeting of the Hospital Society, apparently was not acquainted with or attentive to the constitution of the Society, and this fact has caused us considerable trouble. Out of the seven members (one from each branch) who should have been elected to the nominations committee for the present year, because of the mistake referred to, two were not elected at all, and only three were elected legally. One of these afterwards left the city and when the committee convened only two of the members present had been elected legally. These two, together with two of those who had been elected illegally, and three who have been elected by the above-mentioned four, have constituted a sort of a nominations committee. Since the origin of this committee was contrary to the constitution of the Society, all the work undertaken by this committee will naturally be illegal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to correct these irregularities, fifty of the members of the Society requested that the board of directors call a special meeting of the Society. It is to be regretted that the board of directors did not comply with the request although it is obliged, under the laws, to do so. On account of this the difficulties to be overcome are now greater than before; there is the danger that every election at the coming annual meeting will be illegal and thus there will be no end to the troubles. Would it not be better to correct the wrongs while there is still time?</p>
   <p>If the nominations committee made a mistake last year, thereby inducing the Society to commit an error, these errors can be corrected. This, however, can of course only be done by the Socitey itself. Under any circumstances the Society ought to convene in special meeting to deliberate as to what course of action to take.</p>
   <p>The board of directors has no right to omit calling such special meeting. The pretext that, in the opinion of the board of directors, such a special <pb facs="5423969_3_1269.jpg" n="3"/>meeting can accomplish nothing good and might even do something illegal doe not avail; the board of directors is obliged under the laws "to call the Society for special meeting whenever twenty-five of the regular members of the Society make request in writing for such special meeting". It will then be up to the Society itself to determine whether the proposals presented by the twenty-five members in question be good or bad; the board of directors cannot decide on this in advance. The fact that a man has been elected as a member of the board of directors, or even elected as the chairman of the board, does not imply that this man has been imbued with the highest degree of wisdom and infallibility, making it permissible for him to disregard the laws, making incompetents of all the members of the Society which elected him. The safe course for the board of directors as well as for the individual members is to respect the laws of the Society and comply with them.</p>
   <p>If the laws have been broken, as at present in regard to the nominations committee, the authority which is able to decide what to do and how to act in order to correct the errors made naturally reposes in the Society. It can <pb facs="5423969_3_1270.jpg" n="4"/>lead to no good if individuals, whether members of the board of directors or of the nominations committee, make efforts to force upon the Society their opinions or their will.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
