<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-03">Apr. 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">English Translations of Norwegian Songs</title><title level="a" type="sub">Open Letter to Northwestern Singers' Association by John Dale</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-03">Apr. 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLISH TRANSLATIONS OF NORWEGIAN SONGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Open Letter to Northwestern Singers' Association by John Dale</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Objections have been raised from several sides against the use of English translations of the texts of some of the choral songs for our coming Song Festival. Especially has the use of the English text for the "Olav Trygvason" been objected to. On account of this I beg to call on the singing societies of the Association to use the Norwegian text when preparing the song mentioned for the Festival. I do not believe that the change will cause great difficulty since the song, in its Norwegian text, is to be found in all the more widely used song collections for male choruses, and the text is easily adapted to the music in our new collection of musical numbers.</p>
   <p>I have made this change to mollify certain dissatisfied singing societies, but I have taken the step only with considerable reluctance. I am firmly <pb facs="5423969_3_0127.jpg" n="2"/>convinced that we have arrived at the time when English texts ought to be used in presenting Scandinavian compositions, at least in part. In doing so we are opening a new door in music, as it were, to the English speaking public, and to do so is certainly to take a new step forward towards the goal the Association has set for itself. Anybody will understand why, in furtherance of this goal, I chose some of the pearls of Scandinavian musical creations to be sung in English. For the reasons given at the beginning of this statement, "Olav Trygvason" will be sung in Norwegian at the coming Song Festival, but no further changes will be made in the program.</p>
   <p>The "Peasant Wedding March" will be sung in English; the songs "Vart Land" and "Hor Oss Svea" will be presented as a concert number (A and B), as will "Song for Danes" and "Hoie Nord" (The Far North). My arrangement for a murmur chorus in the "Saterjentens Sondag" (The Sunday of the Dairy Maid) might well be left free from criticism until heard in connection with orchestral music.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0128.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Greatly against my wishes I have been compelled to select the songs for the Festival unaided. Such being the case, I think it proper to ask, now that the selection has been printed, that tolerance be shown in regard to the selected material and that the individual singing societies practice the material presented to the best of their ability. Next time somebody else will be given the chance of doing things better.</p>
   <p>Singing societies wishing to participate in the concerts of the Song Festival are requested to notify me as early as possible and inform me of the pieces selected by them. No Singing Society will have a chance to sing more than one selection at the concerts during the Song Festival.</p>
   <p>I appeal to all the singing societies and the singers to apply themselves seriously to the task at hand. We want to maintain the renown of the Scandinavians as a group ranking high in the art of singing. We also want to see the individual societies as successful participants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
