<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Jonas Lie Lodge Celebrates Anniversary]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[JONAS LIE LODGE CELEBRATES ANNIVERSARY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a self-evident fact that the Sons of Norway is to be an excellent instrument for gathering the Norwegians of Austin. Our countrymen of Austin have, up to the present time, been somewhat isolated from Chicago's Norwegian colony and, while Austin visitors in Chicago have been frequent, this is the first time a large number have visited Austin at one time.</p>
   <p>A group of Austin Norwegians had decided to organize a lodge of the Sons of Norway and Jonas Lie Lodge is the result. The occasion was the third anniversary of the Lodge and was attended by over 250 members and friends. Three tables, each nearly the length of the hall, and another across the entire front (the table for the speaker and special guests) were loaded with good Norwegian food. The wonderful food and a very good program combined to make this a gala occasion indeed. The hall and tables were attractively decorated, Norwegian and American flags lent a festive atmosphere, and the Norwegian music, well played by L. Haugan's orchestra, put the finishing touch to a real Norwegian festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1027.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Consul Rove, who came from Milwaukee to attend this meeting, said he felt exactly as he had felt many times in Norway when, on May 17, he and other children had marched, sung, and celebrated the entire day. Other speakers during the evening were Mr. Finn Mohn, president of Jonas Lie Lodge, Christ Andersen, past president, and Dr. Warlor, who spoke for Norway.</p>
   <p>Jonas Lie Lodge has made an excellent beginning and, if one may judge from the enthusiasm of this birthday gathering, our Chicago locals of the Sons of Norway will have to look to their laurels or young Jonas Lie Lodge will leave them far behind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
