<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1919-10-26">Oct. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Save the Viking Ship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1919-10-26">Oct. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SAVE THE VIKING SHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the friends of the Viking:</p>
   <p>The Viking Fund is growing rapidly. It has reached the sum of $4,005.01 on deposit in the State Bank of Chicago, and the majority of the subscription books have not been submitted. Success is now assured. The Viking Ship will be saved; it will not be permitted to go to destruction. In a few days, it will be placed under our protection, and thoroughly overhauled and repaired. Next spring the good old ship will be found in Lincoln Park, safe and sound, with burnished shields and glittering dragon head--a permanent reminder to all the world, in one of the most conspicuous places in the country, of Norse valor on the sea, past and present, and the first discovery of this country.</p>
   <p>The appeal of the Committee has met with a splendid response. All seem to be eager to have a share in the honor of saving the ship--this historical document which concerns not only Norway, but also America. That this is appreciated <pb facs="5423969_3_0871.jpg" n="2"/>also by others than Norwegian-Americans is interestingly shown by a contribution received the other day from the children of the fourth grade of the Francis Parker School, Americans all. It is the ambition of the Committee to collect a total of $7,000 as soon as possible, and the holders of subscription books (whose splendid aid the Committee gratefully acknowledges) are requested at this time to make a preliminary report of all subscriptions to Mr. Oscar H. Haugan, treasurer of the Committee, State Bank of Chicago. The report must include the names, addresses and amounts of all subscribers, with a remittance of the total sum. This will enable the treasurer to include the contributions with names, addresses, and amounts (and proper credit to you and your organization) in the lists which are published weekly in Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>No contributions are announced until the amount is actually received. Please retain the books, however, for further collections. We shall need your continued generous aid. Be sure to give every member of your organization an opportunity to receive a Viking Subscription Certificate. It will be a proud souvenir in years to come. More books may be had upon application at the <pb facs="5423969_3_0872.jpg" n="3"/>secretary's office. All other friends of the cause who will want to take part in the work of saving the Viking Ship and who have not already subscribed, are requested to mail their subscriptions to Mr. Haugan.</p>
   <p>Yours for saving the Viking Ship,</p>
   <p>Mrs. John C. Thye, chairman;</p>
   <p>Andrew Hummeland, secretary.</p>
   <p>Report by Mr. Haugan</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>New contributions</cell>
     <cell>$ 193.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Collections receipted for</cell>
     <cell>3,811.51</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$4,005.01</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
