<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-10-28">Oct. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Societies and Socials, Etc</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0970</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0970.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-10-28">Oct. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETIES AND SOCIALS, ETC</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. The Norwegian Women's Sick Relief Society will hold its annual bazaar in the Parish House, Humboldt Park, on Monday, Oct. 29. All kinds of beautiful articles. Also refreshments. The Sick Relief Society has done so much good during its existence that it should be sufficient merely to mention the affair in order to get strong support.</p>
   <p>2. Annual bazaar by the Good Hope Society, (Young ladies' society) of Hauge Church will be held in the Sunday School rooms of the church next Friday and Saturday. Beautiful and useful things. Refreshments.</p>
   <p>3. The Society Eikundasund is holding its regular meeting tonight at Wabansia Hall.</p>
   <p>4. Leif Erikson, Lodge #9, R.H.K., is holding dance and card party November 4 in the Hall of the Knights, 1733 N. Kedvale Ave.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0971.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. Skandia Aid Society will meet Thursday, November 1 at 3270 Wabansia Ave.</p>
   <p>6. Great 400 Reformation jubilee at Medina Temple tonight at 8 o'clock.</p>
   <p>7. The Norwegian Singing Society celebrating 47 years jubilee on Tuesday, Oct. 30th at Wicker Park great hall. Members with ladies and friends invited.</p>
   <p>8. Sick Relief Society of Bethlehem church will hold its regular monthly meeting on Oct. 29. The question is to be considered as to whether the society is to combine with the other societies of same type in the Lutheran church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>9. Reformation celebrations: A series of socials in celebration of the 400 years Reformation jubilee will begin at the First Lutheran Church, Cor. Fullerton Ave. and Ballou St. on Wednesday, Oct. 31.</p>
   <p>A very varied program will be presented at these socials. Everybody welcome.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0972.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>10. The Bulletin, the magazine of the Norwegian Women's Association has issued its third number containing all the news of interest concerning the Norwegian Women's Societies in Chicago. It also contains a mass of interesting data about women and their work in general.</p>
   <p>11. Great congress of youth at the Church of St. Paul, 2215 North Ave. on Wed. Oct. 31.</p>
   <p>12. The Harvest Social of the Turners at the Humboldt Park Parish House comes to an end tonight. Excellent entertainment: Music, boxing, singing, readings. Frithyof Werenskjold will be there!</p>
   <p>13. Eidsvold will give a Hard Time Party at Spaulding Hall on the first Thursday in November.</p>
   <p>The great Accordionist Irving S. Shuster will be there to entertain.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0973.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>14. Great Social at the Salem Church this afternoon at 4 o'clock. Speech by Prof. H. Gundersen; music by John Dyldahl, the violinist; singing by Miss Jenny Anderson and the Swedish male quartet.</p>
   <p>15. The ladies' society "Thora" will hold a bazaar in Spaulding Hall, 3316 W. North Ave. Saturday and Sunday Nov. 3 and 4. Both evenings there will be refreshments and dancing. Open from 4 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
