<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-09-25">Sept. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Excursion to St. Joseph, Michigan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-25">Sept. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">EXCURSION TO ST. JOSEPH, MICHIGAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The excursion to St. Joseph, which was undertaken by steamer last Sunday, had been very widely advertised. Part of the income from the excursion was to go to the Norwegian Glee Club, and it was expected that the number of excursioners would be large. Contrary to expectations, however, there were hardly more than one hundred passengers. Probably the public was deterred by the lateness in the season. At nine o'clock the steamer left from Graham Morton's wharf with the excursionists on board. It was the steamer Mary which had been rented, and it was decorated with flags and pennants. Of course, the Norwegian flag was wafting from the foremast. Passing down the river, the Northern Light band played, and the Glee Club gave vocal numbers.</p>
   <p>The weather was excellent, Lake Michigan lay mirror like, not a breath of wind the whole day. The steamer arrived at St. Joseph at 2 P. M. and the excursionists paraded to Lake View Hotel where an elegant dinner was served. After the dinner, three street cars were at hand to take the guests through <pb facs="5423969_3_0102.jpg" n="2"/>the town to Benton Harbor and further on to Orchard Park where the party enjoyed itself for several hours by singing music, and dancing. Many Michigan people joined in the fun and the afternoon passed very quickly and pleasantly. At 8 P. M. the street cars were at hand once more, this time to bring the excursionists back to the steamer.</p>
   <p>Speeches were made both on board the ship and in the park. On the home-voyage there was dancing on board the ship. At 2 A. M., Monday the party arrived in Chicago again, and the agreement was universal that the excursion had been a grand success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
