<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-27">Feb. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Fraternal Insurance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-27">Feb. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">FRATERNAL INSURANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Illinois General Assembly is considering the question of fraternal insurance, and the lawgivers are finding that it presents a riddle that is by no means easy to solve. As we know, there is in this country a very large number of societies that insure their members on the so-called assessment plan; that is, the insured individual does not pay a definite annual premium for his policy large enough to cover the actual cost of the insurance. When a member dies, however, each member of the society is assessed and the total assessment is large enough to pay the policy of the deceased member. As stated before, there is a large number of such societies in America, and no less than one hundred and fifty in Illinois. One of the largest societies, the Modern Woodmen, was organized in Illinois.</p>
   <p>Several of these societies are now in difficulties, and the attention of <pb facs="5423969_3_1067.jpg" n="2"/>the legislature has been directed to the matter which concerns millions of homes in this country. The Ancient Order of United Workmen is one of the societies that is unable to meet its obligations. According to the latest report to the Department of Insurance in Illinois, this society owed $158,000 in insurance claims and was unable to pay. There is not much hope here for the widows and orphans to whom this money is owed. The United Workmen have lost six hundred members during the past thirteen months and have gained only thirteen new members. In other words, the requirements for money to pay to policyholders is constantly increasing while the number of those who are to pay the amounts is constantly decreasing. The Modern Woodmen and many other societies are in a similar position.</p>
   <p>The officers of a number of societies have realized that things are going badly and have tried to have rules amended so as to make the policy payments higher. As a rule, however, the members have opposed such increase in their expenses, and that is the end.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1068.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It has been held that the legislature ought to take this matter in hand so as to fix a minimum premium large enough to safeguard the insured, and that the state ought to supervise these societies in the same way that it supervises the regular insurance companies. Insurance Commissioner Potter, however, advises against this. He holds that it ought to be left to the societies or to the members themselves to solve their difficulties. He also believes that the legislature should not eradicate the difference between the regular insurance companies and the assessment societies. On the contrary, he says, this difference should be accentuated as much as possible in order that people may become fully aware of what they are doing when buying life insurance.</p>
   <p>Governor Deneen, in his message to the legislature, recommended that there be arranged a "test of solvency" for assessment societies, the rules to be prescribed by law. Under such a law the Department of Insurance would be able to take proper steps in time to prevent a fraternal insurance <pb facs="5423969_3_1069.jpg" n="4"/>society from reaching such a state of insolvency as to get beyond restitution.</p>
   <p>The question is of great interest to millions of homes, and most of those who are directly concerned are people who can ill afford to lose their money. Many people informed in these matters hold that this type of insurance is insecure. On their initial stage these societies prosper; deaths are few, and there is a great accession of new members. But as deaths begin to increase in number, many of the members withdraw and the number of new members is low. Finally there are mostly old people left, and their surviving families get nothing when their providers die, although the latter had been paying the required assessments regularly from the very beginning or, at any rate, for a number of years.</p>
   <p>A few years ago Skandinaven presented the result of a critical investigation of these societies by an expert. The author had studied the list of <pb facs="5423969_3_1070.jpg" n="5"/>societies of the type mentioned, which had ceased to exist. He found that the average length of life of such societies had been fifteen years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
