<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-30">Apr. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[The Tabitha Hospital Question]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-30">Apr. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[THE TABITHA HOSPITAL QUESTION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an article in Skandinaven, Mr. W. F. Christiansen is once more bringing up the question of the Tabitha Hospital organization, and refers his questions in the matter to me for elucidation. I beg to state now that I did not reply to his former article in the Skandinaven, nor will I reply to his last article in the paper, for the reason that both articles, I am sorry to say, are so bitter in tone that a reply could serve no good purpose. I do not understand the reason for this bitterness, nor do I know what is the objective of Mr. Christiansen's fight in the various societies to which he belongs. It is to be noticed that he is not a member of the Tabitha Hospital Society.</p>
   <p>Whether Mr. Christiansen is able to strengthen his position in any of the societies to which he belongs, through his attempts to blacken us, the societies in question will have to decide for themselves. If he intends to use <pb facs="5423969_3_1362.jpg" n="2"/>the Tabitha Hospital or the Tabitha Society as a scarecrow, a case for other societies to beware of, and as a weapon to threaten the members of such societies to vote as he wants them to, all of this is something which the Tabitha Society can do nothing about. The matter does not vitally concern us; the type of action referred to is not especially considerate, but is perhaps natural. One may say, perhaps, that a good cause would not need the base means applied by Mr. Christiansen. I do not believe anybody within our Society would desire to expand the influence of the latter, or seek to enhance his or her influence within the Society by the use of action or attitude of types detrimental to the good work of other societies.</p>
   <p>Our Norwegian national traits are rich in characteristics that are laudable, such as honesty, faithfulness, sense of justice, etc. It is to be regretted that our traits contain also the reverse--our tendency toward division, our lack of ability or willingness to unite for good undertakings. So prominent is this trait that frequently it overshadows all the good traits mentioned above.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1363.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In conclusion let me state that the terms "Christian" and "belonging to the church" are used synonymously by many. To do so is not correct, however..... To illustrate: The Visiting Nurses Association in Chicago is sending nurses to take care of sick people who are poor, anywhere in the city. Nobody would dare deny that this Association is doing Christian work, that it is a Christian institution. Yet the institution has no church connection; it does not belong under any church or denomination.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
