<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-05-06">May 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Little History</title><title level="a" type="sub">Memoirs of the First Few Years after the Chicago Fire</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Danish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-05-06">May 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A LITTLE HISTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Memoirs of the First Few Years after the Chicago Fire</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of the fact that the Skandinaven has just celebrated its thirty-third anniversary, I think it is a good time to review the reconstruction of the Skandinaven in the hard years just after the great fire.</p>
   <p>As the readers know, the Chicago Fire started late on the night of October 8, 1871, and burned all day and all night on October 9. The building owned by the John Anderson Publishing Company, where Skandinaven had its offices, on South Water Street, was totally destroyed. With unbelievable speed the fire raced southwest toward the building, and soon it was known that the fire would reach the building, though for a while it looked as if the river would check the fire. We arrived about two-thirty in the morning; the building next door was already afire, and among flying firebrands we began to <pb facs="5423969_3_0551.jpg" n="2"/>carry out what we thought was the most important to save. We could not use the Clark Street entrance, which was a flaming hell, but the fire escape on the alley side of the building was still free of flames. We had carried a few things out, but it became so hot we could stand it no longer, and we soon fled toward Wells Street. When we looked back, our building was one great ball of fire, and the building near ours where the Danish paper Fremad had its office, actually went up like a torch.</p>
   <p>After resting a few minutes on the north side of the Wells Street bridge, we soon had to flee again, and at about four o'clock I arrived at my home on West Erie Street. Mr. Mortensen, my neighbor and the editor of Folkevennen, was sound asleep. I awakened him and we went to the home of Professor Sven Nielson, assistant editor of Skandinaven, where we showed him what little I had saved. He was very happy because the few records I carried were very important.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0552.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>About ten o'clock in the morning of October 10, we met Mr. John Anderson, Skandinaven's owner, and Mr. Knud Langeland, the paper's editor, running northwest on Milwaukee Avenue, and soon all of us were fleeing further west.</p>
   <p>Skandinaven (Daily Edition), May 7, 1899.</p>
   <p>A strong wind drove smoke and sparks more than two miles to the north of the fire, and time and time again John Anderson's home caught fire. Only by throwing water on the roof and sides of the house were the flames kept in check. This was a big job because all the water was carried in pails from a pump in the yard. A change in the direction of the wind saved the property.</p>
   <p>Trying to save the furnishings of the house, they dug a deep pit in the <pb facs="5423969_3_0553.jpg" n="4"/>yard, where everything movable, such as furniture, rugs, bedding, and food, was placed and later covered by dirt. This proved to be the hardest task of all. They even moved the piano into a pit in the yard; what a job it must have been!</p>
   <p>On the first Saturday following the fire, the Skandinaven appeared again. Anderson had had it set and printed in Wisconsin, and it was the only paper to appear on the streets for weeks to come. It was an odd sight to see the boys running through the streets selling the one and only paper published at the time, while flames and smoke were still reaching for the sky. People nearly mobbed the newsboys trying to get a copy of the comparatively few papers for sale. The boys sold the papers for ten and fifteen cents, and sometimes for a quarter.</p>
   <p>Later the Skandinaven, by accident, discovered a hand press in fair shape.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0554.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This they used, and a greater number of papers appeared and were sold as fast as they were printed. The Skandinaven, being printed in Norwegian, was read only by Scandinavians, but one could see groups on the street corners, listening to someone translating to people who did not read the language.</p>
   <p>The printers and setters offered to work for one-half of their usual wages, in order to help the paper in its new start. All insurance being cancelled, the paper needed capital; and it was a great effort to publish it in its daily form.</p>
   <p>The next place used to publish the paper was in a machine shop on the corner of Canal and Washington Streets. The noise there was terrible, but we worked like horses, and the paper was published as per schedule. Then we found a suitable place at 73-75 Kinzie Street, near Milwaukee Avenue. The subscriptions <pb facs="5423969_3_0555.jpg" n="6"/>poured in, and money was now available.</p>
   <p>In the summer of 1872, a competitor started the daily, America. The editors and staff were ex-employees of the Skandinaven; they had quite a lot of capital, so it is only natural that they proved to be real competition. But Skandinaven doubled its circulation every month. And even though the America did have a lot of money to work with, Skandinaven was soon able to buy the paper.</p>
   <p>The growth of Skandinaven was tremendous, and Senator J. A. Johnson of Madison, Wisconsin, and Victor F. Lawson (the present publisher of the Daily News and Record), became partners, and a new era began for the paper. The editorial staff had offices in the present Daily News Building, and we may truthfully say that the Daily News is the English offspring of Skandinaven.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0556.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Skandinaven started printing and selling books in 1877, so they acquired the building at 87-89 Franklin Street. Late in 1877, Skandinaven bought the Danish paper, Heimdal, which increased the subscription list by 2,000. Again the paper needed more space, so a building on Peoria Street, near Milwaukee Avenue, was purchased. This gave an impetus to the growing paper, which was now a national paper.</p>
   <p>The years of hard work just after the Chicago Fire showed that the paper had friends, good friends, that worked day and night to make the one-sheet "fire special" a great and assured success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
