<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-16">Oct. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Sandberg Explains His Proposals for Changing the Statutes by Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-16">Oct. 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Sandberg Explains His Proposals for Changing the Statutes by Karl Sandberg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The changes proposed in the statutes of the Tabitha Hospital Society are the following:</p>
   <p>(1) Paragraph 2 of Article II to be omitted; and</p>
   <p>(2) Article XIII to be omitted.</p>
   <p>Paragraph 2, Article II reads as follows: "Religious instruction and public worship shall not be under the supervision of the Society as such but shall be under the supervision of Lutheran ministers who belong to the Society and are in charge of congregations which subscribe to the Lutheran confession of faith."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1340.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Article XIII reads as follows: "There is to be a committee on spiritual matters. This committee is to consist of the ministers referred to in Article II. It shall be the duty of this committee to provide for the spiritual needs of the dwellers in the various institutions, and also provide the nurses with the necessary religious instruction and development, and to examine into same."</p>
   <p>On reading these paragraphs many people will probably change the stern judgment they have passed on the ministers belonging to this committee....It is hardly to be wondered at if some of them have come to consider all the members of the Society as their spiritual children. On the other hand, is it to be wondered at when old members of the Society, who have been active since its very beginning, are inclined to lose confidence in the ministers?....In 1894 and 1895 ministers of the Norwegian Lutheran Synod highly praised the Hospital as a national cause, the only cause of great importance in which all the Norwegians in Chicago might be interested without regard to political or religious <pb facs="5423969_3_1341.jpg" n="3"/>affiliations or to position in state or socity. They said they were in favor of a Norwegian national hospital as against a hospital dominated by some religious denomination. They also spoke in favor of leaving the control of the hospital in the hands of the board of directors and not with a group of Lutheran ministers....</p>
   <p>When the older members of the Society who still remember these assurances of old compare them with the words and acts of these same ministers as they come to us today, then these older members may well shake their heads. Nowadays these ministers, without being requested by the board of directors, hold public morning worship at the hospital; in the same independent way they deliver prayers at the annual socials for the nurses; they even warn, from the pulpit, against attending socials for the benefit of those who are suffering at the Hospital. Older members of the Tabitha Society thought it had been settled in 1895 that the Tabitha Hospital was to be a Norwegian national enterprise, and now they find that in the "committee on spiritual matters" they are <pb facs="5423969_3_1342.jpg" n="4"/>face to face with a power which, in matters of this type, is the supreme authority.</p>
   <p>For the reasons here given I move that the paragraphs referred to be eliminated from the statutes. Let it not be so that a handful of the members of the Society wield greater power than the Society itself. Let it be left with the board of directors to determine how to take care of the spiritual needs of the patients.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
