<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Orphanage</title><title level="a" type="sub">Unexpected Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN ORPHANAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Unexpected Aid</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Norwegian Orphanage was held last Monday evening at the Bethel Church on Humboldt Street. The meeting was well attended; the majority of those present were women.</p>
   <p>As both the president, Reverend Mr. Hetland, and the vice-president, Dr. Meling, were absent, Mr. Johannes Liabol was elected chairman for the meeting.</p>
   <p>The treasurer of the Orphanage Society, Mr. Hakon Thompson, gave a survey of the finances of the Society since the last annual meeting. The final statement of this survey was sadly received; it announced a deficit of $200 for the month of March; the expenses had exceeded income to the extent of the amount mentioned.</p>
   <p>At this point evidence appeared, however, of the truth in the old maxim, "When the need is greatest, help is closest at hand." [Translator's note: An old Norwegian Maxim.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1633.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A number of young ladies on the Northwest Side had formed a society some time ago, called "The True Friendship Circle". A delegation from this Circle was present and presented the treasurer of the Orphanage Society with $115 from the Circle. This amount added to the regular income of the Society is expected to pull the Orphanage out of the mud of deficit for the time being.</p>
   <p>The president of the True Friendship Circle is Miss Margrete Blom; the vicepresident, Miss Paulsen; secretary, Miss Miller; treasurer, Miss Norman. The chairman of the meeting of the Orphanage Society extended the thanks of the Society for the true friendship which the Friendship Circle had evidenced toward the children at the Orphanage.</p>
   <p>The remaining time of the meeting was given to discussion of the question as to whether the board of directors were to be authorized to give any of the children at the orphanage to suitable persons for adoption. In this discussion the Reverends Rygh; Ofstedal; Mr. Hakon Thompson; and the chairman participated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
