<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Ski Tournament]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[SKI TOURNAMENT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6. "Norge" Ski Club held its annual tournament on its hill at Cary, Illinois on Sunday, drawing a good crowd, and scoring a real success in spite of the poor condition of the snow. Anton Jaeger won the championship scoring 77 and 78 feet in two jumps. The distance cleared by Andrew Schancke was 78 and 79 feet, Edward Anderson 76 and 79 feet and Terje Jensen 81 and 82 feet. Although these three cleared greater distances in their jumps, the better form of Mr. Jaeger enabled him to score a greater number of combined points than his competitors, and he was awarded first place without protest.</p>
   <p>The tournament was strictly an amateur affair as far as competition was concerned, but the exhibition jumps by Aksel Hendriksen was a welcome addition to the regular program. His aerial somersault drew the greatest applause ever accorded a performer on Norge Hill. Starting at the very top of the steep slide he reached the take-off at express speed turning a complete somersault in thin air and landing safely on his feet continued in perfect form through the final turn at the end of the runway.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0770.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the boys'classes Frank Olsen, Clarence Hohnboc and Hjalmar Sorem were the victors, while in the older men's group G. Gundersen, Louis Olsen, H. Fogerheim and H. Brederup.</p>
   <p>The "Norge" Hill consists of a 75 foot tower erected on top of the natural hill increasing the length of the slide to such an extent that it is second to no other hill in the country. The combined excellence of Norge's Hill and club house (where refreshments were served) is bringing the annual National Ski Tournament to the "Norge" Hill in 1912. The entire meet will be held under the auspices of the Norge Ski Club of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
