<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-14">Dec. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-14">Dec. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of directors of the Tabitha Hospital Society held its regular meeting last Tuesday. Eleven members of the board were present. The report from the superintendent of the Hospital showed that sixty-three patients have been cared for at the Hospital in November. During the month there were 1,021 patient days, of which 668 have been fully paid for, and 353 have been free or partly paid for. The total income from patients was $848.30.</p>
   <p>The treasurer's report for November shows:</p>
   <p>Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Membership fees</cell>
     <cell>$60.63</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Patients' fees</cell>
     <cell>789.93</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Miscellaneous</cell>
     <cell>5.57</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lawn Party</cell>
     <cell>76.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donation from H. A. Haugan</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donation from Norwegians'Singing Society</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donation from Studebaker Mfg. Co.</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Other donations</cell>
     <cell>93.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1272.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance from October</cell>
     <cell>$ 264.51</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Income</cell>
     <cell>$1,449.64 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>1,209.66</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>In treasury, December 1</cell>
     <cell>$ 239.66 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Among the expenses is included $137.50 for interest on the Hospital's $5,000 mortgage to Mrs. R. Schwarz....</p>
   <p>Information was received that in addition to the above-mentioned gifts, $85 had been received in small contributions,and that Mr. A. T. Lindberg had increased his subscription to fifty dollars....</p>
   <p>Mr. Rommen reported that he had succeeded in having installed, without cost to the Hospital, a large automatic laundry washer which would make the laundry work at the Hospital easier and less expensive.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1273.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following request, signed by fifty members of the Hospital Society, was read:</p>
   <p>"To the Board of Directors of the Norwegian Lutheran Tabitha Hospital Society of Chicago:</p>
   <p>"We, the undersigned members do hereby request that you call a meeting of the Norwegian Lutheran Tabitha Hospital Society for Sunday, January 5, 1902, 2:30 P. M. at Scandia Hall, for the purpose of constituting a nominating committee in conformity with the constitution, and for the transaction of such other business as may be deemed of interest to the Society."</p>
   <p>A motion was made and adopted that the board of directors accede to the request. The secretary, Mr. Rommen, stated that the board was compelled under the constitution to do as requested. The paragraph of the constitution that deals with the question was read. It is as follows:</p>
   <p>"The board of directors is to call special meetings of the Society whenever it <pb facs="5423969_3_1274.jpg" n="4"/>is so requested in writing by twenty-five regular members of the Society."</p>
   <p>Messrs. J. Oleson, Carlson, Egeland, Reverend Bleken, and Dr. Torrison spoke in opposition to the calling of the meeting. Dr. Torrison declared that according to his understanding of the constitution, the annual meeting was the only place where the nominations committee could be legally elected. The present nomination committee, he said, was elected at the annual meeting in January, and if the board of directors now complied with the request to call a special meeting for the purpose mentioned, it would be calling a meeting for the avowed purpose of undertaking an illegal act.</p>
   <p>After a brief discussion during which it was pointed out that the nominations committee for the present year was not nominated or elected in accordance with the laws, Mr. Oleson said that the proposed special meeting could not act legally, that he was opposed to the calling of the special meeting, and as he wished to go home (it was past 10 P.M.), he moved that the meeting dissolve.</p>
   <p>The secretary replied to this by stating that the members of the Society have <pb facs="5423969_3_1275.jpg" n="5"/>the right, under the constitution, to hold the special meeting; that it was neither right nor considerate on the part of the board of directors to treat the request of the members in such a superior manner, since the request had been presented to the board in the regular way. The board of directors, he said, has no discretion in the matter. After these remarks the meeting was declared adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
