<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Nordfalles Lodge Celebrates Twenty-Fifth Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">Richest Scandinavian Society on the West Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORDFALLES LODGE CELEBRATES TWENTY-FIFTH ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Richest Scandinavian Society on the West Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Nordfalles (United North) Lodge celebrated its twenty-fifth anniversary on February 24 with a most pleasant social in the hall of the Danish Brotherhood Lodge No. 17, Hirsch Street and Fairfield Avenue. Nearly all of the one hundred and sixty members of the Lodge, and many of their friends, gathered for the festive occasion. An atmosphere of pleasant friendliness prevailed throughout, and this, in addition to the excellent program presented, seemed to give wings to time. Before the guests even suspected it, the hour of midnight had arrived, and it was necessary to think about going home.</p>
   <p>In addition to its being the anniversary celebration, the occasion had been taken to remember the past president, Mr. John Wennberg; he was presented with a handsome easy chair and a few other things by the financial secretary of the Lodge and the master of ceremonies of the evening, Mr. John Hansen. Mr. Wennberg <pb facs="5423969_3_1072.jpg" n="2"/>expressed his most cordial thanks for the gift in words appropriate to the occasion.</p>
   <p>The social proper started about 8:30 P. M. when the president, Andrew Anderson, welcomed the guests on behalf of the committee on arrangements and the Lodge. Almost at the same moment, orchestral music was heard in the lobby, and as the doors were opened the Liberty Band, led by Charles Nergard, came marching into the hall to the tune of "Sonner af Norge" (Sons of Norway), while the audience arose and applauded. This excellent orchestra played for quite a while. Selections by Mr. Olaf Schow, violinist, and Frida Larsen, pianist, then followed.</p>
   <p>The heroine of the evening, however, was Mildred Miller, the little daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Miller, 1184 Rockwell Street. Scarcely six years old, she recites in such a delightful manner that many of the grown-ups would be unable to match her liveliness and ready expression. Her voice is clear and soft; <pb facs="5423969_3_1073.jpg" n="3"/>she speaks so clearly and with such perfect pronunciation that there is hardly a fault to find, and her mimicry is excellent.</p>
   <p>She also rendered two vocal solos, and the audience enjoyed her singing as much as her recitations; it was difficult to still the continuous demands for encores. Twice, little Mildred had to repeat her recitations. She seemed to be at home in every medium she essayed. Now it was a humorous story which made the audience shout with laughter; now it was a sad occurrence presented in such a way as to bring the audience to tears.</p>
   <p>Among the others who contributed to the success of the social may be mentioned....the Humboldt Ladies' Quartet....which was rewarded with thunderous applause for its most excellent singing.... It is doubtful if there is another Scandinavian ladies' quartet in all Chicago to compare with the Humboldt.</p>
   <p>The Nordfalles Lodge, now twenty-five years old, is one of the richest societies <pb facs="5423969_3_1074.jpg" n="4"/>among Scandinavians in Chicago. Over the years the Lodge has paid more than nine thousand dollars in sick aid, three thousand dollars for medical aid, and about two thousand five hundred dollars in the form of insurance to the families of deceased members. At present, the Society has funds in its treasury amounting to about two thousand dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
