<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-07">July 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Orphanage Will Be Built in Edison Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-07">July 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN ORPHANAGE WILL BE BUILT IN EDISON PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This week the Society for a Norwegian Orphanage held a well-attended quarterly meeting at the Zion Lutheran Church.</p>
   <p>The meeting was one to be long remembered in the history of this benevolent institution. A resolution was passed to erect the new orphanage building in Edison Park in spite of the school conditions there. The old building plan was discarded and the more up-to-date cottage plan was adopted. Finally it was decided not to move faster than the means in sight permitted. Consequently the new orphanage will have to start with room enough for only eighty children.</p>
   <p>The school question was settled with an arrangement for the appointment of two teachers at the orphanage. This arrangement will entail an extra expense of about six hundred dollars per year. In spite of this, it was calculated that it will be less costly to maintain the institution outside the city limits than inside the city limits. Through the private school arrangement there will also <pb facs="5423969_3_1567.jpg" n="2"/>be opportunity for better instruction in Norwegian and in religion. These branches will probably be listed among the regular courses.</p>
   <p>The new orphanage will be constructed in accordance with the cottage plan. By adopting this plan several advantages will be gained. First of all, it will be easier to enlarge the orphanage as need requires and as finances permit. Second, it makes the orphanage safer for the children in case of fire. Third, it makes it possible to keep boys and girls better segregated.</p>
   <p>President Ellestad's comprehensive special report to the quarterly meeting contained a discussion of the matter. Further details will be presented when the committee meets again.</p>
   <p>The reports from the financial secretary and the treasurer showed that the Society had received and expended during the past three months $1,038.08 for current expenses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
