<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1897-11-29">Nov. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Nansen in Art</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-11-29">Nov. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">NANSEN IN ART</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Skandinaven</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: Sometime ago, Mr. Olaf Ellison suggested in these columns that a bust of Dr. Nansen, in bronze or marble, be made by a Norwegian artist, and that some public-spirited Norwegian, or Norwegians, of Chicago, furnish the necessary funds. He suggested further that the bust be presented to the Chicago Art Institute, where it would serve as a lasting monument to the name of the man whose features were reproduced, to its generous donor, and incidentally, to the Norwegians of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is singular and not at all creditable that the Norwegians, alone of the three Scandinavian nationalities, are as yet absolutely without representation in the Art Institute, not to mention our heretofore evident failure to erect <pb facs="5423969_3_0948.jpg" n="2"/>a monument in some park. Our brethren, the Swedes and the Danes, are well represented in the Art Institute and in the parks as well.</p>
   <p>Are the rich, old Norwegian Vikings hiding?</p>
   <p>Of course, they dug into their pockets when the Viking ship was brought [over] and presented to the Fields' Columbian Museum, and when they brought [over] C. Krogh's painting and presented it to the same institution.</p>
   <p>Neither the donors, nor the Norwegian people in general, have been entirely satisfied with the manner in which the proper authorities have treated these generous gifts. But the possible lack of appreciation shown in these two cases does not bar success, if Mr. Ellison's suggestion be acted upon.</p>
   <p>That the idea of selecting Dr. Nansen as the subject for such a bust is a happy one, is demonstrated by the esteem and popularity he is enjoying, so deservedly, among all classes and nationalities, and by the eager interest and sincere <pb facs="5423969_3_0949.jpg" n="3"/>admiration with which the story of his deeds is received.</p>
   <p>Mr. Asbjornson, whom Mr. Ellison proposes as the right man to do this work, is, as we all know, a young, talented Norwegian sculptor, struggling hard in our midst to reach his goal: a name and success as a Norwegian sculptor in the United States. His several busts of prominent Norwegians and others in this and other cities--lately that of Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesn--have gained for him confidence in his talent from all who are acquainted with his works.</p>
   <p>Is there any Norwegian with heart and means--there are many with either--to put this idea into reality, thus engraving his name on the honor roll of the Norwegian colony in Chicago, as the donor of a bust of Dr. Nansen to the Art Institute? A name thus made will endure, even though the rest of the donor's deeds may be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
