<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>, 
<date when="1913-05-03">May 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Concert of the Old People's Home Society]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>, 
<date when="1913-05-03">May 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[CONCERT OF THE OLD PEOPLE'S HOME SOCIETY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The festival concert of the Old People's Home Society, honoring its founder and honorary president, filled Wicker Park Hall to capacity Wednesday evening. The hall was beautifully decorated with palms, flowers, and flags, and an excellent program was given that made the evening a real treat.</p>
   <p>The Trier sisters (there are five of them--two sets of twins and one other), sang solos and duets, and presented musical numbers for quintets and quartets. They also gave recitations and took the audience by storm. They are a very pleasing and talented group, such as is seldom found in one family.</p>
   <p>The aria by Meyerbeer and "Norge Mit Norge" (Norway, my Norway), sung by Mrs. Ella Ring Ingraham, were exceptionally well rendered and applauded accordingly. The Italian band "Banda Roma", did very well, and is to be commended for modulating its music in deference to the eardrums of an indoor audience. Few bands seem to realize that a band concert in a small hall is torture, rather than enjoyment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The greatest interest was centered about the new tenor, Mr. Woll. Any existing pre-concert anxiety was promptly dispelled when this singer presented his first offering. He possesses a rich, mellow, and well-trained voice whose appeal more than makes up for a lack of volume, and his enunciation and expression give real pleasure to the listener.</p>
   <p>Mr. Woll's place in the hearts of music-lovers of Chicago is thoroughly established. In spite of the caption "No Encores," printed on the program, the applause after each song by Mr. Woll made it impossible to continue until an encore had been given. Truly, Mr. Woll "came, saw, and conquered."</p>
   <p>The tribute paid Dr. [N. T.] Quales by Mrs. Julia Walther was a true expression of the love and respect of our people for this grand old man, who years ago dedicated his life to the task of bringing peace and sunshine into the lives of others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
