<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-07-15">July 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Singing Association Holds Picnic</title><title level="a" type="sub">Today the Singers Meet at Elm Tree Grove</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-07-15">July 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN SINGING ASSOCIATION HOLDS PICNIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">Today the Singers Meet at Elm Tree Grove</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee on arrangements for the picnic held its last meeting on Friday, and if one may judge from the reports of the various subcommittees, the beautiful and large Elm Tree Grove will not be too large today. This occasion will be one at which the Norwegian population in Chicago, adults and children, young and old, come together to have fun and to give their support to the singing societies which on all occasions have been willing to lend a helping hand.</p>
   <p>On the other hand one needs to remember that the program is of a type which the Norwegians in Chicago rarely have had the chance to enjoy. Among the speakers may be mentioned Senator Niels Juul [Danish], Mr. Alfred T. Johnson, and Mr. G. Katzenberger. Good Norwegian music, chorus singing, and turner exhibitions constitute the serious part of the program.</p>
   <p>The two world-renowned black magicians, Owahowa from Zulu and Tootai from Guinea, <pb facs="5423969_3_0110.jpg" n="2"/>are to compete in sausage eating. Each is to start at his end of the sausage, then they eat in their fiery way until they meet somewhere in the neighborhood of the middle; and in order that they may not eat each other when their mouths meet at the middle of the sausage, two watchers have been appointed to prevent possible cannibalism.</p>
   <p>After this the beautiful song "Mindets Bager" (Toast To The Past) will be sung, the singers dressed as vikings. A number of comic songs will also be sung. Then there will be various kinds of races with prizes distributed. There is every reason why the Norwegians will turn out in large numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
