<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-11-14">Nov. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-11-14">Nov. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Fram Branch of the Tabitha Hospital Society held a meeting last Tuesday for the purpose of continuing the discussion and consideration of the proposed changes in the constitution of the Society. More than one hundred and fifty members were present.....Mr. O. A. Thorp functioned as chairman.</p>
   <p>On a motion by Dr. Karl Sandberg it was unanimously decided to continue the discussion of Mr. H. A. Haugan's motion to change the constitution. Mr. Theodor Hansen agreed in Mr. Haugan's proposal that a majority of the members of the board of directors ought to be members of the Norwegian Lutheran Synod....It is not dangerous to have the ministers lined up on the side of the Hospital....If the proposal were adopted, funds could be collected among the members of the Synod....The Synod has a total of 67,000 members with 298 ministers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1303.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All the members counted in the Synod are confirmed, and children are not included. The Synod does not want the Hospital but will probably lend it a helping hand if the proposal is adopted.</p>
   <p>Dr. Karl F. M. Sandberg asked how many Synod members there are in Chicago. Mr. Theodor Hansen replied that he did not remember. Dr. Sandberg then said that reference had been made to the wealth of Augustana Hospital [supported by the Augustana Synod], but the wealth of that Hospital had not been derived from gifts. In proportion to its size the Tabitha Hospital had received far greater help from outside than the Augustana Hospital....The latter hospital in 1899 received only eight and one-half per cent of its total income from donations, while the Tabitha Hospital in 1900 received twenty-one per cent of its total income from free-will gifts, that is, nearly three times as much as the Augustana Hospital. [Translator's note: He also referred to other hospitals having church connections.] Dr. A. Holmboe....insisted that the whole matter resolved itself into a question of money. Help is needed, and to <pb facs="5423969_3_1304.jpg" n="3"/>get this help it is necessary to have the backing of a church body.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Rommen spoke as follows:</p>
   <p>"Those in favor of this Synod proposal say that the matter at issue refers only to the finances; as soon as the Tabitha Hospital gets this backing, then the money will come from the Synod people out in the country, and not only money but patients as well. In order to strengthen this assertion they have, both at the last meeting and several times before, referred to the Swedish hospital which is backed by a large church organization that supports the hospital with contributions from its many congregations. 'Just look and see how well off that hospital is,' they say. Well, let us see what this oftmentioned institution has received in cash gifts from all these congregations out in the country, and all the rest of its contributors as well. According to the institution's official report, the income during the past three years from direct and indirect gifts amounted to about $9,600, that is, less than <pb facs="5423969_3_1305.jpg" n="4"/>seven per cent of the total income. If this institution has been able to reduce its debt by twenty thousand dollars, this reduction has been achieved not through gifts received but through business operations.</p>
   <p>"Our Tabitha Hospital, which during this period has stood under strong Synod influence, received from Chicago people during the same years in direct and indirect donations $9,300 or twenty-seven per cent of the total income. The debt of our Tabitha Hospital on January 1 was $7,700 or about twenty per cent of the value of the Hospital property. The Augustana Hospital has a debt which equals twenty-six per cent of the property value of that Hospital. Clearly the debt on our Hospital cannot be very much of a danger to our institution. To remove fear from the members of the Fram Branch and others I may inform them that for the month of October the total income of the Hospital was $1,355, of which $1,070 was patients' fees."</p>
   <p>Dr. Marie Olsen stated....that the Tabitha Hospital has room for forty patients <pb facs="5423969_3_1306.jpg" n="5"/>while the average number of patients of late has been twenty-five. To take care of these the Hospital employs twenty-four people. The doctor suggested that the board of directors be more careful as to expenses.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Doe wished to hear from the Synod ministers present concerning the freedom of conscience that would prevail if the Hospital were turned over to the Synod.....He thought also that to collect money from the farmers for the Hospital in the manner suggested tasted of fraud....</p>
   <p>Reverend M. K. Bleken was the next speaker. On behalf of the Synod ministers he wanted to explain their point of view. [Translator's note: Reverend Bleken gave a somewhat detailed account of the Synod ministers care for souls in the Hospital.] Nobody can be compelled to become a Christian. If he states directly that he does not wish ministerial visits, the patient in question will not be disturbed....To those who belong to a church different from ours, our attitude is like that of a doctor to another doctor's patients....We do not try to <pb facs="5423969_3_1307.jpg" n="6"/>proselyte. There is free access to the Hospital for any minister who has church members there....</p>
   <p>Captain John Anderson moved to conclude the discussion of Mr. Haugan's proposal. This motion was passed.</p>
   <p>Continuation of Discussion on Changes in Constitution</p>
   <p>The chairman declared Mr. H. Rommen's proposal for changes in the constitution of the Society open for debate. The following paragraphs in the constitution of the Norwegian Lutheran Tabitha Hospital Society are to be changed as indicated below, in the motion proposed by Mr. Rommen:</p>
   <p>Article six is to be altered by the following addition:</p>
   <p>Paragraph 3. Every branch of the Society shall have the right to one representative on the board of directors for every thirty members. These representatives <pb facs="5423969_3_1308.jpg" n="7"/>are to be elected by the branches at their last meeting prior to the annual meeting of the Society, and their names placed before the annual meeting; they are to be elected for three years and remain in office until their successors have been elected and inaugurated.</p>
   <p>Every branch of at least thirty members shall also, at its last meeting before the annual meeting of the Society, elect one of its members to represent it on the revisions committee and another member to represent it on the visiting committee; both of these are to be elected for one year and shall remain in office until their successors have been elected; their names are to be reported to the annual meeting by the branch.</p>
   <p>Article seven, paragraph one is to read as follows: Direction and control of the business and the funds of this Society shall repose in a board of directors to be elected by the branches in the manner prescribed in Article six, paragraph three.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1309.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Article seven, paragraph two, last sentence is to be changed so that the word "eight" is omitted and replaced by the words "a majority".</p>
   <p>Article eight is to be omitted.</p>
   <p>Article nine, paragraph one is to read as follows: There is to be a revisions committee, to be elected in the manner prescribed in Article six, paragraph three.</p>
   <p>Article ten, paragraph one is to be changed so as to read as follows: There is to be a visiting committee, to be elected in the manner prescribed in Article six, section three.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: There now follows a recital of Articles six, seven, eight, nine, and ten in their unchanged form.]</p>
   <p>Mr. Rommen began his remarks by declaring that the adoption of his proposal would give the Society more direct access to the board of directors. As matters are, <pb facs="5423969_3_1310.jpg" n="9"/>he said, the committee on nominations puts up two candidates for each office, and only rarely does one know for whom to vote until the printed ballots are distributed on election day. Thus the nomination committee is a sort of elections committee, choosing its own successors, while the members have but little to say. It is decidedly better that the various branches elect the representatives they wish to the board of directors.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Holmboe agreed that the present election methods were not satisfactory, yet he could not agree in Mr. Rommen's proposal in its present form.</p>
   <p>Attorney Oscar M. Torrison believed that the present laws ought to be improved. According to Mr. Rommen's proposal, however, branches having less than thirty members will have no vote whatever; the laws permit twenty or more members to form a branch. On the other hand, the larger branches may have three or more members on the board of directors. For these reasons he could not vote in favor of the proposal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1311.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Dr. Marie Olsen expressed pleasure on hearing that there was agreement as to the desirability of change in the paragraphs under discussion. As matters now stand, she said, there are branches counting only eleven members that are represented on the board of directors by three members, while one branch of sixteen members has four representatives on the board. On the other hand, there are branches of more than one hundred members that do not have any representatives at all on the board of directors. The branches ought to be represented in proportion to their membership; that would produce greater interest in any activity for the Hospital. The change ought to be made now, since the membership has increased from three hundred to nearly twelve hundred.</p>
   <p>The question was raised as to whether the proposed change could be made without first getting an opinion from the state authorities on the matter. Dr. Sandberg stated that it would not be necessary to consult the state authorities.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Holmboe asked whether Dr. Marie Olsen was not the representative on the <pb facs="5423969_3_1312.jpg" n="11"/>board of directors from the Norge Branch. Dr. Olsen replied that she was elected representative from the Northwestern Branch; she had belonged to that Branch for several years, she said.</p>
   <p>Attorney Torrison did not believe that it mattered much to what branches the members of the board of directors belonged, as long as the directors elected were able people. He added that there are several life members of the Society, not belonging to any branch. One of these, he said, is the present treasurer, Mr. H. A. Haugan.</p>
   <p>Captain H. Michelson said that it was necessary to get capable business people to serve on the board of directors, people who are interested and will work for economic leadership of the Hospital, no matter to which branch they may belong.</p>
   <p>The meeting was continued until Tuesday, November 26, at eight o'clock in the evening, at St. Paul's Lutheran Church, West North Avenue and Leavitt Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
