<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1879-04-22">Apr. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Leif Ericson Fund</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1879-04-22">Apr. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEIF ERICSON FUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To our forefathers belong undeniably the honor of being the first white men ever to tread upon American soil. We have authoritative historical data evidencing their early arrival on this continent, while reports of still earlier discoveries of this hemisphere are vague and uncertain and shrouded in mythological fog.</p>
   <p>In a couple of decades it will be nine hundred years since this great discovery took place, and it is now proposed to erect a monument in memory of this historical event, near the coast where Leif Erikson and his men landed after having sailed their tiny goat across the ocean. On this same continent, which Leif discovered, thousands of his nationals, men and women, have later found their homes, and this monument will for the coming generations, bear proud witness of the race which counts America's first discoverer among its <pb facs="5423969_3_0951.jpg" n="2"/>sons.</p>
   <p>But if this undertaking, so honorable for the Scandinavians, is to attain the national significance which it merits, the funds necessary for its completion should be contributed by our own people. The amount of each individual contribution is not so important but the participation should be general, so that it can truly be said that Scandinavians in America erected this monument. If, for instance, every man and woman of our nationality were to donate 25 cents, on the average, a sufficiently large sum would be collected to really show the world that we, as a people, honor our ancestors.</p>
   <p>But if a national subscription is to be undertaken, the invitation should be issued by our most prominent men. Supposing Ole Bull and Professor R. B. Anderson took the lead? The honor and fame which the violin virtuoso has won in the old as well as in the new world, has been reflected back on the nation, and among our countrymen on this side of the ocean, none has done more to <pb facs="5423969_3_0952.jpg" n="3"/>spread the knowledge of our people's history than Professor Anderson. Both of these men feel warmly for the mother country and our precious memories, and we hope that for the sake of promoting our national honor and dignity, they will go to the front and organize a national subscription for the Leif fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
