<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-13">July 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Full House for Norwegian Singing Society Film</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0411</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0411.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-13">July 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FULL HOUSE FOR NORWEGIAN SINGING SOCIETY FILM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is probable that Logan Square Theatre never has witnessed as large a crowd as that which filled every available space in the theatre last night as the showing of the Norwegian Singing Society's film A Tour Through Norway. The first showing of the film took place at the matinee at 3:00 o'clock in the afternoon. At that time the attendance was good in spite of rainy weather. But at the first evening exhibition the large theatre had become completely crowded by Norwegian men and women wanting to see the beautiful pictures from the land of their fathers. A large number were unable to get in the first evening; they had to wait until the 9:00 o'clock presentation or until today.</p>
   <p>The pictures, as a whole, were good. A couple of the selections from the exposition at Frogner, 1914, might have been clearer as to details, otherwise the pictures are of unusually good quality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0412.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The exhibition starts with a presentation of the old chiefs mansion at Frogner together with the members of the committee in charge of arrangements. After that the main entrance, the mass of people they are coming, by street-car, by auto, by horse-drawn vehicles, or afoot. Then the beautiful exposition grounds. It is the day of opening, the orchestra is playing and the king accompanied by the queen and the crown prince, appears in Royal splendor to give the festive touch to the opening ceremonies.</p>
   <p>In through the large exposition halls. the king moves with his entourage and to music from the orchestra, then, in the Hall of Machinery, Crown Prince Olav presses the button and the immense machines start turning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0413.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The pictures now move through the exposition grounds presenting the many phases of national life and activities represented, and afterwards the grandeur and beauty of Norwegian natural scenery roll forth as well as Norwegian farming, Norwegian fisheries, Norwegian industry, and Norwegian army.</p>
   <p>Between the first and second showing of the film the Norwegian Singing Society gave some beautiful selections. The film will be shown again this afternoon and tonight at 7:00 o'clock and at 9:00 o'clock. But those who want good seats had better secure them early.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
