<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-10">Feb. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Festival Honoring Ole Bull]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-10">Feb. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[FESTIVAL HONORING OLE BULL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Bjorgvin Male Chorus, with their families and friends, gathered at Bjorgvin Hall on Thursday to honor the world-renowned Norwegian music idol, Ole Bull. Promptly at 9 P. M. the waiters entered with great bowls of the traditional fiske (fish) pudding, to the accompaniment of singing by the Norda Ladies' Chorus and violin and piano music by Mr. and Miss Jaeger. Mr. Jaeger, in harmony with the occasion, wore his newly awarded decoration given by the Norwegian Student Singers Guild, and other awards for musical achievement.</p>
   <p>The speaker of the evening was Mr. Sigurd Dahl, who spoke knowingly of what Ole Bull had been to Norway and the musical world in general. Surely not one of the gathering left without a fuller knowledge of the great contribution Ole Bull had made to lovers of real music. He voiced his regret that younger generations have not been given the opportunity to learn more of the language, music, and literature of Norway, stressing this loss to be due to an inability <pb facs="5423969_3_0149.jpg" n="2"/>to understand and speak the Norwegian language. The present generation, outside of a few advanced musicians, know little or nothing of the influence of Ole Bull and his violin.</p>
   <p>Mr. Forthun spoke for Norway and, although he said he was a mere amateur as a speaker, he handled his subject like a veteran, revealing an extensive and intimate knowledge of Norway's history, traditions, and culture. Re gave a word picture of Norway of today, showing a country small in size but big in advancement and achievement, a country of the future, industrially, culturally, and sociologically.</p>
   <p>The Bjorgvin Chorus sang several old Norwegian masterpieces, among which "Norge, Norge," and "Naar Fjordene Blaaner," by Chicago's own professor Alfred Paulsen, were easily the most appreciated.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ben Blessum spoke impressively of the song as part and parcel of Norwegian <pb facs="5423969_3_0150.jpg" n="3"/>life, and what national anthems have meant to various nations. After having heard Mr. Blessum's talk on "Song, the Soul of a Nation," we see this part of our old Norse culture in a clearer and richer light than ever before.</p>
   <p>Other speakers included Mr. Rosenberg, Mr. L. Birkodal, Gustav Ericksen, and Alfred Olsen, all of whom spoke of music in various forms. As a special feature of the festival, all speakers, with the exception of Ben Blessum, were from Bjorgvin's own membership. The Ole Bull celebration is to be an annual event at Bjorgvin Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
