<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-04">Mar. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Ski Club Norge]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-04">Mar. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[SKI CLUB NORGE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 5. - "Ski Klubben Norge" (The Ski Club Norge) enjoyed a festive occasion at Jacobsen's Hall last Sunday evening when prizes for the ski tournement were awarded. Hearty rounds of applause greeted each winner as he came forward to receive his prize.</p>
   <p>Anton P. Jaeger was awarded first prize plus an additional prize for perfect form, although Mr. Schanke made longer jumps but lost out on form. Mr. Jaeger was a free-lance entrant in the tournament but became a member of "Norge" at this meeting. Frank Olsen of the boy's class, and G. Gunderson, of the men's class, were awarded first prizes in their respective classes.</p>
   <p>Around the punch bowl the boys demonstrated that in addition to being proficient on skis, they were able speakers as well. All lauded the clean-cut sportsmanship of the contestants in the tournament and Mr. Anderson spoke enthusiastically of the growing popularity of skiing as an American winter sport and proposed a "Skaal" for Norge's future and the international ski tournament to be held at the Cary Hill in 1912.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0766.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Edward Johnson pointed out the rapid growth of ski activities throughout the U. S. A. and Canada. In fact when one considers the recent date of its introduction, skiing as a winter sport compares favorably with baseball as a summer sport. He also complimented "Norge" because its members had won most of the prizes in spite of the fact that the Chicago boys were at a disadvantage, owing to their lack of training facilities as compared to clubs elsewhere. Many of those are surrounded by hills where training can start with the first fair snow-fall.</p>
   <p>Terje Jensen who made the longest standing jump was awarded a special prize donated by Horsrud and Williamsen, two of "Norge's" members. Mr. Jensen had contemplated retiring at this time but with the international coming to Chicago next year he has postponed his retirement for another year. Mr. Jensen spoke feelingly of the sport as becoming one of the strongest links in the chain of good relationship between Norway and the U. S. A. and paid a special compliment to "Nor" Ski Club which had reported with ten members coming here by private coach.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
