<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-11">June 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Scandia Beach</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contributed)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-11">June 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDIA BEACH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contributed)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scandia has opened a summer resort for members of Chicago's Norwegian colony. I have just returned from a trip to this resort; it was one of the most enjoyable trips I have made in many, many a day, and I feel that I should let my countrymen know of my experience. The resort, if we can call it that, is known as Scandia Community Beach.</p>
   <p>I was simply carried away with the beauty of the country, and upon my arrival at the property I found that it was all that had been told me and more. Words cannot describe Scandia Community Beach, for it is ideal in every way. In fact, all that has been said of this project is true, and you have not published any statements relative to Community Beach that I found untrue.</p>
   <p>Upon the arrival of our big party at Hayward, we were given a royal reception <pb facs="5423969_3_0445.jpg" n="2"/>and taken to a large log cabin where we were served a big fish breakfast by the ladies of Hayward. We were next taken to the office of Scandia Beach, where a large group picture was taken, after which we were taken in automobiles over the most wonderful and well-kept roads to grove and beach, which we were most anxious to see. After spending the forenoon looking over the place, we were entertained by the Chippawa Indians, and greatly enjoyed their council dances. With all their war paint on, and with their Indian music and songs, they put on a great show. During the afternoon a trip was made over the whole beach property, and we found that the twenty-two miles of streets were being put in first-class shape by two big tractors and grading outfits. We visited the big store right on the property, and found a big stock of supplies. As evening came, and it was time for us to leave, we all expressed the wish that we could stay just a day or two more.</p>
   <p>In closing, all I can say to the readers of Scandia is that this project is a real opportunity for pleasure, and, if you wish, for investment, I personally bought two lots near the Community Beach, on these lots there were a number of <pb facs="5423969_3_0446.jpg" n="3"/>real large trees, both pine and deciduous. I heartily recommend that anyone who can spend the summer there should buy a lot or two, and really enjoy a summer there. There is not a lot that hasn't plenty of trees on it.</p>
   <p>Scandia has done a wonderful thing in making possible this beautiful playground in the north woods. I certainly am happy that Mr. L. H. Lund, the editor of Scandia, carried out this idea.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
