<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Norske Klub, 40th Anniversary, 1890 to 1930</title><date when="1930-01">Jan. 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Norske Klub, 40th Anniversary, 1890 to 1930</title><date when="1930-01">Jan. 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greetings to members, ladies and friends on this day, the celebration of our club's 40th anniversary. There are many pleasant reflections that we can picture of these forty years, happy memories of festivals association among old friends and unselfish labors for the cause of our club. Through four decades of loyal and devoted efforts on the part of its membership the "Chicago Norske Klub" enjoys a position which possibly is unequaled by any Norwegian social club outside of Norway. The wide scope of interests which the club embraces, including theatrical plays, lectures art exhibits, receptions for distinguished visitors, as well as the clubs own social functions, membership meetings and every day associations, are the elements which have contributed to the clubs progress during the years. We look forward with great hopes for the future to further progress in our endeavors and continued fraternal spirit among the members. The Chicago Norske Club was founded through the consolidation of "Den-Norske-Kvartet Klub" and "Den Norske Klub, Chicago". The Norske-Kvartet Klub" was founded January 10,1890 under the name, "Skandinauiske-Kuartetklub in Chicago." This name was changed in 1897. The 40th Anniversary which we celebrate this year is based on the date from 1890. "Den Norske Klub" was organized March 1, 1905, and the consolidation of the two clubs took place June 21,1911. On <pb facs="5423969_3_0185.jpg" n="2"/>the occasion of the dedication of our present clubhouse in July,1917, a very interesting book was published, giving a historical sketch of the two former clubs and of the consolidated club up to that time. A short review from this book on this day may be of interest.... The club was invited by Norways Commissioner General of the World's Fair 1893 to be the chorus on the official ship receiving the Viking Ship as it sailed in to Chicago on its voyage from Norway. At the banquet given at the Auditorium Hotel in honor of Dr. Fridtjof Nausen in 1897, the official musical program was rendered by the club and in receiving the visiting student choirs from Sweden (1904) Norway (1905) Denmark(1911) the club also took active parts...... The official paper Blad Lue was a masterpiece of humor and satire and was read at the weekly meetings.</p>
   <p>The dramatic society of the club was formed in 1919 and of the first productions was a "shock" and one a "monster". The dramatic society has produced about thirty plays since it was founded, and a number of lectures a singing society formed in 1924 has enlived many of our occasions.... A Debating Society was formed in 1922, the Society succumbed in its infancy. The moral to be drawn is speak eazy. The club had successful exhibits, display of valuable paintings and works of sculpture <pb facs="5423969_3_0186.jpg" n="3"/>of our Norwegian American artists.......</p>
   <p>Distinguished guests who have visited our club is"Dr. Fritz of Nausen"and"Rould Amundsen", likewise John Bajer in 1922. The club also was headquarters for the Norwegian Students chorus on their visit to Chicago in 1925, and the reception - soiree given on this occasion was attended by over two hundred persons. The club also was headquarters for two conventions at Norwegian-American Engineers and Architects in 1917 and 1927. On this fortieth anniversary let us be resolved to carry on the traditions of our club, and let history of the past forty years be our inspiration for continued efforts to further the objects of the club.</p>
   <p>"CHICAGO NORSKE KLUB - PRESIDENTS.</p>
   <p>Wm. Gerner</p>
   <p>Jaachim G. Giaver</p>
   <p>A.Hummeland</p>
   <p>M. Kirkeley</p>
   <p>B.Osland</p>
   <p>C.F.Arnet</p>
   <p>T.A.Sigueland</p>
   <p>Thos. G. Pihljuldt</p>
   <p>J.W. Sinding</p>
   <p>H.Winther Busch</p>
   <p>Andrew Nesheim</p>
   <p>I.H.Faleida</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
