<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Children's Home at Edison Park</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-10-12">Oct. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHILDREN'S HOME AT EDISON PARK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Children's Home Society held a meeting on Thursday, Oct. 9. The various regular reports were read and adopted. The chairman's report was of special interest because it contained considerable historical information relative to the home. Part of it follows:</p>
   <p>About twenty years ago a few members of the Norwegian Lutheran Church started a home for children in Chicago.A Miss Abrahamson was selected to take care of the little ones. The common dwelling place for nurse and children was at Irving Park Boulevard and 58th Street.</p>
   <p>The number of children increased, then the fire came. The place grew smaller, yet the demands from orphans became more insistent from day to day. A plat of land was bought near Edison Park. Mr. Bessemen, a friend of the little ones, left sufficient money to pay for the land. A building to house girls was donated, in memory of Clara Jevne. Money was solicited <pb facs="5423969_3_1470.jpg" n="2"/>for a building to house boys, and for a main building. Soon it became evident, however, that a miscalculation had been made in regard to space; the buildings that had been provided proved inadequate. Year after year the average number of children has been about ninety. These children have received food, clothing, shelter, education; in short, a good up-bringing based on christian principles, a good home that is a real home. Many of the children know of no other home. When they vist the children's home they feel it as a homecoming, they enjoy being at the place.</p>
   <p>During these many years there have been great changes. Difficult problems have arisen and have been solved; times of depression have had to be faced,, but under it all the work has progressed. The Norwegian people in Chicago have given and gladly. With their own eyes they have seen the blessings springing from their own sacrifices. Today the home stands there, free from debt. Twenty-three and one-half acres of land comprise the grounds, there are four large buildings, a silo, and some minor buildings. There are cows <pb facs="5423969_3_1471.jpg" n="3"/>and a couple of horses. The crops are better this year than ever. A sewer system has been installed. Often in the past the prospects have been so dark that no way out seemed possible; at present we seem to be facing a brighter future.</p>
   <p>The Children's Home has had two important sources of income for several years, the "tag day", and the bazaar. One hundred of our ladies spread over the city on October 15. They start early in the morning and keep on till night fall. In wind and rain they have stood patiently receiving small gifts and large ones. Very hard work, but the love of the children keeps them at it. Our bazaar will be herd this year at Schoenhofen's Hall, the first week in November. Through these and other sources of income, sustenance is provided for one hundred and eight people.</p>
   <p>The chairman's name is L. Harrisville.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
