<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-23">Oct. 23, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Lutheran Deaconess Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-23">Oct. 23, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN DEACONESS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Deaconess Society held its fifth annual meeting Monday evening at the Church of the Covenant, corner of Robey and Iowa Streets. The meeting was well attended, and several out-of-town members were present.</p>
   <p>The meeting opened with worship led by Reverend C. E. Tiller. Mr. Adolph Larson was elected chairman of the meeting. Being also the president of the society, Mr. Larson reported concerning the work during the past year....and gave a brief survey of the work during the five years since the society was organized. The survey showed that the Deaconess Society has cared for 557 patients with a total of 22,282 sick days, of which 13,728 were free; 409 operations have been performed; and 650 patients have received free medical treatment and medicine outside the hospital. The deaconesses have visited 2,110 ailing and needy people.</p>
   <p>To meet current expenses, cash in the amount of $17,121 and supplies valued at $900 have been collected. The sum of $13,384 has been obtained for the building fund. Total income during the period was $31,369....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1327.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are at present twenty-two deaconesses and student deaconesses working under the society's supervision at the Deaconess Home and at the various stations. Reverend H. B. Kildahl, secretary of the society, reported that during the past year the cash receipts for current expenses....had been $5,147; receipts for the building fund had been $5,547. These amounts had been transferred to the treasurer. The treasurer's report is as follows:</p>
   <p>General Fund</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance as of January, 1901</cell>
     <cell>$ 175</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Income for current expenses</cell>
     <cell>5,147</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total available for current expenses</cell>
     <cell>$ 5,328</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>5,248</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance as of October, 1901</cell>
     <cell>$ 80</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Building Fund</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance as of January, 1901</cell>
     <cell>$ 1,928</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1328.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest</cell>
     <cell>$ 30</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Income</cell>
     <cell>5,547</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$ 7,505</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>1,205</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance as of October, 1901</cell>
     <cell>$ 6,300</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The assets of the Deaconess Hospital at the present time are as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash</cell>
     <cell>$ 6,300</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Real estate</cell>
     <cell>6,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Furnishings</cell>
     <cell>1,680</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$13,980</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Sister Ingeborg reported that during the past year there have been 146 patients treated at the Home with a total of 5,156 sick days, 2,979 of which were free. 139 operations have been performed during the year.</p>
   <p>Dr. S. Dahl reported concerning the patients, their illnesses, the operations, and the results. Dr. N. T. Quales reported on the instruction <pb facs="5423969_3_1329.jpg" n="4"/>of the Sisters and the plan of the school. Mr. A. P. Johnson reported on the difficult work of the committee in providing plans for the new buildings which would be in harmony with present-day demands for a first-class hospital and at the same time be within the means of the Society. He reported that a contract was about to be given for the brick work of a part of the building, the cost to be $7,500. The part of the hospital, which it is the intention to erect at once, will cost in the neighborhood of $40,000, and the whole building when completed will cost about $75,000.</p>
   <p>Proposals for changes in the constitution were then taken up. All the proposed changes were adopted with some slight alterations.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Adolph Larson and S. H. Halstad were re-elected to the board of directors for a period of three years. Reverend G. T. Rygh was also elected to the board for the same period....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
