<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-17">May 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Celebrate Norway's Independence]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-17">May 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[CELEBRATE NORWAY'S INDEPENDENCE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Norwegian Chicago, headed by the Norwegian National League, today celebrated Norway's independence day with a parade, speeches, picnics, and other festivals. This is the big day for Norwegians throughout the world, and Chicago is by no means the least among the celebrants.</p>
   <p>The government of Norway is parliamentary; a government which, although Norway is a kingdom, is of, by, and for the people. Small wonder then, that our Norwegians so easily and quickly became good American citizens, having already had this form of government in the mother country. Being well-ground in the principles of self-government before coming to this country, it is perfectly proper that we celebrates May 17th and honor the country where these ideas were impressed upon our minds.</p>
   <p>Hitherto, we have held two parades, but this year there will be one, due to the elimination of the long and bitter opposition accorded the National League by leaders of our Norwegian Churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parade will start at Leavitt and North, where Norwegian and American flags will be give to all children taking part, and will proceed west on North Avenue to Humboldt Park. Reverend Mr. Gullixon, pastor of St. Paul's Church, will speak to the speak to thechildren, and there will be a program of music and singing.</p>
   <p>The folk festival will be held in Brand's Park from 12:00 noon on. A program of athletic events will be held for old and young, and the speakers of the day will be W. Morgenstjern, attache of the Norwegian Consulate at Washington, D. C. and Edward F. Dunn, Governor of Illinois. Mr. Lasse Grundeland, Chicago attorney, will present the speakers. A musical treat is also in store for these who go to Brand's Park; the Norwegian Singers' League, composed of the four Chicago male choruses, will entertain with a program of patriotic and classical songs.</p>
   <p>The festival committee has done a lot of hard work in an effort to make this May 17th celebration one of real pleasure to our people and an honor <pb facs="5423969_3_0263.jpg" n="3"/>to the mother land. Outlying ledges and churches will have their own festivals for those who find it inconvenient to attend the city-wide festivities. Following the program in the park, there will be several hours of dancing to good orchestra music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
