<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1933-07-27">July 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Between You and Me</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1933-07-27">July 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">BETWEEN YOU AND ME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Between you and me--in a manner speaking--I am impelled to say a word regarding Professor Hanson's pleasant reference to my English. He has given me a similar compliment on one or two other occasions. As a rule, journalists do not receive many compliments, and especially not for their language or style. Some do not deserve them. There are, however, exceptions. I am personally acquainted with half a dozen newspapermen in this country--three in New York and three in Chicago--whose names ought to be enshrined in a journalistic hall of fame for the purity and the beauty of their English. Those from Chicago are L. H. Lund, Nicolai Grevstad, and Kristian Baun.</p>
   <p>Whether I am deserving of the praise he [Hanson] so graciously bestows upon me is a matter for him and others of my readers to decide. I am glad to note that, in the article, he pays my friend, Chief Justice John J. Sonsteby, a similar compliment for his good English. With this I am in complete agreement. I have known the judge a great many <pb facs="5423969_3_0435.jpg" n="2"/>years, in fact since his Von Humboldt school days, where he developed the use of good English in the school debating society.</p>
   <p>When compliments come from a qualified source they possess value. Certainly it is a source of satisfaction to know that Professor Hanson's competency to pass judgment is beyond question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
