<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-11">Oct. 11, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quarterly Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-11">Oct. 11, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quarterly Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Tabitha Hospital Society held its quarterly meeting at Our Savior's Church last Tuesday evening. The president, Karl F. N. Sandberg opened the meeting and was elected chairman for the meeting.</p>
   <p>Secretary H. Rommen presented the treasurer's report for the third quarter.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Total received for the quarter $2,755.66. Current expenses, third quarter $2,634.25.] The Hospital has a floating debt of $2,155 in addition to the mortgage of $5,000.</p>
   <p>At the training school for nurses there are eleven students. In the old-age division there are nine aged ones.....One hundred patients were treated during the quarter. Of these, eighty-one have been discharged as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1353.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>healed, forty-four; improved, twenty-seven; incurable, two; desiring to leave, two; dead, six.</p>
   <p>[There were] in the Hospital on September 30, nineteen.</p>
   <p>Eleven patients have been treated without charge, during 235 hospital days.</p>
   <p>Seven patients were paying in part; total hospital days, 204.</p>
   <p>Eighty-two patients have paid in full; total hospital days, 1,636.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar M. Torrison read proposals to make some changes in the by-laws. These will be printed soon and sent to the various Branches for consideration; later to be taken up for final study at the annual meeting in January.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1354.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee on building plans, elected by the board of directors on orders from the Society, to investigate the advisability of adding another wing to the Hospital, reported that there can be no doubt but that the present building is too small; it ought at least to be doubled in size.</p>
   <p>The committee did not recommend raising the money by increasing the mortgage, but did express their belief, however, that much money could be raised through subscriptions, and that an appeal ought to be made to Norwegians in America to come to the assistance of the Hospital.</p>
   <p>It was reported that the annual bazaar of the Tabitha Hospital will be held at Wicker Park Hall starting Monday, October 29 and continuing till November 3. The committee intends to apply the surplus from the bazaar to payment of the Hospital's floating debt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
