<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-31">Oct. 31, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well Attended Discussion Meeting Held by the Fram Branch of the Hospital Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-31">Oct. 31, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well Attended Discussion Meeting Held by the Fram Branch of the Hospital Society</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the invitation of the Fram Branch of the Tabitha Hospital Society, more than three hundred members of the various branches gathered on Tuesday evening in the Sunday-school rooms of St. Paul's Norwegian Lutheran Church.</p>
   <p>The president of the Branch, Mr. H. Kolderup, opened the meeting, stating that the purpose was to discuss the various proposals presented at the last quarterly meeting, to be decided at the coming annual meeting, and relating to changes in the constitution of the Society. A printed leaflet was distributed, containing the proposed changes in the constitution, together with a statement of the resolution previously adopted by the Fram Branch concerning the constitution.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kolderup introduced Mr. O. A. Thorp as chairman of the meeting, stating <pb facs="5423969_3_1318.jpg" n="2"/>that those opposed to the suggested changes as well as those in favor had been invited to the meeting; for this reason he thought it advisable that the chairman of the meeting be someone other than a member of the Fram Branch. He added that not one member of the Fram Branch belonged to any congregation under the Norwegian Synod.</p>
   <p>The chairman expressed his appreciation for the honor bestowed upon him. He called attention to the fact that there are four proposals for changing the constitution, one by H. A. Haugan, one by H. Rommen, one by Dr. Marie Olsen, and one by Dr. Karl F. M. Sandberg. He suggested that the proposal by Mr. Haugan be discussed first. A period of ten minutes was alloted each speaker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Haugan's proposal is as follows:</p>
   <p>"That Article 7, paragraph 1....be changed by adding the following words: 'A majority of the members of the board of directors are to be members of congregations belonging to the Synod for the Norwegian Lutheran Church in America."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Haugan introduced the question....He considered it absolutely necessary to have the Hospital backed by an organization, and a church organization seemed to him the best....Why cannot the Norwegian people steer their Hospital to success as well as the Swedes and other nationalities do in the case of their hospitals? The only way of doing it is to seek the support of a church organization.</p>
   <p>Dr. Marie Olsen stated....that the people want the Hospital run by Norwegians without reference to ministers and churches.....If the people felt certain that the Hospital was not to be governed by the ministers then there would be plenty of money for the running of the Hospital.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Holmboe said that he was no churchman; he had never belonged to any church in America, but he could not quite understand why some people feared ministers....All the hospitals in Chicago except the Cook County Hospital belong under some church organization or other. He had always found the ministers supporting the Hospital....He did not believe that the Norwegian Synod would be willing to accept the Hospital even as a gift.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1320.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. A. Jorgensen said....that the Norwegian people as such had the right to govern the Hospital; this right should not be taken away from them.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. Finholdt supported Mr. Haugan's motion. If that proposal had been adopted earlier the Hospital would have been free from many of its difficulties.</p>
   <p>Dr. Karl F. M. Sandberg....declared that the resent Hospital Society had received a large number of new members. There is no need to fear that the institution will not be able to maintain its existence.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. B. Oyen supported Mr. Haugan's proposal. Reverend Fred Ring did not believe that the Norwegian people who had been working for the Tabitha Hospital ought to be placed under the guardianship of the Norwegian Synod or any other church organization....The united Norwegian people will and ought to support the Hospital as a national undertaking.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Several other speakers took part in the discussion, some in favor of Mr. Haugan's proposal, others against, but no new arguments were presented.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1321.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Secretary H. Rommen read Fran Branch's invitation to the meeting,in which it is stated: "The financial position of the Hospital is not as favorable as in previous years. The debt has been increasing and contributions have been difficult to obtain. Unless the Hospital gets the support of a permanent organization it seems certain that its future is dark."</p>
   <p>"These invitations," continued Mr. Rommen, "have been sent in large numbers to the members of the Hospital Society. On behalf of the Hospital....I must denounce the document as misleading and false; it can only hurt the institution to have it distributed." [Translator's note: In support of this statement Mr. Rommen presented figures showing that the status of the Hospital had improved materially since 1895, being several thousand dollars more favorable in the present year.]</p>
   <p>On the motion of Dr. Sandberg the meeting dissolved, after the president, Mr. Kolderup, had invited the audience to a new discussion meeting to be held on Tuesday evening, November 12, at the same place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
