<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1927-12-24">Dec. 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian-American Historical Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1927-12-24">Dec. 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The press has not had much to say about the Norwegian-American Historical Society. This should not give us the impression that this society has not accomplished anything this past year. They have accomplished a lot. We list a few of these accomplishments below.</p>
   <p>First, they have published, in 1927, the following books and records:</p>
   <p>1. "Studies and Records," Vol. II. 137 pages.</p>
   <p>2. "The Norwegian Sailors on the Great Lakes; a chapter in the History of American Inland Transportation." 219 pages, 21 illustrations.</p>
   <p>3. "Travel and Description," Series II: Peter Testman's "Account of His Experiences". Norwegian and English Text.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Studies and Records" and "Norwegian Sailors" mailed free to members. Peter Testman's book free to sustaining members, to others upon request to Dean J. Jorsen Thompson.</p>
   <p>"Studies and Records" is published by the publishing committee, whose chief is Dr. Theodore Blegen. The contributors to these records are the following gentlemen: Martin B. Ruud, Dr. Henry J. Cadbury, Jacob Hodnefeld, Dr. Laurence M. Larsen, Dr. George T. Flom, and Professor George M. Stephanson. The records also contain all the minutes of the various meetings held by the Society.</p>
   <p>"The Norwegian Sailors on the Great Lakes" has been compiled by Dr. Knut Gierset and Dr. Blegen. Hundreds of people were interviewed, and actually thousands of documents and records read. But the result has been a document of great historical value to the Norwegian-American people.</p>
   <p>Peter Tesman's "Account" is, from the historical angle, a correct and authentic document.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0407.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The cost of "Norwegian Sailors" will be defrayed by A. M. Olsen and Birger Osland. The cost of the other documents was covered by individual donations.</p>
   <p>After two years of exhaustive research, the Society can proudly point to the publishing of eight volumes covering Norwegian-American history.</p>
   <p>The plans for the future are rather broad. Work has already begun on the following studies:</p>
   <p>"Studies and Records," Vol. III. The editorial committee are forever looking for old documents and records that will augment the material at hand.</p>
   <p>The finances for Vol. III have already been secured.</p>
   <p>The Society is at the present working on a document about the Norwegian immigration to America.</p>
   <p>Another volume of great interest is the pioneer preacher Dietrichsen's "Travels <pb facs="5423969_3_0408.jpg" n="4"/>among Norwegian Immigrants." Dr. Rohme has started the translation of this important work into English.</p>
   <p>"Munch-Raeder's Letters, 1847-48" will be translated by Gunnar Malmin. These letters contain very interesting material concerning that period.</p>
   <p>Plans are being made for research covering the Norwegian seamen's activities on the Eastern seaboard of the United States. This work will be done by Dr. Knut Gjerset. This will take a lot of money. It is our job to raise the money for this important work.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian-American Historical Museum that was opened some time ago, is coming along fine. Much historical material has been donated by the Norwegian Government. The museum is quite an imposing sight, with its enormous cases, filled with documents and books.</p>
   <p>D. G. Ristad, the president, informs us that arrangements are being made for a "historical mass meeting" to be held on the grounds of the museum. Meetings <pb facs="5423969_3_0409.jpg" n="5"/>Meetings of this kind should be held every year throughout the country. Meetings of this kind would popularize, not only the museum, but the Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
