<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-04">Nov. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Bjornson, Bull, and Company</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-04">Nov. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">BJORNSON, BULL, AND COMPANY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many funny things may be found in the English language press in our city about Norwegian societies and Norwegian and Norwegian-American matters. Last Sunday, however, the Chronicle published an article relative to the thirtieth anniversary of the Norwegian Singing Society which, from the standpoint of humor, surpasses much....of what has been presented in the line of distorted stories in that and other Chicago newspapers. In the article referred to we are told that "in 1870 ten members of the Scandinavian Turner Society came to Chicago. Among these were Ole Bull, Grieg, Selmer, and Bjornson, all of whom later won great fame. At first it seemed as if their cause was hopeless, but they worked hard, and with the assistance of some of their compatriots they succeeded in organizing the Norwegian Singing Society." It would take some search to find a story quite as far from the facts as the above.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0069.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ole Bull was, at the time, sixty years old and had attained about all the fame he was ever to reach; his name was acclaimed all over the civilized world in such a manner that one might have expected the echo of it to have prevented even a Chicago reporter from making a faux pas like that referred to.</p>
   <p>Even Bjornson, who was twenty-two years younger than Bull, had arrived somewhat further in 1870 than to come to Chicago, as a member of the Scandinavian Turner Society, to organize a singing society. Edward Grieg was born in 1843 and thus in 1870 was still young enough to have been an active turner of a sort, but at the time he was somewhat differently engaged, being the leader of the Philharmonic Society in Christiania, Norway. He had already won a considerable share of that fame which the reporter of the Chronicle is so kind as to accede him. As to the fourth "turner," John Selmer was in Paris, France in 1870, occupied with his great orchestra composition, "Scene Funebre".</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0070.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Further on in this same remarkable article the author informs us that "in 1872 the Norwegian Singing Society serenaded the Swedish Nightingale, Christian Nelson". He probably meant Christina Nilsson who, strangely enough, was in Chicago about the time referred to.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
