<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-05-05">May 5, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Unions, Lodges, and Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-05">May 5, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN UNIONS, LODGES, AND SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A. Singing Societies and Musical Societies</p>
   <p>1. The Norwegian Singing Society meets at Schoenhofen Hall, Milwaukee and Ashland Avenues. Singing practice is held every Wednesday. Business meetings are held every first Friday in the month.</p>
   <p>2. The Norwegian Glee Club holds singing practice every Thursday evening at eight o'clock in Joseph Dost's Hall, corner of Wabansia and Washtenaw Avenues.</p>
   <p>3. The Bjorgvin Singing Society meets for singing practice every Friday evening at 8:30 o'clock at Schoenhofen Hall, corner of Milwaukee and Ashland Avenues. Business meetings are held at the same place every first Monday in the month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1116.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>4. The Viking Marine Band holds its meetings in Scandia Hall every Thursday evening. The Band is affiliated with the Chicago Federation of Musicians.</p>
   <p>5. The Danish Harmony Singing Society meets at Schoenhofen Hall, 876 Milwaukee Avenue. Singing practice is held every Thursday evening at eight o'clock. Business meetings are held every first and third Tuesday in the month.</p>
   <p>6. The Normania Military Band meets at Field's Hall, corner of Temple and Huron Streets, every Wednesday evening from eight to ten o'clock.</p>
   <p>B. Athletic Societies</p>
   <p>1. The Norwegian Turner Society of Chicago meets at Aurora Hall, corner of Milwaukee Avenue and Huron Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1117.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Turner meetings are held every Tuesday and Friday evening from eight to ten o'clock. Boys' meetings are held every Thursday evening from seven to nine o'clock. The board of directors meets on the last Thursday in the month.</p>
   <p>2. The Danish Society of Sharpshooters meets at Sokup's Hall on the first and the third Tuesdays of every month.</p>
   <p>3. The Norwegian Sleipner Athletic Society meets in the evening, on the first and third Wednesdays of each month, at Scandia Hall, Milwaukee Avenue and Ohio Street. Practice meetings are held every Tuesday and Friday evening from eight to ten o'clock.</p>
   <p>4. The Norwegian Society of Sharpshooters meets on the first Tuesday of every month at Sharpshooters' Hall, 789 North Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1118.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>C. Temperance Societies</p>
   <p>1. The Scandinavian-American Temperance Prohibition Club meets every Tuesday evening at Harmony Hall, corner of Ohio and Noble Streets.</p>
   <p>2. The First Scandinavian Women's Christian Temperance Society holds its regular meetings every Thursday evening at 7:30 o'clock and every Sunday afternoon at four o'clock in its new hall at 281 West Ohio Street. The children's division meets every Monday evening. Socials, with fine singing, music, temperance lectures, and refreshments, are given on the last Thursday evening of each month. All Scandinavians are invited.</p>
   <p>3. The Temple Warden No. 51 meets every Sunday afternoon at four o'clock at 451 Mentmore Avenue. Everybody is welcome.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1119.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>4. The Temple Brother-Bond meets every Wednesday evening at eight o'clock, at Normania Hall, 235-37 Milwaukee Avenue. New members are received at all meetings. Everybody is welcome.</p>
   <p>5. The Scandinavian Harmony Abstinence Society holds meetings every Sunday afternoon at 3:30 in the hall of the Society, corner of Noble and Ohio Streets. Everybody is welcome. Social gatherings are held on the last Saturday of every month.</p>
   <p>6. The Success Lodge No. 966, I. O. G. T. [Independent Order of Good Templars], meets every Friday evening at eight o'clock in Harmony Hall, corner of Noble and Ohio Streets. Visiting members of the Order are always welcome. New members will be received at all meetings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1120.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>D. Unions</p>
   <p>1. The Scandinavian Bakers' Union No. 62, I. B. &amp; C. U. [International Bakers' and Confectionary Workers' Union], meets every second and fourth Saturday of every month at Hart's Hall, corner of Townsend and Locust Streets. The meeting hour is seven o'clock in the evening. Mr. Christian Svendsen is the secretary. His office, 174 North Morgan Street, is open every day from nine o'clock in the morning until six o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <p>2. The Scandinavian Shoemakers' Union meets every second and fourth Sunday of each month, at 2:00 P.M., in Nora Hall, 81-83 West Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>3. Scandinavian Local No. 194, Brotherhood of Painters and Decorators of America meets every Tuesday evening at 406 <pb facs="5423969_3_1121.jpg" n="7"/>Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>4. The Norwegian-Danish Typographical Union No. 272, I. T. U., meets on the first Tuesday of every month at Aurora Hall.</p>
   <p>5. The Independent Local Carpenter Union meets every Saturday at 8:00 P. M. in the hall at 402 Armitage Avenue. New members are received at these meetings.</p>
   <p>E. Women's Societies</p>
   <p>1. The Remembrance Women's Society meets every first and third Thursday afternoon from two to four o'clock, at Wicker Park Hall.</p>
   <p>2. The Thora Scandinavian Women's Society holds meetings on the first and third Fridays of every month. The Society offers <pb facs="5423969_3_1122.jpg" n="8"/>aid in illness to its members.</p>
   <p>3. Norwegian Women's Athletic Club meets on the first Wednesday of every month at 96 Bingham Street. The hour of meeting is two o'clock in the afternoon.</p>
   <p>F. Aid Societies</p>
   <p>1. The Danish Brothers in Arms meets every second and fourth Thursday of each month at Schoenhofen Hall, 876 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>2. The First Scandinavian Female Burial Society meets every second and fourth Monday evening at Nora Hall, corner of Green and West Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>3. The Society for the Danish Home for the Aged meets at <pb facs="5423969_3_1123.jpg" n="9"/>Lagoni's Hall, 690 West North Avenue, on the second Wednesday of every month. The hour of the meeting is 2:00 P. M.</p>
   <p>4. The Danish Lutheran Girls' Home is a Christian home for girls. The reading room is open every day for girls. Christian young people's meetings are held on the second and fourth Sundays of every month at 4:00 P. M.</p>
   <p>5. The Northern Light Norwegian Sick Benefit Society meets on the first and third Tuesdays of every month at Odd Fellows Hall, 428 West Chicago Avenue. New members are received at every meeting.</p>
   <p>6. The Danish Aid Society meets in Dania Hall, 251 West Chicago Avenue, on the second and fourth Thursdays of every month. The meeting hour is 8:00 P. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1124.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>G. K. of P.</p>
   <p>1. Denmark Lodge No. 112, K. of P. [Knights of Pythias?] meets every Monday evening at eight o'clock at 432 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>2. Dannebrag Division, U. R. K. of P., holds exercises every Wednesday evening at Aurora Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>3. Dagmar Lodge No. 446, K. of P., meets every Tuesday evening at eight o'clock in A. Plath's Hall, 195 West Division Street.</p>
   <p>H. K. of H.</p>
   <p>1. Dania Lodge No. 2665, K. of H., meets on the second and fourth Fridays of every month at 869 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1125.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>2. Scandia Lodge No. 1211, K. of H., holds its meetings at Odd Fellows Hall, 406-408 Milwaukee Avenue, on the first and third Saturdays of every month.</p>
   <p>I. K. &amp; L. of H.</p>
   <p>1. Freja Lodge 1079, K. &amp; L. of H., meets in Scandia Hall, 100 West Ohio Street, on the first and third Thursdays in the month.</p>
   <p>2. Northern Light Lodge No. 762, K. &amp; L. of H., meets on the first and third Fridays of every month at 81-83 West Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>J. R. H. K.</p>
   <p>1. Nora Lodge No. 1, R. H. K. [Knights of the White Cross] <pb facs="5423969_3_1126.jpg" n="12"/>meets on the first and third Thursdays of every month at Nora Hall, 81-83 West Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>2. Leif Erikson Lodge No. 9, R. H. K., holds its business meetings on the first and third Thursdays of every month, at 428 West Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>3. Dovre Lodge No. 18, R. H. K., meets on the first and third Saturdays of every month at the corner of Armitage and Milwaukee Avenues.</p>
   <p>K. A. O. U. W.</p>
   <p>1. Chicago Lodge No. 91, A. O. U. W. [Ancient Order of United Workme] meets regularly on the second and fourth Fridays of every month, at eight o'clock in the evening, in Flynn's Hall, North Avenue and Robey Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1127.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>2. Tordenskjold Lodge No. 15, R. H. K., meets on the second and fourth Fridays of every month at Nora Hall, 81-83 West Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>L. I. O. M. A.</p>
   <p>1. Norden Lodge No. 164, I. O. M. A., meets on the first and third Thursdays of each month at Lagoni's Hall, corner of North and Western Avenues.</p>
   <p>2. Court Republic No. 1043 of the Illinois Branch of the Supreme Court Independent Order of Foresters meets on the second and fourth Mondays of each month in Normania Hall on Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>3. The Society Nordlandingen, Inc., meets on the second and fourth Thursdays of every month, at the residence of <pb facs="5423969_3_1128.jpg" n="14"/>Mr. Hans Finstad, corner of California and North Avenues.</p>
   <p>4. The society, Daughters of Denmark, meets on the second Thursday of every month at Lagoni's Hall, 690 West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>5. The society, Sons of Denmark, meets on the second and fourth Thursdays of every month at Pearl's Hall, 1546 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Following the name of each society, lodge, and union, there is given a list of officials of the organization.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
