<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1904-01-23">Jan. 23, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Before the Battle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1904-01-23">Jan. 23, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Before the Battle</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are only 404 members in the Tabitha Hospital Society who are eligible to vote at the coming convention.</p>
   <p>The branches have representation, but it is not of a very democratic nature. Some of the branches with a small membership have a greater representation than several of the larger branches. This is not a sound situation.</p>
   <p>We hope that the convention will run smoothly with less strife and better results. It is about time that the factional differences are ironed out.</p>
   <p>When Women Are at War</p>
   <p>At about 9 P.M. last Tuesday, Dr. Marie A. Olsen, the president of the Society, called the convention to order. By order of the fire department the meeting <pb facs="5423969_3_1229.jpg" n="2"/>place had, as usual, been cleared of all combustible material, but no law could cool the hot tempers at the convention. The reporters from various newspapers were removed from the stage, possibly in order to make more room for the warriors. Dr. Marie Olsen, has no love for the press, and she tried to place the reporters as far away from the "scene of action" as possible. The reporters from Skandinaven were seated where nothing could be seen or heard; they did not try to cover the meeting at all, and promptly fell asleep. Scandia's reporter was placed closer to the stage, and though he could hear, he could see nothing of the "battleground".</p>
   <p>There was, at the opening of the session, about 350 people present, about two-thirds of them women. Some 50 visitors were seated in the gallery.</p>
   <p>The president declared that the first thing to do was to appoint a chairman for the meeting. This caused a great deal of confusion (according to parliamentary law the president cannot make any motions while in the chair). Mr. John Waage jumped to his feet and started to talk about the finances of the Hospital, <pb facs="5423969_3_1230.jpg" n="3"/>trying to confuse the issue still more. Soon every one was yelling. Dr. Anders Doe could finally be heard saying, "Are we going to be railroaded? Will nomination from the chair be permitted?" Dr. Marie Olsen banged away with her gavel, and other voices could be heard yelling "Mr. Waage cannot make motions".</p>
   <p>C. E. Fage grabbed Waage by the arm and tried to drag him away, asking him to be "parliamentary".</p>
   <p>Mr. Waage became angry and yelled, "Police! Police! Keep your hands off me!" An officer appeared, but one officer could do nothing among 350 people. Dr. Olsen called the wagon, but this all took time. (This is the usual procedure at a Tabitha Hospital Society convention.)</p>
   <p>Finally some order was restored, and M. Kirkery was elected chairman.</p>
   <p>We will not waste space on the greater part of the meeting, but will attempt <pb facs="5423969_3_1231.jpg" n="4"/>to bring out some of the most important things that transpired.</p>
   <p>Finally, after the arrival of an entire squad of police the balloting proceeded.</p>
   <p>When the result was announced, it was as expected.</p>
   <p>The following were elected as directors; Dr. Marie Olsen, Dr. Valborg Sogn, Miss Bella Olsen, Mrs. W. Johnson, and Mrs. F. Hammer. (All women.)</p>
   <p>Auditors were: John M. Pedersen, Marius Kirkeby, and Lars Johansen.</p>
   <p>The Visiting committee is composed of the following: Mrs. Emma Thaisen, Mrs. Emma Royalson, Mrs. Emma Wakman, Mrs. Henrietta Mathiesen, Miss Hilda Petterson, Mrs. Dr. A. Doe, Mrs. C. Sokup, Mrs. Anton Strand, Mr. T. L. Newgard, Mrs. Ole Gullixson, and Mrs. Louisa Morck.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1232.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The results were that practically the same people were re-elected; and the reason: poor representation from large branches and good representation from the smaller branches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
