<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-01-11">Jan. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Oldest Norwegian Lodge in America]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-01-11">Jan. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[OLDEST NORWEGIAN LODGE IN AMERICA]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nora Lodge of the Knights of the White Cross, the oldest Norwegian lodge in America, will celebrate its 50th Anniversary on Jan. 30. The lodge began its social activities in 1861, and in Jan. 30, 1863, was granted a charter to operate as a fraternal insurance society, thus, becoming the cornerstone of the strongest Norwegian fraternal order in America. The second local was organized in Milwaukee, Wis.</p>
   <p>At the end of the Civil War, the silk flag made and presented by Norwegian women of Chicago to the famous Norwegian regiment, the 15th Wisconsin infantry commanded by Col. Hegg, was given to Nora for preservation. Many world famous characters have been guests of Nora since its organization, among <pb facs="5423969_3_1014.jpg" n="2"/>them the Norwegian violinist Ole Bull, and Jenny Lind. Many of the most prominent members of the Chicago Norwegian colony have been members of Nora, and hundreds of others have been at various times its honored guests.</p>
   <p>Today, due to the Norwegians being scattered all over the city, Nora has only 110 members; former members have been transferred to locals nearer their present homes. At present the Dovre local is the strongest one in membership, although Nora retains the distinction of being the parent lodge.</p>
   <p>A banquet will be held on Jan. 30 at Dania Hall, at which the president of the Grand Lodge Sons of Norway will be the main speaker. Dr. Anders Doe will also speak at this banquet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
