<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-07-09">July 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bjornson Memorial Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-07-09">July 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BJORNSON MEMORIAL FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.col.3,... The Bjornson Memorial Festival was somewhat of a disappointment in the matter of attendance. With the thermometer registering over 90 degrees in the shade for several days the public was not in the proper mood for a large indoor gathering so the hall was only about half filled. The program, however, was good, nearly all numbers striking a happy responsive chord.</p>
   <p>Among those taking part in the program were Mrs. B. Jebbe who recited Finn Rein Simonsena "Bjornson Epilog, Lime. Aslrud Trilish, Mrs. Borgny Hammer; Rolf Hammer. Consul F. Herman Godis lecture on Bjornson fell short of its intent, being more of a collection of quoations than the anticipated tribute to Norway's outstanding writer.</p>
   <p>A marked and pleasing contrast was the speech of Mr. Morton Payne, prominent translator of the works of bjornson and Ibsen, who had mastered Norwegian in order to fully absorb the beauty of these works in the original language. He spoke of the enjoyment experienced in reading the works in Norwegian and of <pb facs="5423969_3_0280.jpg" n="2"/>his pleasure in having been able, by his translations, to share this pleasure with his own countrymen.</p>
   <p>Mr. Payne's statements should awaken the best in our own young people, many of whom think it non-essential to know the mother tongue and there are many whose false pride make them ashamed and too cowardly to admit the flow of good old Vikingblood in their veins. "Kongekvadet" and "Norounakvadit" by the combined orchestra and chorus were exceptionally well rendered and were awarded a storm of applause.</p>
   <p>We sincerely hope that the weather will be more auspicious on future occasions, such as this, as it is seldom we can hear programs that are both entertaining and educational to the extent that this Bjornson program was.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
