<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-09-18">Sept. 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Garden Social</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-09-18">Sept. 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE GARDEN SOCIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mere Earth-people visit the Fairies at Dickinson Park.</p>
   <p>And of course, the garden social given by the Norwegian Women's Federation last Friday evening proved a success. It is to be suspected the Mrs. Sundy-Hansen, from whom came the initiative for the social, must be in alliance with all the good powers; and the Red Cross work of the Norwegian Women's Federation must be highly pleasing to these powers for they lent great help.</p>
   <p>All of September, this year, has been cold and stormy, and scoffers started giving advice that the Fairies would need to appear in fur coats and high boots - and then, on the evening of the social, the mildest and most beautiful weather prevailed, and the Fairies danced in their filmy garments, <pb facs="5423969_3_0225.jpg" n="2"/>everything being as if ordered. Those who were present at the social will not forget Dickinson Park very soon. People coming to the social by auto or by street-car did not need to ask their way to the fete. Even from a far the multi-colored lanterns in the garden sent their gay invitation to the enchanted garden into the midst of the gloom of the night.</p>
   <p>The people came - by the hundreds and thousands - expecting much and finding more. A little while for orientation, and they would find acquaintances and friends among the multitude. Many went about carrying lanterns - it seemed as if the garden were peopled with lights dancing about. Then came the music and the dances of the Fairies, dances transplanted from the woods of Norway to the parks of America. There were various Norwegian national dances too, all to the great delight of the guests. Later there were speeches about the Red Cross work of the Norwegian Women's Federation. Finally the garden social was over, an event not soon to be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
