<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-04-24">Apr. 24, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Novel Reading</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-04-24">Apr. 24, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">NOVEL READING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is hard to believe that novels afford much practical aid to men and women in the various trials and tribulations of this mortal life. The modern story hinges almost entirely upon love, and interesting as this topic is, especially to women, there are many crises in real life into which it does not enter as an element. There can be no doubt that headstrong men have often been lead on to dishonesty and disgrace, and weak women to folly and ruin, by insane tales of heroes who ought to be wearing the striped garments of a state prison, and heroines who would be fit inmates of a lunatic asylum.</p>
   <p>Yet a story may be full of wildly sensational and highly improbable incidents without being wholly worthless. Many eminent men have found pleasure in the perusal of such stories. Their well-constructed plots and ingeniously concealed mysteries keep the reader's attention, and the rapid succession of startling events weans him from the contemplations of his own cares, sorrows, and perplexities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0384.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Honest attempts by writers of competent literary skill to give clear and truthful pictures of healthy, wholesome lives, of difficulties bravely met, of courage, virtue, and endurance, are not aiming at a fictitious glamour derived from depraved and fast life--tales such as these are to be emphatically condemned. But many widely read stories are by no means of this description.</p>
   <p>It is said that the tales printed in the common weekly papers have almost unvaried themes: a girl of humble birth but great beauty, loved by a man of rank and wealth whom, after extraordinary difficulties and all sorts of opposition from misguided parents or guardians, she eventually marries. Into the future history of the ill-mated couple the writers wisely do not inquire and the readers are equally incurious.</p>
   <p>The attractiveness of these stories which are, we believe, largely read by nursemaids, milliners' apprentices and other girls in the humbler walks of life, consists in holding out hopes, foredoomed to defeat, of a great <pb facs="5423969_3_0385.jpg" n="3"/>rise in the social scale. The reader is thus made discontented with the daily round of humdrum duties and unexciting work that falls to the lot of the vast majority of us all.</p>
   <p>The novel of passion, however artistic may be its workmanship, is little to be commended for its spiritual results. Whether merely sensuous, like The Quick and the Dead, or full, like the average French novel, of illicit love and marital infidelity, it is likely to excite prurient desires and to fill the reader's mind with unholy images; to teach men and women to have low ideas of each other; to foster the belief that any man may be ensnared by an unscrupulous coquette, and that every woman has her price.</p>
   <p>Novels are works of the imagination, and it ill becomes those whom nature has showered with a brilliant fancy to employ it in sapping the principles, uprooting beliefs, and imperiling the moral sanity of their less gifted fellow mortals. "We are as liable to be corrupted by books as by companions."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
