<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-09">Dec. 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Deaconess Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-09">Dec. 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN DEACONESS HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plans for the new Deaconess Home and Hospital to be built in the near future at the corner of Leavitt Street and Haddon Avenue have been prepared by Architect Charles Thieslew.</p>
   <p>The building is to be of red brick with cut stone adornments; its facades on Leavitt Street and on Haddon Avenue will each be one hundred and twenty feet long and forty feet in depth. The structure will consist of three stories in addition to a basement and an attic. The rooms in the basement will be utilized for classrooms, clinic, reception rooms for the doctors, drugstore, laboratory, dining rooms, etc. The first, second, and third stories are divided into wards and individual rooms for patients, and there will be room for one hundred and thirty beds. On the second floor is a chapel seating fifty people. The rooms for the deaconesses are on the the third floor.... In the attic, which is of full height on the side toward the yard, are the kitchen, bedrooms, and dining room for the kitchen help. The purpose of this arrangement is to prevent kitchen <pb facs="5423969_3_1350.jpg" n="2"/>odors from entering the halls and sick rooms of the building.</p>
   <p>Space is provided for two elevators, but only one will be put into use at the start. The elevators run from the basement to the top of the building. A dumb waiter will also be installed to run from the kitchen to the serving rooms on each floor.</p>
   <p>Toward the yard, independent of the main building yet connected with it, are two operating rooms....with their adjoining rooms for instruments, etc.....</p>
   <p>A separate building will be erected to contain the engine room, storage rooms, etc., to avoid vibrations and other inconveniences incident to machinery. In the rear part of the yard is to be erected a two-story and basement building of brick for consumptives and other incurables.</p>
   <p>The architecture of the main building is of colonial style and very impressive, yet little money is being spent for decorative effect on the outside. No <pb facs="5423969_3_1351.jpg" n="3"/>expense is being spared, however, for equipment to make the institution a first-class hospital according to the latest and most approved principles.</p>
   <p>As the public knows, the objective of the Deaconess Society is not only to conduct a hospital but also a deaconess home, that is, a training school for deaconesses.....Of course this phase of the work has been fully considered in planning the buildings.</p>
   <p>The Deaconess Society has paid for the ground of the new hospital; in addition, the Society has $2,000 in cash and $3,000 in subscriptions. This, however, will merely cover a fraction of the cost of the buildings.....It is expected that the public will support the undertaking. When finished, these buildings will form a handsome addition to the list of charitable institutions which the Norwegians have established in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
