<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-12-31">Dec. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Danish)</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-12-31">Dec. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian press has not been so actively engaged in propagandizing for Norwegian culture this last year or two as it was in previous years. It seems that the editors think that it is enough to mention that so-and-so will speak at such-and-such a hall, and that such-and-such a society will give a concert at such-and-such a time. But that is not enough.</p>
   <p>The public wants to know about such-and-such a singer, and what this singer gave to the people in song or in music. The readers want to know what is happening at the Old People's Home, at any one of our hospitals, at our clubs, our societies, and our churches. A newspaper must be a "herald" of culture, knowledge, and news. A newspaper must not be an "organ" of the few but an organ of the masses. The editor must know what to give to the people and how; if he does not do this, he loses readers, and soon his paper can sing its swan song.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian people are definite in their wants. They are, for the most part, <pb facs="5423969_3_0453.jpg" n="2"/>intellectuals. It should not be a hard task to write for intellectuals; so why is it that the contributors to our press are careless in this matter?</p>
   <p>And illustrations! There is only one foreign-language newspaper, at this time, here in Chicago that uses lots of pictures, and that is the Danish paper, Dansk Tidende (Danish Times). The editor, Kristian Baun, is a journalist in every sense of the word. Maybe we Norwegians could learn something here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
