<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-05-01">May 1, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian-American Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-05-01">May 1, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN-AMERICAN PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scandia is an excellent example of how a Norwegian-American newspaper can understand its purpose. Scandia is just what a newspaper should be. We can blame the Norwegian people for the fact that Scandia has not been able to reach the masses and bring its liberal and opportune message to those who need it most. We have not at any time given Scandia the support it deserves.</p>
   <p>Skandinaven is an excellent example of what a Norwegian-American newspaper must not be. Skandinaven is always speculative; it is never set as to policy or program. We often see editorials of the widest possible variety. One day it may be an editorial about Mussolini, the next day an editorial explaining why people should sleep with the windows open, or a three-column article about the output and raising of potatoes in Ireland.</p>
   <p>Skandinaven loves to give the impression that it is the only Norwegian newspaper in America that has any cultural background, and that it is the spokes-man <pb facs="5423969_3_0448.jpg" n="2"/>of all the Norwegian people in America. Skandinaven's policy is to "yes" wherever possible, and to play to its readers in order to satisfy them. Well, that is probably a good "policy of economy".</p>
   <p>We wonder what would happen if the subscribers would write and ask the staff just what the policy and program of that publication might be. The unbelievable thing might happen--that Skandinaven would answer and we would find out that the paper has a program. But until this happens we must condemn Skandinaven for what it is: A paper that confuses the people politically, socially, and in every other way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
