<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-12-28">Dec. 28, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[Skandinaven Purlisher Honored]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-28">Dec. 28, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[SKANDINAVEN PURLISHER HONORED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. John Anderson, publisher of Skandinaven, was made a Knight of the Norwegian Order of St. Olaf the other day. The Norwegian-Swedish Consul, John Lindgren, who, for the occasion, represented Norwegian-Swedish Ambassador Grip in Washington, functioned, and the Cross of Knighthood was presented to Mr. Anderson at his home, since he has been indisposed for some time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lindgren said, among other things, that the Norwegian government representing the Norwegian people had witnessed with pleasure the warm interest displayed by Norwegians in America in affairs touching their former homeland. This they have manifested in many ways, especially in their readiness to aid where suffering has come to the people in Norway, as after the great catastrophes at Titran and Rovar. On these occasions money was contributed from all countries, but most of all from the Norwegians in America. This was in a great measure due to the work of Skandinaven which placed all its influence at the service of the cause and thus accomplished a great task for the benefit of Norway.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For ages it has been the custom among rulers of nations to honor people who have given great service, by bestowing upon them medals, etc. Such presentations of signs of honor were in former days chiefly given to warriors and conquerors; nowadays they are presented to men of peace. In recognition of the valuable work in peace accomplished by Mr. John Anderson through his paper, Skandinaven, the Cross of Knighthood, First Class, of the Order of St. Olaf was now being presented the publisher. Mr. Anderson and the other donors to those suffering the effects of the catastrophe previously referred to, Mr. Lindgren said, had already received reward in the gratitude expressed when the gifts were received in Norway. The Cross of Knighthood was the recognition by the country as a whole.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lindgren concluded by referring to the statement of the Norwegian-Swedish King that he was convinced Mr. Anderson would prove worthy of the high honor bestowed upon him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Anderson accepted the distinction with thanks to Norway and its King for the high honor. In regard to the means sent to Norway to alleviate need he had merely considered himself an agent for the Norwegian people, he said. During his years as publisher he had had numerous proofs of the heartfelt response from the Norwegian people in America to requests for aid from Norway....He had seen both rich and poor respond, and he found it natural that the Norwegian government would appreciate this.</p>
   <p>....He asked Consul Lindgren to transmit his thanks to Norway and to King Oscar, together with his best wishes for the welfare and happiness of Norway and its King.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
