<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-01-21">Jan. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Dr. Quales Banqueted]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-01-21">Jan. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[DR. QUALES BANQUETED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.....Wicker Park Hall was center of Norwegian activities on Tuesday evening, The occasion being a banquet honoring the prominent physician and grand old gentleman Dr. N. T. Quales on his eightieth birthday. The hall was beautifully decorated and a profusion of flowers gave an almost audible testimony of love and esteem for this venerable, lovable Viking. Among the many speakers who lauded the work and personality of Dr. Quales were N. A. Grevstad, editor of Skandinaven, Carl Gulbrandsen, president of the Norwegian National League, Oscar H. Haugan, Norwegian Consul, and H. G. Haugan.</p>
   <p>Emil Bjorn and Dr. A. Doe contributed much to the pleasures of the evening with their appropriate solos. A large silver loving cup was presented Dr. Quales who responded very feelingly for the honors shown him. Churches, hospitals, orphanages and old peoples homes were represented, all expressing their appreciation for the friendly assistance constantly and unstintingly given them by Dr. Quales for so many years. An avalanche of telegrams from prominent men both in and outside Chicago were received <pb facs="5423969_3_0278.jpg" n="2"/>during the evening. By no means the least pleasing part of the program was the music by Haugan's Orchestra. Music artistically played by real musicians, it was a pleasent contrast to the usual rendition of crash and blare usually offered on occasions such as this.</p>
   <p>The evening was by far the most pleasant gathering we of Chicago's colony has ever had and it will undoubtedly be some time ere a real duplication will take place. In brief it was a real tribute to a real doctor, a real friend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
