<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-10-28">Oct. 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegians' Singing Society: Thirtieth Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">by E. S. Lindtner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-28">Oct. 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIANS' SINGING SOCIETY: THIRTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by E. S. Lindtner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The s Singing Society is celebrating its thirtieth anniversary today. There are probably not many societies which manage to live as long and at the same time maintain such vitality as this Society. The fact that the Society has retained such vitality after so many years is a testimonial to the power of united effort for a noble purpose. A generation ago the Norwegians' Singing Society first stood forth in the light of day; it has had a generation-long struggle against adverse conditions, yet, today, as thirty years ago, the Society is working with the same youthful enthusiasm, with the same youthful hope. This fact is rich in promise for the future. It is to be hoped that the work of the founders for the development of the Society will be rewarded and their dearest wishes fulfilled.</p>
   <p>When on some future day the history of the Norwegian-American culture is written, it will be necessary, as far as the cities are concerned, to turn <pb facs="5423969_3_0081.jpg" n="2"/>to the history of the various societies for material. For just as churches and priests are the ties which hold the people in the rural districts together, so the societies are the uniting link among us in the cities. When such a history is written, it is probable that the place accorded the Norwegians' Singing Society in the development, will be more important than is believed today.</p>
   <p>Turning our gaze backward over these thirty years, we find a fine example of the cultural history of the Norwegian immigrants. The immigrants, arriving in America, were poor and lonely. In their need they joined hands, and what was more natural than for them to form a singing society. The organization of a singing society was, so to speak, a national undertaking, springing from the love of the people for the music of their old homeland and for the great composers there. Singing, they forgot their troubles and that that they were alone in a strange land; they dreamt they were once more back among the mountain regions of Norway.</p>
   <p>These pioneers in the field of singing had no thought of doing anything great-- <pb facs="5423969_3_0082.jpg" n="3"/>probably most of them were thinking of themselves, hardly dreaming that this idea of theirs, born of need, nurtured under struggles, was to strike roots and spread all over the country, and remain virile for decades. But that was what happened. The Norwegians' Singing Society holds the honor of having maintained itself throughout all these years; in addition the Society has children and children's children in cities and countrysides, singing societies organized by men who previously were members of the Norwegians' Singing Society. It has even been claimed, and probably with good reason, that the Society is the parent of all the present singing societies among the Norwegians in America.</p>
   <p>The books of the Society show that the membership has totaled approximately one thousand people during the years of its existence.</p>
   <p>The Society has held about twenty bazaars and forty independent concerts; in addition it has assisted at about ten times as many affairs.</p>
   <p>It would seem, therefore, quite proper to present a brief summary of the history <pb facs="5423969_3_0083.jpg" n="4"/>of the Society. A historic sketch, as mentioned above, will also show the readers of the paper that the work upon which the Society can look back has not always been "just fun", for on many occasions the Society assumed heavy obligations for the purpose of alleviating need, both private and public, and also did their share when the question arose of carrying to victory some national cause which might otherwise have been lost.</p>
   <p>The original seed of the large Society of today was planted in the old Scandinavian Turner Society. According to tradition, however, the turners demanded too much from the singers. The latter were expected not only to pay their own instructor, but also to pay part of the salary of the turner instructor. At the same time they were expected to be ready to give their singing services to the turners whenever they were required. At last the demands became too irksome for the singers, and under the name of Chicago Scandinavian Singing Society, eight or ten Norwegian youths started their fight for existence as a singing club. Their instructor was Mr. C. Anderson and the president of their society was Bernt Olson. The first regular business <pb facs="5423969_3_0084.jpg" n="5"/>meeting was held on August 30, 1870.</p>
   <p>In the same year, Mr. E. S. Lindtner came to Chicago, a lively and gay young man, a "Norwegian Norseman from Norway" as he put it, filled with enthusiasm for everything Norwegian, and eager to prove himself a worthy Norwegian.</p>
   <p>On October 30, the Scandinavian Labor Union invited the singers to join the Union. The invitation was declined, however, and the motion of Mr. Lindtner to steer the course of the singers under the name "The Norwegians" Singing Society", was accepted. This did not mean, however, that only Norwegians could be accepted as members of the Society. Any Scandinavian of good repute was equally welcome.</p>
   <p>The first hall of the Society was at 204 Desplaines Street; later Aurora Turner Hall was rented by the singers.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavian Labor Union again tried to induce the young Singing Society <pb facs="5423969_3_0085.jpg" n="6"/>to join, but without success. The desire for independence was too strong, although it was often sorely tried during those first years. This desire for independence did not prevent the Norwegians' Singing Society from combining with the Swedish singing society "Freya", and a common board of directors was elected for the two societies, and regular rehearsals were held. Within this co-operative setting, each society preserved its own independence, however; the union was only to attain greater results and at the same time ward off, during the period of youth, such diseases as frequently attack societies during their early years. The co-operative undertaking did not last, however; after a couple of co-operative concerts, the relationship became less cordial. In the meanwhile the Norwegians' Singing Society had given its first assistance in connection with a church concert for the benefit of the church of Reverend Kroghnass, and had held its first picnic at Lyons' Grove.</p>
   <p>At this time, Christina Nelson came to Chicago on her first visit and gave her concerts here on June 14 and 16. The Swedes tried to arrange a reception in honor of the prima donna, but "Freya" was too weak to accomplish anything <pb facs="5423969_3_0086.jpg" n="7"/>by itself and it felt compelled to appeal to the Norwegians' Singing Society for assistance. For a while it appeared that cooperation would be impossible; each society wanted its own instructor to direct the program. At a joint meeting of the two societies, fist fighting among some of the members was prevented with difficulty. The call for a vote saved the situation, however. Several of the Swedes voted for Mr. Lindtner, and he was elected. "Freya's" instructor at the time was Professor Svendson. The concert was given at Germania Hall only a few months before the fire.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Dramatic Society had, in the meantime, celebrated the Seventeenth of May with a festival and play, and the Norwegians' Singing Society had assisted and won great applause. Encouraged by this, the Society decided to give a program in October. This concert was never given, however; the Chicago fire made everything topsy-turvy, and nearly killed the young Singing Society. Many of the members left Chicago, and those who remained did not have courage enough to continue rehearsals with the depleted membership. A special meeting was held at the home of the instructor, and at this meeting <pb facs="5423969_3_0087.jpg" n="8"/>it was decided to maintain the Society in name only, for a while, with no rehearsals and no membership fees. After one month, the Society started its activities once more, however, and since its rooms in Aurora Turner Hall had been rented, a rehearsal hall was found at the school on May Street.</p>
   <p>The Society took courage as the rehearsals went on; a program and a concert were decided on, and assistance was given on Christmas day at a children's festival at the Church of Our Savior [Norwegian]. The rehearsals were now held at a hall on the corner of Union Avenue and Indiana Street, and the singers met for practice regularly, twice a week.</p>
   <p>A concert had been decided upon in honor of Ole Bull, who was in the city, to be held on March 7, but a blizzard kept most of the singers at home, and instead of a concert, Ole Bull received an apology presented by three of the singers.</p>
   <p>The concert was given on March 9, and it may be of interest to know the type <pb facs="5423969_3_0088.jpg" n="9"/>of songs presented; they were as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Vandringslysten (The Desire to Travel)</p>
   <p>2. Klara Stjerna (O, Bright Star)</p>
   <p>3. Sagta, Hun Slumrar Redan (Quiet, She is Already Sleeping)</p>
   <p>4. Hvi Skal Du Fjerran Vara (Why Stay Away)</p>
   <p>5. Bravo, Sode Jensen (Splendid, Sweet Jensen)</p>
   <p>6. Fremad med Lystig Sang (Forward with Lively Songs)</p>
   <p>7. Brodra Horen Ni Signalen (Brethren, do You Hear the Signal)</p>
   <p>8. Hosten er Kommen (The Fall is Here)</p>
   <p>9. Alpesangen (The Song of the Alps)</p>
   <p>The net income from this concert was $100.09.</p>
   <p>For a few weeks the Society moved from hall to hall like a group of nomads. Of course, there was not as much baggage to move in those days as in later years. Finally, a more permanent resting place was found in the familiar Aurora Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0089.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>In April, 1872 a sick benefit society was organized for the members of the Singing Society. This benefit society is still active and is probably the strongest of its kind among the Scandinavian societies. Singers are rarely ill. At the same time a library was started, which now comprises many hundreds of volumes.</p>
   <p>On Thursday, April 18, 1872, the concert for Ole Bull, which once before had been attempted, was given. This was an event which the older singers still remember with pride. The Scandinavian Music Society joined in this greeting to the great violinist. Headed by Norwegian and American flags, the singers marched to Grand Central Hotel, where Ole Bull was staying, while the lights from the candles threw a fantastic gleam over the mass of curious people who were covered by almost a Norwegian snowfall which laid its white crystals over the singers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bull had just returned from a concert on the South Side, and as the band played "Sonner af Norge" (Sons of Norway) and the Singing Society sang "Ja, ri elsker" (Yes, We Love), one felt as if Norway itself had come to <pb facs="5423969_3_0090.jpg" n="11"/>salute this famous Norwegian. The latter was deeply moved and declared that it was the loveliest greeting he could possibly have had. Everybody was invited into the hotel, and....unforgettable hours were passed with the famous violinist. Mr. Lindtner was invited to return the following day, and Mr. Bull then showed his appreciation of the concert by presenting each of the participating societies with fifty dollars. The Norwegians' Singing Society used the money to add to its book collection.</p>
   <p>In April of the same year the Society began preparations for the celebration of the one-thousandth anniversary of Norway as a nation. This was an undertaking which will not be forgotten among the Norwegians in America, and to the Norwegians' Singing Society is due the full credit and honor for this celebration, not only because the idea originated with the Society, but also because, in spite of opposition from every side, the Society went ahead and made the celebration a success. Even if this were its only accomplishment, the Singing Society would have created for itself a lasting monument through its leadership in connection with this celebration. With a willingness worthy of the cause, the $125 which the Society had in its <pb facs="5423969_3_0091.jpg" n="12"/>treasury was turned over to the committee on arrangements, and in addition, $100 was borrowed to buy some new Norwegian and American flags. Aid was sought from other Norwegian societies, but all of them declined; even "Nora", the oldest Norwegian lodge refused to help. In spite of this, the Singing Society went on with its preparations. The singers even drew on their private savings, lending the money to the Society. It was a national undertaking and it was felt that success must be achieved regardless of the cost. The undertaking did succeed as probably no other undertaking among Norwegians in America, has.</p>
   <p>Those who did not dare to take the risk involved in the preparations, were now eager to join in the festivities. With banners and flags, all the other societies assembled outside the Norwegian Hall on North Peoria Street, on the morning of July 18. The singers had already arrived, and when the chairman of the committee on arrangements, Reverend Pettersen, invited them to enter, they marched into the Hall where a group of ladies dressed in white received them and presented the Singing Society with a beautiful silk banner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0092.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Ten societies participated in the parade, followed by twenty carriages, in each of which sat four ladies in white. Three special trains were required to bring the crowd to Haas Park where a gun salute announced their arrival and the Norwegian one-thousandth anniversary celebration had opened in Chicago. The celebration was most successful, and all the Norwegians were justly proud of it.</p>
   <p>As one may imagine, this undertaking brought the Singing Society many advantages. Its name became known beyond the Scandinavian groups, and now there was a steady influx of new members. The financial condition was much improved despite the heavy expenses. In the beginning of 1874, Mr. Lindtner went to California and the Society thus lost their able instructor and eager and energetic friend. It was largely due to him that the Society weathered the storms of its first three years so well.</p>
   <p>Following Mr. Lindtner's departure, the Singing Society had for its instructor, first Mr. Larsen and then Mr. Uhe. These two men remained only a few months, and then Professor J. W. Colberg came to fill the position which he has ably held for twenty-five years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
