<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-10-18">Oct. 18, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ellen Halvorsen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-18">Oct. 18, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ellen Halvorsen</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I am one of the women who started the work for the Norwegian Tabitha Hospital....We were but a few when we started out, and we were not rich; yet we laid the foundation with our nickels and dimes....Later the rich people took a hand in the task, and with them came the ministers of the Lutheran Synod. Since then it has been quite impossible to take part in the work for we all know that the ministers are quite impossible in many ways, and it is quite evident that their intention is to take the Hospital away from the Norwegian people and turn it into a church institution.</p>
   <p>I do not wish this to be interpreted to mean that I have anything against the ministers personally; I do object, however, to their using their churches as tools for the attaining of other goals....A few years ago some of the Hospital members came to realize the attitude of the ministers, and when the time came <pb facs="5423969_3_1333.jpg" n="2"/>for the annual meeting with election of a new board of directors, word was passed on to those entitled to vote that the ministers must be kept off the board. At the time a certain minister had been nominated for the board; he was a friend of mine and a man of honor in every respect--not one of the Synod ministers--and I felt badly about taking steps to keep him off the board; but at the same time I realized that if the Hospital were to remain an institution of the Norwegian people, as had been the intention from the first, then the ministers had to be kept out, no matter to what denomination they might belong. Consequently I went to the minister in question, explained to him the principle which was guiding my actions in the matter; I explained that there was nothing against him personally, but that he would be opposed by me and by those I could influence, solely because of his being a minister representing a religious denomination; it was all-important that the Hospital belong to the Norwegian people and not to a church group. In my honest simplicity I actually believed that we would be through with the ministers, as long as my minister friend was not elected. But....my chagrin and my alarm over the future of the Hospital may well be imagined when, at the election, one Synod <pb facs="5423969_3_1334.jpg" n="3"/>minister after the other was voted on the board; I had used my influence to keep out one minister, an honest straightforward man in every respect, who, in my opinion, had no selfish aim in his work....I had, as it were, helped kick him out through the front door, and then had to see all the doors and windows opened to let in those others who are now working to get the Hospital transferred from the Norwegian people to the Norwegian Lutheran Synod. And thus, while I hate hypocrisy and backhandedness, my efforts had been used as a means to promote the hypocritical scheme which I consider a misfortune to the Norwegian people.</p>
   <p>Yet, the good cause is not lost even now. We may yet realize our hope for a Norwegian national hospital. All those old members who, perhaps, have been at the point of losing courage need to take up the work once more with all their energy. It is important to take hold immediately, for now the attempt is being made to kill forever the idea of a Norwegian national hospital. I appeal not only to the old members, but to all Norwegians in Chicago; join the Hospital Society and work for the one Norwegian Hospital, as was the plan at the beginning. But in order to be qualified to vote at the election of the board of directors it is necessary to join on or before Monday, October 21.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
