<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-16">June 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">C. Athletic or Sports Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-16">June 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">C. ATHLETIC OR SPORTS SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. Det Norske Skytterlag (Norwegian Rifle Club). Meetings for practice every Wednesday and Saturday evening, and Sunday afternoon and evening. Meeting place, 833 West Division St. President, O. Jacobsen, 946 W. 42nd. Avenue; Vice-President, M. Johnson, 1234 N. 41st Court; Secretary, Theo. Eriksen, 1443 Ballou Court.</p>
   <p>2. Den Danske Skyde Forening (Danish Rifle Club). Meetings at Lagouts Hall, 690 W. North Avenue, on the 1st and 3rd Tuesday every month. President, Jacob Nielsen; Vice-President James Lundsberg; Secretary, Niels Anderson, 813 N. Mozart St.</p>
   <p>3. The Athletic Society Viking meets in Rockwell Hall, 985 Rockwell St. President Aug. Nelson; Vice-President, Andrew Skanke; Secretary, M. Petersen; Instructor, August Nelson.</p>
   <p>4. Ski Klubben Norge (Ski Club Norge) holds its meetings at Wabansia Hall, corner California and Wabansia Avenues, on the first and third Wednesday of every month. President, Adolph Swenson, 519 N. Avers Avenue; Vice-President, T. Jensen, 233 W.Huron Street; Secretary J. P. Engedahl, 12 Edgewood Ave.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0796.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. The Norwegian Sports Club Sleipner, meets every first and third Wednesday of the month at Sleipner Hall, 859 N. Fairfield Ave. Gymnastics and athletic exercises every Tuesday and Friday evening from 8:00 to 10:00 P.M. Boys' class from 7:00 to 8:00 P.M. Rifle practice every Sunday forenoon from 9:00 to 12:00 A.M. President P. Baker; Vice-President P. H. Pettersen; Secretary, O.C. Hagen, 902 Armitage Ave.</p>
   <p>6. The Norwegian Turn Forening (Athletic Club) meets in the Norwegian Turner Hall, 580 to 586 N. California Ave. Directors' meeting first Thursday of the month. The men's class, Tuesday and Friday evening at 8:00 o'clock. The ladies' class Monday and Friday, 6:00 to 8:00 P.M. President Martin Arnesen, 922 N. Campbell Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
