<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1908-01-03">Jan. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Turners' Annual Festival</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1908-01-03">Jan. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE TURNERS' ANNUAL FESTIVAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 7. The Norwegian Turn Society has achieved such remarkable success in the fields of gymnastics and athletics during the last year, that Norwegian sportsmen have won the respect and admiration of all sport interested Americans to a higher degree than ever before.</p>
   <p>Just as the French, English and other nationalities feared the Vikings in the olden days, so Chicago's various sport clubs are now afraid of the Norwegian Turners in competition. At the Turner meet last March in Bartlet's Gymnasium, where some 300 of America's ablest Turners participated, Sigurd Dietrich took second prize. Einar Bergendahl, who had hurt his foot, was unable to take part in the gymnastic competition, but, urged by his friends, he did perform in the acrobatic exercises and, in spite of his handicap, took third prize.</p>
   <p>On May 17th, in Brand's Park, the club took eight of the twelve prizes, and in addition its six-man team brought home first prize in the relay race (a silver cup, donated by the Norwegian National League). And that is not all. On June 16th, the boys fought for the Norwegian colors in Riverview Park, and established a record that has never been equaled by any sport society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0783.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the presence of 20,000 fans, mostly Americans and Germans, with a sprinkling of Norwegians, the Norwegian Turner Society took eight out of the eleven prizes, one of them a two-foot silver cup, for the all-around best club. During the season the Norwegian Turners also competed within the Chicago Turners' Baseball League, where they finished up as champions, winning 15 games and losing two.</p>
   <p>At the end of the year the society participated in the Y. M. C. A. wrestling matches, in which Conrad Christensen took second prize in the championship bouts. Tomorrow night, in Wicker Park Hall, these young Vikings, who have won so many honors for the name "Norwegian" will give a demonstration of how they do it, and every red-blooded Norwegian ought to be present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
