<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-13">Jan. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Ibsen Lecture</title><title level="a" type="sub">Arne Kildahl Lectures about the Great Master and His Many Works</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-13">Jan. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">IBSEN LECTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Arne Kildahl Lectures about the Great Master and His Many Works</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday evening in Wabansia Hall, Mr. Arne Kildahl, of Washington, D. C., lectured on Henrik Ibsen. The lecture was given under the auspices of the Norwegian Club. Mr. Kildahl began by bringing a greeting from the Norwegian Society in Washington. He mentioned the president of that Society, Mr. R. N. Sartz, well known in Chicago, and informed the audience that all the Norwegian members of Congress, including Senator Knute Nelson, were members of the Society.</p>
   <p>The speaker expressed regret that his lecture had been written in English. If he had had the time, he said, he would have rewritten it in Norwegian. This was impossible, however, and he appealed to the audience to be not too critical of his English pronunciation.</p>
   <p>It is evident that no thorough discussion of the great author's works could <pb facs="5423969_3_0717.jpg" n="2"/>be presented in a brief evening's lecture. The lecturer spoke of Ibsen's childhood and youth; he referred to the meager circumstances under which the playwright lived; he also mentioned the many other obstacles that Ibsen had to contend with, not the least of these being the fact that his works were misunderstood and misjudged.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kildahl continued with a brief discussion of Ibsen's most important works, classifying them in the usual way. He also told some interesting anecdotes about the taciturn dramatist, and two of these were such as had not been told before.</p>
   <p>The audience regretted that only little was told about the life of Henrik Ibsen in Norway after his return from his long self-imposed exile. The banquet given in his honor on his eightieth birthday was not mentioned. An account of this banquet would have been of special interest to the ladies who were present since all of Ibsen's lady-types were represented at the banquet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
