<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-07-30">July 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Turner Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0845</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0845.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-07-30">July 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE TURNER FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the Norwegian Turner Society in Minneapolis and the Norwegian Turner Society in Chicago met at Aurora Hall on Sunday morning. The members of the Norwegian Athletic Club Sleipner met at Scandia Hall, and headed by the Northern Light Band, marched to Aurora Hall to join the group waiting there. The joint procession then started through the main streets in the northwest part of the city, marching in the following order: The Minneapolis Turners at the head, dressed in blue trousers and white coats; the Sleipner boys, wearing white trousers and blue coats; finally the Norwegian Turner Society of Chicago, dressed like the Minneapolis boys. All the Turners wore white caps with red and blue borders and Turner insignia attached.</p>
   <p>The procession passed the Skandinaven plant on its way. At 11 A.M. the procession dissolved and the participants took the Elston Avenue streetcar to Elm Tree Grove.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0846.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In several of the streets passed by the procession, the business houses displayed the Norwegian and the American flags. Not only business people, but many private families as well honored the Turners in this manner. One of those who thus honored the Turners was Mr. Johnson, corner of Centre Avenue and Erie Street. He said to a reporter of the Skandinaven: "Old as I am, I am interested in the Turner movement, and especially do I honor the guests from Minneapolis."</p>
   <p>The Turners arrived at the Park at one o'clock, and during the afternoon a large number of Norwegians and Danes appeared. Some of the visiting Norwegians were Turner veterans, having been in this country for fifty years or more. There were also many of the younger generation, both men and women, and many had brought their children. A spirit of gaiety prevailed everywhere, and everybody showed eagerness in entertaining the guests from Minneapolis, who were easily recognized by the blue band with inscription which they wore on their breasts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0847.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was but scant time and opportunity for Turner exhibitions at the picnic since all the active Turners were otherwise occupied; yet there were some Chicago Turners performing various types of acrobatics. The Norwegian Turner Society of Chicago and the Sleipner [Athletic Club], also of Chicago, held a tug-of-war and the Turner Society won a ten-inch pull in the allowed time of five minutes.</p>
   <p>Only a few of the members of the Norwegian Singing Society had put in their appearance, and for this reason no songs were rendered. It is said that the committee on arrangements had forgotten officially to request the singers to appear on the program. The time at the Grove was passed in a jovial manner, and the number of visitors was very large.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0848.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In connection with the banquet, Saturday evening at Aurora Hall, a wrestling match was held between Mr. Ludwee of the Sleipner Club and Mr. Carl Lund of Minneapolis. Mr. Ludwee won. A wrestling match was also held between Messrs. Schonnesen and Wick of Minneapolis. Mr. Schonnesen was the winner. Finally there was a wrestling match between Messrs. Charles Stephanson of Sleipner and Sigurd Andersen of the Norwegian Turner Society, Chicago. In this match, Mr. Stephanson won.... On Saturday, The Norwegian-American Turners Association gave a prize exhibition at Douglas Park.</p>
   <p>The exhibition was watched with interest by a large number of men and women. The members of all the three societies constituting the Association performed excellently, so that the judges will find it a hard task to determine which society showed superiority in the exhibition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0849.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. F. Anderson is the leader of the Sleipner Athletic Club. For many years he was a Turner leader and afterwards teacher in the Norwegian Turner Society of Chicago. When last year Mr. Anderson became the leader of Sleipner, Mr. F. Rhein was chosen the leader of the Norwegian Turner Society of Chicago. Mr. Hagbart Hermansen was one of the organizers of the Norwegian Turner Society in Chicago, and he remained instructor of this society until a few years ago when he moved to Minneapolis and became active in the organization of the Norwegian Turner Society there. Ever since the latter Turner society was founded, Mr. Hermansen has been its leader. The three leader-instructors here mentioned had personal command of their troops during the exhibition here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On Saturday evening a banquet was held at Aurora Hall for the guests from Minneapolis....The hall was nicely decorated with Norwegian and American colors, and besides the one hundred active Turners, a similar number of nonactive <pb facs="5423969_3_0850.jpg" n="6"/>members were present. The Northern Light Music Band serenaded the Turners and afterward, during the evening, played intermittently. Mr. G.G. Martin, chairman of the committee on arrangements, welcomed the guests, especially those who, in the interest of athletics had made the long trip from Minneapolis. Later a number of speeches were made, refreshments were served, and a pleasant evening was enjoyed by all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
