<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-06-02">June 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Leif Ericson Monument</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Norwegian Protests against Suggested Plan by a Norwegian</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-06-02">June 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEIF ERICSON MONUMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Norwegian Protests Against Suggested Plan by A Norwegian</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a report from the last meeting of the Society for the Leif Ericson Monument, published in Skandinaven for May 30, it is stated: "A sketch for the monument, presented by Mr. Emil Bjorn, was adopted, and the board of directors was instructed to contract with the sculpture firm Black and Company for the making of a statue in the course of the summer."</p>
   <p>It is true, then, that the Society for the Leif Ericson Monument actually intends to erect a monument as indicated in Humboldt Park. It is no use to try to camouflage the matter by designating Black and Company as a sculpture firm. The firm is simply a company which executes whatever is <pb facs="5423969_3_0940.jpg" n="2"/>ordered, in iron or in bronze, in accordance with drawings submitted. Statues of this type may be quite agreeable to look at--as ornaments in private gardens, at water outlets, etc.--but there is hardly anybody who would call these productions works of art. When, on the other hand, the question is concerning a statue to be erected in one of the parks of the city, and especially where it is a question of a man, the looks of whom nobody knows, then we must demand, first of all, that the statue be a work of art.</p>
   <p>Black and Company possess many statues already finished. Why not buy one of these, then paint in large letters easy to read: "This is supposed to be Leif Ericson." If this were done the fee to Mr. Emil Bjorn would be saved, too. Nobody could claim that the figure thus placed in the park would not be a true likeness of Leif Ericson.</p>
   <p>The Society for the Leif Ericson Monument has taken upon itself the responsibility <pb facs="5423969_3_0941.jpg" n="3"/>of acting for the Norwegians in Chicago. But in doing so, the Society is under obligation to carry out its undertaking in a manner worthy of the Norwegians.</p>
   <p>The Society must not attempt a short cut in order to get rid of the whole matter. Either the Society must get enough money to secure the erection of a monument which is a piece of art, or else wait until the necessary money can be raised in other ways.</p>
   <p>We, who are not members of the Society for the Leif Ericson Monument, are not satisfied to have the Society place in one of the City's parks a statue of the explorer that will be laughed at by people who understand art.</p>
   <p>The members of the Society for the Leif Ericson Monument are nice, decent people, but it is hardly a misstatement to say that they do not understand <pb facs="5423969_3_0942.jpg" n="4"/>art. The present writer begs to urge the Norwegian artists in Chicago to present their views on the matter.</p>
   <p>The sketch presented by Mr. Emil Bjorn is attractive and well executed, as is everything coming from his hand, but this fact does not alter the matter in question. Does Mr. Bjorn really believe that a statue constructed by the firm mentioned above to coincide with his sketch will be a work of art as the term is understood in our days? In other words, does Mr. Bjorn believe that the statue to be ordered will compare, from the point of view of art, with that of Linne erected by the Swedes, or that of H. C. Andersen erected by the Danish, etc.? What do Messrs. Asbjornson, Svendsen, and Hawlins think of the matter?</p>
   <p>And finally, does the Society for the Leif Ericson Monument know that there is in existence a committee, appointed by the Governor, the objective of which is to determine whether or not a statue is worthy of being placed in <pb facs="5423969_3_0943.jpg" n="5"/>the parks of the city, and has the Society made inquiry as to whether this committee will accept a statue which will bear the earmarks of the ready-made? Many Norwegians in Chicago would be interested in some information on these questions. If a monument is to be erected, it ought to be one of which the Norwegians may justly be proud.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
