<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Thirtieth Anniversary Souvenir Directory of the Norwegian Lutheran Bethesda Home Association</title>,
1907-<date when="1937">1937</date>, Chicago, p. 31.
<title level="a">[Report on Norwegian Lutheran Bethesda Home]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Thirtieth Anniversary Souvenir Directory of the Norwegian Lutheran Bethesda Home Association</title>,
1907-<date when="1937">1937</date>, Chicago, p. 31.
<title level="a">[REPORT ON NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN BETHESDA HOME]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Norwegian Lutheran Bethesda Home Society: During 1986 nine old people ended their pilgrimage at Bethesda.</p>
   <p>Dr. Harlow Hanson continues his sacrificing service at our home. Whenever he is called night or day he cheerfully responds. We are greatly indebted to him for his valuable services. We are also grateful to the Lutheran Deaconess Hospital where we my send our sick people whenever it is seen fit to do so. During 1936 eleven old people were taken into our home. At the close of the year we had sixty-nine old people at the home. Pastor C. Michaelson, who is the shepherd of our home, donates much of his time to visit the sick and feeble, to give them comfort and spirited advice and help.</p>
   <p>The weekly visits by members of the Pastoral conference are greatly a preciated If they cannot always come on the scheduled time, they usually try to be <pb facs="5423969_3_1639.jpg" n="2"/>present with the Ladies Aid when they visit the Home. Thirty two Ladies aids, young peoples' societies, and singing societies have made their visits to the Bethesda Home during the last year. Lunches were served and donations given. Four dinners for the benefit of the Home were given by various societies. Two summer festivals were celebrated, one of them by the Norsk Ungdom Fellesforbunds Forening, in Chicago. A flag day and a one week bazaar helped to give substantial support to the Home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
