<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1915-07-18">July 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Lutheran Children's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-07-18">July 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN CHILDREN'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Childrens Home Society held its regular biannual meeting yesterday at St. Paul's Church. It was reported that the Home had cared for 89 children during the last six months. The general health had been good; no serious illness had been reported.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary reported the income from dues, donations, subsidiary groups, benefit programs, etc., to be $2,951.71. The treasurer reported receipts of $3,047.95,expenditures of $2,578.29, leaving a balance of $469.66; after deducting unpaid bills of $213.21, the net balance was $246.45.[Itemized lists of income and expense omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Report of Ladies' Board</p>
   <p>The Ladies' Board held three regular and two extra meetings during the <pb facs="5423969_3_1483.jpg" n="2"/>quarter from April to June.</p>
   <p>During this time all applications received were taken care of to the best of our ability. The three pound parties, held April 5, May 4, and June 7, by different societies, have been a great help to us, and we thank all who helped make it successful. The annual May festival was held on May 30 in St. Paul's English Lutheran Church.</p>
   <p>Eight children were confirmed on May 23 by Reverend Lars Harrisville. Through Mr. E. Wurst of the Board of Education, we have obtained a weaving loom, and we hope soon to obtain the services of a competent woman to teach the children to weave. We arranged for our annual picnic to be held on June 26 at the Home. We received liberal donations from all the societies working for the Home. We are indeed thankful to each and everyone for their help at the picnic and it was the best one we have ever had.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1484.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The children at the Home look well and happy. We have a new matron, Miss Amanda Larsen, who has been such a help to the Ladies' Board. She has made confirmation dresses for five girls and has performed numerous other tasks. We are grateful to God for all his mercies toward us, and we know He loves the little ones who are entrusted to us.</p>
   <p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
   <p>Mrs. <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/>Samuelson.</p>
   <p>Secretary of Ladies' Board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
