<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-16">July 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">First Scandinavian Women's Burial Soceity</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Women Have Done Fine Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-16">July 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST SCANDINAVIAN WOMEN'S BURIAL SOCEITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Women Have Done Fine Work</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At its last meeting, the First Scandinavian Women's Burial Society installed its new board of directors. The new board was not "new", however, for all of the incumbent officers were re-elected. Mrs. Marie Halvorsen, assisted by Mrs. Berg, officiated at the installation because the senior president of the Society, Mrs. Christine Christoffersen, was unable to attend. This was the first time during the thirty-one and a half years of the Society's existence that Mrs. Christoffersen had been absent from an installation ceremony of the Society.</p>
   <p>After the installation ceremony, musical entertainment was provided by the Helve sisters, who played violin and piano selections. Miss Madsen and Miss Bensen sang; there was also singing by twenty of the children from the Norwegian Orphanage. Ice Cream, coffee and sandwiches were sold, the proceeds going to the Norwegian Orphanage Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1058.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The attendance was excellent: the large Northwest Hall, 692-694 West North Avenue, was filled to capacity. During the meeting, the secretary,Mrs. Anna Bergesen, read an extensive report covering the activities of the Society.</p>
   <p>On January 1, the Society had 605 members; during the first half of the present year eighteen new members were admitted, so that the present membership numbers 623. Eight members died during the first half of the year. In cases of death the Society pays $200 to the surviving family, and, in addition, pays for flowers and meets the cost of carriages for the board of directors.</p>
   <p>During the first half of the year, $1,514.37 was received in membership fees. Income from other sources amounted to $154. The income for the period, plus a treasury balance of $780.24 makes a grand total of $2,448.61. Expenses during the half-year period were $1,940.62. The trustees were paid $150, so that $357.99 remains in the treasury.</p>
   <p>The financial status of the Society is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1059.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash in treasury</cell>
     <cell>$357.99</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash receivable</cell>
     <cell>203.79</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Loans to members</cell>
     <cell>435.63</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Stock in Mt. Olive Cemetery</cell>
     <cell>$500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mortgages</cell>
     <cell>1,600.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$3,097.41</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash in bank</cell>
     <cell>273.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Grand total</cell>
     <cell>$3,370.41</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The First Scandinavian Women's Burial Society was founded on February 12, 1879 by nine women, three of whom are still living. These three are Mrs. Christine Christoffersen and her two daughters, Misses Kittie and Arvine Christoffersen. Mrs. Christoffersen was repeatedly elected president of the Society for twenty-five years. She is now eighty-four years old; yet she has invariably been present at the meetings, burials, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1060.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>During the past thirty years there have been 227 deaths in the Society, and no less than $22,750 has been paid as burial aid. The Society has always endeavored to assist its members when they have needed help; it has also extended aid to the Norwegian Orphanage on various occasions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
