<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-13">Feb. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Scandinavian Medical Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-13">Feb. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCANDINAVIAN MEDICAL ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Scandinavian Medical Association was held at the "Tavern", Thursday, February 11. Dr. Egil Olsen functioned as president in the absence of Dr. Roberg.</p>
   <p>Dr. G. A. Torrison reported that he and Dr. Holmboe had presented Dr. N. T. Quales, honorary member of the Society, with the letters of congratulation from the Society in connection with Dr. Quales' seventy eighth birthday, and that Dr. Quales had requested them to convey his best thanks to the Society for the courtesy shown.</p>
   <p>The scientific program consisted of the following:</p>
   <p>First, Dr. Torrison gave a brief lecture on "Foreign Bodies in the Outer Ear Passage". Among the strange things he had found in the ear passage may be mentioned garlic, tobacco, cotton, watermelon seeds, and once he had even found a cricket <pb facs="5423969_3_0431.jpg" n="2"/>in the passage.</p>
   <p>Dr. Egil Olsen reported on a case of "gonorreic blood poisoning "where the disease had taken hold on the heart and partly destroyed the valves. Correct diagnosis had been arrived at through bacteria culture, and later confirmed through the obduction. Dr. Olsen also showed some peculiar temperature curves from a consumption patient.</p>
   <p>Finally, Dr. Ingeborg Rasmussen gave an interesting lecture on "Scurvy in Children". She demonstrated that this disease is caused solely by insufficient nourishment, and that it may readily be cured through proper diet. She illustrated her lecture with narratives of this somewhat rare disease from her own practice as a children's physician.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
