<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1924-02-16">Feb. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Scandinavian Women's Burial Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1924-02-16">Feb. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCANDINAVIAN WOMEN'S BURIAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 12, 1879, the Scandinavian Women's Burial Society was organized by eight women. The Society has steadily grown and is now one of Chicago's most important organizations. Mrs. Christine Christofersen was elected first president, and held that office for twenty-five years. In those days, the '70's and '80's, the women's societies were not recognized as they are today. It was considered a joke that women left their kitchens to become active in any type of work outside the home; "Woman's place was in the home". But this did not scare the eight women who formed the oldest women's society in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The moving factor in the enterprise was the fact that many people had come to America, the land of "golden opportunity," hoping to live in economic security without worry, but even though most of the newcomers tried and worked hard, many of them died poor, often not having enough money for funeral expenses. To have a respectable funeral is something our <pb facs="5423969_3_0956.jpg" n="2"/>Scandinavian people all look forward to. In Norway, Denmark and Sweden the workers were accustomed to having funeral benefit societies, so why not here in America? All the unions had such plans that on the death of a member the union paid a certain sum. This procedure was always welcome in the poorer families. The new Funeral Benefit Society had this in mind. The dues, to begin with, were two cents per week, eight cents per month, and ten cents for initiation. The assessment was two cents per month. This was not much, but as the members were young and healthy, it was expected to have quite a large fund before any money was paid out.</p>
   <p>The organization did not use the banks; the treasurer kept the money in her home in tin cans and boxes of all sorts. It is hardly believable that from such a small beginning the Society today has a large fund, and that they, in 1923, paid out benefits amounting to $4,000. On Jan. 1, 1924, the membership was 452. The Society has 80 bond and stock shares in the Mount Olive Cemetery plus a number of investment bonds in good Chicago real estate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As we mentioned before, the first president held office for twenty-five years. The second president, Mrs. Anna Berg, served for fourteen years; and the present president, Mrs. Marit Sene, has served six years. Three presidents in forty-five years is quite a record. Other functionaries have also served long and faithfully. Mrs. Marie Munsen held the office of treasurer for twenty years; Mrs. Hanna Wilson is the present treasurer.</p>
   <p>The Society has always contributed to every worth-while cause. The Society contributed to the Viking Ship, the Heeg Monument, the Old People's Home, and the Children's Home.</p>
   <p>The dues were raised on January 1, 1924, to twenty cents; assessments, twenty-five cents twice a year, plus twenty-five cents for each death. The initiation fee is now $1.50. The Society now pays a death benefit of $200 plus flowers and one automobile for the officers who usually act as pallbearers. This Society is considered one of the largest and strongest in Chicago today.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0958.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Society celebrated its forty-fifth anniversary last Sunday at the Norwegian Club. The hostess was Mrs. Nicoline Oyen. The affairs committee consisted of Mrs. Helga Nelson and Mrs. Sneve. The main speaker of the day was Dr. Anders Doe. The other speakers were Mrs. Sandberg and Attorney Erickson. The entertainers were Harry Hauge, Mrs. Corby, and Miss Helve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
