<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1935-05-09">May 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian-American Historical Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edward Anderson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III A </item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1935-05-09">May 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Edward Anderson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a recent issue of Scandia an article appeared about the Norwegian-American Historical Society. Apparently it was intended as an advertisement, with the object of seeking new members. This objective probably will not have the desired effect, inasmuch as the many reflections cast upon representative men and women will be ignored.</p>
   <p>It may be of interest to analyze some of the remarks contained in this article, and also remember that those men and women probably are more capable to pass their own judgment on the subject than the author. Just what do you mean when you refer to super-patriotic leaders? You cannot <pb facs="5423969_3_0396.jpg" n="2"/>be loyal to two countries--why this sarcasm? Norwegian-Americans, being citizens of this country, can only be loyal to this country; however no one doubts that they have the highest regard for the country where their parents came from, or probably were born themselves.</p>
   <p>You further state; "a discussion was held in Chicago to settle the question as to whether the Norwegian-Americans had a culture of their own, and that this discussion proved to you beyond doubt that, of the type of culture which means intellectual and artistic refinement, there is mighty little of it in our Norwegian-American society." Evidently you have an opinion of your own.</p>
   <p>Are you aware of the fact that the Norwegians here as well as abroad, are considered as one of the most interesting and singular groups of people, and that even in the remoter ages of her history she possesed a standard <pb facs="5423969_3_0397.jpg" n="3"/>of culture such as hardly any other Northern nation could equal--witness the old Norse laws and institutions, and her ancient literature (the Sagas). This opinion has been expressed by well known writers. In other words, your expressions are nothing more or less than a slam. You further state that, "outside of our colleges, there is only one organized effort among Norwegian-Americans whose standard measures are up to par or more, only one enterprise whose achievements are good for every bit of face value, and which we dare lay open to scrutiny without embarrassment." With due credit to the association you refer to, may I remind you that the great number of large Norwegian-American churches in this country are headed by men whose wonderful work you have no right to underestimate.</p>
   <p>Now, for the next point, quoting from your article, "Historiecaget has in its power to work up Norwegian national consciousness in the second generation, <pb facs="5423969_3_0398.jpg" n="4"/>and a feeling that would give added richness to American life and culture, were the immigrants better able to instill in their children the true evolution of homeland culture". Just let me say that this is America. This country does not have to seek added richness to life and culture from Norway, neither does Norway have to seek its culture from America.</p>
   <p>Are you aware of the fact that true Americans will resent your ideas of bringing Norwegian national consciousness into this country?</p>
   <p>Frankly, I do not like the many insinuations in your article; and the way your refer to the immigrants as a peculiar mixture, frequently of immigrant parents, and sneer of things Norwegian, and indulge in vainglorious bragging, is just as ignorant. Now, according to my opinion, any open-minded person's comment on "slams" of this type, in plain English would be rotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0399.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The immigrants from Norway have played a very significant part in the building of this country, and I believe it is well to give credit where credit is due. From the man who came here and built his home on the prairie to the man who reached the top as United States Senator, let us honor them without exception. It is easier to tear down than it is to build. I do not believe I am personal if I ask you: Are you in a position to tell anyone how to bring up his children? Conclusions are easily drawn, but it is always well to stop and think before you express opinions. The remarks you have heard here and there apparently are nothing more than ordinary gossip.</p>
   <p>I believe it would be interesting if you would further explain what you mean when you say: "In these annals, on the contrary they (American born generations) will find a wonderfully sober detached chronicle of our nation's life on these shores". The word "our," in this case, naturally refers to <pb facs="5423969_3_0400.jpg" n="6"/>American shores. This country has its own colorful history, of which we Americans are justly proud. Do you consider it proper to advocate the teachings of homeland culture in this, our United States?</p>
   <p>Of course, there are liners leaving this country every week!</p>
   <p>Your quotation from Are Frode, reads as follows: "We must write these things down so that later generations shall not believe that we came from slaves and lowly people," what does this have to do with the issue? We are living in the present and for the future. As far as our ancestors are concerned that is history.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, I want it understood that this article is not intended to cast any reflection on any organization or person, but may I suggest to you <pb facs="5423969_3_0401.jpg" n="7"/>that you read more and think less, before you write another article like the one in the previous issue of Scandia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
