<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1902-02-08">Feb. 8, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">The Tabitha Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1902-02-08">Feb. 8, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">THE TABITHA HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Tabitha Hospital Society called a meeting last Tuesday through its vice-president, Dr. Marie A. Olsen. Dr. Olsen called the meeting because of the resignation of the president. Only seven members attended. This not being a quorum, the meeting adjourned and another meeting was called for the following Friday.</p>
   <p>The Synod faction left the above-mentioned [Friday] meeting and called their own meeting at Our Savior's Church. When they arrived at the church to attend the meeting, a boy began to distribute leaflets. The leaflets read as follows:</p>
   <p>"Peace!!</p>
   <p>"Avoid Factional Strife and Legel Litigation!</p>
   <p>Work in Unity and Understanding.</p>
   <p>Vote for a Peace Committee."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The distribution of these handbills did not last very long. Some individual, "loyal to the Synod," confiscated the leaflets and threw them into the church furnace. The "loyal" few who attended, piously called the meeting to order and elected Dr.[J. M.] Meyer chairman and Dr. [M.] Unseth secretary. After a short time, about an hour, three hundred people had shown up, many loyal to the faction, others through curiosity. Of the Hospital staff we saw Doctors Oyen, Holmboe, Remmen, Berg, Rasmussen, Torrison, Unseth, Meyer, Hektoen, and Warloe.</p>
   <p>At the beginning the meeting all was peaceful, but it was not long before strife began in this "holy" faction. The reports of standing committees and officers were finally read. The secretary reported that this meeting had been advertised for three consecutive days in Skandinaven, the only paper friendly to the Synod group. Several reports were read by the executive committee and the "spiritual" committee.</p>
   <p>The meeting then proceeded to elections. After a stormy hour or two, the <pb facs="5423969_3_1251.jpg" n="3"/>following were elected as directors:</p>
   <p>Mrs. William Johnson, Mrs. Andrew Petersen, Henry A. Haugan, H. Stiboldt, and K. E. Edwards. Just before adjournment, it was reported that the opposing faction had put two guards at the Hospital, but no one could report whether these guards were sworn in as special police or as deputy sheriffs. The meeting was then peacefully (?) adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
