<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-21">Oct. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[How Much for Money?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_0528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-21">Oct. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[HOW MUCH FOR MONEY?]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"And now it has been revealed that the orthodox Skandinaven has been printing the anarchist paper Free Society, from the very day the well-known Isaak started the paper! Now we know that it is true, as has often been said, that all that the Skandinaven cares for is money.</p>
   <p>"No less than the murder of a president would suffice to make the Skandinaven cease printing the anarchist paper here mentioned; the money which the printing brought in was too good to miss.</p>
   <p>"(Signed) J. S. Holland,</p>
   <p>"St. Olaf Hospital,</p>
   <p>"Austin, Minnesota."</p>
   <p>The honored correspondent is somewhat misinformed as to the facts in the case <pb facs="5423969_3_0529.jpg" n="2"/>he refers to. It is not true that the Skandinaven all along has been printing the anarchist paper Free Society; Skandinaven never printed the paper in question.</p>
   <p>According to information gathered by SKandinaven, Isaak has published his paper, under various names, in New York, in California, and elsewhere. In February of this year he began its publication in Chicago under the name Free Society. He invited several printing concerns to make bids on the printing of the paper. The lowest bidder was D. W. Mathews and Company, a company which had rented space in the Skandinaven building. Of course, the firm was paid for its work; its printing plant was conducted on the same basis as all other printing plants; it tried to save some money through printing.</p>
   <p>Mathews and Company did not know that the paper was an anarchist paper. It is not the custom in this country for the printing plants to censor what is presented for printing; much of the printing is done without anyone except <pb facs="5423969_3_0530.jpg" n="3"/>the typesetter knowing the contents of the matter to be printed. As to the printing of newspapers, it is enough for the printers to know that the postal service is open to the paper, as was the case with Free Society. It seems safe to assume that whatever is admitted to the mails by the government must be safe to print. Mathews and Company has informed Skandinaven that the firm did not know of the contents of Free Society, but assumed it to be some sort of a socialist paper.</p>
   <p>Last summer Skandinaven took over the plant and business of Mathews and Company--for reasons that are of no concern to Mr. Holland. On such occasions it is customary to complete contracts entered into by the previous owners. It did not occur to the new owners to make any exception in regard to the newspaper in question; they knew even less about it than did the previous owners. Least of all did the new owners suspect the paper of being anarchistic; the Post Office Department was treating it exactly like other newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_0531.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Then occurred the murderous assault upon President McKinley, and Isaak was arrested. In connection with his arrest it was revealed that Free Society was an anarchist paper. Its printing in the building of Skandinaven was immediately stopped, and two or three weeks later the Chicago postmaster decided to stop, temporarily, its transmission through the mails.</p>
   <p>The above constitute the facts in the case.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
