<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-04-20">April 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Old People's Home Socieity Holds Monthly Meeting]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-04-20">April 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[OLD PEOPLE'S HOME SOCIEITY HOLDS MONTHLY MEETING]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Concordia branch of the Old People's Home Society held their monthly meeting at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Anton A. Melum of Oak Park.</p>
   <p>Mr. Melum, a director of the home, announced that the concert by Mme. Fremstad has been called off, due to a misunderstanding with her manager, and that the time was too short to arrange for a spring festival at this time. Director Crook spoke on the financial needs of the home, and suggested, in view of the fact that all present inmates of the home, and suggested, in view of the fact that all present inmates of the home are and those of the future will for some time be natives of Norway, that the Norwegian Parliament [might very well] award the year's Nobel Prize to the Old People's Home Society.</p>
   <p>Dues to the amount of $29.50 were collected, and the men present donated $9.00 for decorations at the Bazaar, which is to be held at Schoenfus's Hall, November 18 to 22, inclusive.</p>
   <p>After the business session the group partook of a tasty lunch, during and <pb facs="5423969_3_1741.jpg" n="2"/>after which they were entertained by Edward Bredshall, a very talented young pianist, whose playing was thoroughly enjoyed.</p>
   <p>This meeting was, in the matter of attendance, the best in many months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
