<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Tabitha Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quarterly Meeting - Reports</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-12">Apr. 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">TABITHA HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quarterly Meeting - Reports</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Tabitha Hospital Society held its quarterly meeting Tuesday evening at Wicker Park Hall. The president, Dr. Sandberg, presided at the meeting.</p>
   <p>The treasurer, Mr. H. A. Haugan, presented his report for the months of January, February, and March, showing the following financial situation:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Income for the three months</cell>
     <cell>$2,616.73</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>2,439.06</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in General Fund</cell>
     <cell>177.67</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in Subscription Fund</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The auditing committee reported that the accounts had been examined and found in order. The auditing committee consists of Messrs. C. B. Stange, W. Daniels, and C. Arnatt.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1375.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The secretary's report showed the current expenses for the quarter to have been $2,759.39. On January 1, 1900 the debt owing on the real estate of the Society amounted to $5,000. Debt on furnishings amounted to $1,510. Ninety-six patients have been under treatment during the quarter. Fortyseven of these have recovered completely; seven are improving; nine died; and thirty-two remain in the Hospital under treatment. Twelve patients have been given treatment free of charge, with a total of 253 days of treatment. There have been eighteen partly paying patients with a total of 563 days of treatment. Finally, there have been sixty-six paying patients with a total of 1402 days of treatment, making a grand total of 2,218 hospital treatment days.</p>
   <p>Of the patients eighty-seven were from Chicago; one from Illinois outside of Chicago; six from Wisconsin; one from New York; one from North Dakota. Considered from the point of view of nationality, there were twenty-four American patients; thirty-six Norwegians; fifteen Swedes; seven Danes; three Germans; three Englishmen: one Irish; one Finlander; <pb facs="5423969_3_1376.jpg" n="3"/>one Russian; one Frenchman; one Greek; one Dutchman.</p>
   <p>The course for training of nurses is at present attended by eleven students. In the department for the aged there are nine residents.</p>
   <p>During the quarter, the board of directors held four meetings. More hospital rooms are needed; the board of directors has rented temporary quarters in the neighborhood. The various reports were accepted by the meeting as rendered.</p>
   <p>On behalf of the staff of doctors at the Hospital, Dr. A. Holmboe reported that the Hospital still is over-crowded, and that steps must be taken at once to provide additional rooms for the patients. Many prospective patients have had to be refused admittance on account of lack of room.</p>
   <p>Either a new building must be erected or some suitable building must be rented; otherwise the Hospital will lose standing. Now the Hospital is <pb facs="5423969_3_1377.jpg" n="4"/>well known and highly considered also among the Americans.</p>
   <p>Dr. Holmboe's report started a debate about the question of a new building. Several of those present spoke in favor of starting an additional building at once; others, however, advocated a policy of waiting until the present debt is paid.</p>
   <p>Attorney Oscar M. Torrison proposed that the board of directors appoint a committee on building to study the question of a new building and present plans for the raising of money, etc. The report of the work of the committee is to be rendered to the board of directors. This motion was passed unanimously.</p>
   <p>The visiting committee reported that a bazaar for the benefit of the Hospital Society will be held at Wicker Park Hall during the last week of October.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
