<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-18">Feb. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Orphanage</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. J. Ellestad, President</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-18">Feb. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN ORPHANAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. J. Ellestad, President</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At its meeting last Monday evening the board of directors of the Norwegian Lutheran Orphanage Society found it necessary to receive five more children at our Orphanage. The Orphanage family is increasing; we simply could not refuse these children admission. The building will be crowded, but the matron promised to find space for them some way or other.</p>
   <p>We have about seventy children at the Orphanage now, and they must be cared for. Much food, clothing, fuel, and other necessities must be secured. Do not let us forget the children under our charge.</p>
   <p>Then there is the question of a new building. As soon as our building fund <pb facs="5423969_3_1569.jpg" n="2"/>reaches $3,000 we will be able to start building. Mr. Oscar Haugan,of the State Bank of Chicago, will be glad to accept donations to the fund whether such donations are large or small. Step in at the bank when you are in the vicinity. Mr. Haugan will be glad to meet you. I have noticed that many people are visiting that bank.</p>
   <p>You have probably considered donating to the Norwegian Orphanage for its new building. Perhaps you are waiting for someone to come to ask you for a donation. Do not wait any longer. There is no time for waiting. Go at once to Mr. Haugan and give him the amount you can spare. If you can afford it, give much; if your ability to give is limited, give what you can, but give, and give at once.</p>
   <p>How we would wish to be able to announce soon to the friends of this our home for children that we are ready to break the ground at Edison Park for the new Norwegian Orphanage in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
