<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-01-25">Jan. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Twenty-second Annual Meeting, January 18, 1918</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1691</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1691.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-01-25">Jan. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Twenty-second Annual Meeting, January 18, 1918</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Treasurer's Report</p>
   <p>Receipts</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand</cell>
     <cell>$ 840.43</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Bazaar</cell>
     <cell>2,832.57</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Building fund interest</cell>
     <cell>55.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donations</cell>
     <cell>1,539.85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Inventory reserve fund</cell>
     <cell>355.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Norway lecture</cell>
     <cell>16.38</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Picnic</cell>
     <cell>550.76</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Annual reports</cell>
     <cell>624.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Tag day</cell>
     <cell>2,089.71</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Entrance fees</cell>
     <cell>7,957.17</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Notes payable on loans [sic]</cell>
     <cell>2,800.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1692.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Bethlehem Branch</cell>
     <cell>$ 489.73</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Concordia Branch</cell>
     <cell>273.71</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Humboldt Park Branch</cell>
     <cell>394.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Logan Square Branch</cell>
     <cell>201.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Wicker Park Branch</cell>
     <cell>483.18</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total receipts</cell>
     <cell>$21,503.69</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Disbursements</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Notes payable (loans)</cell>
     <cell>$ 1,800.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Automoblie</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Drugs</cell>
     <cell>135.08</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Electricity</cell>
     <cell>184.64</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>General expense</cell>
     <cell>288.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Fuel, etc</cell>
     <cell>1,283.64</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Funerals</cell>
     <cell>424.50</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1693.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Furniture and fixtures</cell>
     <cell>$ 21.48</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Gas</cell>
     <cell>260.73</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Groceries</cell>
     <cell>8,701.49</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest</cell>
     <cell>283.74</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Insurance</cell>
     <cell>12.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Payroll</cell>
     <cell>4,177.77</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Repairs</cell>
     <cell>1,250.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Real estate, building</cell>
     <cell>231.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Matron's sundries</cell>
     <cell>163.33</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Reserve fund</cell>
     <cell>310.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total disbursements</cell>
     <cell>$19,585.15 [sic]</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance</cell>
     <cell>1,918.54</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$21,503.69</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>A complete report was given by the Society's attorney.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1694.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Reverend M. L. Nesvig's Report</p>
   <p>"To the Norwegian Society for a Home for the Aged in Annual Meeting Assembled:</p>
   <p>"Grace and Peace! 'Jesus Christ the same yesterday, and today, and forever.' (Heb. 13:8.)</p>
   <p>"There have been many and great changes among the nations this past year; epoch-making changes have taken place at home and a broad. Our Society has seen unusual sweeping changes; Our highly esteemed president and others of our strongest leaders have bravely responded to our country's call to arms, and have gone to their respective fields of action and service. At home too, there have been changes; eleven of the residents have been taken from us by death, and new ones on the waiting list have been glad to take their places in order to rest a while at the end of life's weary journey at our comfortable Home for the Aged in beautiful and quiet Norwood Park.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1695.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"During all these changes some things have remained unchanged. Jesus Christ, the Savior of the world is the same, and His Gospel contains the same message to all changing ages--a message of salvation, of reconciliation, of peace, hope and joy here, and a long rest in the eternal home with Jesus our King. The longings and deep-felt desires in the hearts of men for such an unchangeable message only increases in such times as ours. 'For here we have no continuing city, but we seek one to come.' (Heb. 13:14.)</p>
   <p>"What privilege to be an ambassador of the King of Kings with a message of life to a dying age! My work as pastor at the Home is, therefore, essentially the same from year to year. It is meeting the same need with the same remedy. This year, as heretofore, the usual Sunday afternoon services have been conducted, and the regular monthly week-day calls observed. When the pastor was unable to go, substitutes were sent. On special occasions like Easter, Thanksgiving, and Christmas, the string band from my church has gone with me and brought good cheer to everyone. Choirs from various Chicago churches <pb facs="5423969_3_1696.jpg" n="6"/>have come out to the Home on Sunday afternoons, especially during the summer months. Visiting pastors from many states, and Chicago pastors and laymen have called at the Home and generally preached the word of God while visiting. To all the visitors that come and go from week to week, to those who live at the Home, and to the pastor, it means much that we have a Christian matron.</p>
   <p>"Personally, and in behalf of the residents of the Home, I desire to thank the matron, all the members of the Norwegian Society for a Home for the Aged, all speakers and singers, and any and every one who in some measure helped to build up, maintain and make life enjoyable at our dear Home for the Aged in Norwood Park.</p>
   <p>"May God reward and bless you all."</p>
   <p>The doctor of the Home, L. M. Bowes, reported that eleven residents died during the past year. [The names, ages, and causes of death are omitted in translation.] The doctor reported further that the general health at the Home <pb facs="5423969_3_1697.jpg" n="7"/>has been excellent during the past two months, and he thanked the matron, the residents, and the help who have willingly rendered assistance in caring for those who were so unfortunate as to be helpless invalids for many months.</p>
   <p>Matron's Report</p>
   <p>"To the Norwegian Old People's Home Society, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Dear Friends:</p>
   <p>"At the present time we have one hundred and four residents: seventy-three women and thirty-one men. The ages vary from sixty-six years to ninety-five. We have five residents who have been here since the Home was opened in 1896. [Names of residents who entered Home in 1917 are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>"The general health of the residents at the present time is good; there are <pb facs="5423969_3_1698.jpg" n="8"/>only four who are helpless. During the past year some of my most faithful workers have departed from us, but others have willingly and cheerfully taken their places. Though our Home may have been in want during the last year, we have been well provided for at all times, both with provisions and fuel. I wish to thank the board of directors, the Ladies' Board, the Young Ladies' Aid Society, the branch societies, Reverend Nesvig, and Dr. L. M. Bowes, for their kind and able assistance during the past year.</p>
   <p>"To all the residents and the help I extend my heartiest thanks for their helpfullness and co-operation. I wish to extend an invitation to all, especially the workers who have not visited the Home, to come and see the good cause they are working for.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"Camille Anderson, Matron."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1699.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Report of the Ladies' Auxiliary Board</p>
   <p>"Another year of success has passed and the Ladies' Board is very grateful for all the assistance rendered during the entire year. In particular, the introduction of the new Board members at the Home in February, was an interesting occasion. Likewise, the midsummer festival proved a sociable affair of much satisfaction. The tag day on May 14 was a grand success for our Home, and the entire Society should feel indebted to Mrs. Walther for her able and untiring efforts in bringing this about. Our annual picnic at which Flote Grod [sour cream porridge, a national Norwegian dish] was served, was a big success, as usual.</p>
   <p>"The Alumni met at the Home on November 24. Mrs. Belle Nelson, the president, organized a pound party. A program was rendered and the young ladies sang. The annual bazaar was held during the first week in December and turned out to be a grand success; the public, as usual, was very interested in the affair.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1700.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"I wish to thank the members of the Young Ladies' Aid Society and every member of the Ladies' Board for their persevering labors during the year. I also wish to thank the matron and the old people at the Home who are always so kind and willing to make it pleasant on all occasions, and especially when the ladies pay their visits.</p>
   <p>"The Thanksgiving dinner was an enjoyable one and the turkey was good. The Christmas celebration was one of the finest ever held at the Home, and will long be remembered. The minister was there and brought singers along, and Ulrikka Brun spoke interestingly.</p>
   <p>"Wishing that God's continuous blessing may rest over and guide the work of our Society, the Home, and its residents through the year just begun, I remain</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"Mrs. B. J. Johnson, President."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1701.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Report of the Young Ladies' Aid Society</p>
   <p>"Looking in retrospect upon the year 1917, we observe the members of the Young Ladies' Aid Society performing their duty as faithfully and as conscientiously as they have done in former years. This particular branch of the charitable work the care of the aged has appealed very strongly to our members, and as the retiring president, I wish to express my gratification at the splendid co-operation of the members of our Aid Society whenever asked to assist at the annual picnic and bazaar. Working for a particular object, our members have recently added another donation of $100 to the Niles T. Quales Memorial Fund, making a total of $2,100, given to this fund by the Young Ladies' Aid Society.</p>
   <p>"I regret exceedingly that, because of my removal from Chicago, I cannot be actively engaged in the work of the Young Ladies' Aid Society during the ensuing year, but I hope that some future time I may once again resume my activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1702.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>"With the kindest greetings to the members of the Norwegian Society for a Home for the Aged, and with sincerest wishes for an especially successful year, I respectfully submit this report.</p>
   <p>"Mattie Quales Ericksen."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
