<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1919-05-10">May 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Lutheran Children's Home Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_3_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-10">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1919-05-10">May 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN CHILDREN'S HOME SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following are some of the reports made at the quarterly meeting of the Norwegian Lutheran Children's Home Society:</p>
   <p>PRESIDENT'S REPORT</p>
   <p>A few years ago the Home in Edison Park was built. Miss Abrahamson, the first matron, had only four children to care for at that time, but today the Home is a large and busy institution.</p>
   <p>TREASURER'S REPORT</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance from last quarter</cell>
     <cell>$1,688.74</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Received from Financial Secretary</cell>
     <cell>6,075.41</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$7,764.15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>6,334.37</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in treasury</cell>
     <cell>$1,429.78</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_3_1444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>MATRON'S REPORT</p>
   <p>During the past quarter we have averaged about seventy-five children at the Norwegian Lutheran Children's Home. There are about an equal number of boys and girls in the Home. The children recovered wonderfully from the epidemic of "flu" and are now well again. In fact, at the present writing, we have no illness of any kind at the Home.</p>
   <p>The dentist's room has been used weekly by Dr. Hougan who kindly offered his services to us. This saves the home a great expense.</p>
   <p>A number of donations have come in, all of which have been sincerely appreciated as they were very useful. With the "flu" came unusual expenses, and the Home needs money badly. Donations are appreciated by us, and the donor can feel assured that he is making a real contribution to a deserving charity. I wish to say that at least ninety per cent of the children cared for here, are cared for because they have no one to provide form them. It is true that some of the children <pb facs="5423969_3_1445.jpg" n="3"/>have parents, but they have been cruelly neglected; hence their protection by us. Every day when I see the children assembled I think how good it is that we have this Home for them. It is wonderful work.</p>
   <p>We have been visited by five Sunday school classes and church societies. They have all left something, either a donation or a treat for the little ones. Other larger crowds might be mentioned, such as the Dorcas Society of the Bethlehem Church, which came on Palm Sunday and left forty-two dollars with us. The Senior Bible Class of Hauge Church also made us a visit and donated five dollars. Sixty-five testaments were received and distributed among the children by Mr. Geo. Stokes. At Easter we received four cases of eggs. The Dorcas Circle of St. Timothy's Church visited the Home on Easter Sunday and made the children happy by their distribution of Easter baskets containing candy and cake.</p>
   <p>Reverend Lars Harrisville visits the Home faithfully every week to give the children religious instruction.</p>
   <p>The Ladies' Board has also held its meetings here every month with the idea of <pb facs="5423969_3_1446.jpg" n="4"/>talking things over with the matron, and of inspecting the place. The Ladies' Board has also visited us on Sundays.</p>
   <p>An improvement worthy of mention is the installation of single beds in the upper rooms of the cottages.</p>
   <p>We are short of help at the Home. It is difficult to obtain help of the right kind. By this I mean people qualified to care for children. People who accept work here have substantial wages, and also can feel that they are really doing some good in the world.</p>
   <p>This is only a partial report of the many activities here. I wish to assure the public also that anyone who gives us aid has my personal thanks and sincere appreciation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
