<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Is This the Time For] National Prohibition? [Editorial]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[IS THIS THE TIME FOR] NATIONAL PROHIBITION? [Editorial]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While a nation at War demands subjugation of wishes and interests of its loyal and patriotic citizens, the prohibition fanatics, since the beginning of the War, have tried their utmost to make the conflict subservient to their aims. The importance of War was secondary to prohibition in the opinion of these fanatics, also secondary to the national thought, and certainly above the great national and human interests, which gave impetus to the conflict. They have taken bold advantage of the situation, which necessitated swift War legislation, to further their own interests. The prohibition clique used its contemptible tactics by fighting the most important legislative measures which were due for immediate acceptance if the proposed prohibition law did not receive satisfactory consideration. The Nation's primary need was, of course, disregarded by the prohibition fanatics, who welcomed this opportunity to add more pressure to the economic situation of the country by forcing national prohibition upon a people at War.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0939.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While the Government was encountered with a difficult problem, depending upon the good, loyal citizens for its satisfactory solution, the advocators of prohibition, in unison with the enemies of the Administration, were making the present their harvest time. Thus it appears quite probable that the Senate will pass the amendment which will go into effect January 1, 1919.</p>
   <p>Only the President's veto could save the Nation from the swindle of oppression by the prohibitionists, who parade under the false motto: "National prohibition in the interest and because of war." If the President vetoes the bill, he incurs the enmity of the prohibition fanatics. On the other hand, if the amendment is accepted, it will produce bad results economically, as well as socially.</p>
   <p>The Senate's acceptance of the amendment would place the head of the Nation in a very difficult position, because he could not display his own sentiment in regard to prohibition. The veto would be certain, however, if the President did not have to consider the war situation, and the solution of many other great problems. Nevertheless, there is still a possibility that the President may save us from the injustice and swindle of prohibition by vetoing the bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
