<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-09-26">Sept. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Again the School-Fight (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-09-26">Sept. 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AGAIN THE SCHOOL-FIGHT (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Col. Francis W. Parker, director of the Normal School, High Priest of the 'Fad-Cult,' etc., finds his remunerative, comfortable job jeopardized."</p>
   <p>Thus writes our friend, the Evening Post, crusader of nativism and enemy of any scholastic method which dares aspire beyond the elementary limits. Exalted and jubilant at slapping the Germans once more,-those Teutons who always considered the Normal School to be the result of German agitation and who extolled Col. Parker as an unbiased, progressively inclined pedagogue,-this English paper now predicts Parker's fall! And why the sudden elation?</p>
   <p>Our "friend" Charles S. Thornton, whom Carter Harrison nominated to the City School Board, was elevated to the presidency of the County's School Council... Parker's position is indeed unstable now that he incurred the animosity of the Nativists because of his energetic and sympathetic defense of the special branches. His noble work of last winter aroused their ire more than ever!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0194.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The readers of the Staats-Zeitung may remember some of the details of that bitter fight which Charley Thornton inaugurated against Parker... It was the same standardized form of attack against a school system which Parker had introduced. Parker's ideas made the Normal School a model institution for our land. In his zeal he even printed pamphlets denouncing Parker. Why? At that time it was alleged that Thornton was the attorney of the man who presented the plot of ground on which the Normal School stands. And now that the gentleman is impoverished, he would like to re-claim it, as the property became valuable. If it would be possible to oust Parker, then the first step towards the abolition of the institution would be accomplished. By such conniving, the centrally located ground would revert to the former owner, in conformity to certain stipulations of the deed; it all hinges on the special branches and is very clever! This then was construed as the motive.</p>
   <p>Thornton was not successful at that time. Since then, and in spite of all warnings, Harrison made Thornton a member of the City's School Board. The opportunity came after a German committee expressed its thanks to the mayor <pb facs="5418474_1_0195.jpg" n="3"/>and considered Thornton "all right." Thus Thornton became a member of the City's School Board, besides being a member of the County School Council. Now comes the climax: the Ward politician and ex-superintendent of the letter-carriers, Col Donovan, was made a member by the present County Council. He came to the County School Council a full-fledged member. It was accomplished quietly and unobtrusively, a crime for which our county elders deserve a trouncing next November. Thornton also provided for the re-election of his former ally, Dr. Walden, a definite nativist.</p>
   <p>Parker's ousting was the watchword at yesterday's session of the County School Council, and hear ye, Thornton, Donovan, Walden, and the present president of the County Council, Edmanson, voted for Thornton. Cameron, also a member of both boards, left the meeting because he did not care to vote for Thornton. Three others, Cutting, Biroth, and Bright followed suit. Thornton was declared to be elected, 4 to zero.</p>
   <p>Possibly, this election may be overruled, but Donovan and Thornton, bosses of the Carter Party, are firmly entrenched in the saddle and will not rest <pb facs="5418474_1_0196.jpg" n="4"/>until the "Academy of Fads," a title which Thornton bestowed upon it, will be crippled by Parker's fall.</p>
   <p>Who, then, of our prominent Germans sanctions Thornton, and who commends Harrison's predilection for the special branches?</p>
   <p>Who does not listen, must feel! The progressive element can blame no one but itself if the school fight will now include the County schools.</p>
   <p>Thornton, Donovan, Halle, a real pro-German trio!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
