<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1900-01-30">Jan. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">German Instruction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1900-01-30">Jan. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN INSTRUCTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Zimmermann, the superintendent of the department for German instruction in public schools, and the 3 members of the School Board, Messrs. Meier, Stolz, and Clausenius, met in conference to discuss the problem which arose, in regard to teaching German in public schools. These gentlemen are of the opinion that the instruction of German in public schools should receive more attention or at least the same sum of money should be appropriated for this purpose as last year. This branch of the educational system, which employs about three hundred special teachers, received an appropriation of $150,000 last year, while the Finance Committee now desires to reduce the appropriation to $126,000 this year. Superintendent Andrews with the full support of his district superintendents Kirk, Delano, Sabin, and Lewis declares that the teaching of German is not as important as other subjects, therefore it is that subject which should be dispensed with. They are of course only Andrews' echo. Yesterday we heard a pedagogue, very well acquainted with this city's conditions say: "...The appropriation for German instruction in public schools, should be at least $200,000 and for physical culture $35,000." Messrs. Meier and Stolz, members of the School Board, questioned superintendent of public schools Dr. Andrews directly, whether he really was in favor of abolition of German instruction in public schools, and following is the reply of this great diplomat: "I am and always have been in favor of German <pb facs="5418474_1_0462.jpg" n="2"/>instruction. I consider it an important branch of our educational system, but as one of the subjects taught has to be discontinued, I do believe that we can easiest dispense with the instruction of German, for it is among all the subjects taught, of least consequence in our educational system, and the big sum expended for it, could be easily saved. But I say again, I am not opposed to German instruction, the way it is given in our schools now." Mr. Sohwab, member of the School Board promised to insist on an increased allowance for German instruction...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
