<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-07">Nov. 7, 1871</date><title level="a">(From a Reporter's Article Describing the Progress of the Reconstruction of the North Side.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-07">Nov. 7, 1871</date><title level="a">(FROM A REPORTER'S ARTICLE DESCRIBING THE PROGRESS OF THE RECONSTRUCTION OF THE NORTH SIDE.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A sad spectacle are the churches, chapels, and other prayer houses lying in ruins. The German churches, in every case, were connected with elementary schools. The most urgent business of the Germans as a nationality in Chicago is the providing of temporary school rooms. We saw the ruins of many school houses visited by children who formerly were taught there. It is to be hoped that Germans will insist on their rights in this respect with the utmost stubbornness, so that as many cheap school rooms can be fixed up as possible. The infamous thievery of the "school palaces" must to be repeated in new Chicago. The scoundrelly and arbitrary action of the school board in banishing after the fire German instruction from the free schools, hits the north side painfully because there are settlements that are purely German where English is hardly understood in the homes. The bigoted nativism of the fossils on the school board this time has shown itself in its naked hideousness. The 3 German members find themselves shamefully abandoned by the Irish with whom they are otherwise firmly allied.</p>
   <p>Inns have been put up in great numbers everywhere on the north side. Beer wagons <pb facs="5418474_1_0288.jpg" n="2"/>are driving heavily loaded to the settlements of Germans, as well as the Scandinavians and Irish. The patronage by the public yesterday was very strong, and happy singing resounded from many places as formerly. The proclamation of the mayor about the closing of inns on election day counts hardly for much on the north side; it expects too much from the innkeepers in these hard times.</p>
   <p>It is very pleasant to see that already so many brick houses are being built on the north side for permanence, especially by the Germans.</p>
   <p>The American residential district between Clark Street and the lake front (from Kinzie street to Lincoln Park) is still pretty much in ruins. There is a project to extend Lincoln Park and the driveway along the shore southwards to the neighborhood of the waterworks, and to build a hotel on the corner of Superior and Pine streets. But the Americans want to have the breweries moved out west toward the river. Otherwise permanent luxury buildings and gardens could not be thought of. It is not in the interest of the Germans to drive the Americans through a few disagreeable establishments out of their lake shore strip and thereby possibly to prevent the extension of Lincoln Park and the drive way. We have therefore received with regret the information that Busch and Brand have begun to reconstruct their brewery at the old spot. It is in the interest of the whole north side to <pb facs="5418474_1_0289.jpg" n="3"/>see the breweries moved out at the city periphery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
