<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">Mar. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Committee on School Management Rejected the Proposition to Abolish the Teaching of German</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0537</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0537.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">Mar. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMMITTEE ON SCHOOL MANAGEMENT REJECTED THE PROPOSITION TO ABOLISH THE TEACHING OF GERMAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To judge by the decision of yesterday's meeting of the School Board, it seems that the retaining of German in all grades of our public schools is now assured as the voting on the proposition to abolish the teaching of German after the close of the present school year in the peimary grades resulted in equal votes, which means that the proposition was rejected.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Revell and Halle and Miss Burt were in favor of continuing the teaching of German; Messrs. Laren and Beebe and Mrs. Flower, against it. Mr. Duggan, who left before the voting, declared in favor of teaching in all grades of the public schools.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the opening of the meeting, Mr. Halle presented to the Committee on School Management Mr. Max Stern, a representative of the German citizens. He spoke about the retention of the teaching of German and claimed <pb facs="5418474_1_0538.jpg" n="2"/>to have the signatures of 25,000 citizens of the city who are all in favor of German teaching. Mrs. Flower said that personally she is not opposed to the teaching of German but considers it worthless. Miss Burt, Mr. Halle, and also Mr. Revell spoke warmly in favor of retaining the German language. The latter was of the opinion that the decision of retaining or abolishing German teaching should be postponed till after election, because politics is too much involved in this question, but his proposition was rejected. In the meeting of the School Board, to be held this evening, there will, in all probability, be a final decision about the teaching of the German language. Congressman Julius Goldzier, Mr. Max Stern, and others, will speak in the interest of societies and boards for the retention of the German language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
