<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-30">May 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Session of the School Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-30">May 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SESSION OF THE SCHOOL BOARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular fortnightly session of the school board was held yesterday; Mr. Wells presided. The president, as well as Messrs. Hoyne, English, Arnold, Jacobs, Pruessing, Stone, Keith, Brean, Frankenthal, and Frake attended the meeting. The committee on medals was requested to procure the prizes which are to be given at the completion of each term.</p>
   <p>Upon Arnold's motion, E. D. Vail was appointed as a teacher at the high school of the West Side, and his salary was fixed at fifteen hundred dollars, retroactive to the time when he held the position temporarily. The committee on high schools was authorized to order the necessary diplomas.</p>
   <p>Property purchases.... were considered, as were purchases of coal and wood for fuel....</p>
   <p>The salary of Miss Degeler, who teaches German at the Ogden school, was <pb facs="5418474_1_0265.jpg" n="2"/>raised from $450 to $550.</p>
   <p>Music, German, and Drawing</p>
   <p>Mr. Wells read the majority report of the committee on German, music and drawing. According to the report, the committee made an extensive investigation on the subjects, and recommended the adoption of the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>1.) That the present methods used in teaching German are not entirely satisfactory.</p>
   <p>2.) That German instruction shall be continued, but that changes should be made to obtain better results.</p>
   <p>3.) Considering present circumstances, German should not be taught in the <pb facs="5418474_1_0266.jpg" n="3"/>elementary classes.</p>
   <p>4.) German should be taught in the fifth grade, and continued in the following classes. German should always be taught from the beginning of a semester, except in such cases where the student is far enough advanced to continue readily.</p>
   <p>5.) Music and drawing should also be continued.</p>
   <p>6.) In the elementary schools music shall not be taught technically, as that is too difficult, but it should be taught in a practical way only.</p>
   <p>7.) Whenever the number of pupils who study one or all of the three branches in a class, drops below twenty, instruction shall be discontinued.</p>
   <p>8.) But students of various classes may combine to form a class of more <pb facs="5418474_1_0267.jpg" n="4"/>than twenty students in order to study the aforesaid branches, provided that the regular curriculum is not interupted thereby.</p>
   <p>Pruessing submitted a minority report in which he advocated expansion of the three subjects, instead of their curtailment. The most important feature connected with that would be a better trained teaching personnel; which would provide better and more experienced teachers. The present methods, whereby the young instructors are really not much more than students, must be dispensed with.</p>
   <p>In regard to music and drawing, the teachers should be examined before they are accepted.</p>
   <p>As far as German lessons were concerned, the most eminent scholars in the country agreed on but a single, correct method: Children of German parents <pb facs="5418474_1_0268.jpg" n="5"/>should be taught German in the first grade and children of English-American descent should begin German in the third grade. As soon as a class of forty children had been found to take lessons, a teacher who knows both languages should conduct the class, so that all unnecessary expense would be avoided.</p>
   <p>Stone and English asked for a postponement of any decision, as they also desired to submit another minority report.</p>
   <p>Both remarked that if the three branches were to be continued, they would have to be taught more thoroughly....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
