<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-21">March 21st, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Schoolboard.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1893-03-21">March 21st, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting Of The Schoolboard.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>No decision yet about the teaching of German.</p>
   <p>The decision as to the question, whether the German language is to be taught in the Public Schools, did not occur even during last night's meeting of the Schoolboard, but was postponed another week. The meeting turned out to be very interesting. Besides a number of citizens, the ladies committee, headed by Mrs. Gertenberg and a few more ladies were present. After discharging the usual routine-business matters, the Schoolboard member, Mr. Halle, introduced the Congressman, Mr. Julius Goldzier. The latter presented a petition signed by 35000 citizens, in favor of retaining the German language in the schools, which proved, that the movement was not the expression of a small fraction of the people only. In a lengthy speech, he exhorted the members of the Schoolboard, to do their duty, which in the present case consisted of complying with the wishes of a large class of citizens and taxpayers. Mr. Goldzier's speech was loudly acclaimed, which compelled the President to declare, that such demonstrations at the Schoolboard's meetings were out of place.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Gerdtenberg also submitted a petition, signed by 5000 women; Thomas Morgan <pb facs="5418474_1_0536.jpg" n="2"/>submitted another one of the Trade and Labor Assembly, the Central Labor Union, the Socialist Labor party and the Machinists Union No. 16. Similar petitions were also submitted by Miss Burt. The Committee which was entrusted with the deliberation in the matter of the retention or repeal of the special teaching classes, handed, in a majority and a minority report. The former was signed by the Schoolboard members: Halle Duggan, Trudy, Cusack and Miss Burt, and supported the retention of German teaching in all classes. The other supported the opposite, and bore the signature of Schoolboard member Beebe. After a lengthy debate, in which different proposals were made and rejected, it was agreed, that the final decision in the matter of special teaching, should be arrived at the regular meeting next Monday. At the close, a report of the Committee for Buildings and Real Estate was accepted, which proposed the erection of the following schoolbuildings; Building containing 78 rooms on Sholto Street, between Good and Bette Streets, costing $70,000- Building with 15 rooms on Fulton Street and California Avenue, costing $60,000.- An addition with nine rooms on the Vedder Street School, costing $45,000.- Another one with 6 rooms, on the Armour Street School, costing $30,000.- An addition with 6 rooms on West 14th Street and Union Street, costing $30,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
