<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">German Language Instruction in Public Schools Demanded by Delegates</title><title level="a" type="sub">Representatives of German Day Celebration Adopt Resolutions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN LANGUAGE INSTRUCTION IN PUBLIC SCHOOLS DEMANDED BY DELEGATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Representatives of German Day Celebration Adopt Resolutions</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting yesterday of delegates of the German Day Celebration, held at the Hotel Atlantic, the question of German instruction in our public schools produced much lively discussion.</p>
   <p>Captain George Weideling, the official German speaker at the Celebration, proposed to the assembly of two hundred delegates that they adopt a resolution demanding the reintroduction of the study of German in our public schools. Mr. Weideling went one step further, suggesting that the resolution should be presented to Mr. William J. Bogan, Superintendent of Public Schools of Chicago, immediately following his address, which would be delivered in English. The proposal was endorsed by the meeting, although a minority held the procedure to be impractical because of the fact, that the Board of Education in Chicago has announced that the re-establishment of German in public schools is already under consideration. <pb facs="5418474_1_0307.jpg" n="2"/>However, the delay is to be blamed on the lethargic attitude of the parents, who, in spite of stimulation from outside forces, do not take any interest in the issue. The fault is entirely attributable to the German people who have lost all sense of the value of their mother tongue.</p>
   <p>The resolution proposed by Weideling was nevertheless unanimously adopted, and active propaganda was urged whereby parents of German extraction could best be reached.</p>
   <p>According to information volunteered by the chairman of the Program Committee for the German Day Celebration, special tribute will be paid to the three comrades of the heroic ocean flight, in recognition of their great achievement. The outstanding feature of this ceremony will consist of the presentation of busts of the aviators to representatives of the Chicago Historical Society. <pb facs="5418474_1_0308.jpg" n="3"/>Arnold H. Kegel, Health Commissioner of Chicago, volunteered his services to the German Day Celebration Committee. Doctor Bundesen, Coroner, and Mr. Petersen, City Treasurer, announced their intention to make personal visits to the German Day Celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
