<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-26">June 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of German Societies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-26">June 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF GERMAN SOCIETIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5. The delegates from German societies, responding to the call of the executive committee for intellectual activity, of the Turner district of Chicago, assembled at Haendel's Hall last night. An extraordinary interest in the movement for unlimited German instruction and gymnastics in public schools, was shown by the large attendance at the meeting. A lively debate followed the proposal, for the election of a permanent chairman. Many of the delegates contended, that the Society of German Citizens of Chicago and Suburbs, founded some time ago, has already begun its activities in that direction. That association has already submitted its protest, to the school board and to Mayor Harrison, last March. But the majority of the delegates, did not share this view point, therefore, it has been decided to form a new organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0438.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The election of a permanent chairman was deemed unnecessary. This resulted in the temporary election of Mr. Leopold Saltiel as president and Mr. Charles Alvin, secretary, for the evening only. Mr. Alvin declared in his speech, that not the members of the school board, alone are to be blamed for their antagonistic attitude, toward the German question. The principals and teachers in public schools, are equally as much opposed to German instruction. He cited an instance, where two children of German extraction were deprived of their privilege to choose between the study of German and the study of Latin but were given definitely to understand, that German was out of the question. Nevertheless, in both instances, the parents were ultimately the victors. Furthermore, Mr. Alvin asserted the opposition to the German and the stand taken by the school board, are largely due to the attitude of the Bohemian member of the school board, Mr. Walleck. Due to his intrigues, one of the city's Norwegian societies was moved to approach the school board with the suggestion that the instruction of all foreign languages in public schools be abolished.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0439.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Through the kind services of Mr. Walleck, a copy of this decision reached the school board. As none of the members had any knowledge of who supplied them with a copy of that document, a search for the evil-doer was begun, by Mr. Meier, one of the members of the school board. This led to the discovery of Mr. Walleck, and of the trick he played. Following a lengthy debate, it was decided to appoint a committee, which would be assigned the task of drawing up a plan for a permanent organization. The report of this committee is expected to be read at the July 9th, meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
