<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-12-21">Dec. 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Protest Meeting</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">School Board Sharply Criticized</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-12-21">Dec. 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST MEETING</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">School Board Sharply Criticized</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held at 604 North Wells Street yesterday evening, and a large crowd was present. Colonel Schaffner was chairman. The committee which was appointed at the previous meeting to investigate the North Wells Street school submitted the report published in yesterday's edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung. The report was accepted after some details were explained.</p>
   <p>Miss Babcock, principal of the school, sent a report. She said that all the excitement and gossip about the school's unsanitary condition had originated from one person only, whose motives were by no means honest. The school rooms were not dirty. The assertion that fifteen wagonloads of dirt and filth had been removed from the school building was a falsehood. The statement that twenty-three pupils of the school had died of scarlet fever was <pb facs="5418474_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>not based on truth. Only six cases of scarlet fever had occurred in the neighborhood of the school, and none of the children living in the vicinity was stricken by the disease.</p>
   <p>Mr. Brooke, secretary of the company which owns the building rented to the city for school purposes, ordered the cleaning of the basement on the strength of the agitation in the newspapers and by civic bodies. When the workingmen came to the basement, they found no dirt, so they went to the coal bins and cleaned them. The material they carted away looked very bad, particularly so because it had rained that day. But the stuff was of an absolutely harmless nature.</p>
   <p>As mentioned, one person only had started the scandal. Since September 1, 1879, only three children had died of scarlet fever, and there were 450 pupils. Cases of sickness [scarlet fever] were reported in twenty-one <pb facs="5418474_1_0258.jpg" n="3"/>instances. The department of education was extremely careful. If a pupil was sick, none of his brothers or sisters was permitted to attend school until the board of health issued a certificate.</p>
   <p>The board of health made an investigation and found the school in proper condition. The official who looked into the matter must certainly have felt that his report was reliable, since he sent his own children to the school. Of course, the school might have been situated in a better locality, but, nevertheless, there are schools in worse locations. The school board was not at fault, and had done everything within its power. However, it is to be hoped that the movement started by the citizens of the North Side will result in the building of a new school.</p>
   <p>School board member Delaney read Miss Babcock's report. A lively debate ensued; in fact, the session was turbulent at times. Mr. Wagner, Alderman <pb facs="5418474_1_0259.jpg" n="4"/>Wetterer, and others spoke. Some factions asserted that the report of the investigating committee was an attempt to whitewash the school board.</p>
   <p>General Lieb made a motion that a committee of three be nominated to draft resolutions expressing the views of the assembly (residents of the 14th and 15th wards). Several suggestions were made and Delaney came to the defense of the school board. He said that not enough money was available to build a new schoolhouse, else it would have been done long ago. General Lieb remarked that it appeared ridiculous to him that not enough money was in the treasury for new school buildings; besides, the taxes for 1879 will be available soon, and the board of education usually expects a generous slice.</p>
   <p>School board member Frake explained that the board of education was in arrears, and that considerable money from tax collections for the year 1873 <pb facs="5418474_1_0260.jpg" n="5"/>and 1874 has not been paid. The comptroller objected to paying these claims, and was backed up in his refusal by the mayor and the press. General Lieb then showed, by quoting figures from the comptroller's account, that a large surplus from former years was still available in the school fund, and asked why this money was not used to build a new school. Mr. Frake replied that these extra funds were not available, because the money was set aside to pay various contractors as soon as they finish their work. There was no alternative. "If our citizens have complaints to make, they must appeal directly to the mayor and the city council, and urge them to build a new school."</p>
   <p>Paul Grottkau [labor leader] spoke next. He said that General Lieb had brought out many good points, but had failed to get to the bottom of conditions, the all-pervading corruption. The report of the investigating committee "was'nt so hot!" The school board was partly at fault; however, the City Council was mostly to blame. It was about time that the mothers <pb facs="5418474_1_0261.jpg" n="6"/>avenge their children who had died in the epidemic, and horsewhip those responsible for it.</p>
   <p>Colonel Schaffner, Alderman Wetterer, Alderman Meier of the 16th ward, and a number of citizens then expressed their views about the school question until about half past eleven. Due to the lateness of the hour, General Lieb withdrew his motion to appoint a committee of three and, instead, offered a resolution which he wanted to have incorporated in the report of the investigating committee.</p>
   <p>In this resolution, the school board was severely criticized by the citizens of the 15th and 16th wards, and the board was urged to make drastic changes, in conformance to the findings of the investigating committee and to build a new school as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Alderman Wetterer made a motion to exclude the resolution, but his proposal <pb facs="5418474_1_0262.jpg" n="7"/>aroused objections. He then asked to delete the part which accused the school board, and this, also, met with defeat.</p>
   <p>General Lieb's motion (the adoption of his resolution and the report of the investigating committee) was accepted.</p>
   <p>Adjournment followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
