<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-01-27">Jan. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Regarding the School Question. (Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-01-27">Jan. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">REGARDING THE SCHOOL QUESTION. (Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In regard to the article of Feb. 23rd, published by the Evening Post, I beg to offer a few corrections. You claim that in Prussia, languages are not taught until the pupils are in high school. This is an error. In Berlin, Hamburg, in fact in all important cities, English is taught in the public schools, and in Muenden, Westphalen, (a province in Germany) our mutual brith-place, French as been included in the elementary schools for the last 15 years, as I have been reliably informed. Concerning the other so-called special studies, singing, drawing and manual training; I was instructed in these branches 50 years ago, in a hamlet of the Paderborn District. These subjects were considered to be customary school courses and were not honored with the title "special branches". These Americans who never miss an opportunity to brag about being the richest as well as the best educatednation on earth, and who look with disdain upon Germany, should be ashamed of their incessant pusillanimous objections based on the pretext, that such tuition is too costly, when the Germans, after all, have done the most toward this country's greatness and prosperity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0602.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That the children in Germany are taught more thoroughly, is attributable to the longer school attendance since most children are required to study from the 6th to the 14th year. Those parents in this country who only send their youngsters to school for two years, are anything but commendable specimens. It is therefore the state's supreme duty to thoroughly revise the compulsory school law.</p>
   <p>(signed) M. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
