<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-01-12">Jan. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Business Program of the Illinois Legislature (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-01-12">Jan. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE BUSINESS PROGRAM OF THE ILLINOIS LEGISLATURE (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago the Fifty-first General Assembly of Illinois convened in the State capitol at Springfield. The present session of the State legislature is of the greatest significance for the citizens of the State and especially for the citizens of Chicago. Among the bills in which we Chicagoans are especially interested we want to mention the one calling for a constitutional convention; also the one regarding ratification of the Prohibition Amendment to the National Constitution and, finally, one relating to the reform of municipal administration and city finances.</p>
   <p>The calling of a constitutional convention has already been decided upon. The citizens of the state decided this question at the last election. But the legislative body has to take the necessary measures for the election of the delegates to the convention and for its financing. The greatest difference <pb facs="5418474_1_0923.jpg" n="2"/>of opinion in this matter concerns the manner in which delegates are to be elected. Some consider the primary elections for the nomination of the party candidates the most suitable occasion for the election of the delegates. Others assume the viewpoint that the election to the constitutional convention should not be left to the party machine, but ways and means should be found to make it as nonpartisan as possible. Which group will emerge victorious in this controversy is impossible to say at present.</p>
   <p>The question whether the Illinois legislature will sanction the Prohibition Amendment to the National Constitution is naturally of the greatest interest to the population of a great metropolitan center like Chicago. In the Senate, the "drys" had the majority. Whether the bill will pass the House remains to be seen. The Anti-Saloon League claims that there, too, their adherents command a majority. Their opponents are of a different opinion. The adoption of the bill by the Illinois General Assembly naturally does not make the proposed amendment to the National Constitution, about which there has been great controversy, a law. For that the consent of thirty-six <pb facs="5418474_1_0924.jpg" n="3"/>state legislatures is necessary. But over two thirds of this number have already ratified the measure and a number of further ratifications are almost assured, so that it is possible that our legislature might provide the deciding factor in the fate of the proposed constitutional amendment. The responsibility of the legislators, therefore, is tremendous; the effects of their decision may extend over the boundaries of Illinois and all through the United States. May they always keep that in mind!</p>
   <p>The possible adoption of the prohibition amendment is already casting its dark shadows before. Almost every day some taverns close their doors because their proprietors are not inclined to renew their expiring leases in view of a forced closing of their establishments, or to pay out high license fees. By the dozens, even by the hundreds, one can observe the darkened places at Chicago's street corners; and the windows, blind with dirt, seem to mourn about the ways of all earthly things. These empty places cannot fail to remind the passers-by of the financial consequences which the prohibition clause, once it has become the law of the land, will have for <pb facs="5418474_1_0925.jpg" n="4"/>the citizens. Cities like Chicago will suffer such a tremendous financial setback from the loss of income from liquor licenses that other taxes have to be advanced appreciably to make up for this deficit. Besides that, we have to consider the losses of the property owners and the probably much greater losses of all those persons and families who have been earning their livelihood, directly or indirectly, in the liquor trade and who now, in their older days, have to learn a new trade or start in business all over again. Chicago has already begun to suffer, during the last year, from a gradual decrease of the liquor business and must earnestly consider either the creation of new sources for taxes or making the old ones yield more. This needs the approval of the legislature. Its decision will naturally be of greatest importance not only for the administration of municipal affairs during the next few years, but also for the further development of Chicago in general; for unless permission is granted to levy higher taxes, the efficiency of many branches of the administration will suffer considerably, while the proposed and very necessary plans for beautifying the city and relieving traffic congestion within the city's limits will be postponed <pb facs="5418474_1_0926.jpg" n="5"/>indefinitely.</p>
   <p>The reforms in municipal administration which certain people desire, include a change in the election procedure for officials, the creation of an office of commissioner of finances, the consolidation of the various park boards, and the introduction of nonpartisan municipal elections. The sponsors of the movement for a change in the election of officials are motivated by the desire to shorten a lengthy ballot sheet. According to the plan, quite a number of those officials who in the past were elected by the people directly, including the mayor, the city clerk, and the city treasurer, are to be elected and appointed by the city council. The shortening of a lengthy ballot sheet which, in its present size, would better be put up in book form, would certainly be desirable, for voters are now confronted with a task which only a few people are capable of discharging. But whether this simplification has to begin with the elimination of the mayor from the list of candidates is still a controversial point. The consolidation of the park boards, however, can be recommended unhesitatingly. It can only be of advantage to the city. The <pb facs="5418474_1_0927.jpg" n="6"/>general introduction of continuation schools for children between the ages of fourteen and sixteen, who are past the regular school age, the institution of an eight-hour working day and one day of complete rest after six days of work for employed women, social welfare for underprivileged children, more adequate legal protection for illegitimate children, the reorganization of our Chicago courts, and the accumulation of a fund to improve highways, are other important items which will occupy the General Assembly and which should merit the close attention of the citizenry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
