<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-14">May 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Basic Cause of the School and Prohibition Tyranny</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-14">May 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">BASIC CAUSE OF THE SCHOOL AND PROHIBITION TYRANNY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Altgeld's public utterances during his present travels through the state of Illinois are very frank. But he also penetrates into the bases of these matters.</p>
   <p>Altgeld thinks that spiteful school laws of the Edward type and the absurd and oppressive prohibition laws are the product of a so-called aristrocratic arrogance which is entirely irreconcilable with a true republican form of government.  People affected by this arrogance consider themselves as belonging to a better class, because they were born in this country, or because fortune smiled upon them. Therefore they are presumptuous enough to tell the people to raise their children according to a definite pattern, and are trying also to control the habits of people in regard to drink.</p>
   <p>Both of these kinds of tyranny Altgeld wants abolished. He asserts that the state has no right to interfere with private or church schools, but at the same <pb facs="5418474_1_0213.jpg" n="2"/>time he recognizes the duty and right of the state to insist that parents give their children at least an elementary school education, without being restricted however in their choice of a school.</p>
   <p>According to Altegeld's well-founded theory and personal viewpoint the state can only dictate to individuals in regard to habits of life including the use of alcoholic beverages when it becomes absolutely necessary to the maintenance of peace and public order.</p>
   <p>Altgeld has not come to these conclusions since he became a candidate for governor but they were his own convictions. He stated them long ago, and are the result of his studies and meditations about these important public questions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
