<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-08-01">August 1, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The 14th German American Teachers' Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-08-01">August 1, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE 14th GERMAN AMERICAN TEACHERS' DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night in the beautifully decorated Turnhalle of the Northside the "Reception" of men and women teachers took place. Besides the guests many friends of the science of education and officials were present.</p>
   <p>Dr. G. A. Zimmermann, Chairman of the Central Council, opened the meeting with a hearty welcoming speech, in which he particularly emphasized the necessity of the teachers promoting German instruction and in which he called it their task to preserve "the German character as one of the stones with which to build the American nation". Mayor Harrison followed with one of his characteristic speeches, comparing the German with the Grecian language and agreeing with Charles Francis Adams that we should replace the Greek by the German language in the High School. Learning the German language gives just as much discipline to the mind as the study of Greek, but has the added advantage of being a living language, and indeed one which has a mighty influence on the development of the American nation. The Mayor also praised the German educational system that brought the children <pb facs="5418474_1_0665.jpg" n="2"/>up to happy fun-loving human beings. He terminated with these words: "The German language opens to the American public a great volume of poetry and knowledge, and I, too, hope, ladies and gentlemen, to be able to greet you next year in German." Then the Assistant School President Delano in place of the absent School President Howland and Federal President, Mr. H. Schuricht gave speeches.</p>
   <p>From the latter's address we give a few interesting sentences:</p>
   <p>"My friends, the time is serious. Several times in the last few months storm clouds have threatened the German-American Schools and their achievements, - and though in most instances the sky got clear again, here and there traces of destruction are left and cause a feeling of insecurity in German-American circles.</p>
   <p>"I remind you of the attacks on German instruction in St. Paul, in St. Louis and other places, - and the severe blow the legislature of Missouri has dealt the kindergarten in the City of St. Louis. In facing these fanatical enemies, who are trying to place the German-Americans in an untrue and anti-American position, and are willing to sacrifice to their antipathy, <pb facs="5418474_1_0666.jpg" n="3"/>without any scruple, the sacred and highest interest of the Republic, which is the equal education of all groups of American children- it is our duty to take a resolute and self confident attitude. We only demand to be acknowledged as what in fact we are: As Americans-which we became in clear consciousness and of our own free will not through the accident of birth. We only ask for our due rights: To be permitted to serve the country to which we belong in our way, and with our means, and we demand not to be molested, when we try to implant in the minds of our children through our mother language in which we naturally can express ourselves best, the love and loyalty for the Fatherland which is a recognized virtue of all Germans, for which they have over there(sad to say) as well as over here, frequently paid with their life and blood. Therefore my friends, we must stand shoulder to shoulder in order to defend our rights."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
