<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-19">Feb. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Drawing, Music, German</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest against Discontinuance of these Subjects in our Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0761</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0761.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-19">Feb. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">DRAWING, MUSIC, GERMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest against Discontinuance of these Subjects in our Public Schools</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following protest is being circulated:</p>
   <p>"To the Honorable Members of the School Board of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen: The undersigned, citizens of Chicago, regret that several members of your esteemed Board are endeavoring to discontinue in our public schools the three requested, special branches: drawing, music, and German.</p>
   <p>"We are taxpayers, but regardless of the great sacrifices which we have always been glad to make for the upkeep of our free school system, we do not believe that the mere saving of thirteen thousand dollars justifies the abolition of these cultural subjects, in a city of a half million inhabitants, <pb facs="5418474_1_0762.jpg" n="2"/>who pay four million dollars annually for the maintenance of our municipal government.</p>
   <p>"German is spoken by one third of our population and a knowledge of the language is of incalculable value to everyone.</p>
   <p>"Singing is taught in the lowest classes of all Christian countries, and drawing benefits every person who has learned a trade.</p>
   <p>"We, therefore, appeal to the esteemed members of your Board that they shall not permit any changes in the present school plan, and that the aforesaid studies shall be continued as heretofore."</p>
   <p>Protest forms may be obtained from these places: H. Biroth, 111 Archer Avenue; Vorwaerts Turnhalle; Aurora Turnhalle;.....[Six addresses are given], and after signatures have been obtained, the circulars must be returned to <pb facs="5418474_1_0763.jpg" n="3"/>one of these addresses, not later than next Wednesday, February 26.</p>
   <p>The text of the protest is, of course, in English, but an explanation is given in German which, in the main, is identical; but, the following request is added: "It need hardly be mentioned that the Germans of our city, in particular, are greatly concerned with this question. It is, therefore, their duty to throttle in its incipiency this movement which threatens to develop into a nativistic affair, and which, if successful, would undoubtedly produce further transgressions.</p>
   <p>"Anyone desirous of doing something, should ask for a list and obtain signatures. It would be particularly advantageous to circulate the protest among clubs, lodges, etc."</p>
   <p>We fully agree with this protest in every particular and hope that the signatures of all citizens of German origin will be affixed; that everyone will <pb facs="5418474_1_0764.jpg" n="4"/>do his share. This is a matter of utmost importance. The survival of German culture is involved. It would be desirable if several hundred volunteers would endeavor to bring this protest into homes and shops for the securing of signatures.</p>
   <p>A general meeting has been announced by the Chicago Turngemeinde (Chicago Gymnastic Community) and, it is hoped, no member will be absent. [Editor's note: The Chicago Turngemeinde was one of the most active organizations in the fight to maintain German-language instruction in our public schools.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
