<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-05">Mar. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">To Fight for the Mother Tongue.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-05">Mar. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TO FIGHT FOR THE MOTHER TONGUE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a motion pending and if it is carried, the school board will be authorized to discontinue German language instruction, as well as the subjects of gymnastics, vocal music, and drawing. This is a serious below to German-Americanism and is a challenge to every one. The Germans should be victorious in this battle, due to their numerical strength, provided that they are aware of the cultural importance of these branches, and make the necessary efforts.</p>
   <p>The German and German-American population of Chicago is much larger than the Anglo-American one. The German language is spoken by about a half million people, and it is just as indispensable in every day social and business affairs as English. If a child masters both languages, and is well instructed in those special branches, it certainly has a better foundation, and is far better equipped for a future career, than a child without these advantages.</p>
   <p>Have not the Germans, in view of their numerical strength, a right to German-instruction in the public schools? Besides, there is every where an increasing demand for German; and it enables parents to train their children better, <pb facs="5418474_1_0568.jpg" n="2"/>since they can instruct them in their mother tongue. Therefore, irrespective of the practical value of German, its moral and intellectual influence is important. The fight for the maintenance of these branches is a far reaching battle for culture, particularly in this cosmopolitan city. Every true friend of progress, irrespective of nationality, ought to be interested in this struggle.</p>
   <p>... This is a battle for progress, and is directed against nativistic insolence. Nativism raises its head whenever it believes that its power is endangered; it is the result of a narrow and limited education, and its department leads to the conclusion that the worth and fitness of a citizen in this country depends entirely upon his command of English and his adaptation to English customs.</p>
   <p>As a convincing counter-evidence it is necessary only to point to the almost exclusively English-speaking rowdies and tramps, who maintain gambling and vice resorts, who make our streets unsafe, and who dominated the scandalous primary election, so that decent citizens turned away in disgust... This party (now fighting against German instruction in our public schools), and these contemptible tramps are indeed worthy associates of the anti-German members of the school board and of the English newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What chances for intellectual and cultural progress would there be if this clique should carry out its slogan: "America for Americans only!"</p>
   <p>This republic was not founded only for English speaking people and their descendants, but for the oppressed of all the countries, who through their industry and public virtues, try to make an honest and independent livelihood. The fathers and founders of our country, Washington, Jefferson, Franklin, and others, understood this, as clearly evidenced by the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution.</p>
   <p>The same standpoint should be taken by the representatives of our free public schools.... If man is the product of his training and environment, a narrow and restricted education must, therefore, produce a narrow minded and stupid man - a selfish worshipper of money, with no ideals, whose enthusiasm can be aroused for the almighty dollar only. This is the class of people which gives us on one hand, the fast growing, prosperous exploiters of a monopolistic industrial system, and, on the other hand, the presumptuous "Know-Nothings," the intolerant, puritanical bigots...</p>
   <p>Progressive and liberal citizens should, therefore, never tolerate the suppression of those respective branches of instruction, but insist upon <pb facs="5418474_1_0570.jpg" n="4"/>possible improvements of the same. No citizen should fail to sign the petitions which are now being circulated for this purpose.</p>
   <p>C. H.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
