<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-01-24">January 24th, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">German Instruction. Schoolboard Member Gross Distributes a Questionaire Concerning It.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1899-01-24">January 24th, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">German Instruction. Schoolboard Member Gross Distributes A Questionaire Concerning It.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Acting on his own initiative, Mr. H. H. Gross, of the City's Schoolboard sent a letter to 100 principals of our public schools, several days ago. The filling out of the questionaire is for the purpose and benefit are derive by giving German instruction in the public schools. The questions are about as follows!- "How many scholars of the 7th and 8th grade partake of German instruction in your school?" "Are any of the scholars-those of German origin excepted-able to read or write a German letter after an instruction period of one or two years?" "Would it be preferable to use the time, devoted to the study of German, in giving English instruction instead?" "Do you believe, that the study of German, is useful, as far as the pupils in your class are concerned?"</p>
   <p>So far, Mr. Gross, obtained about 60 replies to his circular, but he is not willing at present to give detailed information concerning it. Pres. Harris and the school board members Schwab and Mrs. Sherman from the Committee on German instruction are not pleased with Mr. Gross's procedure. They have apprehensions that it will lead to a renewed attack on German teaching, and, if at all possible, the administration wishes to prevent this. Mr. Gross declares however, that he is only interested <pb facs="5418474_1_0470.jpg" n="2"/>personality in ascertaining, whether the $150,000.00 (One hundred fifty thousand dollars) have been wasted uselessly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
