<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-04-18">April 18, 1908</date><title level="a">German-American National Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0849</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0849.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-04-18">April 18, 1908</date><title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The branch "Chicago" of the German-American National Union, has offered a prize of $200 to young men who are preparing for the teaching profession, to enable them to visit the German-American National Teachers Seminary in Milwaukee. The conditions are:</p>
   <p>The applicants obligate themselves to attend for two years the Normal course of the Seminary. To the competitive examinations will be admitted those who went through a four year high school course successfully, or can show a preparatory education of equal value. Those who received their preparatory education in Germany, must show that their education is equal to the one obtained in a Gymnasium, Real Gymnasium or a Real school. A written examination must be made in the following subjects:</p>
   <p>German composition (the applicant has the choice of three themes. English composition (choice of three themes. Translation from English into German.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0850.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>German Grammar. For selection: The History of the Greeks and Romans (in German) or, the History of the United States (in English).</p>
   <p>The written exercises begin Sunday, May 16th, from 1 to 5 P:M in the office of the Chicago Branch, No. 912 Schiller Building. The examination lessons are made up and are subject to the revision of the Committee, consisting of Professors Dr. Paul O. Kern and Dr. A. von Noe of the University of Chicago, two Seminary teachers and the Seminary director. The award of the scholarship will be given on the grounds of a report by the executive committee of the branch union. Applications are to be made to:</p>
   <p>Paul Haerting, Secretary,</p>
   <p>912 Schiller Building, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
