<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-12-28">December 28, 1897</date><title level="a">(Editorial) Value of the German Language Teaching</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-12-28">December 28, 1897</date><title level="a">(Editorial) Value of the German Language Teaching</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From time to time the Germans of America have the pleasure and the satisfaction of knowing that the cultivation and learning of the German language is recommended by prominent native English-speaking people.</p>
   <p>For the Americans of German extraction who disregard the tongue of their fathers, this is a shameful fact to be recognized. For the entire nation this advice becomes the more worthy of attention, as it does not come from German-born but from English-born citizens.</p>
   <p>There are mainly the educated American pedagogues who give credit to the value of the German language and to its instruction in the public schools, and who support it. To these men belong the able School Superintendent Emerson of Buffalo.</p>
   <p>In his latest annual report he says: "The German language is now taught in Buffalo in 42 schools. The number of pupils participating in this branch was 6990 during the last year. Of there 752 visited the high schools and 6238 the district schools. During the last four years there is to be noticed an increase of 1555 pupils who participate in German instruction. <pb facs="5418474_1_0472.jpg" n="2"/>It is hardly necessary to mention here again the arguments in favor of this branch of instruction. The subject is demanded by thousands of resident German-Americans who patronize the public schools. Disregarding the practical benefit that is brought along with the knowledge of this language in a city that is inhabited by such an enormous number of Germans or such who are of German extraction, there are also other reasons, and of a purely pedagogical nature, which show that it is expedient and wise, to offer the opportunity to those who desire to appropriate the knowledge of a foreign language.</p>
   <p>The most important authors in educational matters especially Dr. William T. Harris, the Federal Commissioner for Education, recommend such instruction. Also the conference for modern languages, in connection with the famous "Committee of Ten" which was nominated by the "National Educational Association", recommends that the German language should be taught as a non-compulsory object of instruction in the Grammar Schools and should be started with pupils who are in their tenth year.</p>
   <p>The conference maintains that such a study exercises the memory of the pupils, sharpens the mind, does contribute to a more thorough understanding of the <pb facs="5418474_1_0473.jpg" n="3"/>construction of the English language, and expands the intellectual powers by teaching the pupil that the must apply an idea an expression that differs from the one he is used to.</p>
   <p>The conference recommends further those aims which need special attention by the instruction of the language in Grammar Schools: first a good pronunciation; second, the ability to understand the spoken German in sentencesof brief expressions; third the ability to read with understanding simple stories in the foreign language, and fourth to acquire the ability to be able to construct short sentences with recognition of the fundamental grammatical rules.</p>
   <p>I think that in our Grammar Schools this aim is evident. Boys as well as girls who have some talent for language, who are diligent and look for the opportunity to learnto speak the German language, will without doubt become so familiar with the German language that this certainly will be of greatest importance in their practical lives. On the other hand it is clear that many pupils with less talent and less interest never will learnto speak German, but even for these the study is beneficial because it develops their minds and expands their horizon. <pb facs="5418474_1_0474.jpg" n="4"/>It is to be added, that no pupil is allowed to start the study of the German language or if started to continue it unless they fully satisfy in the English branches of instruction."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
