<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-04-13">April 13, 1904</date><title level="a">The Germanistic Institution. Northwestern University Follows the Example of Harvard.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-04-13">April 13, 1904</date><title level="a">THE GERMANISTIC INSTITUTION. NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY FOLLOWS THE EXAMPLE OF HARVARD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A highly important step in the further development of the American spiritual life that especially will be warmly welcomed by the entire German element of the U.S. was made yesterday by the Administrative Board of the Northwestern University. On the occasion of its annual meeting it resolved to found a Germanistic Institution, as a branch of the University, just like the one that is in existence in connection with Harvard University.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the institution is to awaken and cultivate, through the American Universities, a wider interest towards the accomplishments of German civilization, language, literature, history, art, music, archaeology, - in short, of the entire German spiritual life and psychology; also to tie closer the connections between Germany and the United States, and to form more hearty relations between the two nations.</p>
   <p>The plan also envisions the foundation of a Museum in which shall be illustrated, <pb facs="5418474_1_0142.jpg" n="2"/>as far as is possible the development of the German civilization, through collections of pictures, statues, utilities, models of architecture and of applied arts.</p>
   <p>Further there will be established a library that will contain everything that has been created by German spirit and German knowledge. The library and museum shall be housed in one building, whose architecture shall be German and which already by its outer appearance expresses the architectural talent and the artistic taste.</p>
   <p>Further, lectures shall be arranged for which prominent scholars from German Universities and other acknowledged authorities shall be called.</p>
   <p>But the institution shall also become a monument for the importance of the German element of our country, it shall show how far the life and aims of the American people were influenced by the Germans, and it shall thereby remind us of the great part Germany and the Germans played in the history of our development.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following gentlemen were nominated as directors of the Germanistic Institution:</p>
   <p>Judge Theo. Brentano, Otto C. Butz, Member of Congress, Henry Sherman Boutell, Fred C. Gaertner, Chas. F. Guenther, E.G. Halle, Dr. Jas. Taft Hatfield, H. Paepke, Otto C. Schneider, Wilhelm Vocke.</p>
   <p>Besides, there shall be appointed a general council selected of outstanding men in Germany and the United States.</p>
   <p>The Administration Board also resolved to celebrate in suitable manner the Fiftieth Anniversary of the foundation of the University on November 5th, 1905.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
