<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-05">Mar. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to German Women.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-05">Mar. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO GERMAN WOMEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not customary for German women to be active in politics. Their homes are their kingdoms, and their thoughts and efforts are directed towards the welfare of their families. However, unusual circumstances require unusual action. The Germans in Chicago are intensely interested at present, in whether or not German instruction in our public schools is to be continued. This matter affects the German mother and wife so deeply, and is so closely interwoven with her activities and her aims, that her public appearance is not only justified but imperative.</p>
   <p>Every German woman, who merely glances at our daily newspapers, is aware of the fact that instruction in German, drawing, gymnastics, and vocal music is threatened again with discontinuation. These are the subjects which have been introduced into our public schools, chiefly, because they were recommended by intelligent Germans.</p>
   <p>Germans, in this city, have taken up this important matter with zeal and courage. The German newspapers, without exception have defended it, and they have succeeded in having the decision of the school board in this important matter postponed. But this is by no means a favorable decision. The danger still <pb facs="5418474_1_0563.jpg" n="2"/>exists, and is more threatening than it ever was before. It will require the utmost efforts of all educated people to win the victory in this great cause.</p>
   <p>For this reason the German women of Chicago should get together for consultations on how to meet this threatening danger most effectively. The school board must be convicted that the majority of our educated population recognizes the importance of the afore mentioned subjects, and desires the continuation of the same in our public schools.</p>
   <p>To accomplish this, some German women have come together to arouse the interest of the whole German female population of the city. They urgently appeal to all, to attend a mass meeting March 11, at 3 p. m., at the North Side Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>All Germans and friends of the German language are urgently and cordially invited to attend. German mothers, who have the intellectual and physical welfare of their children at heart, should not fail to come. Likewise all German teachers of private and public schools, all German women's clubs and societies should attend. We also invite German clergymen of all faiths, pedagogues, and liberal minded men, who are interested in the practical education of our youth. They are requested to participate personally in this <pb facs="5418474_1_0564.jpg" n="3"/>movement and exert their whole influence.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the mass meeting is to discuss this problem from all view points, make resolutions, and secure as many signatures as possible to present to the school board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
