<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-05-15">May 15, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Science and Politics; Honor and Money</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-05-15">May 15, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SCIENCE AND POLITICS; HONOR AND MONEY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hugo Munsterberg, the fighting German-American professor makes the following interesting statement: "I remember very well a long discussion which I had with an eminent English Scholar, who had come to lecture in this country. At that time I was not very long in this country and therefore inexperienced in American academic affairs. We talked about the low standard of American scholarship, and he said, 'America will never have scholars of the first magnitude as in Germany and England, unless every professor in the leading universities receives not less than $10,000 yearly salary, and the best of them not less than $25,000.'</p>
   <p>"I was very much surprised and considered it a pessimistic and materialistic attitude. He reasserted his opinion and continued, 'The American's consideration for money exists not merely for the sake of money, but to him it indicates the measure of success; therefore the professions of science and learning must have the support, which high salaries affords, to make them socially prominent, and attractive for the most intelligent people' <pb facs="5418474_1_0161.jpg" n="2"/>"My friend did not convince me then, but my contact with hundreds of professors and teachers all over the United States, and my analysis of the careers of the most capable students, who were inclined toward science and learning, but finally chose the legal profession or, business for the sake of social recognition, convinced me of the truth of his statements."</p>
   <p>This is not a pleasant realization, but it is true, nevertheless. Whoever has mingled with our intellectual, public, and social life, with some degree of observation, and recognized the driving power, cannot help but agree with Professor Muensterberg.</p>
   <p>Money is the measure of success. Riches is honor. Wealth is power. To gain wealth is to find admission to the higher levels of life, Of course there are people, who, in spite of their wealth, are despicable in the sight of the world, and there are others who obtain high degrees of honor without a large share of earthly goods. However, these are exceptions which prove the rule.........</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0162.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The career of a scholar with a possible professorship for its goal and an income of from $3,000 to $5,000 per year only, will never have the attraction among our people and in our time for the most intelligent and most capable students. Besides, it must be taken into consideration, that it takes years of laborious preparation and highest mental strain without being compensated by due recognition and honor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
