<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-04-30">Apr. 30, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">The German Instruction in the Public Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-04-30">Apr. 30, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN INSTRUCTION IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting of the Board of Education, Mr. Richberg and Mr. Hosing handed in the following report. To the Board of Education: Last year the Committee on German Instruction recommended a change in the teaching of German. On Sept. 3rd, the committee suggested the following changes:</p>
   <p>1. That the course should last at least three years.</p>
   <p>2. That in order to advance to a higher class, a pupil must pass an examination in German, as well as in the other subjects.</p>
   <p>3. That pupils who once have started a course in German, must continue it.</p>
   <p>These reports were ordered to be printed. But seven months have gone by and nothing has happened as yet. As it is absolutely necessary to introduce some changes at the beginning of the coming school year, we have visited all the schools where German is taught and have consulted all the German teachers. We must acknowledge here that the Superintendent has given us plans and outlines which we have incorporated in this report.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0810.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>German is studied in this country, especially in the West for practical purposes. Since German is a living language it should not be taught in the same way as a dead language is taught. Here can be found the main error in the teaching of all living foreign languages; too much book knowledge, and too little practical acquaintance with the spirit of a language.</p>
   <p>Thus arises the question, how can the teaching of German be made beneficial? Actually we have no method, no course. Each teacher, uses his own method, his own book. Cincinnati and St. Louis have solved this problem by having a superintendent for the German instruction.</p>
   <p>Another question is, if the introduction of German in the sixth and seventh grades is to be recommended? The children are too young to benefit by it and the work of the teachers is in vain.</p>
   <p>Also the study of German should be made obligatory, that is, once a student has taken up German, he should be obliged to keep it up.</p>
   <p>We further add a few considerations regarding the teaching of German in three of our city schools: Newberry school, where the population is almost entirely <pb facs="5418474_1_0811.jpg" n="3"/>German, the Haven school where there are few Germans and the Scammon school where the population is evenly divided.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>School</cell>
     <cell>Number of Students</cell>
     <cell>German Parents</cell>
     <cell>Number of Students in first 3 grades learning German.</cell>
     <cell>German Parents</cell>
     <cell>Total Number of pupils in the first 3 grades.</cell>
     <cell>Average Time of Weekly Instruction.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Newberry</cell>
     <cell>297</cell>
     <cell>208</cell>
     <cell>18</cell>
     <cell>15</cell>
     <cell>65</cell>
     <cell>21/2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Scammon</cell>
     <cell>525</cell>
     <cell>175</cell>
     <cell>70</cell>
     <cell>23</cell>
     <cell>85</cell>
     <cell>1 1/2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Haven</cell>
     <cell>292</cell>
     <cell>118</cell>
     <cell>104</cell>
     <cell>40</cell>
     <cell>210</cell>
     <cell>13/4</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>We thus find here two schools in which teachers are supposed to teach once daily three hundred children. In spite of that the results are very satisfactory. The teacher in the Scammon school has 525 students, while the English teacher has never more than sixty students. In the higher grades, in which there are 175 pupils, they have only ninety minutes of German per week.</p>
   <p>We recommend that German become a four year course, starting with the fourth grade.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0812.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>1st Year: Speaking and writing.</p>
   <p>2nd Year: Reading and translating.</p>
   <p>3rd Year: Further reading and translating.</p>
   <p>4th Year: Reading, translating and grammar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
