<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-02">Nov. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Dividing the School Funds.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0844</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0844.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-02">Nov. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DIVIDING THE SCHOOL FUNDS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Republican and "Know-Nothing" newspapers accused the Lutherans as well as the Catholics  in former years, of striving to get a share of the public school fund for their parochial schools.</p>
   <p>This reproach has practically ceased, as far as the Lutherans are concerned, but continues against the Catholics. It is regrettable that, once in a while, a fanatical Catholic will make some irresponsible remarks, which will occasion such gossip. However, single and stupid fanatics are not the authorized representatives of the Catholic citizens of this country. A highly esteemed bishop, respected by non-Catholics for his brilliant mind and his tolerant attitude, undoubtedly has the right to speak for his fellow-believers. Recently the Republican politician, Harding, accused the Catholic bishops of Illinois of wanting a majority in the State Legislature in order to divide the public school fund.</p>
   <p>Bishop Spaulding replied in one of the local newspapers:</p>
   <p>"The Catholic bishops of Illinois are not ignorant blockheads. They know very <pb facs="5418474_1_0845.jpg" n="2"/>well that the State Legislature has no power to divide the public school fund; but they are hoping that a sufficient number of honest and unbiased men will be elected to the State Legislature, to have the unjust and hated Edward Law repealed. This is what we are aiming at, and not  at the dividing of the public school fund.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Harding need not worry about the financial burden, which the Catholics bear, due to the maintenance of our parochial schools. In reality our present arrangement is less expensive, than sending our children to public schools. The taxes would have to be greatly increased for all citizens, and, therefore, for us also, if we sent our children to public schools. The increase of expenditures would correspond with the increase in scholars."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
