<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1900-07-07">July 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">In the Interests of the German Language and Gymnastics (Turnen.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1900-07-07">July 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE INTERESTS OF THE GERMAN LANGUAGE AND GYMNASTICS (TURNEN.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Delegates meeting of the German Association, which met yesterday evening, it was considered essentual, that particular efforts must be used at this time, in order to maintain German instruction. Its program progressed satisfactorily and at a lively pece.</p>
   <p>Five representatives of the "German Alliance" were also present- the latter is a Central Organization, which was called into existence last year, by the same clubs who Consider the present questions and a quorum was nominated and instructed by the delegates to interview the Mayor today. This delegation should submit the resolutions which have been adopted by the assembly to Harrison.</p>
   <p>"In consideration of the systematic curtailment and antipathy which the German language and Turn instruction (Gymnastics) have to contend with, at the hands of the present administration, the Delegate-meeting of German Associations have <pb facs="5418474_1_0436.jpg" n="2"/>adopted the following resolutions.</p>
   <p>" We, desire, not as Chicago citizens of German origin but in the interests of the education of our youth, and the consequent standard of public culture, that, aside from English, the most important language of the present era, is German; it therefore should be protected and cultivated in all its branches.</p>
   <p>"Furthermore, we request in the interests of the physical development of the new generation, that Turn-instructions should be obligatory in all public schools."</p>
   <p>" We hereby declare, that we hold the Mayor Carter H. Harrison responsible for all further curtailment and antipathy which may be displayed to the above two phases of instructions, in consideration of the fact that the mayor has the privilege of appointing the Schoolboard during the tenure of his administration."</p>
   <p>The representatives who called on the mayor were : Mrs. P. Dupre and E. Stowronski also the gentlemen, K. Haerting, F. Nebel, L. Saltiel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
