<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-20">June 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Taxes and the School (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-20">June 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TAXES AND THE SCHOOL (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Budget Director Herbert M. Lord reminds Americans that Federal taxes are relatively lower today than they were ten years ago. This statement is in part true, but is in need of much modification. Actually, the expenditures of the Federal government are three and a half times as great as they were ten years ago. Of the total sum that is obtained by taxation and subsequently spent, the Federal government receives forty per cent, the remaining sixty per cent going to the States, counties, and cities.</p>
   <p>Formerly [i. e., ten years ago] the relation was exactly the opposite. At that time, sixty per cent of the tax receipts went to the Federal government, while the States, counties, and cities had to be content with forty per cent. The Budget Director's statement is to be understood in this sense, namely, <pb facs="5418474_1_0084.jpg" n="2"/>that the Federal government obtains a smaller proportion of the total tax receipts at the present time than it did ten years ago. Actually, the Federal government has just as little reason as the other [i.e., State and municipal] administrative agencies to be proud of its tax policies. In the case of all of them, expenditures have risen in such a manner as to instil grave doubts in the minds of all sober-minded citizens. Our participation in the World War--with all its startling orgies of graft and wasteful spending--is responsible for the high Federal taxes. In the case of the other [i.e., State and municipal] governmental agencies, the growth of expenditures has, of course, different reasons. In most large cities, the unreasonably high disbursements for school purposes constitute one of the main reasons for their financial difficulties. There is scarcely one branch of human activity which is not included as a subject of instruction in the curriculum of a large school system. Young people possessed of an offensive ignorance in elementary subjects are given instruction in psychology, biology, sociology, and all other sciences. They are instructed in technical subjects which ought to be reserved for the university or for practical experience, and <pb facs="5418474_1_0085.jpg" n="3"/>they are let loose upon their fellow humans with a mass of undigested and confusing facts.</p>
   <p>The American school system has developed with a rapidity which is amazing. It must be acknowledged that in the process of this development the American people has displayed a truly astonishing amount of energy and generosity. It is obvious that in the course of this rapid development many weeds are bound to shoot up. The school is now in danger of forgetting its most important purpose, the real aim of its existence. Instead of affording youth a sound and thorough knowledge of the elementary subjects, thus laying the foundation for future professional training, the school endeavors to supply this professional training. This it cannot and should not do. In making the attempt, it becomes untrue to its purpose and does more harm than good.</p>
   <p>No one until now has ventured to raise his voice against this abuse. Our super-educators and those who make a hash of the school always have available <pb facs="5418474_1_0086.jpg" n="4"/>the miserable stock argument that a man who rises in protest against their giddy ideas to make imbeciles of the youth, values his dollars higher than his children. Much abuse has been made of this catch phrase. It is time that the citizens offer resistance to the onslaughts of the school reformers. For even the tax screw cannot continually be tightened, and if the largest part of the tax receipts is spent for school purposes, then there will soon be nothing left for other important purposes. And what is more, the people will get a totally miseducated offspring made of dunces and ne'er-do-wells.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
