<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-03">Feb. 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">School Question a Victory for Germans of Illinois and Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-02-03">Feb. 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL QUESTION A VICTORY FOR GERMANS OF ILLINOIS AND CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The state of Illinois has been liberated from the tyrannical Edwards' law at last! At the state senate, which is composed of 29 Democrats and 22 Republicans, not one voted against its absolute abolition; but quite a few were absent during the roll call. At the legislature, which sonsists of 78 Democrats and 75 Republicans, 120 voted for total abrogation, that is, 76 Democrats and 44 Republicans; 11 reactionary, dyed-in-the-wool Republicans said no; but not a single Democrat was in that category; 22 representatives were absent, 20 Republicans and 2 Democrats.</p>
   <p>After the vote was taken, 26 Republican representatives made a written declaration, that the Edwards law should be superceded by a new compulsory school statute. Therein it is admitted that the bill must provide equality and liberty for the private and parochial schools; that the state shall not dictate any of its courses nor inhibit the teaching of foreign languages.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune, Republican stronghold, admonished its party brethern to avoid any controversy which is designed to restrict privately endowed church schools or other subventioned individual schools, and to give them unrestricted <pb facs="5418474_1_0598.jpg" n="2"/>freedom in their choice of subject matter and languages. There is no doubt, that the present session will produce a new compulsory school law which follows the desirable Wisconsin model. And its acceptance by the governor will be as certain as has been his consent to the death warrant of the Edwards law.</p>
   <p>The cancellation of the Edwards law is in itself a sublime reward for the three years fight, and the labor and effort which the Illinois Germans have put into it. This German school victory in the Senate has its counterpart here in Chicago. Despite the vituperation and storming of our local Know-Nothings and their subservient press against German language instruction in the public schools, our Board of Education has appropriated a larger sum for its continuance and voted unanimously in its favor; furthermore, this council raised no objections against other branches which the ignorant herd tried to ditch, such as gymnastics, etc.</p>
   <p>The above recapitualtion of that glorious double victory is another indisputable proof of what the Germans of this state can accomplish for their own and the public's welfare, if they are awake and united.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
