<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-23">Mar. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">To the New Superintendent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-23">Mar. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE NEW SUPERINTENDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Upon his recent accession to office the new Superintendent of Schools declared that two matters were uppermost in his mind, an increase in the salaries of teachers, and penny lunches for poor school children. In regard to the last point there should be no dissension among the members of the School Board or among our citizens. But actually there is, unfortunately, for in last year's meetings of the Board determined opposition to the well-meant plan was noticeable. If our memory is not in error, the objection was raised that dispensing breakfast to needy school children is an act of charity and might cause them to feel that they are slighted by those children who were more careful in choosing parents. There is no doubt that such feelings could arise. Despite this fact, the feeling might be preferable to actual hunger. As long as our social institutions are of such a nature that we cannot prevent children from coming to school hungry, we should not let overly tender consideration for their feelings <pb facs="5418474_1_0093.jpg" n="2"/>prevent us from appeasing their hunger. If our conscience can endure prevailing conditions which force hunger upon these unfortunate children, it should not be offended by such farfetched doubt and considerations. Penny lunches should be made a permanent institution in our school system, and the necessary money must be gotten somehow, no matter how poor the condition of the School Department's treasury may be.</p>
   <p>Penny lunches deserve preference to the planned regulation of the salaries of teachers, for even though some of the instructors do not receive as much pay as they or the School Board think they are entitled to, yet there is not one teacher in Chicago who must come to school hungry in the morning because he is too poor to buy the food necessary to still his hunger. The question of teachers' salaries is a sore spot and has been the subject of discussions for many years. Public opinion concerning higher salaries for the employees of the school system is divided. Some think that in view of the fact that teachers work only five days a week, enjoy many holidays <pb facs="5418474_1_0094.jpg" n="3"/>and long vacations (the vacations amount to ten weeks of the year), are usually hired while they are very young, become self-supporting at an age when others are still preparing themselves for a profession and are dependent upon the financial aid of their parents or other members of their family, and the treasury of the Department of Schools is at low ebb, school teachers ought to be satisfied with their present salaries. Now it is true that teachers, as well as all other classes of workers, are affected by the prevalent hard times, and for this reason the School Board may not be able to avoid granting a nominal increase in the pay of its employees. But then those who are really in need should receive first consideration. As a rule those who are paid large salaries reap the greatest benefit from such raises in salary. The new Superintendent of Schools should see to it that those who need it most should receive more pay.</p>
   <p>The Superintendent failed to mention another matter which many inhabitants <pb facs="5418474_1_0095.jpg" n="4"/>of our city consider to be his duty, and so it appears to be in order that we refer to it here. For many years the American school child has been instructed almost exclusively by female teachers. We have no intention of denying that the schoolma'am has proved her worth in some instances. But she has not in all instances. It is a pedagogical blunder to have young girls teach boys who are not much younger than the teacher. A female teacher should instruct the pupils of the lower grades. But the instruction of the children in the upper grades of the elementary schools and of high school students should be exclusively in the hands of men. Only men are able to fathom the mind and spirit of those who are entering manhood. Only men can understand and guide the emotions of young men. The pedagogues have long ago agreed on this. In order to obtain the best results from our schools, boys and girls in the upper grades of elementary schools and of high schools should be separated, and the boys should be taught by men, and the girls by ladies. Every real reform of our school system should be made with this point in view. The Superintendent said that he was <pb facs="5418474_1_0096.jpg" n="5"/>contemplating no changes for the present. That is only natural. Before anybody attempts to reform he must become acquainted with the condition of the object of the reformation. But the reform alluded to must be made some day. Why should it not begin in Chicago? The majority of our local citizens would be grateful to Mr. Chadsey if he would begin making these changes in our school system very soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
