<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-09">Mar. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German in the White House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-09">Mar. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN IN THE WHITE HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under these headlines, we find in the Washington Sentinel of Mr. Louis Schade, the following interesting story: While in several Western States big battles have been fought on the question whether the German language should be taught in the public schools, and while just now through the influence of Irish Catholic bishops and priests efforts are being made to prevent the use of the German language in German Catholic churches, it is a noticeable fact that here in Washington the highest social circles study the language of our Fatherland and that most all the prominent ladies of society speak German fluently. That preference for German has even found its way into the White House. The grandchildren of President Harrison, the six year old Benjamin Harrison McKee, better known as Bobby McKee, and his little three year old sister Mary Lodge McKee, speak the German language better than children of the same age among three fourths of German Americans. We had an opportunity last Thursday to convince ourselves, when Miss Hampe the children's governess, in our home where she is at all times a welcome guest, made a farewell visit before the President's <pb facs="5418474_1_0554.jpg" n="2"/>family returned to Indianapolis.</p>
   <p>It was a pleasure to hear the President's grandchildren speak a foreign language as fluently as their own. Little Ben wrote his name in an album, in English and German letters. He is indeed a very promising child. To learn and speak several languages is a science. It is commendable that President Harrison and his family, in spite of the American prejudice against the study of foreign languages, sets an example which puts to shame many of our "know-nothings" and also German Americans, who either through ignorance or from cowardly neglect, don't let their children learn their own language, through which they lose their children's respect and are the cause for the children becoming ashamed of their foreign parents and finally become American know-nothings.</p>
   <p>We consider it, although not sharing Mr. Harrison's politics, as our duty to express our acknowledgment for the way and manner in which he and his family, especially his wife, who passed away not long ago, have fulfilled their <pb facs="5418474_1_0555.jpg" n="3"/>domestic and social duties as long as they resided in the White House. German Americans, in particular, should cherish the memory of the ex-President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
