<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-06">Oct. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Necessity of Higher Education (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-10-06">Oct. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NECESSITY OF HIGHER EDUCATION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We cannot be too emphatic in warning our people of the importance of not neglecting the physical and mental education of our youth during wartime. This danger is closer at hand than many realize. We already have newspaper reports that here and there schools have had to close, especially country schools, because no teachers could be found. This lack of teachers is due not only to the fact that quite a number of then have joined the colors, to do their duty as citizens, but also to the low salary which is frequently offered them. In times like the present, when wages and salaries almost everywhere have been boosted quite considerably, when the costs of living are steadily increasing, when the demand for workers of all kinds, even white-collar workers, almost exceeds the supply, a meagerly paid position as schoolteacher in some godforsaken spot does not look very attractive. This situation should be remedied at once. where the communities are too poor to bear the expenses of school instruction for their children, country and state must contribute to it. After a closer study of the situation it <pb facs="5418474_1_0103.jpg" n="2"/>will be found that in many cases such a subsidy would hardly be necessary. Many communities will easily be able to set aside a larger amount for school purposes than they have in the past. The matter just has to be made clear to them. In some remote and lonely regions of the country, farmers do not consider an extensive training for their children essential. They themselves have never enjoyed it and, conservative as country people are as a rule, they do not think that their children should learn more than they did. Besides, growing children of both sexes are a valuable aid on the farm, and their working power will not so willingly be given up for school purposes.</p>
   <p>Wherever attitudes like this prevail, they must be corrected in time. Our nation has to see to it that the next generation absorbs more knowledge than the previous one. After the conclusion of the war--and sooner or later it will be concluded--we will be faced with the very important job of reconstruction, an adjustment to peacetime conditions and a revolution in world trade. America, as one of the nations with a large population, possessing a huge territory with a wealth of untapped resources, will in the future play a <pb facs="5418474_1_0104.jpg" n="3"/>leading cultural role. It is the duty of our people to prepare themselves for that time. Therefore all communities, counties, and states should extend their school systems instead of being slack, as many of them are now, and neglecting the training of their youth. All young people, if they can manage, should remain in school until they have completed their sixteenth year and even longer, if possible, in order to obtain a better and more thorough education. After they have finished elementary school they should attend high school. In high school the mental horizon is broadened far more than is possible in a grade school, since in high school subjects are treated for which children of a more youthful age would lack the necessary understanding.</p>
   <p>For no part of our population is the acquisition of knowledge more important than for the inhabitants of villages, small towns, and the open country, in other words, the farm population. Times have changed tremendously. So have standards. In former times it was sufficient if a farmer could manage to read and write and knew the multiplication table. Today different conditions prevail.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0105.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The railroad and the automobile have brought even the most remote farm homestead closer to the great metropolitan centers. Consequently the mental and physical needs of the farmers have increased. They take a much greater interest in the affairs of the world than years ago. Furthermore, the successful management of a modern farm requires more and different knowledge than it did a generation ago. A farmer who wants to make his land yield enough today to meet competition successfully, must be able to test the composition of his soil, to judge what kind of fertilizer is required; he must know plants and farm animals, and know under what conditions they thrive and how to prevent them from becoming diseased; how to reap his harvest quickly and economically, how to sell his products at a profit; he must have some knowledge, at least, of how to operate and repair machinery; he must know bookkeeping and financing, some principles of hygiene, and many other things on which his success as a farmer, the welfare of his family, and their contentment more or less depend. But all this knowledge does not come by itself. It has to be acquired. Some of it may be gained by experience even outside of school, <pb facs="5418474_1_0106.jpg" n="5"/>though usually at great expense. But it can be learned more easily, quicker, and more thoroughly while one is young and is with others who have the same goal in mind. The older farmers, therefore, are pursuing a policy of false economy if they try to cut school expenses. Money spent for good schools is one of the best capital investments one can think of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
