<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-11-19">November 19, 1904</date><title level="a">German Editorial on Sports. They have a tendency to be silly.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-11-19">November 19, 1904</date><title level="a">German Editorial on Sports. They have a tendency to be silly.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Jere Delaney, trainer of football players at Northwestern University, declares that the student players suffer from an ailment which is akin to softening of the brain, which manifests itself in the victim in peculiar and often ridiculous actions. "It is known", says Delaney, "that every football player re-experiences his fights in his dreams, but only those who are in intimate daily contact with these ball players know, that they are absorbed during their waking moments by constant day-dreaming</p>
   <p>The trainer considered the matter seriously and declared that, during the training period, his chief difficulty consists in preventing this day-dreaming and lack of concentration. He has found no reliable remedy, nor does he know of a satisfactory diagnosis whereby he can identify the ailment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Only pious simplicity or the simplicity which we sometimes circumvent by calling it stupidity, could induce Mr. Delaney to make such assertions. After all, he is a professional coach of such ball players and, when making such declarations, does he not saw off the limb on which he sits?</p>
   <p>According to this judge, the student-football-hero is, what is termed as "somewhat balmy" The public has suspected it for a long time, and believed to have an explanation for it, which in the mean, coincides with Mr. Delaney's ideas: This training which constantly absorbs the student's mind and concentrates it on the one subject, the game, may well be the most culpable factor but the knocks and punches help on their part, and, a certain susceptibility to foolishness must be presupposed among such students who sacrifice three months yearly, during the prine of their life, to obtain proficiency in a brutal combat. Maybe <pb facs="5418474_1_0140.jpg" n="3"/>an ancestral trait must also be considered, since thse young men are seldom financially independent, it is evident that their parents must give their "Yes" and "Amen" to it, which shows their mentality to be of a similar caliber.</p>
   <p>We are living in an age of realization and wonders. This claim has often been made and much proof has been submitted to substatiate it. It would be the greatest miracle if the Professors and university presidents would recognize the truth about football. But that time is still remote.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
