<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-11">Oct. 11, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Lutheran Commercial High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-11">Oct. 11, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">LUTHERAN COMMERCIAL HIGH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lutherans of Chicago intend to erect a large Commercial High School and expect to collect for this purpose $50,000 within a short time. Under the leadership of the Concordia League, $12,000 has already been raised. The course at the Commercial High School will follow immediately the course of the Elementary School. Just at this age a large number of Lutheran children become estranged from their church and to keep them in steady touch with their church is the main purpose of the institution that will, besides the subjects of a Commercial High School, also take up Religion in its course of instruction. The new school shall be opened in the business district and shall be large enough to give admittance to several hundred young people of both sexes.</p>
   <p>The Concordia League which fosters the plan consists of representatives of every Lutheran parish in Chicago. It has nominated a Committee to devise plans for the enterprise and it received offers for financial aid from many <pb facs="5418474_1_0865.jpg" n="2"/>other churches. The plan is unique as most of the institutions that are supported by religious societies prepare their pupils only for intellectual professions. Later on it is expected that a manual labor institution will be added.</p>
   <p>As soon as the necessary $50,000 are signed up, a meeting of representatives of the Lutheran clergy and laymen will be called to execute the plan of the chief sponsors of which are Alderman Albert W. Beilfuss, Julius H. Geweke, and Robert Schoenfeld.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
