<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-29">Sept. 29, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The Public Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-29">Sept. 29, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turn community opened its winter season, last night, at the north side Turner Hall. As the program promised to be one of interest to teachers, the audience was composed largely of teachers. Turner Max Stern acting as chairman introduced Charles Bary as first speaker. Mr. Bary is well known for the excellent services he has rendered us on the normal school question, and the retention of its director, Mr. Parker. Mr. Bary, American born, chose for his subject "Our public schools" using splendid German. After a short historic sketch about the development of the American public educational system, and a humorous remark about the now abolished system of memorizing, he devoted his speech to comparisons between the public school system of America and that of Germany. Of course the comparison showed that the German system is much more effective and Mr. Bary closed his address with the recommendation to cultivate the German educational system. This was followed by a play, "A scene in a Berlin police court" played by four members of the dramatic school. The next number on the program consisted of a debate concerning the question: "Would education be benefited by exclusive employment of male teachers in public schools?". <pb facs="5418474_1_0234.jpg" n="2"/>The chairman's invitation for a general participation in the debate did not find any response, therefore, Mr. Bary was approached again with the request to give his opinion on this subject. He paid tribute to women's kind and beneficial influence upon the heart and soul of the child, therefore, prefers a female teacher for the elementary school and male teachers for the more advanced pupils, and he also endorsed Frobel's educational system.</p>
   <p>Turner Neinrich Suder contended, that the disrespect shown to our women teachers is the result of the home atmosphere of the pupil, and caused an outburst of applause when he praised the well mannered boy who, when meeting him would salute him properly and simultaneously remove his hat; but what disrespect was shown by a boy just saying "Hallo Suder". It was a very animated evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
