<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-06-17">June 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">German Instruction in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-06-17">June 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN INSTRUCTION IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Martin Schmidhofer, the eminent pedagogue and superintendent of its German schools in Chicago, supplied valuable and interesting statistical facts referring to the participation of German instruction in the Chicago schools.</p>
   <p>We learn that the number of children who are attending German schools are steadily increasing every year. In the year 1912, in 53 schools there were 7,806 children; in 1913, in 83 schools, 13,507; in 1914, in 103 schools, 17,001; and in 1915, in 112 schools, 18,140 children.</p>
   <p>The increase of the number of children studying German is very gratifying, yet the statistical data of Mr. Schmidhofer form an injurious reflection upon the Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even if all the 18,140 children studying German were of German descent, in proportion to the large German population of Chicago, it nevertheless is a disgraceful trifling number; we see that even this number of German children form only a small percentage.</p>
   <p>While 11,557 children of non-German parents are participating in German instructions, only 6,603 children of German parents hear German sounds in schools.</p>
   <p>The German parents, who, without sacrifice can afford to have their children take German instruction, but are unwilling to do so, not only commit a crime against their children, but are also unfair to the German cause.</p>
   <p>We have to thank such Germans for the prejudice and hate with which we are surrounded.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0374.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The courageous fight of the individual for German truth, can be of no avail when German parents refuse to have their children grow up as future representatives of the German cause.</p>
   <p>With love and understanding only such person can represent the German cause who masters the German language, and through mastery of the same, can penetrate into the German cause.</p>
   <p>We shall hope that in the next school year, all German children will attend German instructions, taught by excellent and efficient teachers.</p>
   <p>The future of Germanism in America depends on our children; every mother who neglects to send her child to a German school helps to doom Germanism in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
