<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-07-08">July 8, 1886</date><title level="a">The National German-American School Association.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-07-08">July 8, 1886</date><title level="a">THE NATIONAL GERMAN-AMERICAN SCHOOL ASSOCIATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The National German-American School Association was founded June 11th, 1885, according to the annual report, received yesterday from President Hermann Schuricht of the branch organization in Chicago. Starting out with thirty members, this branch group took over for one year the supervision of local groups to be organized all over the country. All incoming money was used for propaganda, which aimed to arouse the Germans of America for the preservation of their mother tongue. In order to make this propaganda more effective the Chicago branch group published a journal, the "Correspondenzblatt" which appeared every three months and contributed considerably to spread the aspirations of the young organization. The constitution, adopted by the N. G. A. S. A. is similar to the one used by the General German School Association (Allgemeiner Deutscher Schulverein) in Germany. The German-American Teachers' Association and the German-American Authors' and Journalists' Convention are doing their utmost to further the gigantic enterprise, which will carry German instruction to all parts of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So far branch groups have been established in Milwaukee Wisconsin; Grand Rapids, Michigan; Indianapolis, Indiana; Cincinnati, Ohio; Dayton, Ohio; Alameda, California. Other branch organizations will follow soon in Evansville, Indiana; New Orleans, Louisiana; New York City; San Francisco and Oakland California; Richmond, Virginia; Baltimore, Maryland and Schenectady, N. Y.</p>
   <p>The Chicago branch group is planning the opening of a German kindergarten which would be the first establishment of its kind in Chicago, and has been sponsored particularly by the Illinois Staats-Zeitung and Freie Presse. The German kindergarten will help probably more than the school itself, to interest the youngsters successfully at a tender age in German.</p>
   <p>According to the rules of the organization's constitution, the first convention of the N. G. A. S. A. will be on June 19th and June 20th. The necessary arrangements to receive and house the expected delegates, will be made in time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
