<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-11-06">November 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Hold to your acquirements, (part of Editorial).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-11-06">November 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Hold to your acquirements, (part of Editorial).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a year ago the Germans of Illinois and the neighboring Wisconsin had to fight for a right, that should be evident, namely the right to let their children be instructed in the German language at their own expense. The nativistic impudence went so far, that they wanted to exterminate the German language entirely even in church and private schools for which the government did not contribute a single penny.</p>
   <p>When the German citizens frustrated this plot, they were again offended from another angle. Under the transparent pretext of releasing the public instruction of all "fads", the nativists demanded the removal of that little German instruction that was given in public schools. This time they were partly successful - chiefly because some of the Germans assisted them for the reasons of "abstract justice". This half victory gave them courage to make a test to subdue the German influence entirely. With the assistance of the German voters themselves they hope to succeed with a triumph for genuine Americanism over the "foreigners". Germans shall help them to elect Judge Gary and to humiliate Governor Altgeld.</p>
   <p>Exactly the same newspapers that recommend the extermination of the German language by force, stand up for the candidacy of Gary. Some of them are "candid" <pb facs="5418474_1_0491.jpg" n="2"/>enough to picture this man as the embodiment of all that they like to call genuine American..... ...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
