<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-04-28">Apr, 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">To Restore German.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-04-28">Apr, 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TO RESTORE GERMAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If School Inspector Halle is to be believed the victory of the anti-faddist at the Board of Education meeting Wednesday night is only temporary. He said to them: "Mayor Harrison will appoint members on this board next July who will vote to put back German in the primary grades. We have had our Waterloo. Yours is coming."</p>
   <p>Mr. Halle was somewhat excited, but be probably spoke from the book. He supported Mr. Harrison during the recent campaign. It was reported at the time that Mr. Harrison made him some pledges in reference to German. Since the election Mr. Halle, Max Stern, and Richard Michaelis have assured the German teachers in the schools that German would be maintained to the same extent in the schools as in the past. One of the three has some to the extent of saying that Mayor Harrison will not appoint any member of the Board of Education not satisfactory to the committee of three - meaning Michaelis, Halle and Stern.</p>
   <p>It is certain that the two of the three gentlemen named, Stern and Halle, interviewed of M. J. Keane last Sunday or Monday, and that Keane's name had not been sent to the Council until they had conferred with Mayor Harrison about it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Keane changed his views between Saturday and Monday, too, and was introduced in the School Boards Wednesday evening by Mr. Halle, and he voted under the direction of Halle every time.</p>
   <p>But it is not so certain that German will be restored so its old place. There were only seven members to defend the study Weddnesday. There were eleven against. Inspector Rosenthal who are absent on account of the illness of his child, would have voted with the eleven had he been present. Inspector Brennan, who was absent, might have voted with the seven, but he would have done so most reluctantly. He will hardly vote to restore the study.</p>
   <p>Messrs, Trude, Cusack and Duggan are disposed to think that the action of Wednesday resulted in a fair compromise. They are willing to let the matter stand. There are those who say Mr. Keane voted against his own convictions Wednesday to please Mayor Harrison. Would be do so again and restore the study?</p>
   <p>The members who retire in July are Messrs. McLaren, Cameron, Sunderson, Halle, Goetz, Breman and Keane. The first three named voted to oust German from the primary grade. Two of the three, McLaren and Cameron, are certain to be <pb facs="5418474_1_0520.jpg" n="3"/>re-appointed by the Mayor. It is not to certain that all the faddists will be named.</p>
   <p>Unless Mayor Harrison makes a special effort German will not be restored in the primary grades. It is believed by some that when Halle, Baldenwerk and Bluthardt calm down they will decide to let the matter rest. As to the other fads the report is almost certain to be adopted in an improved form. Clay modeling and sewing will be wholly abolished....</p>
   <p>It is intimated that the German members of the board are disposed to think that the disfavor in which the German language is held in the schools is due to the German Superintendent, Zimmerman, and that there will be an effort to remove him. The German press treats Mr. Zimmerman rather coldly.</p>
   <p>A member of the School Board, however, said: "Zimmerman is not to blame. German is the stepchild of the schools. Everybody takes a kick at it. It is impossible to teach with efficiency as 50 per cent of the class teachers are hostile to it."</p>
   <p>Mayor Harrison said: "I don't want to talk on that subject now. I have other <pb facs="5418474_1_0521.jpg" n="4"/>work to do."Subsequently he delivered a discourse on the subject, but nobody could make out exactly where he stood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
