<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-10-12">Oct. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Deterioration of the German School Instruction.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-10-12">Oct. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial.</title><title level="a" type="sub">THE DETERIORATION OF THE GERMAN SCHOOL INSTRUCTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It sounds unbelievable, but it is true. In spite of the external pressure exerted by the reawakened German race conscience which will induce every German mother to attempt to inculcate into their children the love for German sounds, and with it the desire for German school instruction. This attempt was not successful and although fourteen more schools were won for German instruction, the number of pupils has decreased. Mr. Martin Schmidthofer, this indefatigable superintendent of the German school instruction, prepared a clear compilation of German school attendance during the last four semesters, and has submitted same to us. According to this statement, 17,994 children partook in February 1915, 18,732 in September of the same year, and 20,776 in February of this year in German instruction. At the beginning of this semester, in spite of the opening of fourteen more schools, only 20,470 children reported for German instruction. In his touching optimism, Mr. Schmidthofer attributes this retrogression more to the illness of the children than to the lack of enthusiasm for the German cause. We are not in a position to share this optimism, the less because children's illness in Chicago happily did not <pb facs="5418474_1_0361.jpg" n="2"/>occur in such a large measure, as to influence the school instruction, and because the general attendance has not suffered such detrimental influence. More easily can we assume, that the children did not get special encouragement to participate in the German instruction in schools. This lack of encouragement in the school should be balanced through stimulation in the parental home. And only if the latter does not happen, occurs the lessening of school attendance and for this only the German parents and they alone must be held responsible. We have repeatedly pointed out in this place, that the acquisition of the German language is indispensable to the children not only for sentimental reasons. To penetrate into the German character, makes the growing youth more thorough, and therefore more vital. It helps him overcome many obstacles, upon which the Anglo-American bruised himself. German parents should appreciate this, and act accordingly. But not the whip of the newspapers, but their own conviction and an inner feeling ought to awaken them to that perception.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
