<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-01">September 1, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting on the Northwest Side.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0979</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0979.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-01">September 1, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING ON THE NORTHWEST SIDE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialists of the Northwest- side held their regular meeting last night at Nutzhorn's Hall. Comrade Pollmacher was the first speaker of the evening and pointed out, that the 31st of August was the anniversary of the death of Ferdinand Lasalle, one of the greatest combatants for the cause of humanity. At the close of his speech, all those present honored Lassalle's memory with a Hoch for the dead leader and thinker.</p>
   <p>Comrade August Spies followed Pollmacher on the speaker's platform. His subject was: "The Temperance Question". He spoke of the Puritan history and pointed out the source of the original Temperance movement and of the obsteniousness of the Church, which later on was added to its dozmas, and how one of the measures adopted by the administrators of the former English colonies became one of the corner stones of the Puritan Church.</p>
   <p>He spoke then on Temperance at the present day, saying, that it should not be for Socialists to decide whether the effects from alcoholic beverages were good or not. The question is one of principle. If we were to allow the majority to dictate <pb facs="5418474_1_0980.jpg" n="2"/>to the minority what they should drink, tomorrow or the day after they would claim the right to dictate what they should think. Religious fanaticism would have a free rein, and an initial success would only spur it on to greater demands. Religious freedom would soon be ended; one coercive law would follow the other, etc.</p>
   <p>A resolution was accepted, in which the reactionary agitation for temperance and bigotry were condemned, and vows made for a fight against the fanatics and enemies of freedom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
