<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-04-18">April 18th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The Compulsory School Law.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-04-18">April 18th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The Compulsory School Law.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>175 Representatives of the 35 Evangelic Lutheran Parishes of Chicago and vicinity, divisions of the Missouri, Synod met on the evening of April 14th, in the school of the Evang. Lutheran Immanuels Gemeinde to consider how the above law may be fought most advantageously. Mr. T. C. Diener led, as chairman, Mr. H. Ruhland functioned as secretary. A declaration by Pastor Hoelter, his motion was accepted. Its text in general follows: the members of these districts are antagonistically inclined towards a sensible compulsory school law. They are not opposed to Public Schools; on the contrary, the state would be delinquent in its duty, if it failed to give the growing youth an opportunity to study the elementary subjects. They do not object to the teaching of the English language but they very energetically reject the various provisions of the present compulsory law which curtails parental, personal and religious rights in a deplorable manner, and it subjects all private schools to such state-control, that their continued existence becomes doubtful. It is unfortunate that the necessity has arisen, which compels citizens to obtain their legal rights by political intervention. What has this law achieved? Parents were convicted as criminals, because they entrusted their children to schools, built and financed from their own resources, in which nothing is taught that conflicts with the state. They must, therefore resort to votes, if no amendments will be made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
