<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">German in Our Public Schools (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-09">Feb. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN IN OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The admonition to all parents to register their children in the German classes of our public schools, brought gratifying results. As soon as we receive definite reports about the general enrollment, we shall publish all details and statistics on the subject. We hope to show a substantial increase. By rights, our Chicago Germanism should bring about the inclusion of German in all our public schools. So far, about one half of our institutions of learning have adopted the subject. There are enough Germans attending to justify teaching it universally<pb facs="5418474_1_0363.jpg" n="2"/>but it depends on the parents who should consider it their duty to reach this goal.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that the attitudes of many principals and teachers are hostile and that they do all within their power to create difficulties. The Abendpost has received numerous complaints about teachers who dissuade the pupils, and in some cases even intimidate them, whereupon the parents, fearing reprisals, refrain from pressing their legal rights. The majority of the teaching personnel, however, is not opposed to it. That they show no particular interest in it, is attributable to indifference rather than animosity, <pb facs="5418474_1_0364.jpg" n="3"/>but this will disappear when the superintendents and teachers note the growing interest of the younger generation. This experience has come to light in several schools. Constant, active cooperation, personal visits to the principals and teachers, prompt inquiries if the questionnaire fails to arrive at the bi-annual period, will do much to arouse the lagging interest.</p>
   <p>However, when parents discover an open or clandestine hostility towards the subject, or its inclusion in a certain school, it is then advisable to bring it to the attention of the school board who will remind such anti-German pedagogues about their foremost duties to the <pb facs="5418474_1_0365.jpg" n="4"/>taxpayers. Only a few days ago, such a case came to our attention. The principal, a woman promptly built barriers when an application to teach German was presented. The request was then submitted to the school board. The first day the announcement was posted, more than one hundred students wished to learn German. Regardless of the principal's preliminary objections, German instruction has now found a place in her school.</p>
   <p>Last year, 126 public schools taught German. In these schools, four had more than 400 students each in the German classes; eight over 300; nineteen, from 200 to 300; forty-nine, from 100 to 200; and others, from 50 to 100. The number of schools teaching German can <pb facs="5418474_1_0366.jpg" n="5"/>be greatly increased if our Germanity is energetic. This casual indifference is by no means restricted to the teaching profession, it is quite obvious, unfortunately, in many German families who possess a lanquid attitude that is inclined to evade all disagreeableness. Persons such as these have relinquished the German spirit. Germanism now faces one half of the world in war, and the German-Americans here owe it to their brethren abroad to defend themselves against dissenters, just as their compatriots are holding their own accross the sea.</p>
   <p>In Europe our countrymen are fighting with deathly weapons to maintain Germanism, while we have been spared from such an ordeal. Therefore, it is our duty here at the outposts to disseminate German ideals, morals, and customs, and above all to defend our language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
