<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-24">Dec. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Serious</title><title level="a" type="sub">Instruction in German, Drawing, and Singing Abolished in the Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-24">Dec. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SERIOUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Instruction in German, Drawing, and Singing Abolished in the Public Schools</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of education announced yesterday that German, drawing, and singing will be discontinued in the public schools after July 1, 1880, because the budget estimate for the city's fiscal year provided funds to pay the teachers of the special branches for the current year only. The opponents of the special branches, particularly the German language, capitalized on the absence of John C. Richberg, succeeded in influencing a few members who formerly were liberal-minded, and so connived to exclude the subjects. The vote taken by the board will surprise many of our citizens. That Stone would make such a motion and vote against the special branches was to be expected, since Stone was always vehemently and stubbornly opposed to the teaching of the German language--however, this was his honest conviction; and one could also imagine that English would gladly concur in a motion which the latter was too cowardly to make of his own accord because of political expediency, nor <pb facs="5418474_1_0706.jpg" n="2"/>would Stiles's friends be surprised because they knew his attitude: A man who considered himself broad-minded, a philosopher, but who was at heart a dense and ignorant man. As to Keith and Frake, one could not look for anything else, but Delaney proved an element of surprise, because, prior to his appointment, he favored definitely the teaching of German in the public schools.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, besides Richberg, Armstrong, Brenan, and Stensland were also absent. How the last might have regarded the question would, of course be problematical, but being a foreigner he should have a liberal view--in other words, subscribe to the belief that education should not be limited to mere learning or babbling by heart, nor of teaching only the most elementary subjects. His vote would have been the deciding factor, because Richberg, Brenan, and Armstrong were in favor of the special branches.</p>
   <p>But it is useless to cry over spilled milk. The question now is, what to do about it? The best policy would be that Messrs. Richberg, Frankenthal, and Vocke call a special session to reconsider the matter. If that cannot be <pb facs="5418474_1_0707.jpg" n="3"/>done, recourse must be taken to the city council to make an appropriation to provide sufficient money to pay the teachers, and the final disposition of the case would rest with the board of education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
