<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-12">Feb. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Condemns Cabarets; Says They Are the Most Obnoxious Institutions of the City and Should Be Suppressed</title><title level="a" type="sub">Witness before City Liquor Commission Asks for Higher Tax on Beer Trucks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-12">Feb. 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CONDEMNS CABARETS; SAYS THEY ARE THE MOST OBNOXIOUS INSTITUTIONS OF THE CITY AND SHOULD BE SUPPRESSED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Witness before City Liquor Commission Asks For Higher Tax on Beer Trucks</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A higher license for beer wagons, discontinuation of liquor sales in drug stores and other places, as well as the elimination of cabarets, were advocated yesterday by G. H. Wischmann, representative of a wholesale liquor supply house and legal luminary, who has passed the bar examination. The gentleman testified before the City Commission on intoxicating beverages and gave the most damning verdict on cabarets ever heard of in the City Hall. He advocated a merciless subjugation, since these places not only undermine the social structure but also are the cause of the feminine downfall, as far as the younger generation is concerned. The supposition that the morals of young girls are definitely shaken by indulging in distillery brands of various kinds, was particularly <pb facs="5418474_1_0941.jpg" n="2"/>emphasized by Wischmann. He declared that the cabaret, with its false intriguing splendor, intoxicates the female of the specie just as much if not more so, as the spirituous liquids.</p>
   <p>The cabaret, declared Wischmann with profound conviction, is the most nauseating and dangerous institution of our modern era. A young girl not only imbibes to the point of inebriation during these cabaret performances, but becomes even vastly more befuddled by the false glitter and gloss of her environment. Thereafter a man may proceed with her as he pleases. The cabarets do not even have a semblance of respectability. They should be abolished. They do not benefit a community. It is the most detestable and degrading proposition we have to deal with today, and never should have been permitted to exist in our city. Cabarets should not serve alcoholic drinks and saloons ought to refrain from giving such stage performances. The cabarets ruin respectable places, make decent diversions obsolete, damage our clubs, and undermine social conduct.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0942.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Other reforms which Wischmann recommended would prohibit the sale of alcoholic beverages in drug stores and other unrelated mercantile establishments. He declared more whiskey is consumed in Chicago today than at any prior period. The City Council should draft an ordinance making it unlawful to exhibit liquor bottles in show windows. Then women will not be tempted to buy highly ornate packages of cellar brew mixtures. According to Wischmann's opinion, every beer wagon should pay a $1,000 license, since it is a saloon on wheels.</p>
   <p>John W. Maskell, a saloon keeper, objected. He said that Mrs. Potter Palmer, a leader of Chicago society, controls the Palmer House, where liquor is sold, and that about 75% of the profits accrue to her. Ettelson, City Corporation Counsel, defended the cabarets, saying there are good and bad among them. He was highly opposed to their critics, claiming that objectionable cabarets should be brought to the attention of the Mayor. This virulence against all of them gives the city a bad reputation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
