<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-09">July 9, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">School Work Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-09">July 9, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL WORK EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A highly interesting exhibition of school work at the "Fair" building amazes the friends of our educational system. In this exhibition are included all kinds of school work, the product of school education from different parts of the country under the auspices of the "National Educational Association". The Illinois exhibition is of course the largest one, representing sixteen counties and many local schools. All the states, with hardly any exception, are represented by some form of their educational school system. Five schools of skilled trades are represented. They are Chicago, Terre Haute, Omaha, Toledo and Colorado Springs. This section of the exhibit is under the direction of W. N. Beifield, Superintendent of the school of skilled trades in Chicago. This section includes also the mechanical work from the university schools of Illinois and of the Polytechnical Institute of Terre Haute, Indiana of which Mr. Beifield is an instructor. Although this section of the exhibit is most interesting, the exhibit of the Kindergarten work under the direction of that brilliant German pedagogue, W. N. Hailmann of Lacrosse, Indiana is no less interesting. It fills one with pride and admiration realizing that Frohbel's teaching fell on such good soil as this our country, with the result of bearing beautiful fruit. The Cook County Normal school exhibit under the personal direction of its manager, Mr. <pb facs="5418474_1_0236.jpg" n="2"/>Parker, gives us a clear inside story of the excellent teaching method of this schoolmaster who is one of great worth. This exhibition contains the work from the kindergarten through high school. In the art department are also exhibits from different county schools, among which we find many drawings, pencil sketches, etc., and even oil paintings. In these rooms are also represented the Chicago Art Institute, St. Mary's school of Dayton, Ohio, the Institute for the Blind in Wisconsin; this one being known, especially for the hand work of its occupants. Our neighbor city, Lake View, is also represented by a lovely exhibition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
