<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-17">Jan. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Session of the School Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0777</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0777.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-17">Jan. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SESSION OF THE SCHOOL BOARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special session of the School Board was held yesterday; Mr. Wells presided. The following gentlemen were also present: Messrs. Hoyne, English, Jacobs, Pruessing, Stone, [Wilhelm] Vocke, Brennan, Bartlett, and Frankenthal.</p>
   <p>Several unimportant matters were settled. Mr. Pruessing told the meeting that there are 2,140 students of the German language among the pupils of both sexes.</p>
   <p>Bartlett made a motion that the estimates of various committees for special teachers be accepted; special instructors for deaf-mutes were included in these estimates.</p>
   <p>Stone made a motion to eliminate an appropriation for $1,500--the amount <pb facs="5418474_1_0778.jpg" n="2"/>required to pay the salary of a special teacher of the German language. Experience has shown that including German in the school curriculum is a mistake. In 1865 the School Board decided to give instruction in German a trial at the Washington School. At that time the German class contained one hundred and fifteen pupils; now the class has decreased to fifty-six pupils. And this is true of the progress of the German language in all schools. In the twelve largest schools, ten years ago, 3,065 children were studying the German language; today these classes have an enrollment of about 1,108.</p>
   <p>The speaker then read a part of an article (which he had written) which appeared in the Daily News about a year ago. In this article German instruction is regarded as superfluous, expensive, and useless. In his article stone concluded that the Germans themselves prefer that the subject be dropped in the schools, because they realize that money spent on this language is wasted.</p>
   <p>Bartlett called attention to the fact that Stone's remarks were out of order <pb facs="5418474_1_0779.jpg" n="3"/>and that only the sanction of the motion could be considered.</p>
   <p>Vocke took up the cudgel in behalf of German and said that Mr. Stone could hardly prove his assertions. He said that the German taxpayers, without exception, want their children to learn the German language; he said that he, himself would teach German to his children--or have them taught--because knowledge of another language besides one's native tongue is desirable and advantageous. A general education requires that one be familiar with at least two languages, to provide a comparison by which one may acquire an adequate understanding of expressions. The speaker then cited the importance of studying German and showed the necessity of studying this language in conjunction with English.</p>
   <p>The limited success of the teaching of the German language in Chicago can only be blamed upon the restrictions which were placed on the School Board committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0780.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If Vocke's proposals had been accepted, better results would soon have been apparent.</p>
   <p>Pruessing then added that Mr. Stone had made no reference to the children who study German in the elementary schools. The number of these students is also reduced, because the School Board passed a resolution that German shall not be taught at a public school unless one hundred and fifty parents request this subject by petition.</p>
   <p>English, offering a substitute measure for Stone's motion, asked that all appropriations for German instruction, drawing, and music be dropped; he added that it is necessary to provide a general education before spending money for special branches.</p>
   <p>Jacobs expressed similar views.....A vote killed the substitute measure of English.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0781.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Stone's motion was then voted upon, and the motion was defeated seven--Hoyne, English, Pruessing, Vocke, Bartlett, Frankenthal and President Wells--to two--Jacobs and Stone.</p>
   <p>Thereafter.....bickering followed on the subject of appropriations for special branches...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
