<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Disastrous Influence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE DISASTROUS INFLUENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The greater the failure of the prohibition fanatics to procure the necessary petition signatures, the more questionable becomes their influence. Although Chicago has a voting list of 450,000 eligible voters, the prohibitionists failed to procure more than 30,000 signatures, according to their own statement (probably less), which hardly represents one fifteenth of the voting population. When secrecy was promised to them, many persons signed the document against their own conviction, succumbing either to the wishes of a charming friend of the weaker sex, or for business reasons. Since the publication of the signed petition became a possibility, no person attaches his signature to the document first as an obliging friend. Consequently, the real strength of the "movement" had to be revealed. Considering that only one out of every fifteen voters favors the legalized and highly taxed liquor business against the illegal liquor trade, it is indeed astonishing that the fearless press of the world does not take a stronger stand against this constant minority movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0948.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the small success of these fanatics is of no consequence, they do some harm nevertheless. There is no doubt that any worthy reform movement would receive much more support if the quotation marks of the reformers would not always assure themselves so prominently. That is a condition found in every large city throughout the United States. Furthermore, it is a well-known fact that reform imposers are undiscriminately men of no scruples who would give their support to any politician of their particular fancy. It is not at all unusual that the liberals are forced to support a candidate not exactly to their liking. Thus the divided liberal votes could in this instance be decisive in the success of the prohibitionists.</p>
   <p>The Pharisees, the self-appointed guardians of the inner voice of their fellow citizens, play an important part in the continuation of the undesirable conditions in this city's administration, irrespective of their awareness of the fact. Deception and prohibition lies spread by these fanatics are great aids for corruption and lawlessness, especially in rural districts. Nothing reflects so much upon the character of the American Nation as prohibition does; not even the greed for money equals this danger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
