<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-07">Apr. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Fight with the Superintendent of Schools (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-07">Apr. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIGHT WITH THE SUPERINTENDENT OF SCHOOLS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the first moves of the reinstated powers of the City Council was to challenge the new School Superintendent, who took office only three weeks ago. The "lords" may regard this as an act of great political prudence. Others will earnestly regret that Chicago's schools are influenced by politics. The technical sophistries which are offered in defense of the City Treasurer's malicious tactics toward the highest official of the school system must be censored by thinking people. How can he be held responsible for the quarrel between the Administration and the School Board? If it is absolutely necessary that the two squabble, then they should do it among themselves, and not quarrel with other people who are doing nothing but their duty. Only the Superintendent has conducted himself as a gentleman in this matter; he has refused to accept the challenge, or even to talk about it.</p>
   <p>The State Legislature has recognized the authority of the present School Board.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Mayor's attempt to force upon our citizens by police power a School Board which their representatives did not want, was branded by a judge as illegal procedure. On the basis of this decision the old legitimate Board unquestionably had the right to declare all resolutions passed by the usurpers null and void, especially the appropriations made by the illegally-appointed Board, including salaries which were paid. This was not done generally. The legitimate Board contented itself with the restoration of the officers deposed by the pseudo Board to their former positions. The powers who make up the Council prefer a different prodedure: political hedging. In order to make life miserable for, and force resignation upon the man whom they put in office, but who has incurred their displeasure--they can no longer have him ejected from office by a police lieutenant--they are placing all manner of obstacles in his way. Such conduct is contemptible; it does not benefit, but does greatly harm Chicago's schools.</p>
   <p>The Mayor has declared his intention of again sponsoring the candidacy of the "Solid Six" for vacancies on the Board. That, of course, is his privilege, and should the "Solid Six" be approved by the Council, which has just been invigorated <pb facs="5418474_1_0091.jpg" n="3"/>with new blood, then that new Board, in which the "Solid Six" would again constitute a majority, would be the legitimate one. For the present, however, the old Board is the legitimate one; and since it is their duty to provide a superintendent for the school system, and there is nothing in the statutes that deprives the School Board of authority during the closing period of its tenure, Superintendent Chadsey is the duly-chosen head of Chicago's schools, as far as the system is concerned. That fact cannot be disputed, despite the subtlety of the City Council; if it is opposed, hopeless law suits, financed not by the Mayor, but by the taxpayers will result. If the new Superintendent, whose ability is acknowledged even by his enemies, is forced to resign he would be a fool not to sue the City for damages, and our administrators of justice would be very inadequate indeed, if the State Courts did not rule that the city should pay full damages to an official who, after having been legitimately chosen and placed in office by the School Board, lost his position merely because the Mayor and the School Board are at odds. And who would be harmed most? The President of the School Board, the Superintendent of Schools, or our children, who for years have suffered because of political enmity and strife, and who are obviously very likely to continue bearing this cross?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
