<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-04-09">Apr. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Women's Club for the Promotion of Education.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-04-09">Apr. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN WOMEN'S CLUB FOR THE PROMOTION OF EDUCATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite a number of German women assembled last Tuesday afternoon at the Orpheus Hall in the Schiller Building. Mrs. D. Boettcher opened the conference by explaining briefly the purpose of this gathering. According to the letter of invitation, a Mrs. H. C. Brainard, President of the World's Congress Auxiliary for Higher Education, has requested the German women of this city to represent Germany, through a capable woman, at the Congress of Education, which is to be held next July, in connection with the World's Fair. Miss Boettcher stated that the American women have done much for the World's Fair and that the Germans should make it a matter of pride and honor, not to take a secondary position in this matter....</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of a brief talk by Miss Boettcher, the women elected Mrs. Dr. Bluthardt, president, Miss D. Boettcher, secretary, and Mrs. Ch. Wacker, treasurer....</p>
   <p>After an eloquent address by Mrs. M. F. Crow, Mrs. M. Werkmeister proposed to invite Miss H. Lange to the Congress of Education, and to pay her traveling <pb facs="5418474_1_0204.jpg" n="2"/>expenses. The motion was accepted unanimously. Arrangements were made to take up contributions for this purpose and the secretary was requested to communicate with Miss Lange, and to convey the invitation to her.</p>
   <p>Among the German women present, besides those already mentioned, were: Hedwig Voss, Von Ammon, L. Schaffner, H. Lieb, J. V. Kloeber, L. Glade, G. Kapp, L. Carqueville, A. Kirchhoff, M. Stern, C. Seeger, Loeb, Becker, Cyller, Miss Boldenweck, and others. After concluding this most important matter of the day, it was decided to make this temporary organization a permanent one. They agreed after a lengthy debate to call it The German-American Women's Club for the Promotion of Education. Details about the purpose and aim of this new club will be discussed at the next meeting, which will take place Thursday, April 13, at 3 P. M. in the Orpheus Hall, Schiller Building.</p>
   <p>All the German women who have an interest in the problem of education are urgently requested to attend this meeting, and to also invite their friends to attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
