<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-03">September 3, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Enemies of the German Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0649</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0649.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-03">September 3, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">ENEMIES OF THE GERMAN LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There have been some changes made in the new and revised regulation of the School-Board in regard to German instructions in our schools. This had been done, obviously, to remove the cause of complaints on the part of certain elements, in particular Bohemians, who are opposed to German instructions for their children, and who make the assertions that their children are being compelled to take lessons in the German language.</p>
   <p>The paragraphs, having reference to these regulations, read as follows:</p>
   <p>"Section 53 - German - The instructions in German can start with the third and continued through all the different grades as a graduated course. After the course has started, no more students for the German classes can be accepted, unless they are capable of taking up the study and to continue with the others in the class. Parents or guardians are at liberty to send, or not to send the children to these instructions in German in our Primary, Grammar and High Schools.</p>
   <p>A course in German shall be given in any school, if parents of 50 students of that particular school district send in a written request, and the instructions <pb facs="5418474_1_0650.jpg" n="2"/>shall continue so long as 50 students participate. Only then can an application be considered and counted, if the child, for whom application is being introduced in accordance with regulations by the school-board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
