<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-10-27">October 27, 1897</date><title level="a">The Outstanding German City in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-10-27">October 27, 1897</date><title level="a">THE OUTSTANDING GERMAN CITY IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the public schools of Milwaukee there was for years more attention paid to instruction in the German language than in the schools of any other big city of the country and this is easy to explain in regard to the strong Germanism in Beer - Athens. But also in Milwaukee, like other cities, an attempt is made from time to time to restrict this instruction, which is so terribly hated by the nativists and anti-Germans, although it is usually handled in a more careful manner than in other communities.</p>
   <p>So, some thought last spring suddenly to notice that the German instruction causes larger costs, than was necessary, because it was given to children whose parents do not even want this. If, so it was said, German instruction is limited only to children whose parents ask it for their children, the number of students will greatly diminish; we will need less teacher material and will make noticeable savings. This idea succeeded.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While formerly it was customary to let all children, if their parents were not expressing opposition, participate in the German lessons, under the new ruling only such children can attend German classes, whose parents expecially demand this.</p>
   <p>The result seems surprising In place of the doubtless hoped-for reduction in the number of the German pupils, the new ordinance of the affair resulted in increase of pupils. Of the 32,921 children more than 20,000 participate now in German instruction, by special desire of their parents. Of course under these circumstances a reduction of the costs was not possible. German instruction alone costs about $50,000 a year, The anti-German elements see themselves forced now to make the best of a bad bargain because they introduced the proof that German instruction for the children is desired by the majority of parents.</p>
   <p>Milwaukee, it seems, will deserve also in the future, the name "The Outstanding German City of America", Yes, it may become still more German, as it is not on the outside nor in the language, but in habits and customs and thoroughness, <pb facs="5418474_1_0477.jpg" n="3"/>and this is what does count in the end. It is hardly to be feared that Beer - Athens will be Americanized. But to Germanize it is not possible either. Either it will become German-American, or American-German. Let us hope for the latter. German on the inside, American on the outside. German in thinking and feeling, American in its actions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
