<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Fight against German Instruction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FIGHT AGAINST GERMAN INSTRUCTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A petition to abolish the teaching of German in the Oak Park High School and in River Forest township will be presented tonight to the school boards of the two communities. Leader of the movement against the teaching of German is Mrs. C. C. Bird, former regent of the George Rogers Clark Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, who also drew up the resolution against German instruction which was adopted by the chapter. Mrs. Bird is absolutely certain that the school board, which previously decided against abolition of German instruction, has changed its opinion or is going to change it. Whether the petition will be successful is hard to say, for the president of the school board, Mr. J. Kibben Ingalls, and the school commissioners George E. Ellison and Mrs. Lillian Douglass, have all objected to the petition and are in favor of maintaining the teaching of German.</p>
   <p>"I have not changed my opinion since last May, when I voted against the abolition <pb facs="5418474_1_0350.jpg" n="2"/>of German instruction," declared Mrs. Douglass yesterday. "Why should people let their enthusiasm run away with their common sense? A knowledge of German is required of students who enter our higher educational institutions, colleges and universities. The continuance of German instruction has been recommended by the federal government. I will, therefore, not vote for the abolition of German, unless somebody furnishes irrefutable reasons for its abolition."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
