<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-25">June 25, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Crusade against Hatred of Germanism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0616</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0616.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-25">June 25, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CRUSADE AGAINST HATRED OF GERMANISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-haters are again busy in different states. Again they are aiming their attacks against the German language.</p>
   <p>Instructions in German in our public schools is a thorn in the scanty flesh of the hating Know-Nothings. Since they succeeded in suppressing German in St. Louis, one of the strong holds of Germanism, they have become assertive.</p>
   <p>The Germans not only have to keep up the fight for German in public schools, but must also continually defend their own schools if they do not wish to be defeated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0617.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If, for instance, the present election campaign against the Edward Law fails, the Know-Nothings in other states would immediately attempt to suppress German in their public schools by a similar law.</p>
   <p>For the sake of self-preservation, as well as for the welfare of German-Americanism in general, the Germans in Illinois must summon their whole forces, in order to complete the victory at the coming election, which they won in part only in November, 1890, through the election of Raab.</p>
   <p>We have often stated the irrefutable reasons why we can accomplish this only if Altgeld is elected, and if the state legislature is composed of a majority of men, who will treat this burning question as did the recent Democratic state legislature of Wisconsin. The Germans of Chicago and <pb facs="5418474_1_0618.jpg" n="3"/>Illinois are preparing to form a united and invincible front against the haters of Germanism. Previous religious differences and discords are ignored. We see, for instance, the following announcement in Catholic papers:</p>
   <p>"The German Catholics are now beginning to organize themselves on the school question. The organization is preparing for a large convention, which is soon to be held in Chicago. We understand that this convention will make resolutions favoring the Democratic candidate upon the ballot, and other resolutions which are in accord with those of the Lutherans."</p>
   <p>The Protestant German church members will not permit the friendly attitude of the Catholics toward the Lutherans to react to the former's disgrace. Neither will this happen to those Germans who have no religious affiliation, because this matter is a question of life or death for them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0619.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Everything points to the fact that Altgeld, and the German school will win a brilliant and definite victory at the November election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
