<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-04-09">Apr. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Wall (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-04-09">Apr. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT WALL (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As Emperor of Germany, William II often had clever ideas, but the carrying out of these ideas was bungled in most cases. The system of exchange professors was one of these ideas. At that time the "traditional friendship" between the United States and Germany did not exist merely on paper. The Kaiser and President Roosevelt were really close friends, and the German Ambassador, Speck von Sternburg, was one of the most intimate of the Rough Rider's associates. The system of exchange professors actually worked out very well, but the effects were naturally confined only to a small circle. In the deafening clamor of the World War the voices which came from the quiet studies of the scholars had to fall silent.</p>
   <p>A movement has been in progress for many years to force members of the teaching profession to take a special oath of loyalty, and in many states <pb facs="5418474_1_0039.jpg" n="2"/>this teacher's oath has already been introduced by action of the state legislatures. Of special interest is the debate which preceded the adoption of a law of this sort in the Maryland Legislature. The "Free State of Maryland," which used to pride itself on its free institutions and its liberalism, and which was one of the very few states which steadfastly refused to ratify the Prohibition Amendment, has degenerated, and is today a supporter of nationalism.</p>
   <p>During the debate on the bill it was stated, openly and emphatically, that the chief purpose which the proposed law would serve was the exclusion of foreign educators. One of the most ardent supporters of the bill was John F. McNulty, State Commander of the American Legion of Maryland. McNulty considers that he is chiefly responsible for the passage of the bill, and he is very proud of it. The bill has now been passed in both houses of the Legislature and is in the hands of the Governor, who will sign it in all probability. Meanwhile a Baltimore newspaper has called McNulty's attention to the fact that a number of foreign professors are on the faculty of Johns Hopkins University, and are considered to give distinction to that old and <pb facs="5418474_1_0040.jpg" n="3"/>famous educational institution. If the bill becomes law the university will lose these professors.</p>
   <p>Mr. McNulty has obviously not thought of that, for he has stated in public that foreign professors might be registered as "lecturers" and thus be permitted to keep their positions. We are here faced with this peculiar spectacle, that the very man who, more than any other, is responsible for the passage of the bill, is already looking for loopholes to prevent the law's being enforced. But quite aside from this consideration, the fact remains that the spirit of nationalism is spreading in this country. The idea of an exchange of professors, which necessarily involves an exchange of ideas, is dead and buried. Today, instead, many public figures are attempting to build a great wall around the country in order to shut out all the ideas and movements which develop in some other country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
