<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-28">July 28, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">In Favor of Charles H. Ham.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0651</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0651.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-07-28">July 28, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">IN FAVOR OF CHARLES H. HAM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago "Turner" community held its regular meeting last night at the North Side "Turner Hall" at which current business matters were discussed first. Then Max Stern addressed the audience, pointing out in his speech the importance of electing to the Board of Education, men in favor of the generally recognized excellent German teaching method, such as our Normal School has given as a splendid example. Just recently our Normal School was in grave danger of being put out of existence, but thanks to some of our prominent Germans and to the friends of this institution, through whose efforts this school was saved, and to its splendid director, the German school system was retained. Mr. Stern introduced, then the well known American schoolmaster, Charles Bary. Charles Bary, an English American, delivered a speech in German, praising Charles H. Ham as one of the most inspired followers of the German teaching method, spending all of his leisure hours studying pedagogy, and came to the conclusion that the German school system is the most successful system. "Great deal of credit goes to Mr. Ham for saving our Normal School, and the continuation of its present <pb facs="5418474_1_0652.jpg" n="2"/>system under "Colonel" Parker," he remarked. "Therefore I consider Mr. Ham as a most capable person for member of the school board. Mr. Ham is not willing to accept this position if politics are brought into it, and only if our citizens themselves would make the offer to him. Mr. Rosenthal explained then, that Mr. Stern had worked out a resolution regarding the nomination of a member to the school board, which he would submit to the meeting for approval. The resolution is as follows: It is known to the Turner community that a certain gentleman chosen for this position has declined to accept the honor of the appointment, and being convinced that our citizen Charles H. Ham is especially well equipped to fill this vacancy to the advantage of our growing generation. The Chicago "Turner" community has resolved: to appoint a committee of three of whom the first speaker shall be instructed to contact the Mayor of Chicago in the name of the "Turner" community, with the request to appoint Charles H. Ham as member of the school board. Also to give the committee a free hand in this matter in order to convince the mayor that the appointment of Mr. Ham would be in accord with the wishes of our citizens. This was accepted without a debate, and a committee consisting of the following was appointed: Louis Nettelhorst, <pb facs="5418474_1_0653.jpg" n="3"/>Max Stern, W. H. Hettich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
