<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-09-13">September 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Free Textbooks. They Are to Be Distributed. New Fight against Teaching of the German Language Is Apparent.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-09-13">September 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">FREE TEXTBOOKS. THEY ARE TO BE DISTRIBUTED. NEW FIGHT AGAINST TEACHING OF THE GERMAN LANGUAGE IS APPARENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the schoolbooks have been procured for all the pupils at public expense, so far not one has been distributed. They have remained unused since last week. The delivery was accomplished shortly before the German Catholic Societies obtained a write of injunction. The School-principals were not included in the court order, but evidently they fear, that they may be included. They were not willing to come into legal conflict, so they left the books in the packing cases, otherwise they might be apprehended for ignoring the court decisions. Yesterday the Schoolboard members Dr. Hartung and Rowland brought up the matter during the session of the committee. Mr. Frank Loesch made a motion that the books should be distributed. Loesch and six others were in favor, two dissented...Mr. Keating, in explaining his objection said: "It does not appear ethical to him, that the Board of Education resorted to strategy in order to temporarily circumvent a court order.</p>
   <p>Attorney Monroe, who had the injunction issued, at the behest of the German Catholic Societies, i.e. Mr. Peter Kill, induced Judge Vail to include Mayor Harrison, Mc Gann and City Treasurer Gunther in the petition. Until further notice, these officials cannot make any payments for the books, which the Board brought <pb facs="5418474_1_0423.jpg" n="2"/>for the free use of the pupils." Mr. Monroe threatens to apprehend all, who have ignored the edict and to prosecute them for contempt. Mr. Loesch announced to-day, that 95 % of the books have already been given to the children. Chairman Loesch announced two subjects for discussion, which he likes to have disposed of before January 1st. One concerns the discontinuation of the German language instruction in the Elementary schools, the other.... that married women teachers, shall be stricken from the list.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
