<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-03">Aug. 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Trude Is President... of the School Board....</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-03">Aug. 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TRUDE IS PRESIDENT... OF THE SCHOOL BOARD....</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6.. A. S. Trude is the president of the school board. He was elected yesterday by that august body and will keep that position throughout the coming year. E. G. Halle, the great pedagogue who professes esteem and interest for Germanism, insults the Turner and all the Germans in his famous English manner; indeed, he remains entirely oblivious to the efforts of the Germans who have and are still fighting to have gymnastics taught in the public schools.</p>
   <p>This then is the beginning of the school board's new fiscal year. The election of officials was quietly and quickly accomplished. The mayor's party (Harrison) agreed to select Trude. The results showed ll pro, eight against and he was thus elevated to the seat of the mighty.</p>
   <p>The opposition which supported Cameron was routed. Only six votes rallied to his support, the other two favored Brennan and Thornton.... The appointment of the two gymnastic teachers was postponed.</p>
   <p>It must be remembered that Director Suder recommended eight gymnastic teachers, <pb facs="5418474_1_0198.jpg" n="2"/>including Cobelli and Jahn, but the two great Germans, Halle and Boldenweck, in order to satisfy their political obligations, substituted Schmidhofer and Grundhofer. The contention of Messrs. Rosenthal, Mallette, Beebe and others, that this is a matter which really should be decided by the supervisor, was ignored by Halle and Boldenweck. It amounted to this: "We have the power and we employ those who suit us."</p>
   <p>But yesterday Halle went still further. He declared openly that it was immaterial who was teaching gymnastics, as it is a matter of arms and not of brains any one could teach such nonsense.</p>
   <p>After Halle had expressed himself in such a deprecatory manner about gymnastics -a subject with which he is about as conversant as he is with English or German - he tried to convince the other members also. He told every one, it made no difference who was teaching such arm exercises, and naturally, a member asked somewhat surprised, if gymnastics being of such minor importance, would it not be better to drop it altogether?</p>
   <p>But let us say this much for the German Gym-teachers; they have done enough "Brain-work" to speak German and English correctly, and that is more than can <pb facs="5418474_1_0199.jpg" n="3"/>be said of some school board members.</p>
   <p>Tom Cusack, one of the Council men, showed himself as a better friend of the Germans. He labored assiduously for the acceptance of Suders' recommendations and was adequately supported by Rosenthal, Mallette, and Beebe, but after bringing the issue to a vote for the fourth time, Halle's protegees, Schmidhofer and Grundhofer, were elected nevertheless.</p>
   <p>Cusack's motion to nominate Cobelli as Gym-teacher for the Deaf Mute School was referred to the Commitee on Gymnastics and it is to be hoped that President Trude will not appoint Halle as a member; a worse man could not be found. The Turners have no greater enemy, no one who nullified their efforts as much as Halle, who did his share in abolishing the German language instruction in our schools.</p>
   <p>He is Carter Harrison's chosen leader of the Germans. What will the Turners say who have been so instrumental in achieving Halle's renomination?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
