<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-20">June 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">School Board Forced to Economize (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-20">June 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL BOARD FORCED TO ECONOMIZE (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago School Board has elected a special committee to make recommendations relative to further economy in the operation of the school system. This committee will begin work tomorrow. Years of mismanagement have made it imperative that measures of economy be introduced. The School Board owes a debt of $132,840,000, which was incurred during its eighteen years of operation. This leads us to believe that during its entire existence the Board has operated on a deficit. Money was spent hand over fist; if receipts were not sufficient to cover disbursements, the Board simply made new debts. The final result of this mismanagement was that the teachers were forced to wait months for their salaries, and finally, to take recourse to public demonstrations in order to get their pay.</p>
   <p>It can be readily understood that this financial condition affected the <pb facs="5418474_1_0060.jpg" n="2"/>entire system adversely. A teacher worried with financial cares cannot instruct as well as one who is assured of earning his daily bread. No one could blame the teachers; they, too, are human. On the contrary, the public sympathized with the teachers in their desperate battle for their wages. But there is no doubt that the quality of instruction suffered, and thus the children became the innocent victims of the poor business methods of the Board. That is to be regretted more than anything else, for the lack of a thorough education is usually regretted later in life. This fact proves irrefutably that the sound principle of a balanced budget should again be observed in the operation of our schools.</p>
   <p>It is certainly not impossible to economize. In the first place it can be done in school operation. Many of the higher-paid positions within the school system could be dispensed with, without impairing the education of the children. It will be necessary to retrench considerably in this respect; and, since these high-salaried positions are usually filled by persons who hold other positions in the system, it would work no hardship if they were eliminated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0061.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then again, economy can also be practiced in the division of instruction. Many subjects which require a great amount of special equipment would not be missed if they were abolished. This equipment is expensive, and the money might well be saved. These subjects should be omitted from the curriculum if the money in the treasury is not sufficient to purchase the necessary facilities and equipment. Not practical education, but general theoretical knowledge which in later years may be supplemented by practical experience, is the chief purpose of our elementary and secondary instruction. We are thinking of the typewriters which were purchased for a local school at a very unusual price--we mean at a price which was much too high, not too low. And then again when we hear that even powder and rouge are regarded as necessary equipment for the purpose of instructing girls in the art of applying cosmetics, we get an idea of the superfluous articles which are bought by the School Board. Expensive machines for practical instruction in schools are an unnecessary luxury which we cannot afford today. Their operation alone costs a good deal of money and should be eliminated. And, although it is regrettable, the elimination of certain <pb facs="5418474_1_0062.jpg" n="4"/>branches of study as a step toward retrenchment will necessitate the dismissal of some teachers. In no event should purely theoretical instruction be curtailed, for under present conditions our children must not suffer because of the mismanagement of our schools--and certainly not with our knowledge and consent. But instruction in manual training could be curtailed or abolished without detriment to the children; it is no substitute for practical training in any profession, and, scholastically, can hardly be rated any higher than play.</p>
   <p>This year the School Board was also forced to shorten the school year by two weeks because it lacked the necessary money. It is one of the duties of the special committee to see to it that such abridgments are not necessary in the future, for the children are entitled to full-time instruction. If the necessary attitude is adopted it will be possible to balance receipts and disbursements. There has been enough mismanagement of Chicago's schools; it is about time to apply sound financial principles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
