<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-21">Apr, 21, 1881</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0986</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0986.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-21">Apr, 21, 1881</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="3" reason="illegible"/></title><!-- WHISKY AND BEER, BY BISMARCK [???] --></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The temperance fanatics of America who are not familiar the German language have lost a good deal of enjoyment which they could have derived from Bismarck's remark, namely, that drinking beer makes people stupid. That Bismarck did actually make this remark in a privately held conversation with Mr. Von Buelow, nobody would doubt who is acquainted with the gentlemen's tone and mode of expression. Bismarck, made also a public statement in Parliament to the same effect. Nevertheless, his argument that whisky was preferable to beer would have rather shocked the American temperance advocates.</p>
   <p>There are numerous reasons why Bismarck condemns beer and speaks in favor of more intoxicating liquor. One of them is, that beer-drinking one of his favorite pastimes, but out of consideration for his impaired health he was obliged to give it up. Thus it is quite natural that he became an anti-beer apostle. He is of the opinion that a drink of whisky, taken at the right time, is invigorating, while beer, on the contrary, has a tendency to enervate <pb facs="5418474_1_0987.jpg" n="2"/>and produce sentimental reactions. Be also the story clear, it must be brought to our attention that Bismarck in the owner of large estates, which leads to the supposition that he like most of the Prussian land owners operates a distillery thus using to his best advantage the potato crop. The Germans have been considered beer-drinkers so far, but Bismarck dispelled that illusion. The German idea of enjoyment of life consisted of taking the family to a beer garden, drinking in the beauty of the outdoors, while enjoying the sipping of a glass of beer. This picture of German happiness was held up as an example to many other nations. But Bismarck charged completely this picture of German happiness.</p>
   <p>Just now connect Bismarck's statement was, is a point of argument beyond our authority. But there is no doubt, according to official German newspapers, that the German nation has increased its consumption of liquor. This, according to Bismarck is to be regarded is a gratifying occurence, as it does seem rather strange that a bill for the prevention of and the punishment for drunkenness was submitted to Parliament. Or is this bill principally directed against the light beer intoxicant, while requesting no strict measures against the real demon of intoxicating liquor?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0988.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is also another point to be considered, namely, that Bismarck is wasting his efforts on the introduction of a national beer tax as the means of a splendid revenue. Imposing a tax on an article of general consumption is considered by the Germans as an act of hostility against them. Bismarck, obviously unbeknown to himself, became a foe of beer, transferring his friendly attitude to heavier intoxicants. If this were a cas for the American Minister of Finance to handle, the simplicity of it would be astonishing. Whiskey, the favorite American drink, is taxed 300 per cent of the original cost, while beer, in contrast, is taxed only with fifteen percent of the original price. A shrewd minister of finance in Germany would increase the tax on beer, while diminishing the tax on liquor. But it is neither understandable nor excusable that Bismarck, in order to be successful in his plans, minimizes the importance of beer, of which he has consumed gallons in his day, and glorifies the abominable product derived from potatoes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
