<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-26">Oct. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Attacks on Parochial Schools (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-26">Oct. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ATTACKS ON PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of our great daily papers a reader asks that a law be enacted requiring children to attend the public schools up to their fourteenth year. He claims that this alone would guarantee the complete Americanization of our youth.</p>
   <p>We consider the above an attack on our parochial or church schools. These attacks are nothing new except that at present the indirect charge is made that church schools are an obstacle to complete Americanization; that they are not patriotic enough. Moreover, since it is chiefly the Catholic and Lutheran churches which maintain schools of their own, it is against these especially that the intolerant world reformers are crusading.</p>
   <p>We have a report written in 1914 which shows that the Catholic Church alone maintains 5,448 elementary schools, attended by 1,456,206 pupils. If we add <pb facs="5418474_1_0860.jpg" n="2"/>the number of children attending the Lutheran and other parochial schools, we will have nearly three million children who are being taught in the church schools. Since the churches and their members maintain these schools out of their own income, one can estimate how much the citizens who do not belong to these churches are saving.</p>
   <p>About seventy-three per cent of our school children attend public schools, the maintenance of which requires an expenditure of 555 million dollars; most of the remaining twenty-seven per cent are taught in the parochial schools.</p>
   <p>These figures prove that a law which provides for public schools only, would entail an added burden of twenty-seven per cent for the educational system of our country; it would empty the church schools and many new school buildings would have to be erected.</p>
   <p>To use the school building of the church communities for public schools would <pb facs="5418474_1_0861.jpg" n="3"/>be an encroachment on the property and religious rights of those church communities even if compensation were paid, since freedom of religion is sanctioned by the Constitution.</p>
   <p>As for their educational value, the fact has long been established that parochial schools maintain the same standard of instruction that is found in the public schools. The admittance of parochial school graduates to the higher institutions of learning is further confirmation of this statement. But in order to be absolutely impartial, we must admit that it would be desirable, in a few cases, if English instruction played a larger part in the curriculum, if for no other reason than to take the wind out of the sails of those who are attacking these schools.</p>
   <p>To attempt to defend the patriotic attitude of these schools would be an insult to the teaching personnel of these institutions. We should like to quote here, however, what another reader of the same paper says in reply to these intolerant attacks:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0862.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"About thirty-five per cent of our armed forces received their education in parochial schools. Eight hundred and twenty young men of the church parish in which I live are doing their patriotic duty at the front and in training camps, and eight hundred of these got their elementary schooling in parochial schools."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
