<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-27">July 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Festival of the German Central Union.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Brilliant Speech of School Superintendent H. Raab.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-27">July 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL OF THE GERMAN CENTRAL UNION.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Brilliant Speech of School Superintendent H. Raab.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the time when the German language, the most valuable treasure of the German-Americans, was threatened with suppression by arrogant alien haters and bigots, the German-American Central Union was established. This Central Union, an alliance of more than a hundred different organizations of German-Americans, who united for the same purpose, and stand for the same lofty ideals, achieved great merits during that memorable battle of last fall, when Mr. H. Raab emerged as victor.</p>
   <p>It was natural then that the Central Union demanded a speech from that man who had become their standard bearer in their glorious battle. The union celebrated yesterday its first public festival at the Schutzen Park, and Henry Raab, the School Superintendent of the state, gladly complied with their request to be their speaker at this occasion. Striking and unique German words it were, which H. Raab used as a strong defense against the suspicion and slander of the obscurantists and bigots.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0629.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Francis A. Hoffmann Jr., the President of the Alliance, who introduced Mr. H. Raab, made the statement that the union does not serve a political purpose, but aims at uniting the different German-American elements for high German ideals, and to fight in unison against despotic laws.....</p>
   <p>H. Raab's Speech.</p>
   <p>"In many places in this country the Germans have come together, just as they have done today, to cultivate German manners, customs, tastes, traits, and language. They desire to maintain only those ideas and ideals which are not contrary to the institutions of this country.</p>
   <p>A part of the population of this country thinks it a crime if we try to cultivate legitimate traits. They demand of us to forsake the same and also, they accuse us of requiring them to follow in our steps...... The German nation among all others stands upon the heights of civilization. Its government permits different tribes and clans to live as they please, so long as they do not violate <pb facs="5418474_1_0630.jpg" n="3"/>the laws of the land. Greece was taken up with nationalism, but it permitted its different people to live according to their peculiarities. So it was with the Germans. The Swabians, Frisians, the Franconians, Saxons, etc., they all were loyal to the national ideal, and yet they clung to their peculiar tribal customs and traits. In this country, the different German tribes also are united in the battle against their mutual enemy.</p>
   <p>We are patriotic. We aspire to make our adopted country great and respected before the world. But what is patriotism? It is not of the intellect, but of the emotion. . . . .</p>
   <p>The population of each country is divided into two classes, the workers or producers, and the unproductives. Without fear of contradiction I assert that the Germans belong to the first class. That is patriotism!</p>
   <p>The German farmer wants to own the land which he wrested from the forest or from the wilderness, and that is patriotism.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0631.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The courageous struggle against "bi-metallism" and "Greenback inflation", the determination to pay with honest money, that is patriotism!</p>
   <p>The Germans are conservative in their religion. They are strangers to the sensational, the revivals. But in art, the flower of humanity and civilization, the Germans are leading. They excel in music, drama, sculpture, and that is patriotism..... We love Germany and are also loyal sons of the U. S. A."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
