<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title>Abendpost</title>",
<date when="1893-02-24">February 24th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Temporarily Defeated.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title>Abendpost</title>",
<date when="1893-02-24">February 24th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Temporarily Defeated.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago School board did not decide so far, to abolish the teaching of German and the other "Fads." Some of its members are perfectly aware of the fact, that the knowledge of the "Three R'S" is not sufficient any more, and that the school must lay the foundation of a higher education. The opponents of the so called special subjects, are either fanatical haters of foreigners or are under the mistaken impression that every subject should be on the instruction list only for its own sake. We might call the latter, fanatice of usefulness.</p>
   <p>They demand, that every child partaking of German lessons, should speak it fluently those partaking of Drawing lessons should become finished artists, and these receiving singing lessons at least heroic tenors or Prima-donnas. It is difficult to make then understand, that with the knowledge of another language, the understanding of one's mother tongue and grasping is made easier. Strangely, this side of the question has been best understood by the two women members of the school board. Especially has Miss Burt through her remarks on pedagogical principles, proven, much better qualified for her office, than the majority of the school board's Male members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0579.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When, at the end of the 19th Century, in one of the newest, cultural cities, a school board advocates a standpoint, according to which the schools should only be considered as training institutions. This is certainly very regrettable.</p>
   <p>Those members of the School Board, who vote against the special subjects because they imagine, that by doing so, they are proving their "American Patriotism" beyond suspicions are playing a sorry role. There must be particularly mentioned, one Scandinavian, who brags about his countrymen's ability, to become Americanized, in a short time, and demands, that other nationalities should follow suit and bring up their children as "superficial Americans", a person, who considers an exclusively pedagogical question, from this viewpoint, is a poor guardian of the public schools. For the moment, the attack of these obscure men has been repulsed, but, no doubt it will be renewed, and therefore it is imperative, that the friends of the special subjects, should be watchful. Only, after the principle is conceded, can we discuss whether the methods of teaching could be improved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
