<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-10">Nov.10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Majestic.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-10">Nov.10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">MAJESTIC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to its origin, the title Majesty does not belong to kings and emperors, but to the people. Originally it designated the highest power and dignity of the state and was attributed to the people of the Roman Republic. Majestas populi Romani - (Majesty of the Romans), that was the title originally. Kings and emperors have stolen it from the people, yielding to the precedence set by the Roman emperors.</p>
   <p>In the United States of America, however, one may still say, "Populi Americani Majestas" - (The majesty of the American people). Never before did the majesty of the American people appear so majestic as on November 8, 1892. Never before in the history of the world did it happen that thirteen to fourteen millions of voters made a decision in regard to their future government within a few hours, at the ballot-box, after a few months of quiet investigation and deliberation, and without shedding a drop of blood...</p>
   <p>Is there any comparison between a change of government executed by a great people, and the succession to a throne due to the death of the predecessor? The people of a monarchy simply have to accept a ruler, whether he is <pb facs="5418474_1_0613.jpg" n="2"/>intellectually or morally completely unfit or not, to govern a well educated and cultured people.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the American people have just elected as their president one of the two capable, trustworthy men, whom they themselves had nominated. They have chosen the one whose principles more fully correspond to their own conception of general liberty and equality.</p>
   <p>The American people made the decision on November 8th that there should be no second rate citizens in this country, but that all of them should enjoy equal rights, irrespective of their nationality and their mother-tongue. This is indeed a great and majestic gesture, exceedingly fitting and worthy of a gigantic nation of free citizens!</p>
   <p>The American people manifested on this memorable day its clear foresight and its penetrating understanding, by its decision for a moderate tariff reform, for honest money, for an administration as free as possible from party politics, for the continuation of sensible immigration, for the <pb facs="5418474_1_0614.jpg" n="3"/>protection of the right of parents in matters of education, and against compulsory prohibition.</p>
   <p>Cleveland, in his enjoyment of victory will undoubtedly remember the good advice given to him personally about three months ago by a representative of this paper, our friend, W. Hesing, Four years ago he lost New York, and, as a consequence, the presidency, because he permitted himself to follow bad advice, namely, to be silent on the question of personal liberty.</p>
   <p>This time, however, listening to practical advice, he did express his opposition to the despotism of the prohibitionists, the suppression of foreign languages, and interference with parental rights. As a result of this, be won New York, as well as the presidency, and, in addition, he captured the states of Illinois and Wisconsin, just as the practical adviser had predicted he would do, provided he followed his advice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
