<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-12">Mar. 12, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The School Scandal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-12">Mar. 12, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL SCANDAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American people speak with the same arrogance of their "national education" as the Prussians do of their "glorious army." Unless thoroughly convinced to the contrary, the average American resents any criticism on that subject. So it happened recently that the very intellectual Mr. Richard Grant White was not considered to possess his full mental faculty when he indicated that the sort of education included in the public school's curriculum is by far less desirable than no education at all. Although for the last thirty years-long before White-German educators have said much against the miserable educational system of this country, the average American, though understanding the criticism, remained apathetic.</p>
   <p>What does a "foreigner" know about the intellectual needs and the ability of study of a "free and enlightened nation." Advice from this source is not considered competent to the average American. Nevertheless, some progress has been made in the fight to eliminate subjects of no consequence and the <pb facs="5418474_1_0245.jpg" n="2"/>adoption of more essential studies. The progress, if any, is due to the efforts of Mr. Adams, (grandson of the President) who, in Quincy, his place of residence was instrumental in introducing the German system of teaching, because there is no doubt that it's influence is felt in the cultivation of of the mind, the powers of thinking and in the development of competent judgment. The result was so striking that it could not go unnoticed, and considering it an entirely new method, call it the "Quincy system." This is, however, a misrepresentation of real facts, because the originator of that method was Pestalozzi, and it is, therefore, unquestionably German. But if the belief that the system is a national invention renders it more acceptable to the American people, self deception can be tolerated indeed.</p>
   <p>Mr. James H. Slade, a noted pedagogue recently spoke at a teachers' meeting held in New York. On this occasion he criticized our school system much more severely than Mr. White ever did. He declared the majority of the Board of Education members is absolutely incompetent. They have no idea of a school's responsibility or the importance of a teacher's proficiency <pb facs="5418474_1_0246.jpg" n="3"/>and therefore render educational institutions a playground for affected ignorance and gross incompetence.</p>
   <p>The average citizen contends however, that he is well qualified to make his own decision in the election of members to the School Board as well as other officials of the city and state.</p>
   <p>There lies the danger. A great majority of our young men of voting age (within certain limits) are fully convinced not only of being the personification of excellent virtues, but also of their wisdom. The general idea that one individual is as good as the other has been carried to extremes. Thus it becomes plausible that in the eyes of those citizens void of the faculty of discrimination, nothing should interfere with the appointment of a baker, a boiler maker or a tavern keeper to the high calling of a Board of Education member. Therefore, we say go to the polls and do your duty in accordance with your convictions. What the result of such a broad minded election of School Board members would be is clearly demonstrated <pb facs="5418474_1_0247.jpg" n="4"/>by the city of Cincinnati. The Board of Education of that city is the most ignorant and incapable body of men installed into that office by the public votes.</p>
   <p>Much time will elapse before the American people become aware of the value of Mr. Slade's truthful words, namely; that teaching is a scholarly attainment requiring of the individual an exceedingly thorough educational background. Teaching has been so far the field in which women predominated, and for the vocation of which any young female able to read and write could qualify. And why not? All that is demanded of a teacher is that she be able to read the questions and answers contained in the text book. The other requirement is that she hear the pupils' lessons, although she may be far from understanding them. The mode of teaching by our young school-ma'm's is equal to that of the retired under-officer or village shepherd of a hundred years ago, who taught the village youngsters the A B C 's. . . .</p>
   <p>How long before there is a change from this deplorable educational system <pb facs="5418474_1_0248.jpg" n="5"/>into one of which the nation could justly be proud? We prefer to refrain from a prophecy of that nature; one thing is certain however, namely; that we will not be here to witness this much desired change.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
