<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-04-26">Apr. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">German Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-04-26">Apr. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German pictures, music and songs were presented before the students of the University of Chicago at the Mandel Hall.</p>
   <p>It was a very appealing performance which, under the title, "A German Evening," was given last night at the Mandel Hall at 57th Street and University Avenue, under the auspices of the International Students Association of Chicago and Vicinity.</p>
   <p>The hall was filled to capacity, not only by Germans but also by an international audience, of which probably the greater part were students.</p>
   <p>As the first number of the program, a film of Germany in all its beauty was shown; German cities in their old glory, German <pb facs="5418474_1_0069.jpg" n="2"/>sports in winter and summer. Even the Munich Hofbrau House, with all its "drinking horns" and tankards, was shown to the young spectators, not to mention the pictures of beautiful German landscapes along the Shine, which without doubt is the most beautiful river of the world.</p>
   <p>During the course of the evening, Charles <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>endsen played on the organ a few gems of German music by Handel, Schubert, and Chopin. He received great applause.</p>
   <p>A zither quartet played by the German Zither Choir of Chicago and German songs at the campfire by the German Students' Club, concluded <pb facs="5418474_1_0070.jpg" n="3"/>the program.</p>
   <p>H. Rochall, a young student, welcomed the audience and said that he remembered the time when he actually saw many of the pictures, which had been shown. Consul General Dr. H.F. Simon spoke in English, expressing his pleasure for being able to participate at the celebration. He said that he admired the young people who came to America at an early age, when they were still admissible and not ossified, in order to expand their horizons and benefit by the advantages which America offered them.</p>
   <p>Both speakers, Rochall and the Consul General, pointed with thanks and pride to Mr. B. Dixon, the father of the German students, who deserves special credit for the success of the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
