<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-07">Mar. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German in Chicago's Public Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_1_0558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_1_0558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-07">Mar. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN IN CHICAGO'S PUBLIC SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The attack of the Know-Nothings, against German instruction in our public schools, has increased to such an extent that it challenges every German. These attacks against the German-Americans by the Know-Nothing members of the school board are carried on under the pretense that it is an economy measure, but this is only an empty excuse.</p>
   <p>Every German, irrespective of party affiliations, should sign the petitions which are being circulated by German clubs and societies, requesting the continuance of German instruction in the primary grades, as well as of drawing, singing, and gymnastics in all the public schools. Not only should the Germans sign the petitions readily, but also assist in gathering signatures among Germans and other nationalities. We must present a united front to the school board, and the overwhelming majority of our votes must be our weapon to defend these branches.</p>
   <p>In order to support this movement more effectively, it seems fitting to give a brief history of German instruction in our local public schools, as well as to repeat the reasons for the necessity of continuing instruction in the <pb facs="5418474_1_0559.jpg" n="2"/>third and fourth grade of these schools.</p>
   <p>Upon the recommendation of Lorenz Brentano and Hermann Felsenthal, in 1865, German language instruction was introduced in all the grades of our public schools, except in the tenth grade which was then the lowest one. When, in 1875, a new system of grade arrangement was introduced, instruction in German was restricted to the grammar classes.</p>
   <p>However, German was introduced again into the third and fourth lower grades, when a committee of the school board, to which men like J. M. Clark and G. Stewart belonged, recommended this in 1885. The desire to study German became so general that it gradually had to be taught in all the schools.</p>
   <p>An agreement was made at that time between L. Nettelhorst, president of the school board, and the other members of this department, to take no steps to direct the attention of parents or children of the different schools, to German instruction; but rather to wait until parents requested classes in German, before such classes were organized...</p>
   <p>During the previous season the number of applications required to introduce the study of German in a public school was raised from 50 to 75. Yet in <pb facs="5418474_1_0560.jpg" n="3"/>spite of all this, the subject had to be introduced in all the schools, located in the recently annexed districts, and in each one of them over a hundred pupils were registered.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the difficulties with which instruction in German has to contend, the total number of pupils in German classes rose last January to 34,521. According to this figure, 51% of all the pupils in the eligible grades are studying German.</p>
   <p>... Experience has proven that the study of the German language is by no means an impediment to the progress of pupils in other branches of study... Special branches of study intensify the interest of the children, enlarge their ability to comprehend, and increase their mental activities, making it possible for the child to learn in eight years what formerly required ten years.</p>
   <p>Eminent educators... have agreed that the study of German in the primary grades of our public schools, far from impeding the child's progress in other subjects, is beneficial. It is also stated that the study of another language, besides the English, helps to gain a better understanding, and a more accurate expression of the latter, since the pupils grasp the meaning of the <pb facs="5418474_1_0561.jpg" n="4"/>English words much more quickly and easily, by comparing them with those of a foreign language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
