<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-10-30">Oct. 30, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">For Annexation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0794</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0794.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-10-30">Oct. 30, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">FOR ANNEXATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A debate was held last Friday evening under the auspices of the Chicago Literary Union. The question of debate was: "Resolved that the United States should assume the government of the Philippines."</p>
   <p>Miss Dagny Grevstad, the daughter of Nicolay Grevstad, led the discussion with the following words [in English]:</p>
   <p>"Mr. president, honorable judges, ladies and gentlemen:</p>
   <p>"Only a few short months ago, the proposition that the United States acquire the Philippine Islands would have met with pity and derision as a freak notion of a weak brain. The early annexation of Hawaii was practically settled, but no one dreamed of any territorial expansion. Now, Hawaii is part and parcel of the Republic; Porto Rico is ours; unhappy Cuba is our ward; and we are confronted with the question--a condition and a theory--whether or not we shall assume control over the Philippine archipelago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0795.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"This great problem has been thrust upon us by an all-ruling power speaking through the cannon of Dewey. We can no more dismiss it than we can undo glorious May Day victory in the Bay of Manila. It is a problem fraught with the largest possibilities for good or evil, and the solution is involved in doubt.</p>
   <p>"In approaching a problem of such magnitude, let us first take counsel of the past. We bow in reverence before the immortal legacy of wisdom left us by the 'father of his country', and listen attentively to this 'disinterested warning of a parting friend'. But we hear no warning against American growth, greatness, and glory. As we all know, the keynote of Washington's farewell address is a strong plea for the Union, the life of which was threatened by foreign foes and domestic strife. But it cannot be invoked in support of a clam-policy of inactivity and isolation.</p>
   <p>"From the very beginning of our national life the 'policy of our fathers,' to which some among us appeal with such persistency, has been one of steady expansion. As early as 1803, the area of the United States was more than doubled by the purchase of the Louisiana Territory, and in 1819 the <pb facs="5423969_2_0796.jpg" n="3"/>Floridas were added to our domain, and the whole gulf coast east of the Mississippi became ours. In 1826 the Monroe Doctrine was declared as a barrier to European aggressions in the western world; not as a barrier to American growth, as some seem to think. In 1845 Texas was annexed, and the next year our title to the Oregon Territory was confirmed. In 1848 we acquired, by conquest, the vast California Territory of more than 500,000 square miles, thus extending our domain from ocean to ocean. Alaska, comprising some 531,000 square miles, was bought in 1867.</p>
   <p>"Expansion--expansion by leaps and bounds is, then, the policy of our fathers. Shall we stop now, or shall we follow in their path? This question has been laid at our door by a victorious war. The Philippine Islands are ours by conquest, as was the California Territory in 1848. Shall we answer as we did then, or shall we depart from the path of our fathers and henceforth adopt a policy of stagnation?</p>
   <p>"The exigencies and necessities of the situation in which we find ourselves placed, as well as considerations of humanity and the best interests of our country, forbid our abandoning the archipelago and demand that we <pb facs="5423969_2_0797.jpg" n="4"/>assume the government of the Islands. The Filipinos have expressed a desire to be annexed if they cannot obtain independence. Recent events show that they are unfit for self-government. Our withdrawal would be the signal for anarchy and endless contests between rival native chiefs. The great powers of Europe would then pounce upon the Islands, like vultures upon their prey, and a general war would probably follow. Neither can we sell them, even if we were disposed to consider such an undignified course, because no power would obtain the rival powers' permission to buy. In other words, we must remain there because we cannot leave; we must stay because necessity and duty command. And if we are to stay, it follows that we must assume government control over the Islands and, moreover, exercise it with a strong hand until the people shall have learned to govern themselves. What stern necessity and duty demand, we should do all the more willingly because it is also required by our industrial and commercial needs.</p>
   <p>"As our country has expanded, our resources have multiplied. At the beginning of this year, we produced an abundance of everything that is grown outside of the tropics. Since Hawaii and Porto Rico have enriched our <pb facs="5423969_2_0798.jpg" n="5"/>resources with some of the tropical products, the possession of the Philippines will complete them. The United States will then produce everything needed on our tables and in our shops--an advantage enjoyed by no other country in the world. Of still greater importance is their possession from a commercial point of view. We make more than we use, and with one voice our people demand new and larger markets. The eyes of all selling countries are now centered upon eastern Asia where five hundred millions of consumers are gradually lining up along the bargain counters of the civilized nations. To obtain the largest possible share of this tremendous trade is the leading aim of the statesmanship of the great powers of Europe, and they have all secured footholds there in order to protect their commercial interests--Russia in the north, Germany at Kiao-Chau, England at Wei-Ha-Wei, Hong Kong and other points, and France in the south. The possession of the Philippines would give us a position of equal importance in the coming great struggle for Chinese trade. Manila and Subig Bays are of paramount strategic value. Their possession will place the key to the southern sea of China in our pocket. Whether the struggle for Chinese trade is to be fought out exclusively along the lines of peaceable competition, or partly in other ways, we must possess the Philippine Islands in <pb facs="5423969_2_0799.jpg" n="6"/>order to protect and increase our trade in China. At present our exports to China are second only to those of Great Britain, but they should increase, and they will grow rapidly if the flag be kept at Manila, for trade follows the flag. The Philippine Islands constitute a valuable market in themselves, but the chief value of their possession is that it will enable us to reach the doorknob of China, so that we can keep the door of Chinese trade open if others should attempt to shut it. We must find a market especially for our surplus of cotton, wheat, corn, machinery, and other things, and we have it in China if we improve our present unexampled opportunity. Why should we not be expansionists when expansion means a larger demand and better prices for the products of our farms; when expansion means expansion of our factories and of the demand for and wages of labor; when it will improve our industrial conditions and in a corresponding measure still industrial strife and thus promote the happiness of our people?</p>
   <p>"We hear objections, but they are only faint echoes of the past. Thomas Jefferson was assailed in the most virulent manner on account of the purchase of Louisiana. He had violated the Constitution and annexed <pb facs="5423969_2_0800.jpg" n="7"/>elements that we could not assimilate, etc. The same despairing wail has accompanied every subsequent addition to our territory. It was raised against the annexation of Hawaii, and we hear it now. Jefferson replied that if we could govern ourselves we could also govern the people of Louisiana. History is his vindication. We have solved and are solving today greater problems of this kind. We have shown that even the most ignorant gradually become apt pupils in our majestic school of self-government. To doubt that we can govern the Filipinos is to deny the plainest lessons of our history. And as for the Constitution, it has expanded with the country and grown stronger in the hearts of the people for every alleged violation of this character. The American people never listened to the squeaking voice of the croaker, nor will they ever do so. No country was ever made great and strong by faint hearts and timid counsels.</p>
   <p>"Let us raise our eyes to the mountain peaks of the future. A hundred years ago Washington spoke to five million people; today we are seventy-five million; in fifty years we shall be two hundred and fifty million; and in another century five hundred million souls. Washington's republic was hemmed in on three sides by dependencies of foreign powers; today the <pb facs="5423969_2_0801.jpg" n="8"/>front steps of our house are washed by the Atlantic and the rear steps by the Pacific. In Washington's day our position was 'detached and distant'; when the Nicaragua canal is built by us, to be controlled by us, the United States will be the center of the world, geographically, commercially, and financially. Our statesmen of today must have these great possibilities of the future in view and build accordingly. And we may rejoice because it is plain to all that they have read the writing in the stars and listened to the voice of American destiny. With Porto Rico and Hawaii in our possession and Cuba as our friend, our control of the Nicaragua canal will not be disputed. Hawaii is only a halfway station in the Pacific; it points to the Philippines as the western bulwark of our expanding sea power and trade. The Pacific Ocean will carry the bulk of the trade of the future. The larger share of this trade is ours by right, hence our influence in the Pacific must be predominant, which it cannot be unless we possess the Philippines. With this commanding position in our grasp we can keep the Pacific Ocean open and free, unless we shall declare that it must be an American sea.</p>
   <p>"A great nation never faced greater opportunities or a plainer duty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0802.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Providence has blessed us with power. Shall we make use of the gift or, like the faithless steward, bury our talent? In the past our starry banner has been the hope of the oppressed of all lands. In the future we may speak for liberty in the councils of the nations; and the footfall of Columbia may be heard all over the world and carry consolation to the downtrodden and fear to the oppressor. Are we to shirk this duty to ourselves and mankind? Are we to forfeit our opportunity now and forever? Are we to approach our great task in fear and trembling or with stout hearts and the wisdom of courage? Dewey opened a new epoch in the history of our republic and the world at large. Shall we turn the tide back? Shall we lower the flag that he raised? No! All that is sacred to us forbids such a stain upon our honor. Our duty as the strongest guardian of liberty in the world, our material welfare and growing power, the honor of our nation, the conscience of our people, the teachings of our history, the blood of our fallen heroes, and the courage of the living; the voice of our departed great statesmen and warriors, of Washington, Jefferson, Lincoln, Grant, Farragut, and many others--all point to the flag floating over Manila, and all blend in the impressive command: 'Keep it there!'"</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0803.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: Miss Dagny Grevstad at this time was a student in the North Division High School, hence only about sixteen years old. Her able introduction of the issue discussed was considered as a real contribution at the time. The English press pointed out that this young Norwegian high school girl had delivered an address that was equal to any delivered by the best orators here in Chicago.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
