<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-03-29">Mar. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Sweat Shop Must Go</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-03-29">Mar. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEAT SHOP MUST GO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the request of organized labor, a bill known as the Sulzer Bill has been introduced in the House of Representatives, the object of which is to tax "sweat shop" manufacturing out of existence. It applies to trades in which it has become more or less customary to have certain lines of work performed by workers in their homes.</p>
   <p>It is very generally held that tenement house manufacturing is a great evil, which ought to be uprooted. There are only two ways of doing this; by uniform legislation in all the states or by national legislation. As there is no prospect of securing suitable state legislation in the near future, national legislation is the only practical means of lessening the evil. The Sulzer Bill does not outlaw this kind of work, but it is intended to be prohibitory in its effects, and it is generally held that tenement house <pb facs="5423969_2_0719.jpg" n="2"/>manufacturing would be an impossibility under such a law properly enforced. It is understood that the bill is regarded as constitutional by some of the foremost lawyers of the country, as well as by the law officers of the Treasury Department at Washington.</p>
   <p>While thinking men and women deplore the existence of the "sweat shop," it is argued by some that the cure proposed would be worse than the disease, because it is feared that it would deprive a class of workers of their opportunity to support themselves. But the work to which reference is made would continue to be done by the same people, only with better safeguards as regards the health of both the producers and the consumers of the goods. Moreover, as nearly all social and industrial evils in some way benefit somebody, every reform is secured at a temporary sacrifice on the part of someone. But considerations of this kind cannot be permitted to block the work of improving conditions, unless all efforts in this direction are to be abandoned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0720.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every new invention displaces a certain amount of human labor, thus resulting in temporary idleness and want in many homes; yet every new invention is welcomed as a blessing to the people at large.</p>
   <p>The evils of the "sweat shop" system of work are undeniable. It stunts the growth of workers employed in this manner, thus producing a class of men and women who are weak in body, mind and morals. It robs labor of its manhood and self-respect. It has a depressing effect on the general scale of wages, and hence is an injustice to all workers. It exposes the consumers to unseen dangers of contagious diseases. It is a system under which the faces of the poor are ground down by the poor in their struggle with one another for bread--in the quicksands of an excessive and illegitimate competition. It should be uprooted at once. The sweat shop must go.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
