<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-11">Feb. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[An Era of Political Lawlessness]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-11">Feb. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[AN ERA OF POLITICAL LAWLESSNESS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The primary campaign in Chicago has developed into an old fashioned "free-for-all" and "battle royal." The "powers that be" in both Republican and Democratic camps are badly split and confusion reigns supreme. Mayor Busse has now refused to run for reelection. This is the most sensible thing he has done since stepping from the postmastership, handed to him by President Roosevelt, into his present position as mayor of Chicago. Such rottenness and graft as has thrived during his administration has never had a parallel in the hectic history of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The question of the day is, "Will conditions be bettered by the new administration?" It all depends upon to what extent the man finally selected has torn loose from the "machine" and its "bossism." The "machine" consists of a conglomeration <pb facs="5423969_2_0113.jpg" n="2"/>of office seekers and grafters led by a select gang of bosses (job herders) elevated to leading positions by the hoodlums and political hangers-on in each ward. These "bosses" run not only their own parties but the entire city as they please, and their idea of politics is to run the city for their own gain, and to hand out civic appointments profitable to themselves but expensive to the taxpayer. Under such a system graft and corruption rum rampant, and the decent citizen pays, as usual, through the nose.</p>
   <p>It is high time a thorough housecleaning was started and carried through to a finish in Chicago's political household; drastic ills require drastic remedies.</p>
   <p>Both the Republican and the Democratic party are rotten to the core; how any decent citizen can cast a vote for a candidate of either of these parties is a real mystery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0114.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Socialist party is united, backing one list of proposed officers and offering a clean, honest city administration, where a working man's dollar is his own and not subject to onslaught by petty political thieves. Their program will bring cleaner conditions and higher morality in politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
