<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1908-10-12">Oct. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Look Abroad</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1908-10-12">Oct. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LET US LOOK ABROAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war clouds rising so suddenly in the eastern sky cast their shadows across the seas, even to our shores. While this country is not directly concerned in the territorial disputes and national conflicts in the Balkans, it must be ready to protect American interests in that part of the world. We know from experience that American missions, schools, and commercial interests in the Balkan peninsula and Asia Minor have been seriously imperiled during comparatively insignificant disturbances; the peril and probable injury would, of course, be immeasurably greater should the dogs of war be unleashed.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that the peace of Europe is trembling in the balance. War may be averted for the time being by some sort of international agreement, some substitute for the Berlin treaty of which nothing now remains. But no makeshift plan can insure lasting peace. Servia has ambitions that are rooted in her great past. Her people cannot and evidently will not <pb facs="5423969_2_0508.jpg" n="2"/>submit to the conditions created by Austria's forward move. Servia is and will remain a constant menace to the peace of Europe until her dreams of a greater Servia are realized, or until she is completely and hopelessly crushed.</p>
   <p>If war comes it will not be confined to Europe and European waters. The Mohammedans of Asia and Africa will be deeply stirred, and a concerted movement of Islamism against Christianity and the Christians is to be anticipated. The restless millions of India may attempt to free their land from British imperialism. There is no doubt as to what Japan would do. A general war would leave her a free hand in the Far East, and she would proceed to make herself the mistress of Asia. Manchuria would be reoccupied, and China put under tutelage, and she would look upon the Philippines, and perhaps Hawaii as her legitimate prey.</p>
   <p>All these complications and many others are among the possibilities of the <pb facs="5423969_2_0509.jpg" n="3"/>near future.</p>
   <p>We cannot know where and how American rights may be threatened; but we do know that American statesmanship may be put to a severe test, and it behooves us to prepare for what may happen. Even if the world's peace should remain undisturbed now, the near future is certain to witness a war of diplomacy, a war of wide ramifications and far-reaching consequences.</p>
   <p>Can we trust a Bryan and a Bryan cabinet to safeguard the nation's rights and honor abroad during troublous times? A man with no experience in government, hampered by his own record and notions of "anti-imperialism" and immediate independence for the Filipinos, and who moreover, seems to believe that preachments on peace are the proper weapons against strong armies and fleets--would it be wise, would it be safe to put the government into the keeping of such a man in the face of an impending world crisis? Would it not be wiser and safer to place Taft at the head of the <pb facs="5423969_2_0510.jpg" n="4"/>government, a man with backbone, broad American views, a wide experience in governmental affairs, and practical knowledge of the problems of the Far East, surpassed by that of no other American.</p>
   <p>The voters should take a look abroad before casting their ballots. They should remember that the management of our foreign relations is apt to be the most difficult and delicate part of the duties of the president, even under ordinary circumstances. A mistake at home may work great injury, but some day it may be repaired. A serious mistake in dealing with foreign powers is generally irreparable, and may entail a permanent loss of national rights or priceless advantages. We know we can trust Taft to maintain American rights and honor abroad. We also know that we cannot have the same confidence in Bryan. The safe course for the voter to take is to cast his ballot for the man who he knows can be trusted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
