<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-15">Apr. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Kittel Neresen Is Dead</title><title level="a" type="sub">He Was One of Chicago's Oldest Norwegian Settlers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-15">Apr. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">KITTEL NERESEN IS DEAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">He Was One of Chicago's Oldest Norwegian Settlers</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Kittel Neresen, one of the very oldest of the Norwegian settlers in Chicago, died last Saturday at the age of seventy-nine years and ten months.</p>
   <p>Neresen was born in Skien, Norway in 1820. He came to America in 1845 and settled at once in Chicago, and thus at his death he had been a resident of the city for fifty-five years.</p>
   <p>For many years he was one of the largest contractors in lathings here in the city, and Grand Pacific Hotel was among the many large buildings for which he held contracts. In the great Chicago fire, Neresen, or, as his business friends called him, Charlie Nelson, lost quite a fortune because a number of buildings which he had supplied with lathing burned without Mr. Neresen having received payment for the goods supplied, and the financial crisis following the fire caused many of the firms, the buildings of <pb facs="5423969_2_1165.jpg" n="2"/>which he had supplied with lathings, to go bankrupt. Before the fire, Neresen had about one hundred and fifty men at work. The losses suffered through the fire caused him to retire from the business.</p>
   <p>After the fire, Mr. Neresen opened a crockery business at the corner of Center and Grand Avenues, where he remained with his family for twenty-four years. His latest home was at 104 De Kalb Street. Fourteen years ago he relinquished his business on Grand Avenue and since then has not carried on any business at all. During the last ten years of his life he was blind. The deceased had considerable property including a large stone building on the corner of Desplaines and Ohio Streets, and three houses on Grand Avenue. In all he owned twelve houses.</p>
   <p>Mr. Neresen is survived by his widow, Mrs. Emma Neresen. The couple was married in Chicago, the wife having come from the same district in Norway as her husband. She has lived in Chicago since 1846. The couple had five children, all living.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
