<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-25">Nov. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Bosses and the People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-25">Nov. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">BOSSES AND THE PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democrats elected six members of the county board and will have the whip hand in the administration of county affairs for the next two years. They will have the power to block any measure involving any outlay of money and will have something to say as to the choice of the heads of the county institutions.</p>
   <p>If this is a bad thing the fault is with the Republican county convention. If the convention had nominated more good men and fewer unfit men, more of its nominees would have been elected. If it had chosen all its candidates from among the best material at hand the ticket would have won out from top to bottom by handsome average pluralities. But the convention placed the wishes of a few bosses above the wishes of the people and the welfare of the community. Assuming that anything and everything in the line of <pb facs="5423969_2_0219.jpg" n="2"/>political wrecks would be carried safely to shore on the presidential wave, the bosses dictated a ticket that, in the personnel of some of the candidates, was an insult to the people. This insult the people did not propose to brook, and gave the self-seeking bosses exactly the kind of drubbing they deserved.</p>
   <p>In a few months we shall be face to face with another election. The question of the make-up of the city ticket is already under discussion and plans are being formed by those who have been accustomed and permitted to lead. That is all right. The coming spring election will be one of exceptional importance. Good government was never more of an imperative necessity to Chicago than it is now. The best elements of the community are ready to place good men in charge; and they are strong enough to accomplish any purpose upon which they unite with earnest determination.</p>
   <p>But let the slate-makers remember that the people are not to be trifled with and that there will be no presidential election in the spring! Let them remember that if they do not select men who the people want, their ticket <pb facs="5423969_2_0220.jpg" n="3"/>will be buried.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
