<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-01-16">Jan. 16, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Hypocrisy Unveiled</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-01-16">Jan. 16, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">HYPOCRISY UNVEILED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chairman Berry, of the Senate Investigating Committee, says that thus far the following facts have been established by his committee:</p>
   <p>"That Mayor Harrison, Civil Service Commissioners Kraus, Winston, and Washburne, Corporation Counsel Thornton, also Chief Kipley, have deliberately and intentionally violated the civil service law and have nullified its provisions.</p>
   <p>"That the suits in the courts, ostensibly to test the law, were instigated by Mayor Harrison with the intention of keeping his administration free from the law.</p>
   <p>"That 181 men are on the police pay rolls illegally.</p>
   <p>"That twenty-eight men are on the police eligible list illegally.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"That eight men became experienced patrolmen illegally.</p>
   <p>"That despite the provisions of the law to the contrary, the civil service law has been juggled to oust Republicans and to favor Democrats.</p>
   <p>"That the police pension fund is used mainly for the maintenance of able-bodied ex-policemen capable of performing duty.</p>
   <p>"That it would be advisable to amend the civil service law and to place the chief of police under its provisions.</p>
   <p>"That the present civil service commission should resign.</p>
   <p>"That sufficient evidence has been collected to warrant action on the part of the State's attorney and the grand jury against the city officials named."</p>
   <p>These are grave charges; but however severe it may appear to outsiders, the <pb facs="5423969_2_0288.jpg" n="3"/>indictment is fully sustained by public opinion in Chicago, the assertions of a certain set of newspapers to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
   <p>The evasions and violations of the civil service law during the present administration have been most flagrant and notorious, but some of our daily papers have been careful to conceal the facts from the people. Contemporaries, who generally have very little in common, have found cordial co-operation in this respect a matter of easy accomplishment. Some of them carry Republican colors, others appear to be controlled by an unbridled hostility to the Republican party of Illinois as organized at present, and still others masquerade as independent, I-am-holier-than-thou organs, while Democratic and violently anti-Republican at heart. But whatever may be the particular shades of their respective cloaks of hypocrisy, they sang as with one voice about the saintly glory of that redoubtable reformer Adolph Kraus and those lesser lights of reform, "his honor" and "his sub-honor," the chief of police.</p>
   <p>Whether the investigation conducted by Berry's committee, with commendable <pb facs="5423969_2_0289.jpg" n="4"/>impartiality and thoroughness, will result in a lasting reform of present abuses remains to be seen. In any event, the unmasking of the whole contemptible business of hypocrisy is a great relief to the people of this city.</p>
   <p>This paper has always given the mayor credit for his frankness. He is not a civil service reformer and said so before his election. His policy has been in accordance with his pledges and utterances before election. When he made a clean sweep of the existing board and named three avowed spoilsmen as commissioners, he did only what had been expected--he put the oats into the keeping of the goats. Whether his administration and that of his chief of police involve punishable violations of the law, are questions for the State's attorney and the grand jury to decide. But he is not like Kraus and his colleagues, who are open to the charge of hypocrisy. Their shamming has disgusted all honest citizens, and all decent men and women are glad that Berry's committee has put a stop to the demoralizing business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
