<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-02-19">Feb. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Nelson Land Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0647</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0647.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-02-19">Feb. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE NELSON LAND BILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Senator Nelson has introduced a land bill which should go through both houses of Congress without delay or opposition, but there is a healthy prospect of a rather determined fight against it. This measure authorizes the president to withdraw lands for conservation purposes, such withdrawals to remain effective until revoked by the president or by act of Congress. The bill is offered as a substitute for the administration measure which was prepared by Secretary Ballinger, and which gave the withdrawal authority to the president and the Secretary of the Interior, subject to the approval of Congress.</p>
   <p>Every sound argument,and public sentiment will be found in favor of the bill offered by Senator Nelson. Congress is proverbially slow in acting upon such cases, and the Nelson bill authorizes the president to act in cases of emergency to prevent the public lands from being gobbled up by syndicates until such time as Congress may make disposition of the property <pb facs="5423969_2_0648.jpg" n="2"/>in question.</p>
   <p>Just before his retirement from the White House, Mr. Roosevelt withdrew from public entry several million acres of lands upon which it was believed the speculators were casting covetous eyes. Since then determined effort has been made to restore these lands to entry, but the public sentiment has been so strong against the proposition that Secretary Ballinger has been able to make but little headway in upsetting Mr. Roosevelt's order.</p>
   <p>Under the proposed plan of Senator Nelson, the president could make the withdrawal where conditions indicated the necessity of prompt action to prevent the lands from falling into the hands of speculators. The withdrawal would serve to prevent action until either the president or Congress could make an investigation. If the president or Congress became convinced that the withdrawal was in error, the presidential order could be revoked. In the meantime, the public's interest would be protected. Senator Nelson's bill offers an effective conservation of our national resources and its adoption would eliminate all danger of losing the fruits of the Roosevelt land policy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
