<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-07-18">July 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Milk for Infants</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0937</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0937.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-18">July 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">MILK FOR INFANTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Board of Health is making strenuous efforts to provide pure milk this summer, especially in districts with a high infant mortality. The inspectors of the Board are trying to co-operate with the milk dealers in these districts to see to it that the milk is kept free from all impurities until it reaches the mouth of the child. All milk stores must be absolutely clean and well ventilated, and cans and jars must be sterilized. The inspectors are also demanding that the milk be kept on ice from the moment it is brought into the city until it is delivered to the consumer.</p>
   <p>The greatest danger to the milk is frequently found in the homes where it is being used. Cleanliness is as necessary here as in the store of the milk dealer. But sanitary conditions are miserable in many homes, where ice is frequently an unknown luxury. Unfortunately, the inspectors can <pb facs="5423969_2_0938.jpg" n="2"/>do but little here; even though there were enough inspectors to reach all the homes, there would be little they could do.</p>
   <p>When milk is permitted to remain in an open can, it rapidly absorbs disease germs from the air. These germs multiply with incredible rapidity when the milk is lukewarm, but if the milk is cooled to 45 degrees Fahrenheit, the germs multiply very slowly. A bottle of clean, cold milk should be delivered daily at the doors of the consumer. This may easily be done through proper co-operation between the producers and the dealers. It will then be up to the housewife to see to it that the milk is kept pure until it is used. If the housewife neglects her duties in this matter, the milk will soon become unfit as food for infants. The milk must be kept in clean bottles or jars; it must not be exposed to the air longer than necessary, and it must be kept cool until used.</p>
   <p>As has been already mentioned, the Board of Health is doing everything <pb facs="5423969_2_0939.jpg" n="3"/>possible to get pure milk for the city's infants. But unless the mothers also do their part and comply with the rules of hygiene that have been discussed, the work of the Board will avail but little. It is not enough to bring the milk into the home in a state of purity; the milk must be kept clean in the homes, where, as a rule, it is kept from three to twelve hours, or even longer, before being used.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
