<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-19">Sept. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Municipal Court</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-19">Sept. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE MUNICIPAL COURT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While the charter proposal was completely defeated, the proposed changes in the law concerning the municipal court were adopted by quite a satisfactory majority. There was fear that in its defeat the charter proposal would pull the proposal concerning the municipal court to its grave also. During the discussion of the charter, little time was given to the court proposal, and the fear was that either it would be overlooked, or that many voters would vote no in the one matter as in the other. The outcome shows, however,that the voters had taken full notice of this matter, too.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0670.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The adopted changes in the law concerning the municipal court will strengthen that court and make its work easier. Litigations will be less expensive both for the plaintiff in a case and for the one who is being sued, and litigation will also take less time. And in the future, the police officers of Chicago may act as bailiffs in the municipal court. This is a great advantage, especially so far as criminal cases are concerned.</p>
   <p>The municipal courts have done excellent work during the brief time since they were first inaugurated. With the changes adopted at this past election, one may well expect still greater efficiency.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
