<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-23">Dec. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">More Delay for Dreyer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-23">Dec. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MORE DELAY FOR DREYER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"E. S. Dreyer is not to go to Joliet." This interesting bit of news caught the eye of the n as he took up his morning paper the other day.</p>
   <p>Was he startled? Not in the least. A shade of disgust spread over his features, but not a tinge of surprise. "Of course Dreyer is not going to Joliet," he said to himself. Who ever expected that he would be compelled to spend his Christmas at such a place! If he had been a poor man who had stolen a loaf of bread to still the cries of famished children, or an over-worked and underpaid clerk who, in order to be able to buy medicine for a sick wife, had borrowed a few cents from the drawer to be replaced next payday, or a forlorn widow who had snatched a rag from some secondhand store for her shivering baby--then all would have been different. Justice is a stern goddess to poor folk. The sacred rights of property must be defended and vindicated at all hazards when attacked by the lowly and weak among us. A poor man who, <pb facs="5423969_2_0690.jpg" n="2"/>unable to find work, returns to his starving family with five cents worth of stolen bread, or a mother who forgets everything else at the sight of her suffering baby--such people are dangerous to society. No mercy upon them! The law must take its course. To Joliet with them!</p>
   <p>But this view does not apply to a man like Dreyer, a former bank president, a leader in a great reform association, a social light, a pillar of the church, a trusted guardian of public money and the savings of poor people, a great and prominent citizen. To treat such a man as a common thief would not do. He never stooped so low as to steal a few pennies' worth of food or clothing. No, he helped himself to a public fund of upwards of three hundred thousand dollars and brought suffering into hundreds of homes, the savings of which had been entrusted to his honor. Such a man is no ordinary thief. While he is not, perhaps, entitled to take rank among the greatest embezzlers the country has produced, he has certainly stolen enough to secure him great consideration at the hands of justice.</p>
   <p>The majority of the people of Chicago look upon the Dreyer case in this light.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0691.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And who will say that they are not right? Who can say that the intricate technicalities of our criminal procedure do not destroy our boasted equality before the law? The great majority of the people are not familiar with the details of our complex system of justice, but they know how it works in practice. They know that petty transgressors of the law are convicted and sent to prison with due dispatch, while punishment is slow to overtake felons who wear fine clothes. Is it any wonder that they lose faith in the courts and our system of justice and are filled with rankling bitterness against society? Is anything else to be expected?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
