<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-11-05">Nov. 5, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Another School Wrangle</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-11-05">Nov. 5, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER SCHOOL WRANGLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a fresh case of friction in the School Board--who cares? Such quarrels have been so frequent for some time that they have almost ceased to attract any attention. They are expected as a matter of course and are taken by our good people as a sort of seasoning with their daily breakfast. They constitute the most essential part of one of the great "reforms" inaugurated by the present local adminstration. Harmony, unity, and greater efficiency in the management of our schools was the slogan of the clique of conspirators who ousted A. G. Lane and installed Dr. Andrews in his place as Superintendent of Schools of Chicago. "We must have harmony and unity", they said; and in order to obtain harmony and unity they replaced a superintendent who had demonstrated his ability to harmonize, by a gentleman who had made a national record as a disorganizer. "Greater efficiency is the paramount need of the hour", cried these spoilsmen, posing as disinterested citizens of the goody-goody order; and to attain this end they deposed one of the most experienced <pb facs="5423969_2_0253.jpg" n="2"/>superintendents in the country and intrusted the schools to the management of a gentleman who was known to be absolutely devoid of experience in the field of popular education.</p>
   <p>The result has been what it must be: constant friction, endless machinations and quarrels, and unsavory scandals. The recent unseemly controversy concerning the teaching forces of the evening schools is but a repetition of countless similar wrangles during the administration of the present superintendent.</p>
   <p>That morale and efficiency of our school system has been greatly impaired in consequence, is a self-evident fact. Our children are the sufferers, but the parents have only themselves to blame. They were fully aware of the conspiracy to use the schools as a stepladder for unscrupulous political ambitions; yet they placed the conspirators in power, and--what is even more to the point--continued them in power after they had done their worst. If our children suffer, the people must shoulder the entire responsibility. As they have sowed, so shall they reap.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
