<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-07-04">July 4, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">More Bungling</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-04">July 4, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">MORE BUNGLING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Secretary of the Treasury Franklin MacVeagh is in trouble once more. Recently, he came to Chicago and delivered a rather ill-considered speech on the tariff question. President Taft found it necessary to state that the views expressed by the Secretary of the Treasury did not reflect the attitude of the administration, but were Mr. MacVeagh's personal views.</p>
   <p>As is well known, the customs bureau is included in the Treasury Department, and the Secretary of the Treasury is the chief customs official. There ought to be reason to think, therefore, that the Secretary of the Treasury, when speaking on a pending tariff revision, will be in accord with the President and with the administration as a whole. MacVeagh, however, evidently had not found it necessary to consider this aspect of the matter. He opened his mouth to bless the country with his wisdom, and he was just as loose-mouthed as a number of other speakers who have appeared before the Civic Federation <pb facs="5423969_2_0128.jpg" n="2"/>in Chicago. Then came the reprimand by the President, which Mr. MacVeagh suffered in silence.</p>
   <p>Now Mr. MacVeagh has become guilty of an act of stupidity even graver than the one referred to. On his own responsibility, he has proposed a new law dealing with the tax on oleomargarine. Instead of the present tax of one quarter of a cent per pound on uncolored margarine and ten cents on colored margarine, Mr. MacVeagh proposed a tax of two cents per pound on each kind.</p>
   <p>Everybody knows that it is the colored oleo which is being used to deceive people: this kind of margarine is frequently sold as genuine butter. The producers of butter are not at all opposed to the manufacture and marketing of oleomargarine as long as it is sold under its right name; but they consider it unfair when the product is sold as butter, and this can only be done when the oleomargarine has been colored.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0129.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In order to put a stop to the deception that was going on, the tax on colored margarine was placed so high that it would not pay to deceive the consumers. The Secretary of the Treasury is well informed concerning these matters. According to information placed before the legislature in Wisconsin, MacVeagh's old firm has been engaging in a fraudulent business. He knows that a law like that he has proposed will have the effect of opening wide the door to fraud in the sale of oleomargarine.</p>
   <p>Congress would naturally believe, however, that the Secretary of the Treasury would not propose such a change in the law unless he was backed by the administration. To eliminate any doubt, the President was asked about the matter, and he stated that he had not heard anything about the proposal at all, and that he did not agree with the Secretary.</p>
   <p>A man who is Secretary of the Treasury of the United States ought to <pb facs="5423969_2_0130.jpg" n="4"/>be endowed with at least an average amount of common sense, and when he appears before the public in his official capacity he ought to follow the accepted rules of decency. It is not altogether easy to understand why Franklin MacVeagh was made Secretary of the Treasury; it is easy to see, however, that his departure from the office can only be a matter of time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
