<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-23">July 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Festive Occasion</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Dr. Rasmussen's Speech in Honor of Gina Krog]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0851</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0851.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-23">July 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A FESTIVE OCCASION</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Dr. Rasmussen's Speech in Honor of Gina Krog]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Gina Krog, and Norwegian Men and Women in Chicago! The honorable task of welcoming our guest of honor has fallen to me; it is also my task to thank our guest, Miss Krog, for the meeting tonight and for what she has done for the women's movement in Norway, and hence for the movement everywhere.</p>
   <p>The women's movement is a good cause, but it has not always been considered so, even by women themselves. Many women had been taught to fear the idea of feminine independence. In the early years of the women's movement, a misconception had been developed concerning the goal of the movement and the means of attaining that goal. People who had no knowledge of the movement itself knew that its proponents were "emancipated women", women with short hair, using men's boots in rainy weather. It was thought that the goal of the movement was the obliteration of femininity, of peace in the family, of family life itself; some serious, well-meaning women even created opposition <pb facs="5423969_2_0852.jpg" n="2"/>to the cause through their too mannish behavior. But then, it was not easy in those early days to be a member of the movement for the liberation of women.</p>
   <p>Silly imitators and "copyists" did their part to make the movement ridiculous. The term "emancipated" became a term of reproach, and those who were suspected, rightly or wrongly, of being emancipated were hounded and pointed at as examples of what a woman ought not to be. Many who had a budding love for the movement were frightened away and did not dare to follow. We owe great thanks to the courageous, sagacious, and faithful women who brought the ship--the women's cause--safely over rocks and breakers into a safe haven.</p>
   <p>Gima Krog and her comrades in arms have lightened the work for those who will succeed them. They have made life brighter for women; they have given women a broader field of endeavor, greater self-respect, and they have set before all of us a guiding example of courage and endurance.</p>
   <p>I shall not try to elucidate the cause itself; that has been done by our guest of honor. I shall merely mention, in passing, the work for the rights of <pb facs="5423969_2_0853.jpg" n="3"/>wives, the rights of the unwed, the women who were placed outside society, as it were, by the laws of even the most civilized nations. The unmarried women owe their present standing in society, their very raison d'etre, to the fight for the rights of women.</p>
   <p>The women's movement has raised the banner of work for women; it has found new lines of industry for women; it has put the spirit of modern times into the old time art and home industry; it has safeguarded the home, created better mothers, and perhaps men, too. The movement has also given rise to greater knowledge, and knowledge is power.</p>
   <p>When Camilla Collett published the Amtmandens Dottre (The Governor's Daughters) people started to wonder; some became wrathful, but everybody knew that something new was brewing. Aasta Hansteen stood in the breach and fought courageously, and all of Christiania--one might say all of Norway--hurled sarcasms and words of disdain at her, but she stood her ground without flinching. Now and then, someone stopped and listened to what she had to say, and people began to think that perhaps, after all, there was some sense in <pb facs="5423969_2_0854.jpg" n="4"/>what she was saying.</p>
   <p>I remember one evening when after having attended Ibsen's "A Doll's House," I left the theater in company with a friend of mine who was married. She repeated again and again Nora's reply, "I am first of all a human being, just the same as you! First of all a human being? Why, I never thought of that before." Later on the University [of Christiania] opened its portals to women, and Cecilie Thoresen entered, young and gifted--and feminine. I am sure she did not use men's boots in rainy weather. And thus the "fulfillment of the time" was launched.</p>
   <p>A handful of men and women came together one fine summer day twenty-five years ago and organized the first Women's Cause Society in Norway. This Society has accomplished so much that all the world admires Norway because of the work of this group.</p>
   <p>The first Women's Cause Society in America was organized in 1848. The American women worked persistently and faithfully for sixty years, but they have <pb facs="5423969_2_0855.jpg" n="5"/>thus far failed to reach their goal. Norway is the first sovereign nation to grant suffrage to women....and Gina Krog has been the soul of the movement; she has been at the helm; she has defied storms and adversity, and she has won.</p>
   <p>When the women of Norway go to the polls this coming fall for the first time, we express the wish that all the courage, the persistence, and the faithfulness displayed by the leaders in the women's movement may bear good fruit; that the result may be worthy of the great work. Let it be said that greatly did they sacrifice and greatly did they reap. Let all of us say: Surely it was for the best that things have taken the course we have witnessed. And all thanks are due to Gina Krog.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
