<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-01-20">Jan. 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Social Event]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-01-20">Jan. 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[SOCIAL EVENT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dedication of the new quarters of Normendenes Sangforening (Norwegian Male Chorus) in Wicker Park Hall was a gala event in every way. The hall was profusely decorated with American and Norwegian flags, paintings, portraits, works of sculpture, and caricatures. A truly varied assembly had gathered, including polar explorers, business and professional men, workingmen, embryo poets and authors, journalists, and parasites.</p>
   <p>The most prominent personages of the Chicago Norwegian colony were in attendance, including Hans Oftedal, Dr. Anders Doe, Dr. Wright, Leden (the polar explorer and lecturer), Dr. Meyer (former grand opera star of Bergen, Norway, and Stockholm, Sweden), A. Nokleby, Anton Malone, and many others.</p>
   <p>The evening's program, aside from numerous banquet speakers, included duets by Chas. Hansen and Henry Anderson, Erickson Frank, comedian, Mr. Howaldsen, and <pb facs="5423969_2_1623.jpg" n="2"/>Malone and Hansen in duets.</p>
   <p>An insistent demand for Ben Blessum brought that gentleman to his feet with such a eulogy of Dr. Doe that the doctor, officiating as toastmaster, finally rose and, when silence was restored, said, "there was a fire recently at Dunning and several inmates escaped; Ben Blessum is still at large." Dr. Doe is not a seeker after public acclaim, but at times he cannot escape it; on this occasion the acclamation came before his name could be mentioned.</p>
   <p>We heartily agree with every statement made by Blessum, especially in regard to the Norwegian male choruses to our efforts to preserve a knowledge of the Norwegian language and culture the Norwegian singers have contributed more than any other group. To quote Mr. Blessum, "It is wonderful that we have the language in its purity, but the old songs interpret the spirit of Norway in a manner that cannot be accomplished by the mere spoken word."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1624.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Doe called attention to another outstanding Norwegian, who is no longer in Chicago, but who won many friends and an enviable reputation as a journalist and author both during and after his residence in Chicago. The Doctor recommended that all Norwegians read the latest book from the pen of Waldemar Ager, now editor of Reform, at Eau Claire, Wisconsin. The book is entitled Conrad Walther Welde. Dr. Doe proposed a skoal for Ager and his good friend Blessum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
