<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-01-31">Jan. 31, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">A General View</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0929</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0929.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-01-31">Jan. 31, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">A GENERAL VIEW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I believe the young folks should not leave the farm before they are able to start in a business or at some other work they prefer, that is, if they are determined to leave the farm. They should stay at home and go to school as much as possible because the more education they get, the better it is for them and the better they will be fit [sic] for the business they want to undertake. You all know that a boy or girl that has no education will never succeed in any business.</p>
   <p>Some people think that the youth brought [up] on the farm should not leave it, but that is entirely wrong. The youth from the farm should do what they like best, the same as their city brethren. If one does not <pb facs="5423969_2_0930.jpg" n="2"/>like the farm he should not be obliged to stay there.</p>
   <p>Some say there is more pleasure in the towns and [the] cities than there is in the country. That may be true, in some cases, while again, there may be more pleasure in the country.</p>
   <p>There are also some people who seem to think that education is unnecessary for the farm youth. But that is not true. A farmer needs the same education as those that live in the city, and besides he must study the things that make him better fit to be a farmer.</p>
   <p>I believe the farm youth should be warned not to come to the city if they have no job in view here. In the city many of the young people are out of <pb facs="5423969_2_0931.jpg" n="3"/>work, and they find a hard time getting any. So why should the young people from the rural districts come to towns and cities and join the ranks of the unemployed?</p>
   <p>Here in Chicago the Scandinavian youth find it difficult to find work. Usually, because many of them speak little or no English. In large cities the youth have a hard time of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
