<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1918-07-26">July 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Peril of Hyperenthusiasm</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-07-26">July 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE PERIL OF HYPERENTHUSIASM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Let us have all the enthusiasm we can arouse for the war against autocracy, but let us try to make it both sane and just. It is not sane to shout about a victory until it has been won; it is not sane to celebrate a triumph while it is still in the making; it is not sane to brag about the invincible character of American soldiers in words that imply they will never fall back and never give up a position they have taken. It is not wise to speak as did Senator Lewis, the other day, when he declared:</p>
   <p>"American soldiers in France have again announced to the world that America knows no signal of retreat and cannot hear the call that takes an American flag to the rear. The American soldier does not know how to obey an order that would humiliate his flag. To every order to retire in the face of the <pb facs="5423969_2_0396.jpg" n="2"/>enemy his reply will be: 'We are going to counterattack.'"</p>
   <p>We must, of course, allow for hyperbole in the Senator's remarks, but the hyperbole is unfortunate. It implies that when French troops obeyed the order to retire in the face of the enemy--as they did at Verdun and on the Aisne--they were humiliating the flag of France. It implies that American soldiers are more foolhardy than intelligent, that their enthusiasm is as undisciplined as the Senator's and will not obey orders. It encourages the wholly untenable notion, for which a certain type of American mind is too receptive, that American troops are going to keep right on advancing until they reach Berlin; that they will never have to fall back as their comrades of France and Great Britain have often had to do.</p>
   <p>We are just as certain as the Senator that in the long run our boys will reach any goal that is necessary to complete victory, but we do not expect them to finish the long run without reverses. Hence, we will not be <pb facs="5423969_2_0397.jpg" n="3"/>discouraged if the American flag has to retreat or American soldiers retire in the face of the foe. We will see in such happenings merely the exercise of good sense and not the humiliation of anything or anybody. There are times when retreat is as necessary to ultimate victory as attack, and at such times the humiliating thing would be to lack the intelligence to do what is necessary. A retreat may be as an advance; the retreat from Mons was no less splendid than the battle of the Marne. It is a stupid thing, leading to painful disillusion and needless disappointment, to encourage the idea that the only valorous and effective fighting tactics are attack and counterattack.</p>
   <p>America is building a magnificent army in France; as much of it as is now on the firing line is demonstrating its spirit and courage in a manner that justifies our pride and our confidence. We are right in believing that eventually it will prove the decisive factor in overthrowing the armies of the Kaiser and establishing the peace of democracy on a secure <pb facs="5423969_2_0398.jpg" n="4"/>foundation. But let us not fall into the egregious error that has blinded our enemy by regarding our soldiers as supermen, in some extraordinary way immune from the vicissitudes of conflict through which their allies have had to pass on the rough road to success. That is neither sane nor just. It is unjust to our men and to their comrades.</p>
   <p>And let us view sanely and justly our victories. When we rejoice as we should, at the achievements of our armies, let us remember that French and Italian and British soldiers are fighting on the same firing line. And let us bear in mind just now that, taken at its utmost significance, the success of America and her allies in the recent battles has only proved that Germany cannot win the war by a military decision. It remains to be proved that we can.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
