<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1910-10-24">Oct. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Nordmaendenes Singing Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1694</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1694.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-10-24">Oct. 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NORDMAENDENES SINGING SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Nordmaendenes (The Norsemen's) Singing Society was organized by several professional Norwegian singers on October 30, 1870, and was originally known as the "Scandinavian Singing Society". But since only one Swede and no Danes belonged to the organization, the name was soon changed to its present form. The Swedes had previously organized the Freya Society, and the Danes the successful Harmonien (Harmony) Singing Club.</p>
   <p>The well-know landscape painter, Wilhelm Junge, was the organization's first president, and Johan Lindtuer the first director. Of the various directors, we mention a few of the most outstanding: A. Larson, August Uhe, and John W. Colberg, who served for twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>In 1872, the chorus was considered one of the finest in the city. One of its programs was arranged for Ole Bull in person. Bull was so impressed by the <pb facs="5423969_2_1695.jpg" n="2"/>quality and tone of the chorus that he donated a large sum of money to be used for founding a library for the Society.</p>
   <p>In 1876 the Society sang in the international chorus on the occasion of the opening of Humboldt Park.</p>
   <p>Succeeding Colberg as director was Christian Nilson, who was followed by Gusaf A. Carlson.</p>
   <p>Today, the Society has approximately one hundred and fifty members, with about fifty active singers. The library contains one thousand volumes of the finest and most modern literature.</p>
   <p>At first the Society met in the Kolamina Club on Green Street. It then met in a saloon; later, in a church; and, finally, from 1874 to 1878, it met in the <pb facs="5423969_2_1696.jpg" n="3"/>more presentable quarters at 107 Milwaukee Avenue. After moving its headquarters several times, the Society finally occupied its permanent home in Schoenhofen Hall, Ashland and Milwaukee Avenues. The Society has, it will be noted, occupied nearly every hall on Milwaukee Avenue from Green Street to Ashland Avenue in its forty years of activity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
