<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-07-11">July 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Charles Sethness</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-07-11">July 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES SETHNESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mayor has removed Charles Sethness, a member of the School Board. In view of this Scandia's editor wrote to Mayor Carter H. Harrison requesting that Mr. Sethness be reappointed. Below is the mayor's answer:</p>
   <p>"Mr. L. H. Lund, Editor Scandia.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir,</p>
   <p>"Replying to yours of recent date asking me to retain Mr. Charles O. Sethness as a member of the Board of Education, I do not see how I can comply with this request without self-stultification. If there were two members of the Board of Education in whose personal friendship I placed absolute confidence, and on whom I felt able to call for assistance in any emergency, they were Mr. Sethness and Mr. Rothman. Each of these gentlemen knew that I was pledged to use my influence to secure the re-election <pb facs="5423969_2_0068.jpg" n="2"/>of Mrs. Young as school superintendent. To each of them I had spoken in reference to the matter and had expressed my desire.</p>
   <p>"Because of their close personal and political relationship their voting against Mrs. Young's re-election affected me more than the action of all the other members combined. Had Mr. Sethness and Mr. Rothman seen me and expressed their inability or unwillingness to support Mrs. Young for re-election, they would have acted fairly with me. Instead, the first word which I had, came after action had been taken.</p>
   <p>"When Mr. Sethness and other members of the Board placed their resignations in my hands, they either did so in the belief that I had the right to ask for their resignations, or they did so with their "fingers crossed". If these resignations were given to me in the belief that they were legally ineffective, the gentlemen certainly showed small friendship to me, nor did they display what I should term high citizenship. If they <pb facs="5423969_2_0069.jpg" n="3"/>sincerely believed that I had the right to ask them to resign and later on learned that the resignations were illegal, I feel that having signed them in good faith, they were ethically bound to stand by them.</p>
   <p>"I regret exceedingly that I am forced to take the action which I am obliged to take relative to Mr. Sethness. I have no personal ill feeling towards him, but in self-respect I cannot persuade myself that his appointment, from my standpoint, would be desirable.</p>
   <p>"Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>"Carter H. Harrison,</p>
   <p>"Mayor."</p>
   <p>And now, of all things, Mr. Harrison has appointed Mrs. Charles Sethness to succeed her husband! Mrs. Sethness is very friendly to Mrs. Young; so that's that.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
