<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-12-19">Dec. 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Victory for Political Honesty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-12-19">Dec. 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY FOR POLITICAL HONESTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The verdict in the election frauds case against John J. Hanrahan and Patrick Ferris is sustained by public opinion in the Seventeenth Ward, whose citizens for years have suffered at the hands of unscrupulous political gangs of both parties. In the opinion of the honest people of the Ward, it is none too severe. Their only regret is that the head gangsters and boss rascals thus far have escaped the clutches of the law. They do not regret that Mr. Harrison's administration must drop Mr. Patrick Ferris from the pay rolls because of the prospective absence of that gentleman. They know that Maurice O'Connor, his political sponsor, backer, and boss, will remain to support the administration and draw his salary.</p>
   <p>The outcome of this case is a great victory for the decent people of the Seventeenth Ward, and especially for Alderman Walsh, Joseph A. O'Donnell, and other <pb facs="5423969_2_0296.jpg" n="2"/>citizens who have spent their time and money in securing evidence and assisting the prosecution in other ways. There is reason to hope that it will teach those political rascals of the Ward, who still have not been indicted and convicted, a wholesome lesson, and that they will remain in hiding in their holes in the future--at least for some time.</p>
   <p>But the good effects of this victory for political honesty and decency are not limited by ward boundaries but extend throughout the city. This conviction will strike terror in all political heelers and thugs in Chicago: those who plot ballot frauds as well as those who execute them. The repeated failures of all previous attempts to punish them for their crimes have emboldened them and has taught them to believe that do whatever they might, they will go scot free. The conviction of Hanrahan and Ferris will teach them a lesson. It has shown that the ballot-box stuffers and the tally-sheet forgers can be reached by the law, when the administration of the laws is vested in honest and capable men.</p>
   <p>State's Attorney Deneen and his able, fearless assistant, Mr. Barnes, have <pb facs="5423969_2_0297.jpg" n="3"/>made an enviable record for themselves in this instance and have set the pace for their successors. Mr. Deneen's predecessor had not only a more sensational, but also a stronger case against certain members of the "Market Street Gang" two years ago, but for some reason failed to secure a conviction. His failure was a distinct encouragement to thuggery and a severe blow to all friends of honest elections. The success of Mr. Deneen in the Seventeenth Ward election frauds case has vindicated the honor of the State's Attorney's office and has freed it from the legacy of suspicion left by the administration of Mr. Kern.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
