<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-10">Aug. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Peace and Disarmament]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-10">Aug. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[PEACE AND DISARMAMENT]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Apropos of peace, our daily press throughout the world is printing articles on peace while the nations are spending enormous sums for armaments and crying for more funds to make more instruments of destruction. Can there be the least shadow of a doubt as to what the result would be if all nations were to gather in a peace conference in which peace and disarmament were to be promoted? Is it difficult to foretell the reaction on the part of the manufacturers of cannon and rifle, of powder and other explosives, on the part of monarchs whose thrones rest on a brutal base of bayonets, or on the part of the financial giants whose coffers are filled to overflowing with the blood-money of wars? Would it be difficult to imagine the crash resulting from a decision favoring peace and disarmament? Taking the initiative in such a movement would be a grander gesture by ten thousand times than an appropriation of many millions for war and destruction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0497.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The amount spent for one lone battleship would build hundreds of schools and provide work for thousands of craftsmen, thereby helping not only the worker but his family, the grocer, the butcher, the baker, other merchants, the farmer, and the manufacturer. Would it not be ideal if we could, by some method, arrange the social setup of the world so that industry and happiness would replace war and desolation? Sherman was right; war is hell.'</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
