<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-05">Aug. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Women's Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0833</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0833.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-05">Aug. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN WOMEN'S FEDERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Women's Federation has finished its first year of activity and is beginning its second year full of courage. The Federation received an unexpectedly large support from the very beginning. Every meeting has been well attended, and the interest has been keen. Women have obtained the right to vote; it is evident that they need to study the issues which are of importance for the welfare of the city.</p>
   <p>The Federation has contracted various political parties in the city. Representatives of these parties have been present at meetings of the Federation, giving information concerning the work and the objectives of their respective programs, as related to the development of the city.</p>
   <p>The Federation has limited its study and its work to the city for the present. It is the needs of the city which are closest to the house and home also, and which touches most vitally the life of the family as whole.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0834.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Federation has an excellent department for the study of home economics. Food-stuffs are being investigated; deputies are being sent to watch the places of sale for groceries and meats.</p>
   <p>Representatives have also visited the Bureau of Immigration under which the Federal Employment Bureau is trying in order to gain information and help relative to employment for women.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian language, too, has received its due. Two evenings were set aside for Norwegian lectures; also a social with a dramatic production feature as well as singing and dancing was presented.</p>
   <p>The Women's Federation has also obtained its own division of the Red Cross, an invitation is extended to all Norwegian women whether members of the Federation or not, to co-operate. The division of the Red Cross is under the Council of National Defence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0835.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The new paper of the Federation, The Bulletin, will be sent to all the members free of charge. On the whole it may be said that membership in the Federation is not a matter of money. The fee is so low that anyone will be able to join. There are at present 1,500 members, and there is room for many more. By working together in unity we shall be able to accomplish that which, singly, we could not touch.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
