<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-09-07">Sept. 7, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Peace Jubilee</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-09-07">Sept. 7, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEACE JUBILEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a brief outline of the character and features of the national peace jubilee, Mr. Charles Truax, chairman of the general committee, says in part:</p>
   <p>"Our present arrangements provide for general thanksgiving services to be held in all the churches throughout the city on Sunday, October 16. On the afternoon of the same day it is proposed to give sacred open-air concerts in the various parks. Monday will be devoted to private receptions of such guests as may arrive in the city on that day. The two days following will be devoted to oratory, music, and a grand street reception or ovation to the President, our distinguished guests, and returning soldiers. This ovation will be in the nature of a parade. It is intended that the streets will be elaborately decorated, and if the necessary money is provided, a street display will be <pb facs="5423969_2_0573.jpg" n="2"/>presented that will outrival any decorations ever before produced.</p>
   <p>"The proposed celebration is one of peace and not of victory, and as a consequence such features as pertain more to Fourth of July celebrations and carnivals would be somewhat out of place. The committee is aiming to prepare such a program as will dignify and exalt the reputation of our city, rather than to furnish to the people two days of simple amusement. Reception, oratory, and music should, in the minds of the committee, form the distinctive features, rather than commercial parades, firecrackers, and fireworks. I admit that the Sunday evening union services to be held in the Auditorium under the management of Dr. H. W. Thomas, the banquet to be given in honor of our guests, and the benefit ball to be given in aid of the Army and Navy League, can only be participated in by a few. What we earnestly desire is light upon this subject, and suggestions are in order. It was suggested at the meeting of the committee today that the cycling fraternity be invited to present a magnificent parade on wheels, and it is possible that this feature will be adopted, and that such a parade in the evening will be rendered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0574.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I believe the committee, after the close of the jubilee services, and while the city is decorated, would be willing to devote an evening to a grand display of fireworks, to take place in various parts of the city, but the necessary funds are not in sight. Our committee desires to fairly represent all classes of people, and we believe that the proposed festivities should be of such a character that all the people, without regard to occupation or station, might participate and feel that they were directly interested in the demonstration."</p>
   <p>It will be a surprise to the people of Chicago and the country at large to learn that a body of brainy, intelligent men could be so radically mistaken as to the real character of a vast undertaking, the management of which has been entrusted to their hands. If the peace societies of the land, reinforced with all the other peace-at-any-price forces who so persistently opposed the war for Cuban liberation, were to arrange a jubilee, they would accept the statement of Mr. Truax as an adequate expression of the character and purpose of their enterprise. But history has not been made according to their notions during <pb facs="5423969_2_0575.jpg" n="4"/>these eventful summer months. The people did not listen to their piping voices, but drowned them in a tremendous thunder of righteous indignation. The American people willed the war and made it, not to kill, but to rescue a people threatened with extinction; not to destroy, but to up-build; not to enslave, but to set free. They were ready for heavy sacrifices, but they were also determined to pursue the war at any cost until its high purpose should have been accomplished. They rejoice in the brevity of the contest and the comparatively light sacrifices in blood and treasure that they have been called upon to make, and they hail the return of peace with a deep sense of gratification. But it is not peace they celebrate, it is victory, because victory means that the great task of the nation has been fulfilled and the lofty aim of the struggle realized, and because it also means that this nation has entered upon a new epoch in its history. If we are to celebrate peace and nothing else, the first number on the program should be some sort of emphatic denunciation of ourselves for breaking this peace; for such a jubilee would be a rebuke to the nation for engaging in the war, besides belittling the contest itself, as well as the heroism and valor of our brave boys on land and sea.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0576.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>No, when Mr. Truax says:</p>
   <p>"The proposed celebration is one of peace and not of victory," he is wrong. He may speak for himself and the committee, but he does not speak for the people.</p>
   <p>There is probably no danger that the jubilee shall be robbed of its true character. The people who made the war and sent their sons to the camps and battlefields will celebrate the glorious fulfillment of their aim--they will celebrate victory and peace. No committee, be it ever so ornamental, can stem the tide of national sentiment or dictate to the people what they shall feel and think these glorious days; no program, however well arranged, can make the popular pulse slacken its beats in order to suit mugwumpish notions. But there is reason to fear that the complete success of the jubilee may be marred. The narrow ideas of the committee as to the true character of the jubilee have naturally led to the adoption of a program projected along narrow lines. A jubilee begotten in this spirit must needs be exclusive--arranged for the special benefit of a select few. The common people can have no part in it, <pb facs="5423969_2_0577.jpg" n="6"/>except as spectators, and even such crumbs will fall to the lot of but a few. The majority will be made to feel that while they were permitted to do the fighting and win the victories, the glory of victorious peace is not for them. The Inter-Ocean has sounded a timely warning in demanding that the people be given a chance. The Skandinaven joins its contemporary in this demand, and knows that in so doing it expresses the unanimous sentiment of its large constituency.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
