<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-07-13">July 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Is America a Free Country?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-07-13">July 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">IS AMERICA A FREE COUNTRY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>America cannot be justly called a free country as long as women do not have the right to vote. What attitude is taken in this so-called land of liberty as far as women are concerned? Do we find liberty and human rights for them? The answer must be in the negative.</p>
   <p>America cannot be considered a free country as long as one-half of the people living there are being deprived of the most fundamental individual rights. Women produce life; they nurse life; they support everything that is good, and fight against the evils of society in order to prevent the deterioration of the race. Women are strongly represented in the work of the church, in the various benevolences, in everything which promotes good. But now we meet the strangest of all strange phenomena: when the question arises of writing laws, of governing and guiding the society which women keep alive through their mother love, then they are disregarded and excluded as incompetent. Here it is only the male half of the world that is allowed <pb facs="5423969_2_0869.jpg" n="2"/>to take part, while the female half--although carrying the heavier burdens--is shoved aside and treated as useless.</p>
   <p>Now consider the case of the churches. Here women are tireless in their work for advancement. But what about the annual business meeting? What about inter-congregational conferences? The women are not there; they are not elected as delegates. What a shame! Imagine how much a woman delegate would have to tell her sisters in the congregation about the things heard and seen at the annual business meeting! Her report would interest the ladies, and stimulate them to new exertions for the new year. But watch the ministers as they issue their calls! If it be a matter of business leadership, men are always chosen. But if the issue involves raising money for the work, or preparing for a supper or other festivity--or even if it is the question of cleaning the church--then the women are well remembered.</p>
   <p>Where are the women on election day when the fate of the community is to be decided? We see crowds of twenty-one-year-old boys whose greatest ability is that of emitting clouds of smoke from pipe or cigar; but the intelligent, experienced mothers we do not see. You will say, perhaps, "They are staying <pb facs="5423969_2_0870.jpg" n="3"/>at home". But why are they staying at home on a day of such importance? Because the men in their egotism and folly want them to stay home, in spite of the fact that for fifty-five years women in this country have been fighting for permission to help in keeping the community from decaying politically.</p>
   <p>From this it can be clearly seen how greatly the men are lacking in understanding. The women realize that their influence would renovate our Social order, now soiled through and through; but the men object to this influence; they cannot see that anything is wrong in society.</p>
   <p>How long will the patience of the women last? Is the day coming when they, too, will go on strike? Perhaps.</p>
   <p>See how the "New Norway" is flowering. What is the reason? Simply this: the influence of the women has come to be felt in all walks of life; remember, in Norway women received their voting rights twelve years ago. Another happy country in Europe is Finland. Why? Because there the word "liberty" has been given its true interpretation: equal rights and equal duties for women and men. When will America reach a similar state of liberty?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
