<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-11">July 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Mason and His Sons</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-11">July 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MASON AND HIS SONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Congressman William E. Mason of Illinois is to be sure, not a man of outstanding ability. No one has accused him of such. Neither as senator nor as congressman has he brought about accomplishments to preserve his name for the generations to come, unless it be all the nonsense that has been uttered by him from time to time. Now in his old age Billy has become a pacifist and for this reason he found it necessary to tear himself away from his duties in Washington in order to get a chance to give vent to his wisdom at the blessed meeting which has been held in Chicago of late.</p>
   <p>Billy Mason does not like the conscription act; the act is unjust, he holds, and of course we do not begrudge him his right to an opinion. His arguments, however, are quite amusing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0477.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I have two sons," says Mr. Mason,"one wanted to go to war, the other not. But this darned conscription law keeps at home the one who wanted to go to war while the other one has to go to France."</p>
   <p>It is unnecessary, of course, to inform our readers that the conscription act does not prevent Mr. Mason's war liking son to go to France. He has had the most beautiful chance to satisfy his desire, simply by joining the army or the navy. Since, however, he has not taken advantage of this chance, we may assume that the reason is found in sharing with his father the desire for a life in peaceful Illinois.</p>
   <p>If Mr. Mason is aiming for the White House, he had better brush up his argumentation. Unless he does, we fear his prospects are none too bright.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
