<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1890-10-03">Oct. 3, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the Republican Politicians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1890-10-03">Oct. 3, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE REPUBLICAN POLITICIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Any one who is acquainted with the Scandinavians of the West will know that in every State they have uniformly been found almost solidly massed in the Republican ranks at every election. The exceptions are so few as to prove the rule only. This is a fact of which we are proud, and for which the Skandinaven makes bold to take its share of credit. We also assert that the Scandinavians are Republicans from principle and not for office or boodle. Nor do they believe that the consideration of nationality should play any important part in politics where all are citizens of a common country, equally sharing its privileges and amenable to its laws. But the leading politicians themselves have studiously cultivated this feeling of nationality by appealing to it, and holding out inducements before elections which often have been forgotten or ignored afterwards. In this way, the nationality consideration has been dragged into our politics and must henceforth be taken into account with some care. For broken promises have produced an irritation in some quarters which, if continued, threaten to obscure the consideration of party principles, and raise the question of nationality to a dangerous place, or at least of an undue importance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Michigan, the Scandinavians have not been numerous enough to attain any large share in the management of public affairs, but still strong enough to be duly appreciated when votes are desired, and of considerable importance when Republican majorities are counted. For the reason above stated, we regret that we must record the fact that the Democratic party in Michigan has outstripped the Republicans in offering a prominent place on the State ticket to a Scandinavian. Democratic shrewdness may by this method reap the fruits of the seed sown by unwise and faithless Republicans.</p>
   <p>We regret also to say that we think it is about time this lesson was administered not only in Michigan, but also in Minnesota and Illinois.</p>
   <p>The Democrats have not only chosen a Scandinavian, but a man with both business and personal qualifications, which make him eminently qualified for the position, and fully the equal, if not the superior, of his opponent on the Republican ticket. Even with no grudge from past disappointments, the Scandinavian voters might well be pardoned, if pride <pb facs="5423969_2_0367.jpg" n="3"/>and satisfaction in the recognition of a worthy countryman should lead them to cast their votes for him without regard to party allegience, especially in an election where national issues are understood to be less prominently involved.</p>
   <p>To insure that the Republican leaders of Michigan more fully comprehend what we mean, and to give them an insight into to the feelings which prevail in some places among the Scandinavians, we will give the substance of a communication from a creditable source, and which is only one of several of the same nature, detailing circumstances and actions which can hardly fail to allienate a large number of voters from the party in the approaching election.</p>
   <p>The communication referred to is from northern Michigan, and is in substance as follows: "In the election of 1888, the Scandinavians were, as usual, faithful to the Republican party. With our gray hats on, we marched in a procession night after night, and shouted ourselves hoarse for 'Harrison and protection,' while the bread-and-butter politicians and office seekers <pb facs="5423969_2_0368.jpg" n="4"/>stood on the street corners, rubbing their hands in glee, and encouraged us with such friendly expressions as 'that's right boys!'-'the Scandinavians are in line'--'faithful as ever,' etc. The result of the election is well known. We were then told that nothing was too good for the Scandinavians. The fruits of victory were to be distributed, and in the council of the party it was determined that the deputy collectorship should fall to Ishpeming, and of course, a Scandinavian would get this 'plum'. We, therefore, were determined to present the name of Andrew Sandberg, a Swede. He is in every way an honorable and competent man. When Mr. Stone of Detroit had been appointed collector, Mr. Sandberg went to work and got the recommendations and endorsements of the prominent Republicans of the district and forwarded his application to the proper authority. He was so sure of the appointment that he already began to look for suitable office accommodation, forgetting in his ignorance the old adage that"it is imprudent to sell the skin until you have shot the bear.“ Mr. Sandberg soon received word from the collector that he wished to see him in Detroit. On his arrival there, Mr. Sandberg was shown letters from some of the very persons who had recommended him and indorsed his application, but who now <pb facs="5423969_2_0369.jpg" n="5"/>opposed his appointment, giving as a reason the fact that the Scandinavians were such faithful Republicans that they needed no such encouragement.</p>
   <p>"The office was consequently given to another nationality whose fickleness had made it necessary to strenghten their Republicanism by substantial recognition. But to show that gratitude was not a feeling entirely foreign to the Republican breast, Mr. Sandberg was graciously offered an inferior clerkship in the office he sought with the magnificent salary of $500."</p>
   <p>(Continued next issue).</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0370.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We shall not pursue this unpleasant theme farther. Much might be said on all sides of it and all around it. We have reason to believe that the above account is substantially correct. And we may add that occurrences very similar are not unknown here in Illinois and other States than in Michigan. We will say in conclusion that while the leading politicians, themselves, are largely responsible for bringing the consideration of nationality into politics, they should also be held strictly accountable for the results of their ill-advised policy. We should regret to see the Republican party defeated in Michigan, or in Illinois, and most of all do we regret to see that end accomplished by a defection of the Scandinavians, but we are by no means disposed to find fault with the voter whose pride in nationality might lead him to resent the slight put upon him by the perfidy of political machinists. We rather think such a lesson would be wholesome discipline, and an element in our political education quite suited to the <pb facs="5423969_2_0371.jpg" n="7"/>times. And it would do the Republican party substantial good if the leading politicians in every State in the Union would give some careful thought to these matters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
