<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-01">Nov. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Re-Elect Peter B. Olsen to the Legislature</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-01">Nov. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">RE-ELECT PETER B. OLSEN TO THE LEGISLATURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Peter B. Olsen has represented the Eleventh Senatorial District in the legislature during the past two years. He is now a candidate for re-election. The District comprises Wards Fourteen, Twenty-seven, Twenty-eight and the western half of Ward Fifteen. A large number of Scandinavians live in the District, so it is quite natural that one of its representatives in the state legislature should be a Scandinavian. Mr. Olsen was born in Christiania, Norway, and came to Chicago in 1872. During the following sixteen years he was associated with the Skandinaven in various capacities, and during the past thirteen years has been connected with the offices of the County Recorder and the County Clerk here.</p>
   <p>Mr. Olsen is one of the old settlers in Ward Fifteen where he has taken a lively part in politics--always as a Republican. His record during the past <pb facs="5423969_2_0083.jpg" n="2"/>legislative session shows that he was ever ready to support proposals in the interest of the workers and the taxpayers. Thus it is due to his energetic exertions that the legislature adopted a law changing the term of service of four Superior Court judges in Cook County, whereby $150,000 was saved--the cost of the special election for the four judges, which would have been necessary last fall if Mr. Olsen's motion had not been adopted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Olsen was also a diligent worker in behalf of laws in which the labor unions were interested; among these was an important change in the cigar makers' "Blue Label Law".</p>
   <p>Many proposals for new laws will be considered by the legislature next winter. The re-election of an honest, tried man such as Mr. Peter Olsen will unquestionably be of great benefit to the state as well as to the Eleventh District which he represents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
