<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-04-15">Apr. 15, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[Lincoln as a Prophet]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0821</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0821.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-04-15">Apr. 15, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[LINCOLN AS A PROPHET]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Lincoln as a prophet" is the title of an article signed "F.N.S." which appears in an editorial in one of our monthly magazines. The writer says in part:</p>
   <p>"One of the last public statements of Abraham Lincoln--one which the orators of that great commercial agency called the Republican party are careful always to suppress--one which ought long ago to have been recognized before the party machine became the instrument of its present commercial proprietors--is well worth the careful thought of all patriotic citizens. It is a prophecy whose prophetic truth is now our sorrow. It is worthy of a place beside the prophetic warnings of George Washington against the dangers of partisan blindness and foreign influences. Lincoln's words, in brief, were as follows:</p>
   <p>'It has been indeed a trying hour for the republic; but I see in the future <pb facs="5423969_2_0822.jpg" n="2"/>a crisis that unnerves me and causes me to tremble for the safety of my country.</p>
   <p>'As a result of the war, corporations have been enthroned and an era of corruption in high places will follow, and the money power of the country will attempt to prolong its reign by working upon the prejudice of the people until all wealth is aggregated into a few hands, and the republic destroyed.</p>
   <p>'I feel at this moment more anxiety for the safety of my country than ever before, even in the midst of war. God grant that my suspicions may be groundless.'"</p>
   <p>F.N.S. concludes by saying:</p>
   <p>"Were Abraham Lincoln now alive...., he would feel that his suspicions were by no means groundless."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0823.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every good citizen will admit that such a statement, coming from the greatest of all Americans, is "worthy of a place beside the prophetic warnings of George Washington." In the opinion of Skandinaven, the prophecy is invested with surpassing interest and should be exhibited in the proper historical frame.</p>
   <p>F.N.S., having made use of the statement, will not refuse to "frame" it. The people are entitled to know the date of the alleged statement and the precise circumstances under which it was made. Is it part of a speech, or a conversation, and if so, when and where was the speech made, or did the conversation occur? Or, is it a quotation from a diary? If so, what date does it bear, and where is the original to be found?</p>
   <p>It will not be denied that these queries are proper and justified from any and every point of view, and that they only call for facts which the people should know and have a right to demand. F.N.S., it is hoped,will furnish a prompt, complete and satisfactory answer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
