<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[New Steamship Line]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[NEW STEAMSHIP LINE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Birger Osland, who has assumed the responsibility of placing Norwegian-American Steamship Line shares in Chicago, reports that the shares are meeting with a ready sale; in fact, unsolicited requests are coming in regularly. Dauchert Richter, for instance, phoned to ask whether shares were still available, and purchased five with the promise of buying more.</p>
   <p>The purchasers are not only our own Norwegians, but Swedes and Danes are also showing great interest and faith in the future of this Line. After thorough investigation, H. P. Nelson, owner of the huge piano factory on Kedzie and Chicago Avenues, bought fifty shares for his son, Gerhard, and is buying another fifty shares to present to his father in Skaane, Sweden.</p>
   <p>That an investment in the new Norwegian-American Line will be sound and profitable can readily be seen by examining statistics covering passenger and freight traffic between Norway and the United States, the bulk of which will naturally be handled by our own Line.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1085.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the past ten years, there has been an average of twenty thousand immigrants entering this country, with approximately eight thousand other east and west passengers (tourists) per year. Exports to Norway during the 1905-09 period increased from eight and one-third million crowns to seventeen and one-half million per year, and 1910 will show the greatest increase in history. Since 1905, imports from Norway have increased from seventeen million crowns to over twenty-six million, with 1910 prospects still larger. In terms of weight, the tonnage carried between the two countries is well above 160,000 tons per year.</p>
   <p>The board of directors and officers of the Line includes several prominent American citizens of Norwegian birth: Fred Eugen; I. L. Grondal, Seattle, Washington; A. Ueland, attorney, Minneapolis, Minnesota; H. G. Haugan, banker, Chicago; E. T. Christensen, treasurer of the Line, New York City; and E. H. Hobe, consul, St. Paul, Minnesota. In Chicago the N. A. L. shares are on sale at the office of Skandinaven, H. G. Haugan, State Bank of Chicago, and Birger Osland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1086.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There are two good reasons for the quick sales of stock in the new transatlantic line: One is pecuniary gain and the other is pride in our own business enterprise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
