<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-12">Sept. 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Children Work Like Slaves in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-12">Sept. 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN WORK LIKE SLAVES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many are kept home from school and made to work hard far into the night in order to earn the necessities of life. When making a tour through the slum districts, one finds that, in spite of all regulations and inspectors, child labor is going on in Chicago; in many cases the children are kept practically as slaves. This does not often happen in factories or shops, and for this reason the practice may not come into conflict with the letter of the law. But in hundreds of homes on the south side, the west side, the north side, and the northwest side, child labor is going on, and almost invariably, the parents who thus are making life a burden for the poor little ones are immigrants from the south and east of Europe.</p>
   <p>Children nine years of age, and frequently even younger, are put to work. True, they have no foreman to oversee their work but in spite of this, the work is destructive to health. An angry look, repeated beatings, and even worse maltreatment at the hands of an angry mother keep the children at work just as steadily as any adult working in an ordinary shop. During the summer months, when the children are home <pb facs="5423969_2_0675.jpg" n="2"/>from school, this child labor in the homes is most destructive, and also more noticeable than during the winter months. But the work does not stop at the opening of school in the fall. In some cases, the children may be kept at home for long periods under various kinds of excuses on the part of the parents. At other times the mother may simply inform the school principal that she needs the child to help her earn the daily bread. Those who go to school off and on have to work so much later in the evening to retrieve the time wasted by going to school.</p>
   <p>Settlement workers and the public inspectors have done much to do away with this kind of child slavery, but many of the parents involved keep almost constantly on the move, and this makes effective inspection difficult. And they frequently pick for dwelling places dark basements and other quarters, not suitable for human habitation. In some cases the home may be completely underground, making child slavery nearly impossible to detect. The tales of tired fingers and heavy hurting eyes may forever be hidden to the outer world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0676.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This child labor in the homes bring before us again and again the ever recurrent problem of the sweat shop. The so-called "child finisher" was banned from the shops; instead the child finisher has been set to work as the mother's assistant at home. Travelling any morning between seven and nine o'clock through the district between Harrison Street and 18th Stree (north-south) and between the river and Center Street (east-west), one can see hundreds of women, mostly Italians and Poles, carrying great bundles of clothing on their shoulders, containing articles to be finished in the homes. Similar sights in other localities, involving other nationalities,may be met by the investigator. Frequently the women are accompanied by children less than twelve years of age, helping their mothers to carry the bundles. Frequently these bundles are heavy enough to form loads for grown men, and one may notice how the child is getting stoop-shouldered and pressed together, as it were, under the heavy burden, while staggering along on weary feet.</p>
   <p>A visit to the homes of these women and children discloses miserable conditions. The pay given these "finishers" is low beyond imagination.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0677.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Even when assisted by the children, the income per day for one of these families is rarely more than 75 cents.</p>
   <p>The manner of living in these families is then in accordance with the income. There is no time for cooking, and even the cold food is frequently poor in quality and dirty. Many children become mental and physical wrecks before they have passed school age. And often the cause of the miserable conditions may be traced to the fact that the father is using for liquor the money which might have built up a decent home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
