<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">Jan. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">"Fat and Forty"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">Jan. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">"FAT AND FORTY"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Scandia</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: A more unfair, unjust, and unwarranted attack on our Norwegian "fat and forty" sisters is unimaginable. The ladies in question are two keenly gifted women who, having an uncanny knack of mimicking the quaint dialect of Norwegian-Americans, have evolved a series of amusing sketches. Anyone taking offense at such innocent satire, as these "horrible" examples present, must be "lackink" in any artistic sense or discrimination. The presentations are at all times for entertainment, and if the yokels are to restrain all spontaneous and original effort, excepting that which one can only label propaganda, then the future of all art is indeed dark.</p>
   <p>The art of the dialect story or monologue has rather an illustrious past in our theatrical history. Who is not familiar with those famous dialect comedians, Weber and Field? If one or two take offense at their fun, how many <pb facs="5423969_2_1376.jpg" n="2"/>thousands enjoy their efforts. Then there are Vesta Victoria, Harry Sander, and innumerable others.</p>
   <p>These sisters are absolutely original in their work, and though their creations are not in any way subtle, one derives much pleasure from them. As to their pulchritude, I know nothing of their attempt at posing as Ziegfeldian beauties.</p>
   <p>Many a corner in the hinterland has been lit up by their cheer. Instead of a galopade a la Lydia Pinkham, I would suggest a western lecture tour by Hil, Menchen or Clarence Darrow.</p>
   <p>Sincerely yours, H. Jacob Zimmerman</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
