<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-03-24">Mar. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian National Lutheran Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-03-24">Mar. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN NATIONAL LUTHERAN COUNCIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian National Lutheran Council passed, after long debate, the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We acknowledge with grateful hearts that in spite of the sacrifice and suffering of war, the many problems of readjustment, and the evident social, political, and religious unrest, the people of our country are bountifully blessed with the necessities, and even the luxuries of life, and our nation is enjoying peace and prosperity; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We further acknowledge that our Lutheran Church in the United States and Canada, standing firmly upon the unshakable rock of Holy Scripture, is at present favored as our Church of no other land in opportunity, in resources, in man power, and in spiritual strength; and</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0382.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Whereas, We have heard with sad and bleeding hearts of the indescribable suffering and distress of our starving and destitute fellow believers in Europe, of the struggle now raging between order and anarchy, between atheism and Christianity; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We fully believe that only by effective and speedy relief of the most dire need, by the support of order and faith through the strengthening of the followers of Christ and the work of His Church, as well as by the old Gospel preached and practised in all its fullness can there be any hope of rescuing distressed Europe from political and spiritual ruin; be it resolved</p>
   <p>"That we, Synod Presidents, Editors, Pastors, leaders of young people's, laymen's, and women's work, state and district chairmen, etc., etc., called together by the National Lutheran Council to launch the Lutheran World <pb facs="5423969_2_0383.jpg" n="3"/>Service Campaign for the sum of $1,800,000 for the relief of our fellow believers in Europe, for the strengthening and reconstructing of their churches, and for the saving of a vast foreign missions work from disintegration, assembled at the Morrison Hotel, Chicago, March 18, 1920, do most solemnly declare that:</p>
   <p>"1. We believe that God placed before our Church the most wonderful opportunity of far-reaching and blessed service, and that He has laid upon our heart and conscience a great and real responsibility, that we dare not shirk.</p>
   <p>"2. Having put our hand to the plow in the initial work already done and the obligations assumed, we will not turn back, but will, by the grace of God, exert our utmost ability for the fulfillment of our sacred obligations and the full achievement of our God-given opportunity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0384.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"3. In this convention and purpose we are in conscience bound to call on our fellow Lutherans in the United States and Canada, to the last man, woman, and child, belonging to the bodies which we represent, wholeheartedly, to give of their interest, their sympathy, their prayers, and their money for the achievement of this Christ-like purpose."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
