<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-03-13">Mar. 13, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Woman Suffrage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-03-13">Mar. 13, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">WOMAN SUFFRAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Shall the coming generation of women be permitted to vote, or shall they continue to obey the laws made by men without a murmur? It has been said, and truly so, that "the peculiar mission of women is to become wives and mothers." Is it not as true, that the peculiar mission of men is to become husbands and fathers? They are to be each other's helpmate. They are alike bound to protect and educate their children, and to perform the other duties of parents. The private improvement of self and the public improvement of society rest on them both.</p>
   <p>Women must be subject to the same laws as men; why can she not have a voice in the making of these laws? The truth is that men like to monopolize the power, and they hold up passive obedience as the fittest type of womanliness. Of course, women have their faults; many are vain and like the flattery of the stronger sex; but remember there are all kinds and degrees of women as well as <pb facs="5423969_2_0891.jpg" n="2"/>of men. The question is not what women desire; it is what is right and best for the average woman. Some say the women are not qualified. What about four-fifths of the men, whose votes can be bought at a very low price? Are they better qualified? Let us have a law for the qualification of voters and not of sex.</p>
   <p>The "son of Adam" knows women to be a step or two lower than men, both in physical power and intelligence. I wonder what kind of a mother he has that he can display such knowledge of all the low meanness which can be found in a woman's character. Remember my friends, God Almighty made women to match men. You forget that women have not had any liberty until the last fifty years. If you will take a peep out of your grave about two hundred years hence, you will most likely be astonished by the work done by women, for they are progressing and do not intend to stop.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
