<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-06-23">June 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">"Don't" Statesmanship</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-06-23">June 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">"DON'T" STATESMANSHIP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>And now comes former President Cleveland out of his grave to cry "Don't" to the American people.</p>
   <p>"I once," he says, "saw a very useful book entitled 'Don't'. It contained a statement of numerous things which should not be done. I am inclined to adopt the plan of this book to the extent of cautioning you against the imperfect ideas of civic duties and warn you against certain dangers which threaten the soundness and safety of true American citizenship, and which, especially at this particular time, seem to lie in wait for us on every side."</p>
   <p>Some of the young Americans whom Mr. Cleveland addressed upon this occasion probably wondered why he did not follow the golden rule of his new <pb facs="5423969_2_0593.jpg" n="2"/>primer in statesmanship in his dealings with Hawaii. It said to him in plain language: "Don't attempt to destroy the young republic! Don't try to restore the rotten monarchy of Liliukalani! Don't send 'my special paramount Blount' with instructions to work up a case against the republic and haul down the Stars and Stripes!" Yet Mr. Cleveland did all this in the face of his "Don't"-primer, though his labors were all in vain.</p>
   <p>But they also knew that as regards Cuba, his primer worked like a charm. It said to him: "Don't listen to the piteous appeals of the oppressed people!"--and his ears were deaf to their cries;</p>
   <p>"Don't believe what the newspapermen and other reputable American citizens tell you!"--and he believed they were ghouls and mischief-makers;</p>
   <p>"Don't think Weyler is a butcher and a monster"--and he believed Weyler was an angel worthy of the companionship of that good man, Henrique De Lome.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0594.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The ex-President is very much concerned about the temptations besetting this nation. "The American people are," he says, "tempted every day and every hour to abandon their accustomed way and enter upon a course of new and strange adventure." What he means by his "accustomed way" may be inferred from his protest against any acquisition of "new and distant territory".</p>
   <p>But American history is all against him. The territorial expansion of the United States by purchase and conquest is the overshadowing feature of the nation's growth during the past century. Florida, Louisiana (comprising the empire of the Mississippi valley and more), and Alaska have been acquired by purchase, Texas by admission, and vast California by conquest. If the destinies of this nation had been moulded by "Don't"-statesmen of the Cleveland type, or "milksops", to use another term employed by the ex-President, the nation would still have been confined to a comparatively narrow strip of land lying mainly east of the Alleghenies and hemmed in on all sides by populous European colonies, <pb facs="5423969_2_0595.jpg" n="4"/>most or all of which would probably have been jewels in the British crown. Instead of being the greatest of nations, the United States would today have been a third- or fourth-rate power, had its "accustomed way" been mapped out according to Mr. Cleveland's new primer.</p>
   <p>Grover Cleveland did not conceal from his youthful listeners that the present war is not to his liking, but he told them that if Congress decides to make war, "our ready and unquestioned acquiescence becomes patriotism and the support of our country's intentions becomes good citizenship." The people knew as much ere Grover spake. They knew that if he could have had his way, Weyler would still have been doing business in Cuba. And as for supporting the war, they have not been content with showing mere "ready and unquestioned acquiescence" but have given much more emphatic expression to their patriotism and good citizenship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
