<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-15">Apr. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The New Council</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-15">Apr. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW COUNCIL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The temerity of the Republican majority of the new City Council is a cause for wonder to a goodly portion of the "reformers" of this wicked city. Just think of it! The Republicans have actually made use of the power entrusted to them; how shocking! They do not think that the minority should rule, nor do they believe that those in majority have the right to shirk the responsibility placed upon their shoulders by the people; how incredible! They have organized the City Council on partisan lines because they held that it was their plain duty to execute the mandate of the people as registered at the polls; what unfathomable depths of depravity!</p>
   <p>Is it any wonder that the "reformers" wring their hands in despair? But <pb facs="5423969_2_0247.jpg" n="2"/>what are we going to do about it? It is very evident that the people have lost faith in the "reformers". They have counted the cost and have reached the conclusion that this nonpartisan business has been a source of reeking corruption and a fearful waste of public funds. When they consider the huge mountains of public debt piled up by the Harrison administration, the millions that have been squandered, the impaired credit of the city, the abundant evidence of incapacity, misrule, and waste in every department of the city government--they cannot but conclude that a nonpartisan council results in bad government because it is irresponsible government. And they have decreed that it shall cease. They have now vested the power of the City Council in the Republicans and will not fail to call the latter to account for their stewardship. Let every Republican alderman make a note of this! The sense of responsibility of the old members has undoubtedly been more or less dulled in the air of nonpartisan demoralization that has pervaded the Council Chamber during the last three years. But the people will not listen patiently to excuses of any kind on the day of reckoning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Republicans have made a good start; they have accepted the responsibility, and it is to be hoped that they will know how to use their power for the best interests of the city, the taxpayers, and the people at large.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
