<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-16">June 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">List of Societies in Chicago A. Singing Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1749</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1749.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a (Danish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-16">June 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">LIST OF SOCIETIES IN CHICAGO A. SINGING SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. Det Norske SangerForbund (Norwegian Singing Association), President,John R. Zimmerman; Secretary, Martin Clausen, 1070 N. 42nd Avenue; Vice-President, Carl Gulbrandsen; Treasurer, Anton Ness.</p>
   <p>2. Mands Koret Jubal (The Male Choir Jubal) meets every Monday evening at 8:00 o'clock in the Scandinavian Y.M.C.A.Hall, 317 W. Erie Street. Christian singers wanted to join. Instructor, Otto Olsen, 4 Catalpha Pl.</p>
   <p>3. Sang Foreningen Magneten (Singing Society The Magnet) (Danish) meeting in Jacobsen's Hall, corner Wabansia and Washtenaw Avenues, every Monday evening at 8:00 o'clock.</p>
   <p>4.Den Skandinaviske Arbeider Sang Forening (Scandinavian Workers' Singing Society). Meetings every Thursday evening in Jacobsen's Hall, corner Washtenaw and Wabancia Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1750.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. Den Norske Glee Club (Norwegian Glee Club). Meeting place Jacobsen's Hall, corner Washtenaw and Wabansia Avenues. President, John Gabrielsen; Vice-President C. A. Simonsen; Secretary, H. L. Hansen, 536 Thomas Street.</p>
   <p>6. Normendenes Sang Forening (Norwegian Singing Society). President, M. Clausen; Secretary, Christ Huseley, 487 Potomac Avenue.</p>
   <p>7. Bjorgvin Singing Society. Meeting every Friday at 8:00 P.M. at Bjorgvin Hall, 876-878 N. Artesian Avenue. President Julius Jaeger; Secretary E. J. Fonteen, 309 Dickens Avenue.</p>
   <p>B. MUSIC SOCIETIES</p>
   <p>8. Liberty Band. Meeting every Thursday evening at Giese Hall, 881 W. Division Street. President H. Gassman; Secretary, John Wennberg, 2122 N. Humboldt Street; Director, O. Enger. Belongs to Chicago Federation of Musicians.</p>
   <p>9. Northern Light Band. Meeting every Monday evening at 311-313 W. Division Street. Director, Chas. Nergard. Belongs to Chicago Federation of Musicians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
