<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1902-07-13">July 13, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">A Public Disgrace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1902-07-13">July 13, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">A PUBLIC DISGRACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 28, Patrick H. O'Donnell, public administrator of Cook County, was convicted of jury bribing and sentenced to a fine of two thousand dollars. On July 3, Governor Yates requested his resignation in the following terms:</p>
   <p>"P.H. O'Donnell, Chicago.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: Please forward at once your resignation of the office of public administrator of Cook County."</p>
   <p>The Honorable P. H. O'Donnell evidently construed the Governor's "at once" in his own way; he was not in the least bit of a hurry. He waited until <pb facs="5423969_2_0160.jpg" n="2"/>July 7 before complying with the Governor's request.</p>
   <p>On July 9, Governor Yates accepted the resignation in a letter in which he says:</p>
   <p>"The resignation is not accepted because I believe that you will ultimately be found guilty of crime. On the contrary, I hope that you will ultimately be found to be entirely innocent. Some of your friends claim that you have been convicted upon perjured testimony. Should this prove true, and should you, upon a motion for a new trial, or upon appeal to the courts of last resort, be triumphantly acquitted, no one can or will be more gratified than I.</p>
   <p>"Nor do I accept your resignation because I believe you have failed to do your duty. You have been a capable officer, to the best of my knowledge and belief. I have no doubt that your settlements with your successor will show <pb facs="5423969_2_0161.jpg" n="3"/>that you have been an honest official. But even if judgment be, for the time being, suspended upon the point, it must be conceded that unless you have succeeded in deceiving most capable probate judges (which seems impossible), you have performed your duties satisfactorily for five years past.</p>
   <p>"Nor do I accept your resignation because it is demanded by public sentiment or clamor upon the part of the people of Cook County. You were indorsed or recommended for reappointment one year ago by a large number of the best citizens of Chicago, without regard to party or business affiliations. It is a significant fact that not one of these men suggested or requested your resignation or removal.</p>
   <p>"I do deem it necessary to accept your resignation for another reason. The position of public administrator creates a fiduciary relation and brings the official into contact with, and in charge of, sacred interests. Accordingly, <pb facs="5423969_2_0162.jpg" n="4"/>the latter must be confined at all times to hands absolutely above the breath of suspicion, and free from reproach in any particular whatever. The interests of the numberless widows and orphans and heirs and other parties, committed by the laws and the courts to public administrators, absolutely demand the avoidance of the very appearance of evil by the appointing power. For this reason your resignation is accepted.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully,</p>
   <p>"Richard Yates"</p>
   <p>The former public administrator was very much pleased with this communication. "There is not a thing in that letter about me which I cannot reciprocate about the Governor," said he. "I knew he would feel that way, and I have been expecting just an expression of confidence from him. He is one of my very best <pb facs="5423969_2_0163.jpg" n="5"/>friends. He is a loyal, good man. He is the right kind of a man. He is one of the kind of men God made and, you know, God didn't make all of us by a good deal."</p>
   <p>The Governor's note of July 3 evidently hurt the feelings of the Honorable Patrick H. O'Donnell. But the apologetic communication of July 9 restored the Governor to Mr. O'Donnell's favor. The convicted jury briber grows outright enthusiastic and informs people that he regards the Governor as just as good (?) a man as himself--"one of the kind of men God made". "God did not make all of us by a good deal," the former public administrator adds by way of explanation. But we are inspired that we have among us two good men whom God made--the Honorable Patrick H. O'Donnell and the Honorable Richard Yates.</p>
   <p>If the convicted jury briber is elated--and who can blame him?--the people of Illinois are humiliated. But for its belated appearance the Governor's note <pb facs="5423969_2_0164.jpg" n="6"/>of July 3 was in good taste; its tone and brevity were in keeping with the occasion. The letter of July 9 is a public disgrace. If the Governor of the state had stepped into the court room, had locked arms with the briber, had told the court and the jury that the conviction had been secured by perjured testimony, and furthermore, had expressed the belief that it would be shown that witnesses had committed perjury--if he had done these things he would merely have expressed in action what he has said in plain words in his letter. That a governor could so far forget his self-respect and the dignity of his office is nothing short of amazing. His action is a public indecency that cannot be too severely condemned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
