<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-10-28">Oct. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Norwegian Male Chorus Gives Annual Concert]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-10-28">Oct. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[NORWEGIAN MALE CHORUS GIVES ANNUAL CONCERT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nordmendenes Sangforening (the Norwegian Male Chorus) gave its forty-first annual concert at Wicker Park Hall on Wednesday, October 25, drawing an attendance of a thousand lovers of good singing. Every effort had been put forth to give the public the best evening's entertainment ever offered in Chicago, and nothing was held back. Something new in the annals of male choruses was presented during the evening and the public welcomed the innovation with hearty applause.</p>
   <p>When a private or amateur male chorus like the Nordmendemes musters a twenty-five-piece orchestra, which includes a number of really good soloists, it is safe to say that the accomplishment is really unusual. Some years ago it was our custom to drop in at the old Scandia Hall for a "coffee concert" that gave us the classics as well as the lighter works in Scandinavian music. The <pb facs="5423969_2_1634.jpg" n="2"/>orchestra used to be conducted by Professor Anton Pedersen, and included such musicians as Hartleb Thinn, Albert Huseby, Emil Bjorn, and other well known favorites. One would not expect, during the present time, that an orchestra could be assembled that would play the old Norwegian masterpieces with any degree of mastery, but this new orchestra played Grieg's orchestrations in such manner and with such excellent interpretation and perfect attack that one could only marvel at their aptitude. Their rendition of the "Norsk Dans No. 2" (Norwegian Dance No. 2) was nothing short of marvelous and a revelation of what a soul of music there is to be found in a Norwegian-American colony.</p>
   <p>Miss Middlethon sang several Norwegian songs, and sang them very well, although the audience was a bit chary with its applause because of the newer style of composition, which, frankly speaking, does not come up to the standard of the old masterpieces and their style.</p>
   <p>The chorus kept itself somewhat in the background during the evening, giving preference to the orchestra in that group's first public appearance. While we <pb facs="5423969_2_1635.jpg" n="3"/>would gladly have had many more numbers by the chorus we were well pleased with the entire program. The annual concert by this chorus is a gala event our colony looks forward to each year as religiously as we look forward to July 4, May 30, Christmas, or Easter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
