<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-02">Feb. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Poor People Pay</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0662</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0662.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven, (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-02">Feb. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE POOR PEOPLE PAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Investigation has revealed that the poor people in Chicago are paying far more for coal and wood than other people, because the poor are able to buy their coal only by the basket. In this way they pay so much more for their coal in the course of the winter that the total expenditure is equal to the total amount contributed to the five leading charity organizations in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The investigation was made by the Chicago Relief and Aid Society, and it proves once more the truth of the old saying: "It is expensive to be poor." The housekeeper who has to buy in small quantities is compelled to pay more for the necessities of life. With the colder weather the coal question has become acute, and both the charity organizations and the city relief board have their hands full in the endeavor to provide fuel for the needy who are <pb facs="5423969_2_0663.jpg" n="2"/>found worthy [of aid].</p>
   <p>Soft coal, which is sold by the ton for $3.75 or $4.75, costs as much as $8.55 per ton to the poor who have to buy in smaller quantities. The baskets, which under the pending ordinances must measure a bushel each, are found to vary in weight between fifty-six and sixty-eight pounds. At first sight all the baskets appear to be full, but it makes a great difference whether the baskets have been shaken well. Also of importance is the question of large or small pieces of coal.</p>
   <p>Generally speaking, the poor are paying twice as much for their coal as do those who buy by the ton. According to figures compiled by the Chicago Relief and Aid Society, the poor of the city provide the coal dealers with an extra income of $162,000 per year. It is expensive to be poor.</p>
   <p>The City Council should enact an ordinance requiring sale of coal by weight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
