<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-02">Mar. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Nordmendenes Chorus Honors its Director]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1616</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1616.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-02">Mar. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[NORDMENDENES CHORUS HONORS ITS DIRECTOR]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorary and passive members of Nordmendenes (Norwegian Male Chorus) entertained the active members of the group at a supper in Wicker Park Hall on Thursday. The occasion provided an opportunity to honor the director, Gustav Carlson, on his fortieth birthday, on behalf of the entire club. He was presented with a fine punch bowl and cups.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hans Oftedol made the presentation. The set was made by a member of the chorus and is a work of art. The cups are engraved with the recipient's name and picture and the name of the club. About 250 members of the club were present and all enjoyed the entire evening, although there was an undercurrent of sadness due to the announcement of the death of Martin Losby, an old and much loved member of the organization. The sad message was delivered just as the gathering had been seated at the festive table. The entire group stood up for two minutes in silent tribute to the departed comrade.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Doe, as speaker of the evening, expressed gratitude on behalf of the inactive section to the active members for the contribution they had made to <pb facs="5423969_2_1617.jpg" n="2"/>the musical and cultural life of the community in general and to the Norwegian colony in particular, and confidence that the work they were doing would never be abandoned.</p>
   <p>Among special guests for the evening, were Emil Bjorn, director of the Norwegian Singers League;Julius Jaeger, of Bjorgvin; Mr. Bernts, representing the Norwegian Consul; Senator Juul; Olaf Ray; and representatives of the Norwegian Press. Mr. Larse Grundeland spoke for the Norwegian National League, thanking the chorus for services rendered at city-wide festivities. Senator Juul brought greetings from the Danish and Swedish Chorus groups, stating that each of the Scandinavian groups was proud of the others, and complimenting the three groups on their spirit of good will and cooperation at all times. Olaf Ray also spoke of the good will between the groups and directed a scatning denouncement of the intolerance evidenced by the Lutheran Church in this country toward lodges and all other organizations that would not be dominated by nor dictated to by the clergy. "This intolerance," said Mr. Ray, "could only be brought on by an astounding ignorance of the principles of the Bible they pretend to preach and <pb facs="5423969_2_1618.jpg" n="3"/>an even greater ignorance of progress and ethics." The object of Mr. Ray's attack was a cartoon in the Lutheran Almanac for 1912, picturing two trees. On one are pictured good fruits, heaven-acknowledged and glory-bound, while on the Devil's tree are such Hell-bound fruits as Sons of Norway, Masons, the G. A. R., Singers League, public schools, universities, and all institutions which refuse to bend the knee to the great leaders in the church. "The church and its intolerance," said Mr. Ray, "should have been pictured as the largest and most pleasing fruit on the tree belonging to his Satanic majesty".</p>
   <p>Olaf Bernts, Julius Jaeger, and Dr. Worloe wished the chorus every success on the trip to Norway for the 1914 festivities and the evening ended with a hearty three-times-three for Emil Bjorn, director-in-chief.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
