<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-09-05">Sept. 5, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Not Wanted at the Ballot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-09-05">Sept. 5, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">NOT WANTED AT THE BALLOT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In some articles favoring woman suffrage it has been asserted that our women are kept back by their male brothers who deny them the rights which would bring them up to the level of men. If given the right of suffrage, a right which is not her right, women would, it is said, strike the first blow of reform by choking the liquor traffic.</p>
   <p>It seems to be an easy task on paper, in resolutions, etc.; but, alas, just think of it for a moment! These weaklings that need the protection of men, even while going a few blocks to church in the evening, to say nothing of their more distant expeditions into this world of danger, claim to be able to crush such a mighty power as the liquor organizations! Never on earth can they do it. Consequently, the argument of giving women the right of suffrage on that basis is out of place.</p>
   <p>Still we hear the everlasting plea for women's rights. But let us raise the question: What rights are they enjoying, and what more do they demand? Meet <pb facs="5423969_2_0885.jpg" n="2"/>a lady on our streets, and if circumstances demand, you have to give her the right of way every time. You get into a crowded railway coach or streetcar and pay your hard cash for a seat; but if a woman enters she has undisputed right to your seat if the seats are all occupied. She has the advantage of men in the courtroom, a very sacred advantage. In war the order is given to save the women. On sinking ships, with open watery graves on all sides, the captain's first order, after the boats are lowered, is "women first".</p>
   <p>Poor creatures, how I sympathize with them when we hear the cry that they are robbed of their rights and privileges by us poor males. The most substantial argument against woman suffrage is that the best of women do not want to vote. These women say it is not their mission to mix in vulgar, currupt politics, as they have a grander and nobler calling to fill at home. They are not willing to exchange the exalted position they occupy in the minds of brave and honest men for the privilege, so unbecoming a woman, of mixing in modern politics. The grave difficulties confronting our government today strain the abilities of men who have spent nearly a lifetime in public service. Right here I want to ask the question: What could these delicate things, with their <pb facs="5423969_2_0886.jpg" n="3"/>"riot act" theories, do if put in the places of the men? Let us assume the dear creatures have a majority in Congress and a Frances Willard for President, and that circumstances should arise which necessitated a declaration of war. Would it be justice that one class of our race that is unable to go to war should have the privilege and power to order the other class into mortal combat, to kill or be killed? Arbitration--Oh, how seldom it prevails!</p>
   <p>Ladies, be thankful that you can stay at home and be protected. The ballot box never was intended for you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
