<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Dangerous Legislation]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0642</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0642.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[DANGEROUS LEGISLATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a pleasure to note how our Norwegian-American citizens are taking more and more interest in local, state and national politics. Of the many important issues at this time is the "Recall of Judges" legislation. We are not in favor of the "recall."</p>
   <p>Many beneficial laws are being passed and in between these are a number of questionable issues that at first glance seem good but upon being analyzed display glaring defects, some of them impracticable to the least degree. The recall is plainly one of the latter group and should be discarded. The fundamental question here is whether or not the Constitution shall be amended. One of the reasons advanced by those who advocate the proposed "recall" is that courts often destroy a law by declaring it to be unconstitutional. This has been done even where a law is absolutely good and progressive in every way. The new law proposes that where a judge refuses to budge from the letter of the law and tempering his interpretation <pb facs="5423969_2_0643.jpg" n="2"/>according to the wishes of the community, this community shall have the privilege of recalling this judge. Such intimidation has no place in this country, as a law that is enacted decides certain forms of procedure during the present time and plans for future procedure as well. These forms of procedure should not be changed in application without amending legislature following the procedure laid down by our constitution, whether this be state or national.</p>
   <p>If our judges are to be forced to violate our constitution to hold their jobs, what will become of justice and liberty? The result of enacting the "recall" law would make our judges the pawns of political leaders and the moneyed individuals and place our constitution on the highest and most inaccessible shelf and we will revert to a condition where neither life nor property of an individual would be secure from theft by the rich and the powerful. Our present elections are all the recall we need.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
