<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1910-04-01">Apr. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Supreme Court Vacancy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-04-01">Apr. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE SUPREME COURT VACANCY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The successor to the late Justice David J. Brewer will be a Republican, and it may be assumed that he will come from some of the states of the eighth circuit. In Justice Brewer this large group of important states had a worthy representative tribunal of the land, distinguished alike for his great ability and his attractive personality. Were the vacancy created by his sudden death to go to some other section of the country the Supreme Court would be weakened in respect to geographical balance.</p>
   <p>The great West, a vast empire in itself, and one of the most prosperous and progressive sections of the country, never had the honor of furnishing a judge for the Federal Supreme Bench. It is only fair to assume that a western jurist, measuring up to the standard of a Supreme Court judge, may expect to receive favorable consideration this time. Questions of <pb facs="5423969_2_0755.jpg" n="2"/>far-reaching importance are likely to come from the West to the Supreme Court for adjudication in the near or not very far distant future, and a judge familiar with all conditions surrounding such cases would be in a position to render the Court particularly valuable assistance in disposing legislation of such a character.</p>
   <p>Since the first years of the Republic there probably never was a time when the make-up of the Supreme Court was of greater importance than now. It is plain to all thinking men that we are on the eve of another era of fundamental judicial construction of a different character, but scarcely of less importance, than that of the days of John Marshall. The great economic and industrial questions of today and tomorrow present problems that will tax the knowledge, wisdom, and farsightedness of our best legal minds. It will depend upon the Supreme Court as much as upon any other agency of government, or perhaps more so, whether we are to attempt to adjust our industrial and social development upon a Procrustes bed of principles that have outlived their usefulness, or in accordance with the <pb facs="5423969_2_0756.jpg" n="3"/>broader views of our own time. Upon this choice of paths depend the safety and orderly growth of society and the liberty of the people.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, we have a president who is exceptionally well qualified to select men for the Supreme Court. Himself a jurist of recognized ability, a judge of long, varied experience, and a man of progressive views and broad sympathies, President Taft may confidently be relied upon to make wise judicial appointments.</p>
   <p>The large corporations are, of course, as vitally interested as are the people in the make-up of the Supreme Court, perhaps more so at this stage than at any other time before, and, generally speaking, it is probably true that such jurists as the corporations favor for judicial honors are among the very ablest lawyers in the land. And it may be readily admitted also that if they attempt to influence judicial appointments, corporations are actuated only by honorable motives: to secure the selection of men who command confidence on account of their tried ability. But present <pb facs="5423969_2_0757.jpg" n="4"/>exigencies do not call primarily for another judge who has received his training in the corporation school of practice, however worthy and honorable he might be as a man, or however eminent as a lawyer. New blood is needed in the Supreme Court--men who are close to the plain people and have a broad understanding of the questions and problems that we are now facing--men of the type of, say Senator Knute Nelson. And the people expect that President Taft will select a man of that type to succeed Justice Brewer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
