<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Borgny Hammer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BORGNY HAMMER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mme. Borgny Hammer's debut as an English-speaking artist is and will remain a success.</p>
   <p>One of our foremost dramatic clubs, the Playgoers, entertaining in the Florentine Room of the Congress Hotel, had as their guest of honor our own Norwegian actress Borgny Hammer. The speaker upon introducing her spoke of her as the "Bernhardt of the North," and the audience upon hearing her give H. C. Andersen's touching little story, "The Mother," fully agreed with him.</p>
   <p>This searching little symbolic tale was given with rare poetic feeling. Each mood was depicted with that great inexhaustible fund of inner fire which Mme. Hammer possesses to a superlative degree. That it was possible to attain such excellent English speech in so short a time shows her ceaseless striving after perfection. Her success with this cultured audience was very gratifying to Mme. Hammer as well as to her friends.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1394.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The time is not far distant when Mme. Hammer can claim as great success as Modjeska Kalicn, Nazimova, and a score of others have attained on the American stage after their foreign training. Even in such case she will not forget Norway, for at heart Mme. Hammer is a true Horwegian.</p>
   <p>Besides Mme. Hammer's reading a very select musical program was offered. Marie Sidenius Zendt sang with rare charm Charpentier's "Depuis Le Jour" from "Louise". Mr. Goldman played some selected violin numbers. Among those present were Mr. and Mrs. E. C. Bye, who helped Mme Hammer a great deal in her preparation for the American stage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
