<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-12-29">Dec. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Democratic Civil Service</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-12-29">Dec. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">DEMOCRATIC CIVIL SERVICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The decision of the Supreme Court, upholding the constitutionality of the Chicago civil service law, was a well-deserved rebuke to Burke, Harrison, Thornton and Company, but it is not likely to result in any real and practical gain for the cause of civil service reform. The Democratic party of Chicago worships at the shrine of Tammany and is violently opposed to civil service reform. Mr. Harrison has always been frank in the avowal of his faith in this respect, and the industrious posing of Mr. Kraus has misled no one. If the administration yields to the decision of the Court, it is because it can do nothing else and because it is expected that the law may be so enforced as to defeat the very object it was enacted to accomplish. The recent examinations of police officers, conducted by the civil service commission, were farcial and grotesque in the extreme, and the examinations soon to be held in consequence of the recent decision rendered by the Supreme Court, will probably be conducted in the same manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0294.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The validity of the law has been established; that much has been gained. But unless they are honestly enforced, even the best laws are worthless. However, the people of Chicago got only what they voted for. They were informed in advance by Mr. Harrison himself that he would undo what his predecessor had done. In tearing the civil service law to tatters, he is keeping what he may fairly regard as his pledge to the people. If they do not like his performances, the people have no one to kick but themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
