<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 246-47-48.
<title level="a">[Biography of Charles Olinus Sethnes, Che] 6-47-48</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 246-47-48.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF CHARLES OLINUS SETHNES, CHE] 6-47-48</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sethnes Company are manufacturers of flavoring extracts and colors,oil essences and chemicals specialities as used by confectioneers, bakers, ice-cream manufacturers, soda-water dispensers, perfumes, rectifiers, brewers, syrup refiners, cider and vinegar, relish refiners , etc. They also handle bottling machinery and supplies.</p>
   <p>Their laboratory and factory is located at 262-268 North Curtis Street, Chicago. They employ eight traveling men who cover every state in the Union and Canada and have an office force of ten and a regular force in the factory of twelve, not counting teams and drivers. It is an incorporated firm with C. O. Sethnes as president and manager. It is the largest concern of its kind in America.</p>
   <p>Charles Olinus Sethnes was born in Christiansund, Norway, Aug. 5, 1860. He attended school in Norway and also the public school in Chicago and was confirmed in the Norwegian Lutheran Church on Grand Avenue and Peoria Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1873 he came to Chicago and in 1874 entered the employ of Christopher Stanze to learn the profession of a druggist and chemist. He worked for him ten years or until 1884, when he engaged in the same business at Raligh and Milwaukee Avenues. Later he moved to his present quarters at 262-68 North Curtis Street, where he manufactures flavoring extracts.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sethnes is at present a member of the Board of Education. He is also a Mason, a Knight Templar, a Shriner and a member of the Irving Park Country Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
