<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-14">Sep. 14, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Book Store</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Northern Book and Music Company at Humboldt Park</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-14">Sep. 14, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN BOOK STORE</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Northern Book and Music Company at Humboldt Park</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>G. Gundersen from Decorah, Iowa, came to Chicago a few days ago after a couple of months vacation in Minnesota. Now he is going to settle down in Chicago having been made partner in the firm, Northern Book and Music Co., which for about a year has been doing business in the Viking Building, 857 W. North Ave Mr. Gundersen is a graduate of Luther College, Decorah, Iowa, and also of Luther Seminary, Hamline, Minnesota. He was with the Synod Book Store, Decorah, and for four years was an assistant on the editorial staff of the Decorah Posten.</p>
   <p>Mr. Haldor Hanson, the senior partner of the firm, has had twenty years experience as a teacher of music at Luther College and other schools. But music did not claim all of his time. His unique collection of books in various languages, now on sale at the finely decorated store on North Avenue, presents evidence that he has acquired a profound knowledge of literature and is in the full sense of the word, a bookman. When to these facts concerning the training of the two men of the firm is added that both of them are known and have friends all over the Northwest, one realizes that they possess all the qualifications <pb facs="5423969_2_1103.jpg" n="2"/>for doing good business.</p>
   <p>For quite a long time Skandinaven's Book Store has been planning to open a branch in the district referred to, in order to accommodate customers on the Northwest Side, but it has not been possible to release from the main office the man who could have taken charge of the branch. Now the branch is becoming an actuality. The Northern Book and Music Co. keeps in stock the books carried by the Skandinaven Book Store, both those published by Skandinaven and imported ones.</p>
   <p>Now, then, customers for whom it is less convenient to come to headquarters at Peoria Street may hereafter do business with Skandinaven's Book Store through Northern Book and Music Co., 857 West North Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
