<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">Jan. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Slander</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">Jan. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">SLANDER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Scandia</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: I notice in your January 2 issue of Scandia that a former president of the Norwegian National League, with abject humilation and utter chargrin, gives vent to his own and other's feelings regarding the actions and behavior of two well and favorably known sisters who reside in Chicago. We have, among our American-born Norwegians, a good many seminarister [college and university men who never finished their studies] who utterly fail to grasp anything but what rules and regulations demand. This man has demonstrated in his article that he is in no position, either mentally or artistically, to criticize artists of the standing of these two sisters [Ethel and Nora Olsen]. To my knowledge these two women enjoy the acquaintance and friendship, of some of the best-known men and women among Norwegian-Americans, both foreign born and native, from United States senators and governors of states down to us ordinary folks; and I have never heard of <pb facs="5423969_2_1197.jpg" n="2"/>anyone taking offense at there having been representations of the humorous peculiarities of speech sometimes found among Norwegians in this country.</p>
   <p>Norwegians in America who have had the pleasure of witnessing the programs of these sisters know that this "fun-making" has never been the essential part of the team. Their musical work has been considered of the highest type by leading critics of this country.</p>
   <p>The older of the sisters has been one of our best contraltos and will be remembered as a well-loved artist among the Norwegians; the younger also is an unusually gifted singer and musician.</p>
   <p>The article, which I am surprised, Mr. Editor, that you allowed to be printed in your otherwise clean and interesting paper, is, to my way of thinking, the most coarse and uncouth I have ever read in any newspaper. The writer of this article, and many other Norwegians, know that any charitable organization giving benefit concerts could always expect a <pb facs="5423969_2_1198.jpg" n="3"/>favorable response from these same artists year after year. When a man, supposedly in possession of some culture and education, stoops so low as to write an article such as was published in your issue of January 2, I think some of us will refuse to acknowledge that this man belongs to Vor Egen Stamme [our own race--our own species--our own clan].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
