<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-11-08">Nov. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Election in Four Cities</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-11-08">Nov. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION IN FOUR CITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the election on November 5, reform in the city government was the main issue in four of the largest cities in the country. Corruption lost out in two of these cities but was victorious in the other two. The fight and its result in Greater New York naturally attracted the most attention. The shameless corruption carried on by Tammany Hall had attained such magnitude as to awaken even the most indifferent voters. Greater New York is a Democratic city, but the Republicans gained the support of the independent voters and the better elements among the Democratic faction, and this coalition sealed the doom of Tammany Hall.</p>
   <p>A similar situation was witnessed in Baltimore. Here, too, the Republicans represented the demand for better city government, and they won by the aid of voters from other parties.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0168.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Philadelphia, one of the most corrupt cities in the country, the situation was the reverse. The regular Republican ticket was dictated by the leading corruptionists, while the opposition, consisting of the Democrats and some of the Republicans combined on a coalition ticket. The friends of reform lost, however. The Republicans, unfortunately, are so strong in Pennsylvania that they are able to do about anything they choose.</p>
   <p>In San Francisco, too, the Republicans represented misgovernment and corruption. Here, however, the workers reform party won. As far as we can see, the newly elected mayor is the right man in the right place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
