<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-11">Nov. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Bjorgvin Male Chorus Gives Annual Concert]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-11">Nov. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[BJORGVIN MALE CHORUS GIVES ANNUAL CONCERT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Saturday, November 4, the Bjorgvin male chorus gave its twenty-ninth annual concert at Bjorgvin Hall. The singing of the chorus brought to light the fact that "Bjorgvin" like the rest of our male choruses at present is suffering slightly from lack of strong tenors, although the numbers offered by the chorus were very good. The entire program was pleasingly well balanced and quite equally divided between the chorus, Joel Mossberg, Schmidt's Orchestra, and the Swedish Ladies' Quartette. The quartette had two new members this year and seemed to lack a little of their usual smoothness, though their harmony was commendable.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mossberg has not lost his power to entertain and to hold his listeners enthralled, and his offerings were, without a shadow of doubt, the high lights of the evening's program. Mr. Mossberg's tones are pure and true and the feeling he puts into even the simplest song touches the heart. Schmidt's Orchestra was really a treat. It is a well-balanced group, every member of which is a master of his instrument. It played several difficult numbers in <pb facs="5423969_2_1626.jpg" n="2"/>perfect harmony and time while its control of volume was truly refreshing.</p>
   <p>Bjorgvin's hall has recently been remodeled and redecorated, and a new electric lighting system has been installed. Thus it is an inspiration to both chorus and friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
