<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-05-02">May 2, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Injustice to Homesteaders</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-05-02">May 2, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">INJUSTICE TO HOMESTEADERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A trustworthy correspondent has called our attention to certain practices and abuses that have wrought gross injustice to honest homesteaders. Hundreds of poor settlers have, it appears, been robbed of their lands and homes just as they were about to reap the profits of many years of suffering and toil.</p>
   <p>A poor man would take a claim, spend his ready cash for the necessary land-office fees and materials for a shanty, then build his little house and begin to make improvements. In the open seasons of the year he would work for other farmers and thus secure funds for his "grub" in the winter season and for continuing the improvements on his land. His progress would necessarily be slow; yet by unceasing hard work and stinting he would manage to comply with the requirements of the law and in five years would be ready to prove up. A home at last! His untold hardships were forgotten in this hour of joy.</p>
   <p>Vain hope! A government agent steps up and robs him of his land, alleging that he has failed to comply with the law. The poor settler has spent his last cent; all that he has earned and owns is invested in the land he was about to call <pb facs="5423969_2_0919.jpg" n="2"/>his home; he is utterly unable to fight any contest, however unjust, in the courts; he has no choice but to abandon his claim and improvements.</p>
   <p>This rank injustice is on a par with the worst outrages committed against western settlers by Mr. Sparks during Grover Cleveland's first administration. If there ever were honest settlers upon the public domain these homesteaders are such. The very purpose of the homestead law is to enable people in their position to secure free homes. They have complied with the law as it has been understood and interpreted, and are beyond question entitled to receive their patents.</p>
   <p>The government agents have probably acted in good faith. But they have certainly erred; they have shown poor discretion and their policy is contrary to the spirit of the law. In some instances they may have been misled by some of the scoundrels who make a specialty of preying upon poor homesteaders and have succeeded in making the government a party to their despicable confidence game.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0920.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No time should be lost in securing justice to those abused settlers. By prompt action Senators McCumber and Hansbrough and Congressman Spaulding could right wrongs that have been inflicted and prevent similar hardships to other settlers in the future. And the press ought to have something to say in this matter. If it desires ample success in its campaign for new settlers, it must not fail to protect the poor homesteaders of the country in their just rights.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
