<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-10-09">Oct. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">In the Matter of Filth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0965</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0965.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-10-09">Oct. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE MATTER OF FILTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>And now everybody is aroused over the unspeakable condition of the streets and alleys of Chicago. How can this be? Has not Carter H. Harrison again and again been telling the people with parrot-like persistency that the streets have been kept clean? Have not some of our best-known "non partisan" fellow citizens seized every opportunity to offer excuses for the shortcomings and rottenness of his administration? Have not our most righteous "independent" newspapers been closing their eyes to the dunghills that have grown up all over the city as monuments to the inefficiency of the Harrison administration, and have they not ever been ready to cover the accumulation of filth with cloaks of immaculate charity?</p>
   <p>The complaints that have been showered upon the City Hall from all parts <pb facs="5423969_2_0966.jpg" n="2"/>of the city have rudely disturbed this beautiful game of blindfolding the people. But it cannot be helped. The dirt is here and nobody denies it. McGann admits the fact, and even His Honor has, since his return, refrained from making another speech on the model condition of the streets.</p>
   <p>The Commissioner of Public Works has, of course, entered the usual plea, "lack of funds". If this plea is valid, why have conditions improved since the people began to complain? Did the funds come with the complaints of the "kicking" citizens? If the money that has been squandered for the support of Democratic ward heelers had been extended [sic] wisely and economically for street and alley cleaning there would have been enough on hand wherewith to do the most necessary work.</p>
   <p>One feature of this business is rather puzzling. When he took the reins, Mr. Harrison found the street cleaning service fully organized under the civil service law. The work was in the hands of competent and <pb facs="5423969_2_0967.jpg" n="3"/>zealous men and women and the service was efficient and satisfactory. The employees felt that they were protected by the law and strove to do their duty without fear or favor. But this condition of things was anything but satisfactory to Mr. Harrison, who wanted the jobs for hungry followers. One night Mr. Harrison and Mr. McGann put their heads together, and the next morning Chicago awoke to find the whole street cleaning service abolished and a "new system" created. The people were told by the conspirators that the change had been made for the sake of economy. But the real reason was, of course, that the jobs were wanted for Democratic workers. A cheap Democratic politician was put in charge of the work and nearly all subordinate places were given to men who were still more incompetent. The whole service was disorganized and has since been worse than useless. Instead of pleading a shortage of funds, let Mr. McGann turn his thoughts to the coup executed by himself and Mr. Harrison at the City Hall on that night a little over a year ago, and if he is disposed to tell the truth he will confess to the people that right here lies the cause <pb facs="5423969_2_0968.jpg" n="4"/>of the disgraceful inefficiency of the present street cleaning service.</p>
   <p>But now comes the puzzling question: Why are these facts ignored by our champions of civil service reform, now that the deplorable effects of Harrison's and McGann's coup for spoils are so painfully visible? We have among us some newspapers that attack the spoils system in season and out of season when the Republicans are in power at the City Hall. Why are they silent now? Is it because they have done their best to keep the people in ignorance of this and other violations of the civil service law at the hands of the Harrison administration? The Civic Federation has done some good work in this line as well as for the introduction of the civil service system. Is it ignorant of Harrison's and McGann's conduct in this instance, or will it permit their trampling upon the law to pass unnoticed and uncensored? In short, why have our champions of civil service reform and other good people nothing to 'say about the reveling in spoils during the present administration, with every street and alley <pb facs="5423969_2_0969.jpg" n="5"/>in the city filled with filth and reeking with death-dealing germs in consequence of shameful spoils practices?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
