<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-05-29">May 29, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">J. P. Johnson about to Retire</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I A 2 a (German)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-29">May 29, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">J. P. JOHNSON ABOUT TO RETIRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. J.P. Johnson, well known to most of the older Norwegians in Chicago as the result of his long activity as teacher here in the city, has been ill for quite some time and now believes that it will be necessary for him to retire.</p>
   <p>For thirty-one years Mr. Johnson has been a teacher at the St. John's German Congregational School, corner of Bickerdike and Superior Streets. Here he has taught German, English, religion, and other subjects.</p>
   <p>Until December 10, of last year, Mr. Johnson was, in spite of his advanced age, healthy and energetic. On that day, however, while in the midst of his teaching, he suffered a stroke and fell down.</p>
   <p>Under a doctor's care, Mr. Johnson recovered somewhat, but he had to remain in bed for more than three weeks, and his voice had received a lasting blow.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1040.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On January 2, he decided to start his work as teacher once more, against the advice of his physician and his friends....For five weeks he went on teaching, when a second stroke occurred and he once more had to stop his activities. The congregation, which now has appointed a new teacher, continues to pay Mr. Johnson his full salary.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson was born in Fredrikstad, Norway, 1830. He graduated from Asker Normal School and for a while taught at the higher schools in Christiania and Drammen. In 1860 he came to America and for more than three years served in the Civil War. After the war, he taught among the Norwegians for about five years. Privately maintained grammar schools did not gain a permanent foothold among the Norwegians, however, and they finally had to be discontinued. As a result of this, Mr. Johnson became engaged as teacher at St. John's German Congregational [School], where he remained as such until illness laid him low.</p>
   <p>Many Chicagoans have received their grammar school instruction from Mr. Johnson, who is well known and loved by thousands on the Northwest Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
