<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-08-01">Aug. 1, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Expansion Is Our Destiny</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-08-01">Aug. 1, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">EXPANSION IS OUR DESTINY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To me the questions of government which have loomed up recently are of just as much importance to the young people as those which have been discussed before. And as these questions will have to be settled by the people and for the people, and as the writers and readers of these columns are part of the people, I consider it time well spent, nay, an imperative duty to consider and discuss these questions.</p>
   <p>I have, of course, reference to the Philippines. And in the discussion of these questions, preponderate weight should not be attached to the clamor of that commercial class that has suddenly discovered that there are vast unopened markets and consuming populations beyond the seas. Nor should we accept the feeble wailings of that pessimistic class which sees in every exhibition of national progress and self-respect nothing but fearful visions of imperialism and coming danger. Neither should we be of that "know-it-all," fault-finding <pb facs="5423969_2_0563.jpg" n="2"/>class whose views are brought forward only in a spirit of reproach to the powers that be. But it should be remembered that destiny and not desire has confronted us with these new problems and responsibilities, and hence we should be reasonable in our expectations of their performance.</p>
   <p>We have a class of statesmen today, claimed to be thoroughly saturated by Jeffersonian principles, who say that expansion is unconstitutional and tends to the destruction of the free institutions of the republic. But, may I ask, was not Jefferson the greatest expansionist we ever had? Is it not a fact that in spite of frenzied opposition he bought Louisiana without the consent of Congress and upon his own responsibility? And is it not a fact, also, that today the civilization of thirty million people, now resident in the Mississippi valley, justifies and approves the wisdom of his act? In view of these facts it seems to me that our anti-expansionist statesmen of today are more of the type of Jefferson's opposition than perpetuators of his principles.</p>
   <p>But that is not all. The party of Jefferson preponderated in power from his day to Lincoln's, and during all this time Jeffersonian principles lost no <pb facs="5423969_2_0564.jpg" n="3"/>opportunity to extend our national domain. In 1819, Jackson applied very little rhetoric in seizing Florida. This he did because she had become a common nuisance, and also because she was misgoverned by Spain in the same manner as she had misgoverned the West Indies and the Philippines. In 1848, our government acquired the best portion of Mexico, and in 1850, Oregon. But in neither of these instances did Jeffersonian principles point out to the government that it disregarded the birthright in the Declaration of Independence that "governments derive their just powers from the consent of the governed".</p>
   <p>Instead of weakening the republic, our acquisitions have really made it what it is today. About half of our population is resident in the acquired portions of the United States. More than half of our natural resources and fundamental wealth will be found in such portions as we have annexed since we became a nation. And the best of all, its people are enjoying liberty and equal rights.</p>
   <p>But today Jeffersonain principles have taken another turn. Today the governors of Nebraska, South Dakota, and Minnesota, in their ambition for manufacturing political capital--executives that could not have existed but for expansion--are <pb facs="5423969_2_0565.jpg" n="4"/>denouncing the government for "the subjugation of a race" and for "waging a conflict against liberty and in the interests of exploiting capital," and demand the immediate return of their regiments.</p>
   <p>But I do not believe that these governors have voiced the true wish of the people, nor of the regiments. When our brave boys went forth in response to the country's call it was not only to share the fortunes of war, but to endure if necessary, both hardships and death in defence of the flag and the nation's cause. And while we anxiously look for the day when our heroes shall return, we are confident that when there is no longer demand for their services, the government will return them to their loved ones with all speed consistent with the honor and dignity of the flag.</p>
   <p>The Philippines came to us as a legacy of the war and not of our seeking, and this government can best discharge its new obligations by building upon the ruins of Spanish misrule a just, stable, and liberal government, and by teaching the natives the story of liberty and equal rights as exemplified and illustrated by civilization and enlightened American institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
