<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-07-21">July 21, 1901</date><title level="a">The "Foreigner" in City Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-07-21">July 21, 1901</date><title level="a">THE "FOREIGNER" IN CITY POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In 1890 the "foreign element" constituted twenty per cent of the total population of Philadelphia, whereas in Chicago forty per cent of the people consisted of "foreigners". In New York there was even a larger percentage of foreign-born citizens. The census of 1900 shows a decrease in the percentage of foreign-born citizens.</p>
   <p>Considering the bearing of these statistics upon our municipal government, the Chicago Tribune says: "It is evident that the foreign element is not responsible for the poor government of large American cities, for Philadelphians seem to be unable to manage their municipal affairs honestly and efficiently."</p>
   <p>The Tribune is correct though its statements may be news to some of its readers. Many of our fellow citizens are wont to charge all our social and political ills to the "foreign element". It is so comforting to believe that somebody else is <pb facs="5423969_2_0170.jpg" n="2"/>at fault, and the scapegoat is a handy critter. The "foreigner" has his weak points as a citizen, and his short-comings are so easily magnified, especially by those who know least about him and his ways and of conditions abroad in general. Thus many well-meaning people have drifted into the belief that the "foreign element" is the main source of all that is bad in the social and political conditions of our cities.</p>
   <p>If we are to accept this view as correct we must believe that the "foreigner" is changed to the core for the worse as soon as he sets foot upon American soil. For in his old home he was not a source of corrupt local government. City government, generally speaking, is cleaner and better in Europe than here, especially in those countries whence, until recently, came the bulk of the immigration. There, as here, universal suffrage is the controlling force in the government of cities. Just why a man who in Birmingham, Glasgow, Paris, Hamburg, Leipzig, Vienna, Budapest, Copenhagen, Christiania, or Stockholm cast his vote for good government should begin to vote for corrupt city government in the United States is not apparent. As a matter of fact he does not. He is proud of his American citizenship and, as a rule, circumspect and careful in the use of his ballot. He knows that none but rascals <pb facs="5423969_2_0171.jpg" n="3"/>have anything to gain by bad or corrupt government, and he votes to put honest men in office and keep the rascals out.</p>
   <p>Of course there are "foreigners" and "foreigners". Some of our larger cities contain foreign elements that readily become instruments of misgovernment. Coming here untutored in liberty and unpracticed in the use of the ballot, and being unfamiliar with the American tongue, they are apt to fall under the sway of unscrupulous bosses. But the boss that leads them astray is in most instances a native-born citizen, or at least a politician thoroughly schooled in the tricks and stratagems of ward politics.</p>
   <p>The chief difficulties in the government of American cities spring from the question of taxation, and the selfish greed of public service corporations is at the bottom of other forms of abuse. Who owns the bulk of the property that escapes taxation? Not the "foreigner". Who own and manage the great corporations that are granted valuable privileges without rendering adequate compensation? Most of these men pass for Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0172.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But there is a promise of better things. Our municipal government is improving, gradually if slowly. Some day the management of the public affairs of our cities will be as enlightened, businesslike, and efficient as the government of the nation. However, a correct diagnosis of our ills must precede their cure. The "scapegoat" policy is a distinct obstacle to progress. The truth is that we have good and bad "foreign elements" in our cities as we have good and bad native elements. The point is to get the good citizens to work together. Unfortunately, an effective union of the best forces in the community is frequently blocked by prejudice. We are all more or less handicapped by lack of a through understanding of one another; but--and this is not said in a spirit of capricious faultfinding--the native American is more prejudiced in his conception of the "foreigner" than is the "foreigner" in his estimate of his native-born fellow citizen. In the very nature of things this could not be otherwise. But the calm and impartial view taken by a newspaper of the standing and influence of the Chicago Tribune is an earnest of a broader and better mutual understanding between the various elements in our many-tongued cities. When the bars of prejudice shall have been lowered, and all good citizens, irrespective <pb facs="5423969_2_0173.jpg" n="5"/>of their race or native speech, join hands upon the common platform of American citizenship, every year will witness a step forward for the betterment of the government of our cities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
