<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-06-03">June 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Tanner's Park Policy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-06-03">June 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">TANNER'S PARK POLICY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once more Governor Tanner has exposed himself to justified criticism through his appointment of members to the Lincoln Park Board and the West Park Board. His first appointment of park commissioners was dictated by political ends, and now he has, in part, made over his own work, and for the same ends.</p>
   <p>The changes in the West Park Board have made an exceedingly bad impression on the West Side. The term of Mr. Anton Peterson had expired, but he ought to have been reappointed. Everybody agrees that he is a man of great ability and altogether honest. Clearly it was an abuse of power not to offer him a reappointment.</p>
   <p>A similar or worse abuse of power was apparent in the discharge of Superintendent Jens Jensen [Dane]. This able man has been in the service of the Park Board <pb facs="5423969_2_0231.jpg" n="2"/>for many years, and his work has won the appreciation of all. The great improvements made in Humboldt Park during recent years have been accomplished under his supervision and trained leadership. But he tended to his work in the parks instead of serving the Tanner machine, and as a consequence he was discharged.</p>
   <p>Governor Altgeld was the first governor to introduce politics into the park boards. His appointments were made for political reasons exclusively.</p>
   <p>Governor Tanner's rule forms, in many ways, a pleasant contrast to that of Governor Altgeld. The finances of the state have been put into good shape, and the various state institutions are being managed in an improved manner. But the park policy of Governor Tanner is as rotten as that of his predecessor, if not worse. The end desired in his appointments has been to reward personal adherents of the governor. The people of Chicago, however, are not satisfied with the service rendered by that type of appointee, and the acts of the governor in these matters have caused justified anger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
