<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-05-24">May 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. A. M. Wergeland</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Norwegian Lady Who Won a Name for Herself in America by Aasta Hansteen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-05-24">May 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">DR. A. M. WERGELAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Norwegian Lady Who Won a Name for Herself In America by Aasta Hansteen</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is time that we heard a systematic account of our famous countrywoman, Dr. A. M. Wergeland. In 1880 she went to Germany, where she studied the history of art for two years, in Munich. She then returned to Norway, but found no opportunity for activity. She went abroad once more, this time to Switzerland. There she studied at the University of Zurich, from which she received the doctor's degree. When she returned once more to Norway she found as slight use for her powers as before; consequently she decided to set out for the United States.</p>
   <p>She taught at Bryn Mawr College, later at the University of Illinois, and then at the University of Chicago. While at the latter institution, she wrote <pb facs="5423969_2_1028.jpg" n="2"/>several treatises, which were published by the University. She was at this time particularly interested in conditions in Germany during the Middle Ages, and especially the subject of serfs and their masters. Dr. Wergeland has also taken a deep interest in Henrik Ibsen's dramas and has given lectures on a number of his books. She has also given lecture courses in French literature and the development of the drama in France. As a lecturer she was very interesting, as witnessed by the fact that her audiences did not dwindle in numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
