<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-09-15">Sept. 15, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Martyred President</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-09-15">Sept. 15, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT MARTYRED PRESIDENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The memories of Abraham Lincoln and William McKinley will be linked in the hearts and the history of the American people as the two great martyred Presidents of the republic. Though unlike in temperament and intellectual cast, and though each was allotted a great task widely different from that confronting the other, yet their life currents as public men and their respective historic missions present parallels of great and absorbing interest.</p>
   <p>Both came out of the ranks of the plain people--Lincoln from a pioneer's rude log cabin, McKinley from the more prosperous average American home of a later day. Both were sturdy youths, strong in mental gifts and energy. If Lincoln was endowed with greater intellectual force, the delicate tact <pb facs="5423969_2_0782.jpg" n="2"/>of McKinley and the charm of his winning personality were to him an unfailing source of strength with the people. Both were thoroughly unselfish, generous, and benevolent, with hearts flowing with the milk of human kindness to all men. Both had served their country in war and in the halls of legislation when they were called to the very highest position of trust by the voice of the people--Lincoln to lead in a crisis involving the integrity of the nation and the fate of liberty; McKinley to lead the people out of the slough of stagnation, ruin, misery, and despair.</p>
   <p>Each assumed his duties with the full confidence of the plain people in his ability, integrity, and rectitude, while the conservative forces of the nation were not fully convinced that he possessed the capacity and strength of character necessary to deal with a grave crisis. But each surprised not only the doubters but his most enthusiastic admirers by his firm grasp and broad-gauged, wise, and far-seeing statesmanship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0783.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lincoln freed four million bondsmen at home and saved the Union, but did not live to see the unity of national sentiment restored. McKinley delivered ten million people under a foreign flag from the bondage of a hopeless oppression, brought them under the benign civilizing influence of free America, and in so doing cemented the Union in the hearts of all Americans.</p>
   <p>Lincoln's was the greater task; but the problems confronting either were sufficiently difficult to tax the wisdom and ability of the greatest of statesmen. Each kept his ear to the national heart, and while he was clear in his own mind as to the course to be followed, neither moved until the people had given the word of command. So each, marching abreast with the people, with abiding faith in the unerring aim of the moral sense of the popular heart, moved with unswerving purpose, conscious of the justice and strength of his cause.</p>
   <p>Lincoln inaugurated a new era in the history of the republic: he made the <pb facs="5423969_2_0784.jpg" n="4"/>republic all free; he vindicated the sovereignity of the flag on every spot of American soil; he unshackled labor and established the foundations of new economic policies.</p>
   <p>With the administration of William McKinley began another epoch of American history: the perfection and full fruition of a thoroughly sound economic policy, and the flag of the republic established as a controlling factor in the council of nations.</p>
   <p>Each had to confront a traitorous sentiment during his campaign for re-election, and each was assailed with venomous falsehoods, though the attacks of the political opponents of McKinley were tame in comparison with the seditious assaults upon Lincoln. Each fell a victim of assassination at the beginning of his second administration; but as the shadows of death fell upon them each could lay down his burden with the knowledge and conviction that his work was done and his duties fulfilled.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0785.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the national hall of fame these two great men will be placed side by side--each representing a different type of American character and a great chapter in American history; the furrowed, melancholy features of Abraham Lincoln expressing the deep tragedy, the infinite sorrow of the gigantic struggle between brothers, with the Union and human liberty at stake in the conflict; the regular, open, and genial cast of William McKinley reflecting the self-confidence, optimism, happiness, and high aspirations of a nation that has come into its own and assumed its rightful and honored place among the family of nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
