<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-03">June 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Another Home Gone to Pieces]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0847</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0847.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-03">June 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[ANOTHER HOME GONE TO PIECES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4. - The suit for divorce filed by Stephen H. Bridges brings to light a shocking condition in our social setup. The correspondent in the suit is the famous (or infamous) Arthur Erelyn See, founder and high priest of the so-called "Absolute Life" cult. Mrs. Bridges, with her sixteen year old daughter, were among the first to be ensnared by this moron, who pronounced them the "chosen" or "elect" of the new organization.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bridges, a respected and active man of affairs, had not the slightest inkling as to what was transpiring until the whole sordid mess was exposed in the press. The scandal involving his wife and daughter aroused him to such an extent that he went to the "See Temple" with the intention of ridding the world of this human vulture, but unfortunately the police prevented the killing. Foiled, Mr. Bridges went home where he "read the riot act" to his erring wife and left the house. At his home at 130 Wrightwood Avenue he has since been conspicuous by his absence.</p>
   <p>The sixteen year old daughter, on account of her part in the plans of High <pb facs="5423969_2_0848.jpg" n="2"/>Priest See, has become a ward of the Juvenile Court. One wonders, when hearing of such practices, if a mother, who in addition to sacrificing her own self-respect drags a sixteen year old girl into such a scandal and disgrace, really can be even partly sane.</p>
   <p>It is indeed horrifying to behold the moral atrocities committed in the name of religion, and when one considers how woman and womanly virtues have been placed on such a high pedestal and been the object of man's respect and admiration, one wonders whether a woman should deliberately disregard all conventions and rush to the support of every new cult, regardless of its morals, with all the ardor in her soul.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
