<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-10">Jan. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Municipal Court</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-10">Jan. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE MUNICIPAL COURT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual report of the Municipal Court and its work, issued by Chief Justice Harry Olson (Swede), shows that this court has not been lazy. During the court year ending December 6, 1908, no less than 124,136 cases of various types were brought before the court. Of these cases 49,002 were civil; 10,187 were criminal; 56,742 were cases of both civil and criminal nature.....Of all these cases, at the end of the year there were 2,361 cases not yet decided....As is well known, the other courts are several years behind in their work. But then, the Municipal Court has in Chief Justice Harry Olson a leader who is capable of working and who is able to make other people work. It was fortunate for the city to get as chief justice in its new court a man of such outstanding ability as Harry Olson.</p>
   <p>The report points to strong faults in the present law concerning the Municipal Court and shows how these may be mended so that the court may be enabled to do <pb facs="5423969_2_0139.jpg" n="2"/>more and better work.</p>
   <p>The original intention was that the majority of ordinary criminal cases should be tried before this court after having been transferred to the Municipal Court from the Circuit Court. The Supreme Court had declared such transfer unconstitutional, however, and as a consequence the Municipal Court is devoting its time chiefly to the consideration of civil cases while the Circuit Court and the Superior Court must apply a disproportionate part of their time to criminal cases.</p>
   <p>This trouble could be avoided if a special grand jury were constituted for the Municipal Court. The task of the court in connection with criminal cases would then be made easier and simpler. The legislature has full right to adopt the necessary laws for this purpose, and Chief Justice Olson proposes that the required laws be enacted. It is to be hoped that the legislature will find time to carry through this desirable reform.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0140.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among other reforms proposed is the establishment of a special court of appeals for the Municipal Court, consisting of three of the judges of the court. This, too, is a reform which would aid justice in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Professional tramps, people who do not want to work, ought to be dealt with sternly, according to the report, in order that this evil may not spread. The report recommends punishment for these tramps consisting of imprisonment for longer periods than now is customary, combined with hard labor for the prisoner.</p>
   <p>Ordinary tramps, drunks, and other prisoners of this class ought to be located on farms provided by the city for the purpose in question. This, according to the report, would make possible a more suitable treatment of this type of prisoners.</p>
   <p>The report refers to a custom of long standing among the police, which ought to be abolished. When an officer has been given a warrant to serve it has <pb facs="5423969_2_0141.jpg" n="4"/>frequently happened that the officer simply put the warrant into his pocket, and nothing more was heard of it. This misuse of position has now been stopped. The Municipal Court has decreed that these warrants are to be considered public record, and has prescribed definite rules for their serving. A police officer who hereafter fails to serve a warrant for the purpose of aiding law breakers may be sent to Joliet.</p>
   <p>The Municipal Court has, in addition, discontinued many other customs inconsistent with justice, and which for years have constituted a condition of scandal in the city. On the whole, the Municipal Court has proven itself a court for the people, for the benefit of the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
