<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-09-23">Sept. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Triumph for Chicago Girls]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-09-23">Sept. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[TRIUMPH FOR CHICAGO GIRLS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2. Ranier Hall, on Saturday, September 16, was the scene of triumph for a trio of our Norwegian Chicago girls, Pearl Wetterlund, Natalie Jensen and Anna Meyer.</p>
   <p>Miss Wetterlund has a beautiful voice that captured her audience and held them, from beginning to end, spellbound with its richness and power. Coupled with a winning personality her voice and talent will carry her far in the realm of song.</p>
   <p>In solo and obligato Miss Jensen displayed a talent almost unbelievable in one so young and with only a year's (at Jacksonville Musical College) study. Her rendition of Tchaikowsky's compositions were masterful in tonal quality, and execution, her control and interpretation of the various moods in these difficult melodies seemed to bring into actual view the very soul of the great composer himself. Breathless suspense is but a meek phrase with which to describe the enchantment in which this girl held her audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Anna Meyer, at the piano throughout the program, proved herself a very able soloist and a perfect accompanist, a combination seldom found in old or young. In playing the perfect accompaniments to both vocal and instrumental soloists she demonstrated a wonderful knowledge of proper co-work with voice and instrument, while in her solo numbers her timing, phrasing and attack were worthy an artist of twice her years. Hail to all three!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
