<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1892-02-20">Feb. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Our Fair City</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0970</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0970.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1892-02-20">Feb. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">OUR FAIR CITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A glance at the streets of our fair city will arouse only disgust and melancholy. The present condition of our streets and alleys places our city government, as regards civilization, on a level with the individual whom tradition has credited with the tender sentiment of fellow sufferers (sic).</p>
   <p>What shall we do? It is a terrible tangle; how shall we ever get through it?</p>
   <p>These are the questions which just now perplex men and women and overwhelm public spirited citizens with shame and mortification if not with despair. The picture can hardly be overdrawn: exaggeration is not possible. Public indignation must vent itself and everyone should be aroused to a sense of his duty. Whoever has any responsibility in the matter should <pb facs="5423969_2_0971.jpg" n="2"/>be made to feel it. The pride and satisfaction felt in the splendid showing our city has made in material development only intensifies our mortification when we contemplate the indescribable filth. The consolation we may extract from the assurances of some patriotic travellers that other cities are just as bad is not adequate to our needs. To accept the explanation that the evil is inherent in our institutions and must be endured because it cannot be cured, is cowardly and unworthy of a community so justly noted for enterprise and public spirit.</p>
   <p>If a sense of propriety, if the instinctive love of neatness, if local pride and patriotism are insufficient to arouse us, sanitary and moral considerations should. For if the saying that cleanliness is next to godliness is applicable anywhere, it surely is in this matter.</p>
   <p>The condition of the streets in the business center of the city is barely tolerable; in more opulent residential quarters, it is bad. This probably accounts for the inaction of many of those who shape public sentiment <pb facs="5423969_2_0972.jpg" n="3"/>and have influence in matters of moment. They receive visitors from abroad, and hear flattering expressions from polite guests about our splendor and magnificence. It is all right to put our best foot forward and shut the closet doors when we have company, but we wish now that our most honored visitors might see the whole city as it is, might be taken through the kitchen and into the back yard, so to speak, and that they might turn about and show their amazement and disgust at the abominable spectacle, and shame us into action.</p>
   <p>What scenes we are called upon to witness every day in our streets! To a distance of six or eight feet from the mud-covered sidewalks, the streets a short time ago presented the appearance of plowed fields. At a couple of crossings, a mile apart, a few sad and disheartened-looking laborers might be seen in the act of opening a path across an avenue, but the never-ending procession of trucks and delivery wagons rendered the task well-nigh impossible and soon obliterated all traces of their effort. At <pb facs="5423969_2_0973.jpg" n="4"/>another place the mud was being shoveled leisurely into heaps in the gutter. This unusual activity made us wonder if a city election was to be held soon. But on the following day a merciful providence sent us a cold wave and the mud piles, cut through to the pavement by heavy wheels, were hard as rocks awaiting another thaw which would melt them again into mud, an event which already has taken place. Near viaducts and bridges, where they are less liable to be disturbed, municipal activity has been so great that monumental mounds weighing several tons may be seen. And the little boy, always watchful for the main chance, often looks wistfully towards heaven for a sign of snow that might cover the heaps and thus give him an opportunity for coasting.</p>
   <p>A sense of the ludicrous sometimes furnishes the only diversion from the monotony of nauseating nastiness. At about half past nine one windy morning, a well-dressed lady leaning on the arm of a courtly looking <pb facs="5423969_2_0974.jpg" n="5"/>gentleman, promenading along a busy thoroughfare on the West Side, attracted our eye. The whistling wind was at their backs. Too much absorbed in each other, they did not observe that they were passing one of the elephantine garbage boxes and that a huge wagon was stationed by its side and a couple of men armed with scoops were contemplating its enormous size. When the aforesaid couple were about ten paces beyond the box, one of the men plunged his scoop deep into the dry coal ashes with which his end of the box was filled, and pried up a half bushel of its contents, most of which was at once caught by the wind and enveloped the unsuspecting couple like a Dakota blizzard. In wonder and surprise both turned around to see whether a volcanic eruption had taken place, when the second volley struck them squarely in the face and made them turn their backs. We would not like to record the meditation that followed this incident in the minds of the outraged couple. Now if it had been a hot summer day, the odors accompanying this shower of ashes would have been even more distressing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0975.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>During the last hot season there was hardly a street on the West Side in which for several blocks from the river it was not necessary at frequent intervals to hold one's breath and nose and hasten by these filthy boxes. These are the localities where the less favored classes of the community are obliged to dwell because of the lower rents.</p>
   <p>In these places there are always many cases of poverty, of sickness and distress. The opulent often look with contempt upon these people on account of the evidences of filth and degradation about them. There may be cause for this at times, but what encouragement is there for thrift and cleanliness amid such surroundings?</p>
   <p>If the proper authorities should enforce cleanliness in the streets and alleys and on the sidewalks in these quarters, it would do more both for the physical and moral amelioration of the people than missions and Sunday Schools. There is need of a Salvation Army with shovels and brooms instead of drums and quarters. You must literally prepare the <pb facs="5423969_2_0976.jpg" n="7"/>ground here before there is any use in sowing the seeds of higher moral and mental life.</p>
   <p>There are many foreigners in these places, naturally enough; where else can the masses of the poor go? We often talk of the "hordes of ignorant and degraded foreigners who flock to our shores" as elements of danger to the community and the state. But this comes with rather poor grace from a community where wealth and luxury abound, but whose free institutions cannot enforce the simplest demands of outward decency and show these strangers that something better is expected of them than to wallow in filth and nastiness. If we expect them to do their duty loyally to our institutions, these institutions must first arouse themselves to do their duty and set an example worthy of imitation.</p>
   <p>The innocent children in these quarters have no place to amuse themselves but in and around these heaps of mingled mud, ashes and manure. They can have no conception of cleanliness, and brought up amid such surroundings, every natural impulse towards decency will be blunted, if not <pb facs="5423969_2_0977.jpg" n="8"/>obliterated. Their sense of smell is dulled to such a degree that they may be seen even in summer playing hide and seek in and around these horrible boxes redolent with pestilential odors. This picture is not overdrawn. The only inhabitants in these quarters who have the means to carry on a somewhat successful warfare against the flood of filth are the saloon keepers, whose places are made conspicuously attractive. Amid such surroundings it is that this proud "Queen of the Prairies" is rearing her future citizens!</p>
   <p>We are fully aware that our city government just now is burdened with affairs of unusual magnitude and importance. Never before, probably, has city government been encumbered with greater cares. But that is not a sufficient excuse. The outward appearance of our city reflects the character of its government. It is not so bad at heart, but its extremities seem to be paralyzed. Whether this is a sign of premature decay or an evidence that full maturity has not yet been reached, may be a matter of doubt. We trust that the latter is the correct analysis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0978.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Our point of view is from the 17th Ward. Can anything be worse? Look at it today. A lady, boarding a car, finds her rubbers inadequate. She has barely placed her foot in the mire, when she is bespattered to the shoulders by mud from the hoofs of a passing team. Yesterday we waded heroically through the mud southward as far as the middle of the 19th Ward, in order to assure ourselves of the pre-eminence of the glorious 17th. On Blue Island Avenue a scene was witnessed which would have touched the heart of Ward McAllister. A little dog, probably belonging to the "better people", had by some chance gotten into the middle of the street. There it stood looking alternately at both sides of the street and then at its feet. Finally it set up a howl of despair to the great amusement of a number of onlookers. We retraced our steps in sadness. If that dog should ever visit the 17th Ward, it would never get out alive.</p>
   <!-- 5423969_2_0979 omitted, duplicate of 5423969_2_0980 -->
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0980.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Each ward is said to have two aldermen; they work with their heads. It is also said that the city is provided with a large force of inspectors of all kinds, of streets, of alleys, of sidewalks, etc., these work with their eyes, if they have any. But where on earth are the men who work with their hands? How shall we get through the mire, political and otherwise?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
