<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-20">Feb. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Bjorgvin Children's Chorus</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Walter Hjertstedt, President of the Chorus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1727</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1727.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-20">Feb. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">BJORGVIN CHILDREN'S CHORUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Walter Hjertstedt, President of the Chorus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bjorgvin Childrens' Chorus has in the past taken part in several programs, including the festival at Orchestra Hall honoring Bjornstjerne Bjornson on the occasion of his seventy-fifth birthday, and has won much applause. It is therefore desirable that we now gain support from the Norwegians in Chicago in connection with the concert planned for the benefit of the Norwegian Orphanage. We hope to be successful, and it is important that the children meet in full numbers for the practice sessions which are to be held regularly at Bjorgvin Hall, 876 North Artesian Avenue, every Saturday afternoon at two o'clock. Parents are urged to send their children. Past members as well as new members are invited.</p>
   <p>While the main purpose of the Chorus is to perform in behalf of a worthy cause, it should also be remembered that the children in the Chorus learn <pb facs="5423969_2_1728.jpg" n="2"/>many beautiful Norwegian songs. Children who lack the desired knowledge of the Norwegian language will be given an opportunity to get acquainted with the language of their parents. If we are to develop into good American citizens, it is important that we should also be or become good Norwegians. For this reason I plead for sturdy co-operation.</p>
   <p>Editorial Comment: The foregoing appeal made by the young president of the Bjorgvin's childrens' chorus is of importance, and it is to be hoped that all Norwegian parents in Chicago will take it to heart and send their children to the song rehearsals.</p>
   <p>The preservation of Norwegian singing by the growing generation is an important item in the work for the maintenance of Norwegian traditions, and this cannot be done any better than through the work of a children's chorus such as the one mentioned above.</p>
   <p>Under Miss Lulu Lund's leadership the children are in good hands; she is <pb facs="5423969_2_1729.jpg" n="3"/>greatly interested in her work, and her energetic efforts have already borne good fruit. Since, in addition, the Chorus has set for itself the goal of assisting in the task of building the new Norwegian Orphanage, the parents ought to be all the more eager to have their children join the Chorus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
