<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1891-06-07">June 7, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">County Hospital Still in Limelight</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0726</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0726.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1891-06-07">June 7, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">COUNTY HOSPITAL STILL IN LIMELIGHT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Herald of yesterday has an account of another patient in the Eighth ward of the County Hospital. What this patient, Mrs. Christina Silox, of 222 North Clark Street, relates, confirms in every particular Selma Berg's account of the treatment received by Miss Berg and Miss Johnson, and refutes quite effectually the defense which Warden Taylor of the Hospital sought to make to the County Board, before which he was summoned.</p>
   <p>We take the liberty of quoting from the Herald what Mrs. Silox said in reference to Anna Johnson and Selma Berg, as follows: "On the day Miss Berg was released, Mrs. Silox says she saw Nurse Fay drive two sick women from the ward, whose cases were recently published. She says they were scarcely able to stand. One of the women, Anna Johnson, fell dead of exhaustion and heart failure at 108 North Elizabeth Street the same day. Her companion's name was Selma Berg."</p>
   <p>Here we have the testimony of a disinterested eye witness, fully confirming <pb facs="5423969_2_0727.jpg" n="2"/>Selma Berg's statement that both of the young women were driven out against their wishes. We will simply add that according to Selma Berg's understanding of the case, Nurse Fay did not drive the young women out of her own accord. Selma Berg got the impression that Nurse Fay acted under orders, and this impression is without doubt the correct one. It is not to be supposed, that the nurses have authority to discharge or retain patients of the County Hospital. This authority rests with the Hospital Warden, and with him alone. He, therefore, and no one else, can be held responsible for the carrying out of such orders.</p>
   <p>We take the liberty also to quote from the Inter Ocean of yesterday Warden Taylor's explanation to the Public Service Committee of the County Board in regard to the case of Anna Johnson and Selma Berg, as follows: When Warden Taylor was asked to explain he did so volubly. "Some people seem to think, said that official, "that when a person is discharged from the hospital there is reason that he should live forever." He went on to state that the rule <pb facs="5423969_2_0728.jpg" n="3"/>was imperative that the house physician should attend to the discharge of patients. He, himself, never saw a patient who wished to be discharged, unless such patient came to him.</p>
   <p>"Now the facts are these," he continued, "This woman was suffering from typhoid fever and was convalescent. She demanded to be discharged, and we had no option in the matter. Gentlemen, the County Hospital is not a jail, and we have no power to keep any one against his will. "Supposing a patient is delirious and wants to go?" asked General Smith, "would you grant the request?" The Warden hesitated, and replied he thought such a patient would be retained.</p>
   <p>It was finally decided to refer the matter to the Hospital Committee to thoroughly investigate. "And please find out," suggested General Lieb, "whether under the rules of the hospital, or by the rules of humanity, the Warden has the right to keep patients until they are fit to go out."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0729.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When Warden Taylor's explanation is compared with that of Selma Berg and Mrs. Silox, it needs no comment. The committee of the Board will doubtless be able to estimate it according to its true value.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
