<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-12-16">Dec. 16, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Historic Words</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0569</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0569.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-12-16">Dec. 16, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">HISTORIC WORDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another chapter has been added to the glorious American saga of this historic year. It is brief, a single sentence that fell from the President's lips in the legislative halls at Atlanta. But the utterance, at once bold, magnanimous, and statesmanlike, embodies one of the most important results of the war in a manner that has touched the northern and thrilled the southern heart, and forever blotted out the last vestige of the Mason and Dixon line.</p>
   <p>The mission of war is to make peace, and our armed conflict with Spain has wrought peace in a double sense; it has put an end to bloodshed in the former Spanish colonies and to the lingering sectional war in our own land. Grant's wish has come true at last, and it fell to the lot of President McKinley to proclaim its happy and auspicious fulfillment. "Let us have peace!" was the prayer of the magnanimous victor upon sheathing his sword after the fratricidal war. After the happy conclusion of another, more fortunate war, in which <pb facs="5423969_2_0570.jpg" n="2"/>the former foes fought shoulder to shoulder, another President carries the long wished-for message to the people of the South that "the time has come in the evolution of sentiment and feeling, under the providence of God, when, in the spirit of fraternity, we (the people of the North) should share with you in the care of the graves of the Confederate soldiers."</p>
   <p>The audience quickly caught the deeper meaning of these significant words. It was electrified as if by magic and poured out its pent-up feelings in a flood of indescribable enthusiasm. One Confederate veteran had pressed forward until he was leaning against the speaker's desk, hanging on each word the President uttered, and when reference was made to the Confederate dead, this old man buried his head in his arms and while the cheers rang out, he cried like a child. "The stigma had been removed from the 'lost cause'. It had been hallowed, as it were, by the nation's recognition of the devotion and valor of those who gave their lives for it, and through the sacrifice of their sons for the honor of the 'old flag'. The disgrace of defeat, always the <pb facs="5423969_2_0571.jpg" n="3"/>greatest obstacle to a complete reconciliation between the vanquished and the victor, vanished before this tender and graceful tribute to the memory of the Confederate dead."</p>
   <p>President McKinley's happy faculty of saying the right thing at the right time and in the right place has probably never been better illustrated than on this memorable occasion. He went to Atlanta to inaugurate the first jubilee held in a southern city and he brought a message of peace that has made the old flag dearer to all the people of the South. History will treasure his utterance as the complement of Grant's prayer, and both as landmarks in the evolution of national sentiment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
