<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-01">Sept. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Development of Agriculture</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-01">Sept. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOPMENT OF AGRICULTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The value of the products of agriculture in the United States of America has practically doubled during the past ten years. The total value of such products in 1899 was, according to the census of 1900, $4,717,000,000. The following year, the value was estimated at $5,017,000,000, and in 1901 agricultural production was valued at $5,317,000,000.</p>
   <p>From the period subsequent to 1903 we have estimates based upon careful studies by the experts in the Department of Agriculture. According to these studies, the value [of agricultural production] for the years 1903-1908 was as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1903</cell>
     <cell>$5,917,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1904</cell>
     <cell>6,159,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1905</cell>
     <cell>6,309,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1906</cell>
     <cell>6,755,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1907</cell>
     <cell>7,488,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1908</cell>
     <cell>7,818,000,000.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0904.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The reports present the value of the crops on the farms as of December 1 of every year, in other words, the value of the crops to the farmer or producer. The amounts which have been paid by the consumers in this country or abroad would, of course, be much higher, because it would include handling, freight, and the services of the various intermediaries in distribution. No estimate has yet been presented by the Department of Agriculture for the present year.</p>
   <p>A well-known trade journal has made estimates, however, according to which the value of agricultural products for 1909 amounts to $8,481,000,000. This figure is based upon the official estimates of the yields of the various crops, and the probable prices to be paid the producers on December 1. The total yield is separated into two groups. The first group comprises fourteen products with a total value of $4,695,000,000. The second group comprises ten products, including livestock, and represents a total value of $3,786,000,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0905.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our country has made enormous progress in almost every field. Farm products, however, have doubled in value during the past ten years, and the progress here surpasses that achieved in practically any other field. And yet, agriculture in the United States has hardly stepped out of its childhood shoes. Only during the past few years have the farmers started practical or scientific farming....</p>
   <p>What may not the soil of America produce when all of it is cultivated in a scientific, practical manner, and when up-to-date care is provided for live-stock! The future of the greater part of our people is bound up with agriculture; this is something anybody can understand. The greater the progress of farming, the greater the rise in prices. For this reason, everybody who is at all able to do so ought to get hold of some land, before land becomes too expensive for the common people to secure.</p>
   <p>Many farmers consider it important to have their boys go to college to get "higher education", so that they may become lawyers, doctors, merchants, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0906.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But the best way of safeguarding the future of the farm children is to provide a farm for them and give them an opportunity to learn up-to-date farming. No profession can surpass farming as far as good living is concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
