<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-07-18">July 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Government Ownership</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-07-18">July 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">GOVERNMENT OWNERSHIP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The suggestion made in the Young People's Department by Mr. Mason and others, during the past year, that discussions on political and social problems be conducted, has received the approval of many but has not been acted on to any extent. It is our purpose, therefore, briefly to touch upon a question which, though agitated considerably in some parts of the United States, has not received the candid and unbiased consideration of the majority of intelligent citizens. It is the problem of government ownership and control of the means of transportation of passengers and freight and of the means of communication, i. e. railroads and telegraph facilities.</p>
   <p>To delegate any of the prerogatives of republican government to private individuals or corporations is dangerous to national liberty and personal security. That the operation of the great agencies for transporting "intelligence" [this word appears in English in the original text] and passengers and freight is <pb facs="5423969_2_0713.jpg" n="2"/>clearly the duty of the government can scarcely be doubted. For when we consider the fact that they [the aforesaid agencies] control the destinies of the nation, that they are mighty cords which bind us together as one people, we can only conclude that the rights, the liberty, and the happiness of every citizen depend upon the operation of these agencies in such a way as to preclude the possibility of private interests menacing the public welfare.</p>
   <p>It is a profound truth that no part of this nation produces all the necessities and comforts of life, and that no man produces with his own hands enough to feed, clothe, and house himself and those dependent upon him. Every worker marches to the music of machinery and the hum of industry with the hope that he can produce more of a particular article than he wants for himself, and that he can contribute his surplus production to men engaged in other vocations, in order to receive in return a just proportion of their production. And it is by this means that the farmer of the West is permitted to wear the clothing made in the East, while the tailor of the East is permitted to eat the bread <pb facs="5423969_2_0714.jpg" n="3"/>[made of wheat] raised in the West.</p>
   <p>The duty of the government, as I interpret it, is to promote the welfare of all the people, granting special privileges to none, protecting all from oppression, and safeguarding the interests of everyone. Is it not obvious that these corporations [railway and telegraph companies] have the people at their mercy as regards the rates they charge? Does not the government give the railroad corporations the right of compelling landowners to sell them right of way through their [the owners'] property? Is it just, then, that they should be permitted to charge whatever suits their convenience for transporting the products of these same landowners? Is it not the duty of the government to see that people are not subjected to rank discrimination and unjust exactions anywhere along the great steel highway of distribution?</p>
   <p>But some say: Legislate to keep them within bounds. What has this kind of legislation accomplished in the past? How have such laws been observed? As an example of the respect corporations usually entertain for restrictive legislation, the national banks might be cited. The government sought to control <pb facs="5423969_2_0715.jpg" n="4"/>them in the interests of the people by providing that the banks could not charge a higher rate of interest than that prescribed by law. What is the result? A little office adjacent to nearly every national bank in the land is appropriately furnished, and in these private offices you will find the cappers [slang for agents] of the bank--operating under the pretense of a private account--loaning the funds of the banks at from one to two per cent per month. It is a striking illustration of the inability of the government to control public institutions when private interests are involved. Nowhere is there a single instance of the government having succeeded in controlling public institutions in the interest of the people as long as such institutions were privately owned. And it is always an open question in the public mind whether the government controls the corporation or the corporation controls the government. Viewed in the light of history, this doubt is dispelled by preponderance of evidence showing that corporations have controlled governments.</p>
   <p>The postoffice furnishes an example of the success, the desirability, and the <pb facs="5423969_2_0716.jpg" n="5"/>benefits of government ownership and control. We do not hear accounts of low wages or of people complaining of excessive rates or extortionate charges here. Nor do we hear of them [the postoffice officials] spending millions every year to subsidize the press and to deceive the people. Now the question arises: Is the transportation of human intelligence written on paper [i. e. the transportation of mail] any more the duty of the government than the transportation of goods? Is human thought more sacred when inscribed on paper than when it is flashed by wire across the continent in the twinkling of an eye?</p>
   <p>Government ownership [of railroads] is a success in the countries where it exists. Rates are less than one-half of those in the United States, and still the railroads provide large revenues to those governments.</p>
   <p>That the railroads are notorious for bribery and other dishonorable means of securing power is well known. They exercise a widespread detrimental and <pb facs="5423969_2_0717.jpg" n="6"/>dangerous influence in the politics of our country. How does it comport with the American principles of freedom and liberty to submit to this oppression? Tyranny has many guises. In the United States it domineers by force of wealth. Should we not rise against it before it becomes too powerful to crush?</p>
   <p>Many, no doubt, are in favor of government ownership, but are at a loss as to how to acquire possession of the railroads. Why should railroads be exempt from the law of the land? When they become a menace to the peace and prosperity of the people, it becomes the duty of the government to assume control of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
