<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-03-08">Mar. 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Vote Trading Is Corruption</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0353</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0353.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-03-08">Mar. 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">VOTE TRADING IS CORRUPTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a letter to the Municipal Voters' League, friends of Alderman Stanwood attempt to set his record right by stating:</p>
   <p>"In every instance where he is charged with having voted for a so-called 'boodle' ordinance, his vote was not made with corrupt intent, but in order that he might secure votes for some meritorious measure that would benefit all of the people."</p>
   <p>This being the case, they think he is entitled to renomination, so that he may continue to do wrong in order that good may result. And these men are reputable citizens! They rush to the defense of their friend, apparently oblivious of the fact that their plea in behalf of his conduct argues a condition of public morality which, of necessity, will breed corruption.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0354.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Cole, the president of the Municipal Voters' League, replying for the executive committee of the League, punctures their corrupt logic in the following sledge-hammer style:</p>
   <p>"We regard this defense of Mr. Stanwood, which is put forward by men of your standing, as painful evidence of the low standards by which city officials have come to be measured by even good citizens. Gentlemen, has it not occured to you that the defense which you suggest for Mr. Stanwood--that he gave his vote for corrupt measures in exchange for votes for meritorious ones--is a defense which is equally available to the most notorious 'boodler' in the council? Do you not know that this is one of the most insidious and common forms of legislative corruption? Would you have a reform movement endorse the support given to corrupt ordinances in exchange for the votes of their sponsors in behalf of meritorious measures?"</p>
   <p>It is well that the issue has been thus squarely drawn. The system of trading votes is really the most powerful lever for corruption in all our legislative <pb facs="5423969_2_0355.jpg" n="3"/>assemblies. The boodlers will organize and block every measure until their support is bought with votes for their corrupt schemes. Honest men find that they can accomplish nothing unless they make terms with the "gang", and thus the whole legislative machinery is placed at the mercy of the boodlers.</p>
   <p>Until we can uproot this pernicious system, we cannot have clean legislation. And the way to uproot is to uproot.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
