<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-08-26">Aug. 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Why Is He Silent?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-26">Aug. 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">WHY IS HE SILENT?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Colonel Bryan contends strongly for the principle of "the consent of the governed" in the Philippines, and he condemns the course pursued by the administration as the policy of the bully and the coward". He used this epithet the other day in a speech delivered at Auburn, Nebraska. Colonel Bryan is still silent, however, about the consent of the governed as practiced by his party in the southern states. The Negro is a sovereign citizen, entitled to the privileges of American citizenship, including a share in the government. He was robbed, however, of his vote until the Democrats grew tired of the task and concluded to rob him of his franchise. The methods by which the colored citizens of the South were deprived of their right to be governed by their consent is thus graphically described by Senator Tillman in a recent speech:</p>
   <p>"We took the government away. We stuffed the ballot boxes. We shot the Negros.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are not ashamed of it.</p>
   <p>"With that system--force, tissue ballots, etc.--we ourselves grew tired. So we called a constitutional convention, and we eliminated, as I have said, all the colored people we could eliminate under the fourteenth and fifteenth amendments."</p>
   <p>What sort of a policy is that? Let the Kansas City platform speak:</p>
   <p>"We declare once more that all governments instituted among men derive their powers from the consent of the governed; that any government not based upon the consent of the governed is a tyranny, and that to impose upon any people a government of force is to substitute the methods of imperialism for those of a republic."</p>
   <p>Colonel Bryan knows that his party in the South has "substituted the methods of imperialism for those of a republic" and disfranchised millions of colored <pb facs="5423969_2_0701.jpg" n="3"/>citizens. He knows that imperialism in the South is not a phantom but a fact, the greatest of all dangers that confront the republic. But he has no word of condemnation for this national sin. The southern Democrats may publicly glory in their shame as much as they list, Colonel Bryan has no word of reproach for them. On the contrary, he selected Colonel Tillman to help him frame the platform declaration about the consent of the governed.</p>
   <p>Why this silence? How is it that Colonel Bryan has not a whisper of censure for the policy of the bully and the coward in the South? Does he maintain silence because he knows that this policy is the very foundation of the political power of the Democratic party, and that his own hope of election is based mainly upon the imperialism in the southern states?</p>
   <p>Let Colonel Bryan explain. The people have a right to know. Perhaps he can show to their satisfaction that his silence is an evidence of sincerity, not of inconsistency, of courage, not of cowardice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
