<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-10-24">Oct. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Fiftieth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-10-24">Oct. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Early in June, 1870, a young musician, John G. Lindtner, arrived in Chicago from Norway. He was Norwegian from top to toe, and he said that he "was very proud of his fatherland". In those days Chicago had no Scandinavian turner society. Lindtner called a meeting on August 14, 1870, to discuss organizing a Norwegian singing society.</p>
   <p>On September 11, a few days before the first meeting, John Winger joined the group, and on September 25 Hans Nordahl and George Holst became members of the small company that originally organized the Norsemen's Singing Society. [Translator's note: In later years, the chorus was called "The Norwegian Singers".]</p>
   <p>Later, on the eve of the first meeting, several other representative and outstanding men of the Norwegian Colony joined. We mention a few, such as Lars Kjolberg, Bernt Olsen, Carl Jensen, Conrad Grimm, <pb facs="5423969_2_1450.jpg" n="2"/>Johan Hafsten, Chr. Junge, the society's first president, Chr. Gray, Nils Peter Dahl, Frithjof Dahl, A. C. Christensen, Martin Losby, John Remerson, Hans P. Hansen, Lars G. Bredesen, Thor Thorson, Olaus Olesen, P. Holst, Hans Winger, O. H. Josten, John Lundin, Chr. Paulsen, E. Amundsen, E. Severson, and Christian Tonberg. Nearly every one of these men became active, either socially, politically, or organizationally, in the life of the Norwegian Colony.</p>
   <p>Several of the members wanted to call the new society the "Scandinavian Singing Society," but Lindtner, the nationalist, arose and said, "If we do not call the society 'The Norsemen's Singing Society', you may then count me out; and I will organize my own chorus." So the chorus accepted the name.</p>
   <p>The first president was Christian Junge. It was decided that the Society should have both active and inactive members. As we see, the first Norwegian singing society was organized on a national basis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1451.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the latter part of the year 1872 the Society gave its first concert, calling it a serenade for Ole Bull. In 1873, Ole Bull donated fifty dollars to help defray current expenses. In the same year the Society established a library of a thousand volumes.</p>
   <p>On August 7, 1874, a well-known singer, J.W. Colberg, was elected director.</p>
   <p>The first home of the Society was Kulamina Hall, on Green Street. The quarters were very primitive. They had once been occupied by a saloon, and later by a church. The Society later removed to 107 Milwaukee Avenue, where it remained from 1874 to 1878. From 1878 to 1894 it was located in Erickson Hall, 228-30 Milwaukee Avenue, and in 1894 the Society removed to Normanna Hall, just across the street. Two years later Schoenhofen's Hall, Milwaukee and Ashland Avenues, became its headquarters. So for thirty-seven years the Society was on Milwaukee Avenue. In 1911 the Society removed to Wicker Park Hall.</p>
   <p>In 1870 the Society had sixty-two members. It was incorporated in 1876.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1452.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the winter of 1880 the chorus gave a serenade for Bjornson. The first big concert was given in 1881, in Central Music Hall, and the Society received its first real recognition in the American press.</p>
   <p>Below we give a few historical milestones in the history of the Society.</p>
   <p>On October 30, 1870, the organization was named "The Norsemen's Singing Society". The first executive board consisted of Chr. Junge, Olaus Olesen, and Carl Jensen. John S. Lindtner was instructor. The hall was at 204 North Desplaines Street, near Milwaukee Avenue. A proposal of affiliation offered by the Scandinavian Workers' Singing Society was voted down.</p>
   <p>At the first meeting at Aurora Turner Hall a motion was made and carried that all active members be required to donate twenty-five cents at each meeting to fill the punch bowl. The vote was unanimous. At the following meeting the minutes reported that every member was present, and they emptied the punch bowl.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1453.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On July 8, 1872, the centennial anniversary of King Harald the Fair-haired was celebrated. Over 5,000 Norwegians attended this celebration.</p>
   <p>In 1870 the Society sang in a concert with the Swedes in a serenade for Christian Nilson, under the direction of John S. Svendsen.</p>
   <p>In 1876 the Society was part of the international chorus at the formal opening of Humboldt Park.</p>
   <p>The following men have functioned as instructors: 1870-1872, John S. Lindtner; 1872-1873, August Vhe [a Swede]; 1874-1899, John W. Colberg; 1900-1903, Kristian Nilsson [a Swede]; 1903-1913, Gustav L. Carlson; 1912-1914, Kristian Nilsson; 1914- , Otto Clausen.</p>
   <p>The oldest Norwegian society in America is Nora Lodge No. 1 R. H. K. [Knights of the White Cross]. The oldest singing society in America is <pb facs="5423969_2_1454.jpg" n="6"/>Normanna of La Cross, Wisconsin. Hauman G. Haugan, the Chicago banker, organized it.</p>
   <p>Hans Oftedal has written the history of the Society. It is offered for sale by the John Anderson Publishing Company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
