<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-14">Oct. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Women and the Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-14">Oct. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE WOMEN AND THE ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Had I the honor of being a voter I would cast my vote for William McKinley," says Clara M. J. Farson, president of the Illinois Federation of Women's Clubs. Other well-known club women who have expressed their views agree with her. They favor the re-election of William McKinley because, obeying the injunction of the Good Book, they believe in proving all things and in holding fast to that which is good; because he has shown himself to be worthy and true; because he stands for honor and prosperity at home and the civilizing and Christianizing mission of America abroad; and because the nation needs a tried and experienced pilot at the helm.</p>
   <p>The Republican managers have done well to enlist the active co-operation of our public-spirited women. Though their franchise is restricted, except in some <pb facs="5423969_2_0873.jpg" n="2"/>small western states, their intelligence and education, their refinement, enthusiasm, and experience exert a decisive influence in moulding public opinion upon all questions of importance; and unwise indeed would be the political manager who should fail to draw to himself this powerful ally. While the women cannot vote, they can make others vote. If a husband, brother, or son is too busy at his work to attend to his duty of insuring the permanence of our present prosperity, his wife, or sister, or mother will induce him to cast his ballot if anybody can do it. Woman's sense of impending danger is keen and subtle, keener than that of man; and though she has had no vote she has turned the scales of many important contests by arousing the voters from their sluggish apathy.</p>
   <p>It is fortunate that the political inspiration of woman is felt throughout the whole body politic and is by no means restricted to the circles in which most of our club women move. As we descend in the social scale, the political power of women increases rather than decreases. Great as is the influence of <pb facs="5423969_2_0874.jpg" n="3"/>the club woman that of her sister in the humbler walks of life is generally greater. The role of the club woman is mainly that of a political revivalist. She is competent to instruct, but the class of voters among whom she moves either do not need her instructions or they may reject them, while they are yet likely to listen to her entreaties to wake up and vote. Her unlearned sister who may not know much about the theories of free silver, or free trade, or the "constitution and the flag", etc., is, nevertheless, not only a revivalist but also a political instructor, and her teaching is generally both sound and effective.</p>
   <p>Look at our millions of wives and mothers in this broad land, on our farms and in our cities, towns, and villages--are they indifferent, or can they be in-different to the outcome of the election? No, they are, as they ought to be, most keenly alive to its bearing on the welfare and happiness of their homes. They know by instinct, if not from books, that government is for man and not man for government--that those policies are good which insure and promote the happiness of the homes while those that expose the home to misery and want are <pb facs="5423969_2_0875.jpg" n="4"/>destructive and bad. They know also that a happy home must be its own protector--that unless the influence of the home speaks through the ballot representing its voice there is no security for its welfare and comfort.</p>
   <p>The farmer's wife has no difficulty in persuading her spouse that he had better leave well enough alone. Better prices, mortgages lifted, improvements made and paid for, wants filled, comforts and luxuries added to their home, plenty of money at lower rates of interest--all these things are arguments that cannot but convince the most stubborn among rural hobby-riders.</p>
   <p>The task of the wife of the mechanic or workingman in the city is more urgent if not more difficult. If she be poor--if she is compelled to live from hand to mouth--her anxiety will be all the greater and her efforts to make her husband vote right all the stronger, because she knows, from sad experience, that the least disturbance may reduce herself and her children to want. These <pb facs="5423969_2_0876.jpg" n="5"/>humble mothers of the city who are never interviewed, may be weak on grammar; but they are strong on argument. In the forums of their own hearths they speak to their husbands with an eloquence no orator can match. When a mechanic or a workingman listens to what his wife has to say on the money question, he knows that she speaks to the point--that there are no alluring fallacies in her reasoning. When she discusses the dinner pail she knows what she is talking about--she knows that she could not fill it a few years ago while she can do it now. When she reminds him of their empty home, their ragged and hungry children of that time, she paints a picture that recalls to him his own vain efforts to get something to do, his grief at his inability to relieve the sufferings of those most dear to him. And when she points to their home now, to herself and himself, and to their well-clothed and well-fed children, and asks him whether he is going to sacrifice this comfort and happiness for the sake of glittering phrases he does not understand, because they mean nothing--for the sake of the dangers that do not exist, his common sense and love will dispel his error or doubt if he has been misled, he will gather his beloved wife and dear little <pb facs="5423969_2_0877.jpg" n="6"/>ones around him and say: "No, mother, such a fool and brute as that I am not. I promise you to cast my vote for you and the children and McKinley and Roosevelt."</p>
   <p>These are campaign meetings that tell. They occur every night in almost every home and are conducted in all languages. The arguments are the same and equally sound and forceful, whether presented by polished or unlearned tongues.</p>
   <p>Here we behold the most effective work done by women in this campaign; here is the strong force that will decide the election; the home is for William McKinley.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
