<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-13">May 13, 1911</date><title level="a">Glee Club Gives Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-13">May 13, 1911</date><title level="a">GLEE CLUB GIVES CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.............The concert given by the Norwegian Glee Club on Sunday April 7, at Bjorgvin Hall drew a crowd of "standing room only" proportions; literally hundreds were turned away. The committee had failed to send this correspondent a ticket, but, through the courtesy of Mr. Bjergsjo, we were fortunate in getting a seat inside the door where on account of late comers we only managed to hear snatches of the program here and there. We missed the first part of the concert but the remainder of the evening bore a resemblance to good old fashioned family gatherings. The chorus emphasized the popular in Norwegian music; old favorites predominated and among these were Borg's "Aftenroster," Linderman's "Jeg Ser Dig Utfor Gluggen," Paulsen's "Kjerringa Med Staven," and many others. A new song, (dedicated to the glee club) drew prolonged applause. It was Paulsen's "Den Store Sommer," which included variations in solo, quartette and humming accompaniment effects. The composition was in a lighter vein than other songs, but was heartily applauded as is the case whever one of his songs are sung, and that means often.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joel Mossberg (director) not only contributed solos during the program, but sang <pb facs="5423969_2_1662.jpg" n="2"/>the solo parts in chorus numbers, including "Den Store Hvide Flok" (The Great White Robed throng.) Piano solos by Miss Alphild Pedersen were masterfully executed including Liszt's "Campanella" and several compositions by Edward Grieg. Judging by the applause accorded her we can only come to one conclusion; those who heard her will want to hear her again and again.</p>
   <p>Another guest artist, who appeared for the first time in Chicago, was Miss Betzy Mickelsen, a young lady who, despite a Chicago cold, impressed her audience with a voice, art and personality that will win many friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
