<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-18">Sept. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Voters' Decision</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0671</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0671.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-18">Sept. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE VOTERS' DECISION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The charter proposal was overwhelmingly defeated, but the proposal for the municipal court was adopted. The politicians are sad. There is talk of a new charter convention.</p>
   <p>By 121,497 votes against 59,581 the voters of Chicago declared that they did not want the political muddle presented them.</p>
   <p>The opponents of the charter were quite sure in advance that they would win, but they had not expected the victory to reach such proportions as the figures indicate. The proposal concerning the municipal court was accepted by 90,100 votes against 71,363.</p>
   <p>This election shows clearly that the voters are awake; they are no longer led by political organizations. The days of the political machine politician are numbered. The power of the political bosses has received <pb facs="5423969_2_0672.jpg" n="2"/>a smashing blow. Many of these politicians have had their hands in the pie for many years because they could "control" their compatriots, the "ignorant foreigners," as the immigrants have so considerately been called by some of these political hangers-on. These immigrants showed - yesterday - that they are not to be led either by politicians of their own groups, or by those of other groups, and the sooner the politicians understand this the better for them.</p>
   <p>The results in the Norwegian Wards clearly show that the Norwegians voted against the charter. This is indicated by the following figures:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>For charter</cell>
     <cell>Against charter</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ward 15</cell>
     <cell>1,176</cell>
     <cell>3,999</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>" 17</cell>
     <cell>824</cell>
     <cell>2,894</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>" 27</cell>
     <cell>2,305</cell>
     <cell>5,695</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>" 28</cell>
     <cell>1,617</cell>
     <cell>4,277</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>" 35</cell>
     <cell>1,844</cell>
     <cell>3,108</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0673.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of course, the defeated politicians are not in a pleasant mood today. They predict darkly that Chicago is going to seed or ruin, that the legislature will wash its hands of the city and not trouble itself about conditions here anymore. All this, of course, is nonsense. The first steps have already been taken towards a new charter move, based on a charter, not for the benefit of politicians, but for the benefit of the people. Some time will elapse, of course, before a new proposal can be brought before the legislature, but we are convinced that the rumored opposition in the legislature is mostly a myth.</p>
   <p>Chicago has its own representatives in the lawmaking body, and no doubt they will win a hearing for the cause of the city. As far as the people of Chicago are concerned, the landslide yesterday will produce nothing but good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
