<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-03-13">Mar. 13, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Duty and Public Office</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-03-13">Mar. 13, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">DUTY AND PUBLIC OFFICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The acquittal of Civil Service Commissioners Kraus, Winston, and Washburne may be regarded as a handsome victory for the indicted gentlemen. The offense charged against them was the act of placing twenty-six policemen on the list of eligibles and certifying them to the Chief of Police in defiance of the civil service law or rule fixing five feet eight inches as the minimum height for patrolmen.</p>
   <p>Judge Waterman held that the board had a right to make rules which became binding upon it, and that, since no rule was set up in the indictment and since there was no violation of the civil service act itself, the indictment was faulty. Accordingly, a decree of "not guilty" was entered.</p>
   <p>While disposing of the criminal charge, a decree of "not guilty" which, as in the present instance, is based upon technical grounds carries no moral vindication. But even though the judge added: "While I by no means approve of all that the <pb facs="5423969_2_0277.jpg" n="2"/>commissioners have done," he should have censured them for what he regarded as their culpable acts. On the other hand, they are "not entitled to thanks for what they have undertaken or for what they have done," not even if it be assumed that they have done their duty. Public officials are not entitled to thanks for doing their duty. If they do their duty, their whole duty, and nothing but their duty, they are only "unprofitable servants". The thanks of the community are not due to any official unless he has done more than his duty and this is not claimed for the three gentlemen in question. On the contrary, Judge Waterman expressly states that they have done less. Hence his opinion upon this particular point is neither good law nor good public policy. His pleasantries were probably intended for balm, but clothed, as they are, in the garb of a judicial opinion, they are in poor taste and will be demoralizing in their effects.</p>
   <p>And right here another phase of this celebrated case comes into view: the disgraceful attacks upon the grand jury, especially upon two of its members. It is the duty and business of the grand jury to consider all cases of criminal violations of the laws that are laid before it and to return true bills whenever the <pb facs="5423969_2_0278.jpg" n="3"/>evidence produced appears to be conclusive--without fear or favor, or without any regard whatever to the social or political standing of those accused of crime. This is the plain duty imposed upon the grand jury under our Constitution and laws. It has not always been fully performed by the grand juries in this community. There has been a growing suspicion among the people that the meshes of the grand jury will catch the small criminal fry while permitting high-toned and influential offenders to escape. But the last grand jury was not open to this suspicion. It was made up mostly of well-known citizens of high character, and it performed its duties with courage and without fear or discrimination.</p>
   <p>The Indictment of the civil service commissioners may, or may not, have been due to a misunderstanding of the law; it may, or it may not, have been a "mistake". In any event, it cannot be regarded otherwise than as a conscientious performance of duty. The violent attacks upon the grand jury by the Mayor, the indicted men, and the whole crowd of officeholders under the administration are not only a disgrace to the city but outright anarchistic in character. And this <pb facs="5423969_2_0279.jpg" n="4"/>talk about "retaliation" against the foreman and other members of the grand jury is not only undignified but a public indecency. By giving encouragement to this kind of rot, the commissioners place themselves on a level with the thug who intimidates witnesses and promises that he will "get even" with the officers of the law. It is to be hoped that the people of Chicago will be spared this additional disgrace and humiliation. Judge Whiteman voiced public sentiment when he said:</p>
   <p>"I have no sympathy with the assults that have been made upon the grand jury in this case or upon the public press."</p>
   <p>One thing is certain: the effects of this "civil service case" will be whole-some. It has set a precedent that is needed in this community. It has demonstrated for once that social position and influence are not all powerful in the grand jury room--that we can get grand juries that will perform their duties without fear or favor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
