<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>. pp. 381-382.
<title level="a">[Biography of Thurvald Johnson]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>. pp. 381-382.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF THURVALD JOHNSON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thorvald Johnson, president and treasurer of the T. Johnson's Company manufacturers of cooperage and dealers in Coopers' stock, 206 North Carpenter Street, was born in Enebak, Norway, January 24, 1851. He came to America and Chicago in 1871. In 1877 he started in business in a small way, his first location being on Austin Avenue near Jefferson Street. The business grew and needing larger quarters he moved to 206 North Carpenter Street and later to 38th and Morgan Streets. He is now operating both plants and employs over 125 men steadily. During all these years he has never been troubled by strikes or discontent among his help.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson once ran for alderman of the seventeenth ward as an independent Republican. It is generally conceded that he was elected by a large majority, but he never took his seat. He secured all but seventeen votes in his own precinct.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1147.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the most beneficial things Mr. Johnson has done for the public was in helping to eliminate the manufacture of prison goods in competition with free labor. In 1892 a convention of manufacturers of cooperage throughout the state was held in Chicago to take vigorous action against this evil. A committee was appointed, of which Mr. Johnson was a member, to bring the matter before the governor of the state but with unsatisfactory results. Prison labor was finally abolished during Governor Yates term. When the Security Bond of Chicago was started in 1906, Mr. Johnson became one of its directors, an office which he still holds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
