<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 244-518.
<title level="a">[Biography of Tarris Wald]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 244-518.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF TARRIS WALD]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tarris Wald was born in Norway, June 19, 1847. The founder of Tarris Wald &amp; Co., left the employ of the Crosby Co., where he had charge of the die department and bought half interest about twenty years ago in the firm of Sieversen &amp; Jensen which was located in the Edison Building, on Market Street and the firm's name was changed to Jensen &amp; Wald. About six years later Mr. Wald bought out Mr. Jensen and operated under the name of Tarris-Wald &amp; Co. After the business left the Edison Building it was moved to 11 South Jefferson Street and later to the present quarters at the corner of Fulton and Jefferson Streets.</p>
   <p>Twenty years ago, the canning industry in this country was just beginning and naturally also can-making. Thus Mr. Wald prides himself on having made the first dies for cans used in Chicago. Since then the canning as well as the can-making industry has grown rapidly; can-making has grown fast enough to offer inducement for the formation of one of the largest trusts, the American <pb facs="5423969_2_1145.jpg" n="2"/>Can Co. In spite of this trust the growing demand for cans has led a number of independents to start can companies during the last three or four years. As far as the output of cans is concerned it is about six to four with the odds still in favor of the trust. Tarrus-Wald Co., in a way had grown up with the industry in which it is now engaged, that of can-making machinery. In the beginning when cans to a great extent were made by hand, they did a large business in dies, presses, small hand tools, etc. Later hand tools had to be replaced by small power machines and these again were replaced by automatic machinery. During the last two or three years the firm has made it their aim to push to the front with an absolutely complete line of automatic machinery. for all kinds of cans. The firm now stands at the head of the industry with complete lines of automatic machinery for anything in the trade.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
