<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-10">Feb. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Concert by a Young Chicago Artist]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-10">Feb. 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[CONCERT BY A YOUNG CHICAGO ARTIST]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday a young Norwegian-American pianist, James S. Whittaker, made his debut in the Chicago Music Hall. He studied in Berlin and Paris, and has returned to Chicago as a renowned artist.</p>
   <p>His reputation was more than justified by his masterful performance. His playing inspires one involuntarily to think of higher things. We came expecting something out of the ordinary, and out of the ordinary it was in every sense of the word.</p>
   <p>When a mere boy of twenty puts on a concert with Chopin's Sonata in B minor as an opening number and follows this difficult masterpiece with a series of Schumann's compositions, all perfectly played, one realizes that here is an artist with a real musical soul, one who is delving deep into the realms of great music, finding golden nuggets of beauty instead of kicking around in <pb facs="5423969_2_1620.jpg" n="2"/>the chaff of today's so-called popular music and finding exactly nothing.</p>
   <p>Chopin, Schumann, Grieg, and Liszt--an array of masters, all interpreted by a young man possessing a rich temperament, deep feeling and an intimate understanding of each individuality. Mr. Whittaker's technique is that of a virtuoso in its power to grasp and hold the heart of a vast audience to such an extent that during a pause in a selection one could have heard the sound of a pin dropping to the floor in the intense silence.</p>
   <p>What a difference when compared to the general run of music, when a pianist must be a magician or a witch in order to satisfy the taste and appetite of a ragtime-maddened twentieth century dance hall and nickel show public. Would that the latter could be eliminated at a stroke and only real music taught those who are musically inclined.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
