<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-08-14">Aug. 14, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Let the Women Vote</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0887</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0887.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-08-14">Aug. 14, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">LET THE WOMEN VOTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Should women have the right of suffrage? A great many say no and attempt to give some reasons for their positions, but these reasons either contradict one another or else are so ridiculous that they cannot settle to the ground. There is no solid foundation to build them upon. The class of people that do not have a right to vote are lunatics, criminals, insane people--and women. What an injustice to include women in that class! It is a shame! How long will the women tolerate it?</p>
   <p>People say this is a free country, where all have equal rights. If so, why do not women have the right to vote? Or are they not included in the "all"? It appears to me that women are in the same condition as The Old Thirteen [Colonies]. Do they not have to abide by the laws that are made, without having any voice in the making thereof? Are they not taxed without being represented in the government? Are they allowed to have anything to say about taxes? No, all they have to do is just to pay them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0888.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Again, we say that "the majority rules". Does that mean the majority of the people, the citizens, or does it mean the majority of the voters? And when we boast of having a government of the people, by the people, and for the people, we do not seem to remember that women are people too. There has been a theory entertained by some, that if women get the right to vote they will have to exchange places with men--give up the kitchen and assume the duties of men. If that is what we call women's rights, let them never be granted. Let women and men stay where they belong on that point; but let women help form the government that governs them as well as men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
