<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-10-31">Oct. 31, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">The Case of Ferris</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-10-31">Oct. 31, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">THE CASE OF FERRIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the morning paper Mayor Harrison has not been "entirely satisfied" with the record of Patrick N. Ferris, inspector of streets and alleys in the Seventeenth Ward, and previous to his departure for New York issued an order requesting the resignation of Mr. Ferris.</p>
   <p>If this be true, His Honor must have experienced a sudden change of heart. When Mr. Ferris was appointed inspector under the "sixty day" rule the Mayor knew that he was charged with complicity in election frauds committed in the fifteenth precinct of the Seventeenth Ward at the last municipal election. Subsequently, Mr. Ferris was indicted by the grand jury; but Mr. Harrison retained him as a servant of the city. The sixty days expired many weeks ago; but Mr. Ferris was not disturbed. These facts were brought to the special attention of Mr. Harrison by reputable citizens of the Ward, but they were unable to obtain any redress. Mr. Ferris clung to his job, drawing his salary <pb facs="5423969_2_0305.jpg" n="2"/>with never failing regularity. The only inference that could be drawn from these facts was that His Honor was "entirely satisfied" with the record of this man. Why he should have changed his mind at this particular time is somewhat of a puzzle. Can it be that the disclosures made at the last meeting of the Civic Federation have convinced some of Mr. Harrison's friends that, if he did not call for the resignation of the inspector before he left for New York, he ought to have done it, and that it would not hurt him to get the people to believe that he had really done it?</p>
   <p>As stated, Mr. Ferris has been indicted by the grand jury, but the indictment does not appear to worry either himself or his friends. They are confident that he will not be convicted. The belief is prevalent among them that the prosecution will be entrusted to some young assistant in the State's Attorney's office who will lose no sleep should the jury disagree or acquit. It may be of some use to State's Attorney Deneen to know that such things are whispered among Mr. Ferris' friends in the Seventeenth Ward.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0306.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Alderman Walsh has done more than any other one man to break up the gangs that for years have been tampering with the ballot and stealing elections in the Seventeenth Ward. If the criminals should escape, now that proofs against them are so overwhelming, the things would take fresh courage and intrench themselves more firmly than ever. However, the good people of the Ward have confidence in the integrity of the State's Attorney and hope that Mr. Walsh will follow up his good work by rendering the prosecution such assistance as is in his power and is proper for him to give.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
