<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 245.
<title level="a">[Central Manufacturing Company, Pioneers]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 245.
<title level="a">[CENTRAL MANUFACTURING COMPANY, PIONEERS]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Manufacturing Company is the largest manufacturer of office desks in Chicago and is entirely composed of Scandinavians. The president, Mr. Nils Anderson, has been engaged in the manufacture of furniture for the past forty years; in fact, he is one of the pioneer furniture manufacturers of Chicago. The secretary, Mr. Alf. Norman, has been connected with the Company since 1899.</p>
   <p>At the present time furniture making constitutes so large an item in Chicago industrial output, and Chicago's large enterprises in that trade are so many and so strong, as to bar from special notice any concern not exceptional either in magnitude or character.</p>
   <p>Exclusion on this count however, does not touch the Central Manufacturing Co., whose huge factory at 37-41 Armour Street produces the most complete and salable assortment of roll-top and flat-top office desks and office furniture in the West.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1129.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From this fine plant with its acre of floor space, its $90,000.00 machinery set up, its corps of more than six score expert artificers in wood; the Central Manufacturing Company turns out a line of business furniture containing sixty styles of desks, twenty styles of library tables, and a long list of other specialties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
