<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-07-08">July 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Dramatic Critic of Skandinaven Weds]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1016</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1016.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-07-08">July 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[DRAMATIC CRITIC OF SKANDINAVEN WEDS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Elizabeth Anderson, musical and dramatic critic of Skandinaven for many years, is now Mrs. Marius Anderson. Mr. Anderson is a prominent merchant at La Crosse, Wisconsin, and Scandia wishes the newlyweds everything that is good during the coming years.</p>
   <p>Our Norwegian colony will always remember Mrs. Anderson as one who always did her best in the really difficult position she held, and one who was at all times just in her criticism. Although Mrs. Anderson was born and raised in the United States of America, she has a thorough knowledge of Norwegian history, tradition, literature, and music, and it is this knowledge that has enabled her at all times to detect the false note in whatever production she witnessed. Circumstances surrounding the presentation of a play or concert were always considered when she wrote her criticism, and the sharpness of other critics was absent in her reports which, due to her intimate knowledge of the subject presented and the circumstances of production, were the drop of charity that has kept alive hopes that would have been utterly destroyed <pb facs="5423969_2_1017.jpg" n="2"/>by a more literal-minded or materialistic critic. Even though at times her criticism was not flattering, it was tempered with a mildness and understanding that won her an ever-growing host of friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
