<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-12-16">Dec. 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Ministers' Crusade</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-16">Dec. 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE MINISTERS' CRUSADE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of ministers and laymen was held in South Chicago the other evening to discuss the present conditions in Chicago. Many long speeches were made and finally a considerable number of resolutions were passed. These resolutions describe the conditions in Chicago and ended in hearty praise of Mayor Harrison for having taken steps in the direction of the "reforms" demanded. Further, it is stated that the time is ripe for the planning and execution of a "clear and firm policy with reference to the evils mentioned".</p>
   <p>Many able and prominent men were present at the meeting although it seems incredible that such could have been the case. To dignify with the name "reform" the temporary closing, for appearances' sake, of a few of the most notorious night cafes, is a misuse of language, a throwing of dust <pb facs="5423969_2_0212.jpg" n="2"/>into the eyes of the people. And to speak of a "clear and firm policy" at a time when it is evident to everybody that the only "policy" required and effective is the enforcing of the laws, tastes suspiciously of humbug.</p>
   <p>These ministerial crusades against vice are, on the whole, of doubtful value. Most certainly they do not benefit the participating ministers. The presupposition is, ever, that the ministers are constantly at war with the Devil and all that is wicked. But when they blow their war trumpets only now and then, the people will be prone to think that when the trumpet of war is not sounding, the ministers are taking their fight lightly. Still less do these ministerial crusaders benefit the cause of the people. As a rule the people are misled by the crusaders, the attention of the former being turned away from the main issue, the fact, namely, that the law is not enforced.</p>
   <p>A voter cannot extinguish vice in general, but if he is not misled he may refuse to reelect officials who disregard the laws, taking pains, on the <pb facs="5423969_2_0213.jpg" n="3"/>other hand, to place in office men who will enforce the laws. Just in regard to this, however, the ministerial crusaders mislead him. The crusaders start a movement; the politicians respond with some move or other which induces the ministers to adopt resolutions of "hearty approval" of steps in the direction of reform, and many people are led by this to think that all is well; that no vigilance is needed.</p>
   <p>If the ministers are to enter the field of politics they need to be not simple-minded as doves, but sly as serpents. If not, the politicians will know how to turn the work of the minister to their own account. The result will be that the voters lose sight of the goal and are rocked to sleep, and the final state of affairs becomes even worse than the initial conditions.</p>
   <p>Nobody doubts the good intentions of the ministers. As a rule, however, they conduct their crusade in such an impractical manner that the whole ends <pb facs="5423969_2_0214.jpg" n="4"/>in disappointment and defeat or, at best, with nothing gained.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
