<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-22">Aug. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Singing Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enthusiasm for the Trip to Norway</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1706</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1706.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-22">Aug. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN SINGING SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enthusiasm for the Trip to Norway</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It may indeed be said that the Norwegian Singing Society is advancing steadily. New members, both active and passive, are continually joining. At present there are fourteen new singers passing through their trial period, and new applications are being received at every meeting.</p>
   <p>One of the reasons for the present interest in the Society is the decision to undertake a trip to Norway in 1914 to participate in the centennial of Norwegian independence. At the same time it appears that there is a general increase in interest in our other singing societies as well.</p>
   <p>A number of the leading men in the Norwegian colony have been appointed to the committee on arrangements for the trip. This committee consists at present of the following men: John Anderson, publisher of Skandinaven; Dr. A. Doe, Consul <pb facs="5423969_2_1707.jpg" n="2"/>F. H. Gade, Carl Bergesen, C. J. Olsen, H. Oftedahl, O. Nelson, J. Braecke, and N. Hall.</p>
   <p>The following decisions [of the committee] may interest the singers: Regarding election of officials, it was decided that the director of the chorus was to be selected two years before the trip began, and that the president of the chorus is to be elected one year before the start of the trip. It was also decided that the acting president of the Society shall be acting president of the committee.</p>
   <p>N. Hall was elected secretary. The election of a treasurer was postponed. It was also decided that every active member must pay fifty dollars to the committee at least one month before the singers are to leave Chicago. This payment is to serve as guarantee that each member will properly fulfill his obligations to the chorus. The money will be returned in Norway when the official part of the program is over. It was also decided to invite the other <pb facs="5423969_2_1708.jpg" n="3"/>singing societies to participate. These various societies have not yet given any definite reply, but rumors are that they all want to take part.</p>
   <p>The committee has started a sort of a savings bank for the members of the chorus. A dollar or more may be deposited each wee.., and the money may be withdrawn only by the members themselves. There is also an opportunity for the passive members to join in this deposit scheme, and several of the latter have already deposited various sums.</p>
   <p>It has not been definitely decided whether singers from out of town may participate in the undertaking. The matter will be decided at a future meeting. The question of the size of the chorus was also considered. Musicians and men familiar with musical theory and technique have stated that a chorus of sixty or seventy men will be able to render a harmonious and creditable singing performance for the purpose intended, and that one might have a chorus of as many as one hundred voices, but not more....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1709.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A considerable number of singers have already applied for membership in the special chorus. Several of the other members of the Society have applied privately instead of waiting for the official decision of the committee. Applications will be received by the secretary and numbered in the order received. It may be appropriate to remind those singers who nave not yet applied for membership in the Society that they should apply as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>The extent of the singers' interest in the proposed trip...may be understood by anyone who visits one of the practice sessions on a Wednesday evening. The attendance is good, and the enthusiasm is high. It is easy to realize that the Society will have little difficulty in putting through its great undertaking; in other words, the trip to Norway promises to be a great success.</p>
   <p>The intended trip has also aroused great interest outside of Chicago. The secretary has received many letters concerning the trip from singers in the West and even from singers in Brooklyn. Several singing instructors have declared <pb facs="5423969_2_1710.jpg" n="5"/>their wish to become active singers in the chorus.</p>
   <p>The committee will meet soon to consider these various matters, including the question of the size of the chorus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
