<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">America's Reason for the War</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA'S REASON FOR THE WAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Speaking before a mass meeting Saturday night, Mr. Otto H. Kahn, an American of German birth, said in part:</p>
   <p>"America is not waging a war of vengeance or hatred, notwithstanding all the injuries and measureless provocations we have received. The divine lesson, which was given to the people of the east two thousand years ago on the mountain, still holds good as the only safe lodestar for the guidance of the world. We have lighted a fire to purity, not to burn at the stake.</p>
   <p>"If ever a nation entered a war after having maintained infinite forbearance in the face of grave menace and dangers and the most intolerable provocations and from motives as pure and as high as the great blue dome of heaven, America is that nation. We seek no reward whatsoever of a material nature. We seek no 'place in the sun' (to use the German Chancellor's term), but the <pb facs="5423969_2_0407.jpg" n="2"/>sun of liberty, and we do not seek selfishly but share with all the world. America is incapable of hating an entire people, but we do hate; we are fighting and we shall fight with every ounce of our might the spirit which has power over the people of Germany, and which if it were to prevail--as under God it never will--would destroy liberty, justice, and democracy.</p>
   <p>"It was not the people of Great Britain that America fought in the War of the Revolution, but the spirit and the ruling caste which then held sway over them, America fought for an ideal--for liberty and independence. America sacrificed blood and treasure, and suffered and endured and won. And so it will be now. The spirit of Prussianism and the spirit of Americanism cannot live in the same world. One or the other must conquer. In the mad pride of its contempt for democracy, Prussianism has thrown down the gauntlet to us. We have taken up the challenge and now stand arrayed by the side of the other freedom-loving nations of the world, giving our fresh strength and our boundless resources to them who, heroically striving, <pb facs="5423969_2_0408.jpg" n="3"/>have borne the heat and the burden of a dreadfully long and exhausting struggle, yet stand unwearied, erect, and resolute.</p>
   <p>"The enemy is of formidable strength, but even if he were far stronger than he is; even if we did not have the men and the means which are ours; even if our comrades in arms had not demonstrated their superb and indomitable prowess, still must our cause prevail. For there is fighting with us a force which has ever proved itself stronger than any other power on earth, and again and again has triumphed over overwhelming odds. That force, God-inspired, death-defying, and unconquerable, is the soul of man. And when--Heaven grant it may be soon?--the soul of the German people will have freed itself of the sinister powers that now keep it in bondage; when it will have found again the high impulses and aims of its former self; when it will once more understand and speak the universal language of humanity and right, then, in God's own time there will be peace."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0409.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Kahn, we know the Norwegian people agree with you wholeheartedly. You have spoken as any true American would and should speak. Yes, we want peace. But only after the monster of militarism has been removed from the face of the earth. We, the Norwegian-Americans, are with our government. We will back America to the last man, come what may.</p>
   <p>We are fighting for the freedom of the peoples. Peace? Yes, but with liberty!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
