<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-04-01">Apr. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Same Old Play</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-04-01">Apr. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE SAME OLD PLAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Grover Cleveland and his sturdy Secretary of State were as putty in the hands of De Lome, who made them believe that there was no war in Cuba and that the butcher Weyler himself was an angel from heaven.</p>
   <p>There has been a change of casts and a shifting of the stage setting both in Madrid and Washington, but the same performance is still going on upon the boards. The wily Sagasta is playing with McKinley and his cabinet precisely as De Lome hoodwinked Grover Cleveland and his advisers. There are good and strong men in the present cabinet, but it looks very much as if a majority of its members are old grannies compared with a man with the cunning of Sagasta. Neither the President nor his advisers are a <pb facs="5423969_2_0616.jpg" n="2"/>match for Sagasta at diplomatic fencing. The longer they keep it up the more assured will be their ultimate defeat.</p>
   <p>It is generally believed the President has submitted certain milk-and-water propositions to Spain. His "policy" is a mistake from the start. We owe no courtesy whatever to a nation of murderers. By every law of civilization and humanity, Spain has forfeited her rights to Cuba. For the government at Washington to appear at her door as a supplicant for concessions is compatible neither with the dignity of this land nor with the sense of justice and honor of our people.</p>
   <p>The only dignified proposition that President McKinley can, or could have, submitted to Spain is that she get out of Cuba instantly, unless she prefer to be driven out. If such action is not in line with his much advertised "policy", the best he can do is to get out of the way of Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
