<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-11-14">Nov. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayor and the 'S Job</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-11-14">Nov. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYOR AND THE <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>'S JOB</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Hale Thompson, titular head of the city government, has professed to feel surprise on learning that the chief belier inspector ordered the discharge of an employee of his branch of the municipal administration because a certain alderman, a brother of that employee, would not vote in the City Council in accordance with the supposed wishes of the Mayor. The inference to be drawn from Mr. Thompson's remarks is that he had given no directions to Boiler Inspector Nye to bring pressure to bear upon Alderman Bergen to induce him to support the administration's program.</p>
   <p>According to Alderman Bergen, the boiler inspector expressed regret at being obliged to discharge the alderman's brother and said that he was acting under orders. If Mr. Thompson did not direct the boiler inspector to discharge the man in question as a means of punishing an alderman for <pb facs="5423969_2_0107.jpg" n="2"/>failure to vote for the Mayor's program in the Council, who did? Who is giving orders generally about the City Hall in such a way as to make no end of needless trouble for the administration? Who is exercising the power of the Mayor of Chicago anyway?</p>
   <p>In his talk before the Association of Commerce Tuesday evening, Mr. Thompson called attention to the need for co-operation between the Mayor and the Council. He is right. The need is great. But who is responsible for the failure to secure co-operation? It is true that the Mayor has made enemies among the Aldermen by his Sunday closing order, but that is not the chief reason why Mr. Thompson has failed to secure the co-operation of the Council. One alderman expressed the view of many when he said: "We are ready for co-operation, but not for complete domination of the Council by the administration."</p>
   <p>The Chicago Civil Service Commission started the trouble by seeking to deprive the municipality of the services of experienced and capable efficiency <pb facs="5423969_2_0108.jpg" n="3"/>
    experts. This was followed by venomous and unjust attacks by the Commission on the work of certain Council <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>.  Mr. Thompson himself struck a blow at co-operation when he vetoed the just ordinance for the creation of a board of standards and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to be composed of aldermen and a representative of the city comptroller's office.</p>
   <p>It is evident that someone exercising great authority in the City Hall has been issuing orders calculated either to make the aldermen mere pawns in the hands of the Mayor or to produce serious friction between the Council and the administration. About the best thing Mr. Thompson could do at this time would be to find out who is Mayor--whether the real directing power in the City Hall is himself or some person holding the commission from the people of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
