<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-04-23">Apr. 23, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">The Rotation of Rascals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-04-23">Apr. 23, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">THE ROTATION OF RASCALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The contemplated Humphrey bill's steal furnishes another illustration of the absolute necessity of keeping constant watch upon our lawmakers. Most people are apt to consider their duty performed when they have cast their ballots and had them counted. They will then sit back and let matters drift until a new election is at hand. If they should then find that any senator or representative elected by their suffrage has been guilty of corruption or other forms of malfeasance, they will, or may, punish him by relegating him to private life--at least for the time being. New men will be chosen and when that is done the sovereign people will sink back into their former indifference and apathy.</p>
   <p>So it goes from one election to another, and meanwhile legislative corruption and bad or rotten legislation runs its course unchecked. Succeeding <pb facs="5423969_2_0322.jpg" n="2"/>elections are only so many attempts at locking the stable doors after the horses are stolen, and the only perceptible result of our legislative elections under such conditions is a more or less lively, or more or less complete, rotation of rascals in our lawmaking bodies.</p>
   <p>Legislative corruption is growing to such proportions that our system of representative government is in immediate danger of breaking down, and if we cannot remove this cancer from the body politic it will break down as surely as the sun will set today. Our efforts to arrest the course of corruption are generally spasmodic and often misdirected. We denounce the briber and the bribed, but we are prone to forget that the main source of the evil is the indifference, apathy and neglect of duty of which we, everyone of us, as individual citizens, are guilty. If the general standard of honor in public life were what it ought to be, only a comparatively small percentage of corruptible men would be elected to make our laws. And if a lawmaker were made to feel the Damoclean sword of public scrutiny, indignation <pb facs="5423969_2_0323.jpg" n="3"/>and wrath always suspended over his head, ready to drop at the least sign of wrong doing, he would be less liable to stray from the path of duty.</p>
   <p>Let us strain every nerve to put bribers in the penitentiary, even if they be found in the ranks of those who pass as our "leading" and "best" citizens. Let us relax no effort to give them the pleasure of enjoying the company of their tools. But let us not forget that eternal vigilance is the price of liberty and that we ourselves are the main source of the evils that threaten the peace and welfare of society, because we have been and are faithless watchmen on the ramparts of citizenship. That is the main reason why a rotation of rascals is one of the most striking features of our local law-making assemblies.</p>
   <p>Yes, let this be a call to arms, for our Scandinavian voters, against corrupt legislation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
