<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-12-04">Dec. 4, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Pledges of 1896</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-12-04">Dec. 4, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLEDGES OF 1896</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a Washington dispatch to the Times Herald, the President has again publicly declared his determination to redeem all the pledges of his party for a reform of the currency. His statement to H. H. Hanna was of great significance. "You can say," he said, "that I stand for monetary legislation, and that I am determined that every pledge the Republican party made along this line shall be kept."</p>
   <p>Under the caption: "Republicans must redeem their pledges of 1896," the Times Herald says editorially: "The decks are cleared for the Republicans to redeem the one pledge by which alone they won the Presidency in 1896 and the Senate in 1898. Here is the unfilled pledge of the St. Louis platform:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0708.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"' All our silver and paper currency must be maintained at parity with gold, and we favor all measures designed to maintain inviolably the obligations of the United States, and all our money, whether coin or paper, at the present standard of the most enlightened nations of the earth.'</p>
   <p>"This was a good enough Morgan to carry the Republican party into power in 1896. The pledge was reiterated in every Republican convention of 1898. A special session was summoned in 1897 to reform the tariff schedules. A special session must now be called to save the party honor. What the Republicans could not do in the Fifty-fifth Congress because of a silver majority in the Senate, they must do in the Fifty-sixth Congress when they have a majority in both Houses."</p>
   <p>The above statement is not the truth. The Morgan of 1896 was represented by the tariff and reciprocity plank and the following words of the money plank: "We are opposed to the free coinage of silver except by international agreement." This declaration was strengthened by a promise not to destroy any <pb facs="5423969_2_0709.jpg" n="3"/>part of our money then in use.</p>
   <p>What does the Times Herald mean anyway? Where is the unfulfilled pledge? It cannot be found in the above quotation from the money plank nor anywhere else in the national platform of 1896. Is there [anything the] matter with any of the money paid over the Times Herald counter? Is not every dollar of it as good as any other dollar, and every dollar as good as gold?</p>
   <p>In the nature of things the pledges made by the Republican party in 1896 concerning our money system were mainly of a negative character. Our entire financial system and our national credit were threatened with destruction, and the Republican party pledged itself to defend and maintain existing conditions. This pledge has been kept and will be kept inviolate. Free silver is crushed and "the gold standard is established as firmly as it ever possibly can be among people living under a republican form of government."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0710.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But the money plank of 1896 contains also two pledges of a positive character. One made it the duty of the administration to promote an international agreement concerning silver coinage. This promise has been fulfilled, though the efforts were fruitless on account of opposition encountered in Europe.</p>
   <p>By the other pledge the party bound itself to "maintain all our silver and paper currency of parity with gold." This pledge was aimed at rabid cranks of the Times Herald ilk, who were busy in the convention, striving with might and main to commit the party to a policy that would have led to disaster in 1896, as it will result in defeat in 1900 if the cranks are to have things their own way. Fortunately for the Republican party and the people at large, the cranks were defeated in St. Louis. But they have been at it ever since, demanding that the Republican party shall break its pledge to maintain all our silver and paper currency at parity with gold. That is the long and the short of this "currency reform" nonsense. The <pb facs="5423969_2_0711.jpg" n="5"/>"pledge" these busy-bodies have in mind is a pledge to them that they attempted to sneak into the platform, but in vain, because they were detected and caught in the act--a promise to wipe out the greenbacks. The pledge made to the people to maintain the greenbacks and all other forms of money at parity with gold, has been kept and will be kept.</p>
   <p>The effort of the Times Herald to misrepresent the President in the premises will deceive nobody. The people know that the "monetary legislation" favored by the President is a legal enactment that will break the "endless chain" without destroying the greenbacks. A provision to this effect would be in line with the Republican platform and public sentiment. But that is precisely what the "currency reform" howlers do not want. What they insist upon is the destruction of greenbacks as a means of strengthening the money power and destroying the Republican party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
