<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-07-15">July 15, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Not a Partisan War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-07-15">July 15, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">NOT A PARTISAN WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his speech to the Democratic convention at Springfield, former Governor John P. Altgeld generously appropriated the war with Spain for the exclusive benefit of the Democratic party. "The Democratic party forced the present Administration to take this step," exclaimed Mr. Altgeld. "It is our war, a Democratic war."</p>
   <p>The ex-Governor did not explain why the Democratic party did not force its own Administration or itself "to take this step," when the party was in full power at Washington. The infamous concentration decree of Weyler was promulgated and put into operation during Mr. Cleveland's Administration. But the Democrats in power did not lift a finger in protest. General Lee's reports were pigeonholed, while the mouthpieces of the Democratic Administration represented the Spaniards in Cuba as Angels <pb facs="5423969_2_0587.jpg" n="2"/>and the Cubans engaged in a heroic struggle for liberty as bandits. The people remember these things, if Mr. Altgeld does not. They remember, likewise, that the change in the Cuban policy of this government dates from the inauguration of President McKinley.</p>
   <p>The attitude of the Democrats in Congress concerning the war was patriotic, but it was not consistent, and in some respects it was unwise. Recognition of the Cuban Republic was the pith and moment of the policy of the Democratic party in Congress. Whether the President's firm opposition to recognition had anything to do with shaping their policy is an open question. But a blind man can now see that the President was right and that recognition in the form insisted upon by the Democrats would have embarrassed our government seriously. As regards the financial legislation necessitated by the war, the Democratic party in Congress assented to all appropriations made for war purposes while opposing necessary revenue legislation.</p>
   <p>The war with Spain is not a partisan war, and any attempt to drag it into <pb facs="5423969_2_0588.jpg" n="3"/>politics should be frowned down. It would be an insult to Mr. Altgeld's intelligence to assume that he did not know that his partisan cry was unpatriotic and discreditable nonsense. Nor is it fair to assume that his rank utterance represented the sober sentiment of the convention. Chairman Prentiss probably voiced the prevailing sentiment when he said: "This is a war waged by the American people in the cause of humanity, and Democrats and Republicans bear no party name in the conduct of this war."</p>
   <p>This is fair, and what is more, it is true from one end of the land to the other. Mr. Altgeld's mouthings were not only untrue and absurd but disgracefully unpatriotic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
