<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-19">Mar. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Get a Farm</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-19">Mar. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">GET A FARM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Leave the city as soon as possible unless you have a good position.... Do not wait until you are too poor to get away."</p>
   <p>One of the older farmers in Wisconsin gives this advice to the readers of Skandinaven. He himself was a city dweller many years ago but decided to become a farmer. He has been working hard, but he has received rich rewards for his struggle. And it did not take him very long to get on top. Now he is as "snug as a bug in a rug".</p>
   <p>Many others are in similar fortunate circumstances. None of them regret having left the city and having acquired homes in the country. Most of those who remained in the city, however, are probably sorry that they did not follow the example set by those who became farmers, at least when <pb facs="5423969_2_0908.jpg" n="2"/>they take time to consider what they have gained in the city as compared with what in all probability they could have gained by becoming farmers. The advice of the old Wisconsin farmer is as valuable today as ever, perhaps more so. For life in the cities is becoming harder year by year; it is even becoming more difficult for people with little or no money to get ahead. Competition is becoming fiercer in every field and subjects everyone to its pressure. In addition, wages will probably become lower from now on. The new tariff demanded by the people will bring about a reduction in wages, and it is not probable that these will ever again reach the level which has prevailed hitherto. "Leave the city before you become too poor to get away."</p>
   <p>The farm workers--at least all the intelligent farm workers--are striving constantly to progress to the point of owning their own farms. Thousands of Norwegian farmers in various sections of the country who are now the proud owners of farms have won their farms by way of the farm-worker route, and they have no regrets. On the other hand, there are many, farm-hands <pb facs="5423969_2_0909.jpg" n="3"/>with city backgrounds who cannot or will not stick to their jobs in the country. Back to the city they go, although they must realize that idleness and need are lying in wait for many of them when the money they saved on the farm has been dissipated....</p>
   <p>Many of the most able men in the cities are beginning to realize that life on the farm offers the safest future for the country's youth. While many Norwegian farmers educate their children for a life in the city, well-to-do people in the cities send their children to agricultural schools....There is already a very noticeable flow from the cities to the farms, especially among the better educated and well-to-do people.</p>
   <p>If Norwegian boys and girls in the country think that it is more elegant to become city people, they are mistaken....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0910.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Get a farm if you are a city dweller; get farms for your children if you are a farmer. The farmer's life may be hard now and then, but does not the city dweller have to struggle to gain his livelihood? And day by day the life of the city dweller becomes more precarious, while that of the farmer becomes lighter and brighter with the passing years.</p>
   <p>Get a farm! A capable farmer on a good farm is the most independent man in the country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
