<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-18">Mar. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Cannon's Pyrrhic Victory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-18">Mar. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CANNON'S PYRRHIC VICTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "insurgents" in the U. S. House of Representatives lost the main battle at the very moment when they appeared to have won a victory; Mr. Cannon was re-elected speaker, and, in the main, the old rules of order were retained. Yet, so much was gained that the final victory is almost at hand. The battle lines of bossism were forced to give way, and it was only through more or less shady alliances at the last moment that the old guard saved their position. They did find it necessary to make concessions. In other words, the walls of the fortress have been cracked; at the next assault the cracks will be larger even though the whole wall may not crumble at once.</p>
   <p>One difficulty that the insurgents had to contend with was the fact that they had to yield the leadership to the Democrats. For this reason the whole movement took on the appearance of an attack on the Republican party; many were fearful <pb facs="5423969_2_0132.jpg" n="2"/>that a victory for the insurgents would place obstacles in the way of the new government and possibly slow up the great task of changing the tariff. These facts show that the next step must be to prepare for the change within the Republican party. To do so may delay the work, but the road is safer and will more certainly lead to the desired goal.</p>
   <p>The readers of Skandinaven need no further information as to the desirability of this reform. Scandinavians are not fond of boss rule whether this rule be by one boss or a group of bosses.</p>
   <p>Thus it was quite natural that the move against Mr. Cannon was started by a Scandinavian, Mr. John M. Nelson of the second Wisconsin district, and that the other Scandinavians in the House, Swedes as well as Norwegians, with one exception, joined him in the fight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
