<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-22">Mar. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Charity Patients</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-22">Mar. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY PATIENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ailing people who need care, but who cannot afford to pay for treatment at a hospital, are usually sent to the County Hospital at public expense. This may be preferable to no care at all, but it is not with a light heart that sick people take this course. And no wonder! At the County Hospital charity patients are frequently treated in a manner which does not in any way denote charity.</p>
   <p>Medical students gather with their instructors at the bedside of the patient, and his sickness is discussed and investigated in all its details without the least consideration for the patient, who must listen to it all and must submit to all kinds of examinations. When the demonstration is over, the patient <pb facs="5423969_2_0941.jpg" n="2"/>is left to be treated by some young medical student in order that the latter may gain experience and continue his studies through the treatment.</p>
   <p>If, in spite of these unfavorable conditions, the patient recovers to the extent of being able to leave his bed at the hospital, he is discharged and turned out on the street, a worn and weak creature, frequently with no place to go for a period of rest to regain his strength. Naturally, a relapse will often occur, and he is sent to the hospital once more. This second visit to the County Hospital only too frequently includes a visit to the operating table.</p>
   <p>Such are conditions in Chicago, and similar conditions, we are sorry to say, are probably prevalent in most other places in our country. It is a cruel and heartless treatment of suffering humanity, under the guise of benevolence. In addition, it is indefensible waste not only of human life but also of public funds. For this careless, inhuman treatment of the sick is too <pb facs="5423969_2_0942.jpg" n="3"/>frequently a "cure" resulting in the death of the patient. No wonder that people are afraid of going to the County Hospital!</p>
   <p>The physicians know that the situation is bad, and the hospitals that accept charity patients know it, too. It would not be difficult to correct this evil if the physicians and the hospitals would co-operate to this end.</p>
   <p>The medical societies should take this matter under consideration. Let us have more intelligent and humane treatment of patients at the County Hospital! Let us have some real charity for the medical treatment of people who are ill and lack the funds needed for private treatment!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
