<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-01">Nov. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Tammany and its Prophet</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-01">Nov. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">TAMMANY AND ITS PROPHET</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a speech by Colonel William Jennings Bryan at Cooper Union Hall, New York, on October 16, this year he said among other things: "Great is Tammany and Croker is its prophet!"</p>
   <p>The prophet referred to here is the same man who declared from the witness chair a few months ago that he is "in politics for his pocket every time".</p>
   <p>The New York World, a Democratic Bryan Paper, has informed us how Croker and Tammany obtain at least a part of this income. The World brings the information that a Tammany committee, aided by Tammany policemen, every year provides for Tammany an income of $4,150,000 by "taxing vice". The record of this tax is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>150 Pool Rooms</cell>
     <cell>$780,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>100 Swell Gambling Houses</cell>
     <cell>$520,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1,000 Little Gambling Houses</cell>
     <cell>1,300,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>500 Policy Shops</cell>
     <cell>650,000.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1,000 Dives</cell>
     <cell>900,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$4,150,000</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>This is the rock upon which Colonel Bryan is building his hope in this election campaign. Richard Croker is the leader of the election campaign on the Democratic side, and the money which fills the Democratic campaign treasury comes from Tammany's corruption fund. From this source are coming the enormous amounts which during the past few days have been sent to Indiana to buy floating voters, and also to West Virginia, Maryland, and other doubtful states.</p>
   <p>Mr. Croker is not satisfied with this. He wants to have the votes counted in the manner of Tammany Hall and the Democrats in the South. Last Monday <pb facs="5423969_2_0223.jpg" n="3"/>he issued the following manifesto:</p>
   <p>"My advice to Democratic voters the country over is to congregate about the polling places on the evening of election day, count noses, and then, if the election returns don't tally with their count, to go into the polling places and throw those fellows in charge of the returns into the street."</p>
   <p>This is plain speaking. First the voters are to be bought for Bryan by Tammany's corruption fund collected as "tax on vice"; but if this be not effective the Democrats are to use force and rob the ballot boxes. Such is the order from the mightiest leader within the party.</p>
   <p>Colonel Bryan has the deepest admiration for this ring and its chief; he even turns to the Bible of the Mohammedans to find expression for his enthusiasm, "Great is Tammany, and Croker is its prophet!"</p>
   <p>And a man of this type is the candidate of a great party for the presidency in a free and enlightened nation such as the United States of America!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
