<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-05-12">May 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Ike Rosen's Victory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-05-12">May 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">IKE ROSEN'S VICTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The expected has happened: Mayor Harrison has put the brake upon the restless activity of Chief O'Neill. Ike Rosen, whose saloon was closed by the chief because a man had been robbed in the tough joint, promptly resolved to have a heart-to-heart talk with His Honor. No record of this interview has been preserved, but it was perfectly satisfactory to Ike Rosen. He emerged smiling from the Mayor's office with his license in his pocket. He had the air of a victor, and why not? Had not his ex parte testimony been sufficient to overthrow the official reports of the captain of the district and the chief of police?</p>
   <p>Some of the followers of the "man of destiny" are painfully surprised at his action in this instance. Ike Rosen is an old offender; his place is one of the toughest joints of the levee, one of the worst dives frequented <pb facs="5423969_2_0183.jpg" n="2"/>by criminals and the vicious of both sexes. Under the old dispensation the residents of the district made repeated efforts to have the notorious place closed, but Ike Rosen's pull with the police department and the police courts was too strong for them. The present chief was satisfied that the joint was running in violation of the law and recommended the revocation of the license. Perhaps the chief had forgotten, or chose to overlook, the fact that thirty-four tramps, staunch supporters of Carter Harrison, were registered from this place for the spring election. If he did, the Mayor evidently had a better memory. "I am Ike Rosen," says Ike Rosen; "I saw the Mayor and he told me all right and to go ahead." And go ahead he does with a vengeance. His place is crowded day and night with men and women of the lowest type who drink his beer and gaze with admiration upon the man who is bigger than the police. No wonder some of the admirers of His Honor are shocked.</p>
   <p>The Mayor has, in effect, served notice upon Chief O'Neill to leave the tough joints alone. And the chief must bow to his superior. "I shall," he says, <pb facs="5423969_2_0184.jpg" n="3"/>"make no further investigations unless another complaint is received; the matter is in the Mayor's hands."</p>
   <p>As if to emphasize his true position, His Honor has attacked the press for its support of Chief O'Neill. "The press is spoiling the new chief," Mr. Harrison exclaimed with wrathy irritation in a recent interview. The average citizen will take the view that it is the duty of the press to hold up the hands of a chief of police or any other public official who honestly strives to do his duty, and that such encouragement can only strengthen the authority and increase the usefulness of the faithful public servant. But that is where the average citizen differs from the viewpoint of Mayor Harrison.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
