<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-08-14">Aug. 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Fruits of Victory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-08-14">Aug. 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE FRUITS OF VICTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The terms of peace laid down by the President, and now accepted by Spain, will meet with the approval of the people. A handful of mossbacks are opposed to the acquisition of Porto Rico and the Ladrone Islands, but they represent nothing American and count for naught in America.</p>
   <p>There is, however, some difference of opinion concerning the question of war indemnity and the fate of the Philippines. It has been customary among nations to exact from a vanquished foe a cash indemnity to cover the cost of the war, and many people can see no good reason why an exception should be made in favor of Spain. But everybody knows that Spain is unable to pay a dollar and that Spain's note would be worth less than so much white paper. The very best disposition that could have been made of the question as to a cash indemnity was to eliminate it altogether, as the government has done.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0584.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Concerning the Philippines, it is evident that it was the purpose of the President to leave the matter in such shape that Congress may deal with it with a free hand. This is in line with the general policy of the President on all matters and especially as regards our relations to Cuba and Spain. His aim has been to ascertain and execute the will of the people, faithfully and vigorously and the clause of the peace protocol relating to the Philippines was framed in strict accordance with this basic principle of his policy. The American people have fought the War and they will, through their representatives in Congress, determine what disposition is to be made of the fruits of Dewey's and Merrit's victories. Meanwhile they appreciate the diplomatic skill of the President in handling the difficult question in such a manner that the people are perfectly free to do what they think best. Clause three of the peace protocol is the most conspicuous instance ever known of the application of the principle of referendum in international affairs.</p>
   <p>The peace commission will not begin work until later in the fall, hence there is no need of hurry in selecting the commissioners. It may be confidently <pb facs="5423969_2_0585.jpg" n="3"/>assumed that President McKinley in this matter also will consult the popular sentiment before taking action. The importance of the make-up of the commission is paramount. Whether the legitimate fruits of the glorious war shall be secured or frittered away--whether the position of the United States as a great power shall be strengthened or weakened, depends largely upon the character of the American peace commission. Noisy cliques of mugwumps, weak mossbacks, and nondescripts in general, are clamoring for the selection of men who believe that the oyster is the true ideal of the foreign policy of the American people. But the President has no sympathy with this un-American crowd. He will entrust the momentous task to broad-gauged and true Americans who believe in American destiny and have the courage of their convictions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
