<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">How the War Came to U. S</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">HOW THE WAR CAME TO U. S</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Misinformation and misunderstanding as to the causes for our entering the world war are yet prevalent in many quarters. It seems well therefore to present the facts in the matter, and these facts were clearly and plainly summed up by President Wilson in his Flag Day Speech:</p>
   <p>"It is very evident how we become involved in the war because of the unusual taunts and aggressions on the part of the German Government we had no choice, if we were to retain our self-respect; the only possible thing to do was to take to arms in defense of our rights as a free people and of our honor as a sovereign nation. The war lords of Germany denied us the right to remain neutral. They filled our non-suspecting cities and towns with criminal spies and conspirators and sought to mislead the public opinion in our country in their interest. Not succeeding in this, their agents began systematic attempts at creating risings <pb facs="5423969_2_0469.jpg" n="2"/>among our population to mislead our citizens to become unfaithful toward their country - and some of the agents active in this work were men belonging to the official diplomatic corps of the German Government right here in our capitol. They sought to destroy our industries, to stop our commerce by violence. They tried to make Mexico start war against us and to lead Japan into an unfriendly alliance with Mexico against us - and this by war of direct request from the foreign department in Berlin. They insolently denied us our right upon the ocean; time and again they put into effect their threat to send to his death any American daring to approach the coasts of Europe.</p>
   <p>Many of our fellow citizens were led astray. People began to suspect even their own neighbors, and in their surprise and anger they began to ask themselves whether there was any neighborhood where hidden enemy rascally were not at play.</p>
   <p>Under circumstances of this kind, what large nation would not have taken up arms? However, much we were wanting peace, peace was denied us; we were forced into war.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0470.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This flag under which we serve would have been dishonored is we had not taken up arms.</p>
   <p>But this is not all. The whole world is at war because the whole world is being crushed by the German military power, standing now in the midst of the great fight which is to determine whether the world is to be dominated by this power or is to wrestle itself free. If victory is won by the German military power, then will Germany itself lose the hope of freedom, and Europe will arm once more, for the next, the final encounter.</p>
   <p>For us there is no choice. Woe unto the men or groups of men who will try to stop us in this our great move to validate the principles which we admire, and to enforce them for the salvation of the nations. We are ready to appear before the court of history, and our flag will gain added honor. Once more we are to sacrifice life and blood for the high principles to which we were born, and the face of our nation will shine in added glory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
