<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">St. Olaf College Chorus</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1467</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1467.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ST. OLAF COLLEGE CHORUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert in Orchestra Hall last night by the St. Olaf Lutheran Chorus attracted a large audience and proved an entertainment of exceptional musical worth and beauty. The choir, which numbers some fifty-two men and women under the leadership of M. Melius Christiansen [composer and well-known musician], comes from St. Olaf's College, and a tour which is to include the principal cities of the east was started with this concert. If the singing offered throughout the tour be of such quality as was that last night, the reputations of both the Chorus and its leader will hold a high place in the choral world.</p>
   <p>The Chorus sings exceptionally well. The voices are beautiful in their freedom of emission, their roundness, and their purity, and all seem to possess a <pb facs="5423969_2_1468.jpg" n="2"/>suggestion of freshness and outdoorness that involuntarily creates visions of wide plains, huge forests, and clean air. The voices are the singing voices of the Scandinavian,with the tang and freshness that so often distinguish such. And these voices are admirably trained. They are true as a bell and they respond with the same certainty, exactness, and clarity. The tone is capable of the finest graduation, ranging from ringing forte to an exquisitely soft piano, and the soft tone is ever just as pure, just as true as is the loud. The voices blend perfectly, thus making the tonal mass invariably a delight.</p>
   <p>Musically and interpretatively, too, the chorus stands on a high level. The diction is such that every word is clearly and easily intelligible, and in the handling of either massed harmonies or in the weaving of polyphonic lines, the singers do exceptional work. The program was purely religious in musical matter, but it nevertheless interested and held the listeners because of the rare manner in which every number was sung.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
