<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">Feb. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Ole Bull's Birthday Remembered</title><title level="a" type="sub">Telegram to Bjorgvin from Mrs. Bull and Daughter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">Feb. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">OLE BULL'S BIRTHDAY REMEMBERED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Telegram to Bjorgvin from Mrs. Bull and Daughter</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The birthday of Ole Bull is February 5. Bull was born in Bergen, Norway, ninety-nine years ago. On both sides of the Atlantic the day was remembered in various ways. Here in Chicago the Bjorgvin Singing Society held a most successful banquet in his honor.</p>
   <p>A number of invited guests, mostly members of the Society and of the Ladies' Chorus gathered in Bjorgvin Hall. At nine o'clock in the evening Carl Rosenberg welcomed the guests. The assemblage stood and sang the Norwegian national anthem, and then sat down to tables that were heavily laden with food. The Hall was bright with Norwegian and American colors, and on the wall at the head of the tables there was a large picture of the world-famed violinist. A telegram was sent to Mrs. Sarah C. Bull in Cambridge, Massachusetts, and a reply came shortly afterwards from Mrs. Bull and her daughter....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1737.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speech in honor of the day was given by Bjorne Klausen who gave an outline of the main events in the life of Ole Bull.</p>
   <p>Born under the pressure of poverty, even though in a city where culture was highly valued, the violinist early ventured into the world outside his native country, and wherever he went he advertised the name of Norway. His was the sentiment of the mesas and the heaths and everywhere he created from this background of nature an air of dreams and joy and hope as nobody else had or could have done. He became the most famed violinist of his age, acclaimed wherever he played. Toward spring, however, nostalgia pulled him back to his homeland. And home again in Norway he did one of the real great things for art in his home city: he created Bergen's National Theater....</p>
   <p>Ole Bull was misunderstood, however; that is too frequently the lot of the genius; and he left his homeland once more. This time he came to America where music is loved by the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
