<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-07-09">July 9, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Politics in the Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-07-09">July 9, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS IN THE SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whether the Board of Education has gained or lost in ability, character, and standing by the recent changes in its make-up will not be known until the backbone of the new members shall have been tested. They are comparatively young and inexperienced men, but any shortcomings on this account will be forgiven if they oppose, resolutely and vigorously, further debauchment of our schools by "rat-hole politicians" of the City Hall.</p>
   <p>Already incalculable harm has been wrought by the bold and persistent assaults made upon the schools by cheap and designing politicians. Their tactics have been so shameless as to attract the attention of the entire country. The condition of the schools of Chicago has become a byword in the land and is cited by our foremost educators as a warning to other cities.</p>
   <p>Our schools had been kept free from politics until Mayor Harrison, Dr. W. R. <pb facs="5423969_2_0265.jpg" n="2"/>Harper, Mr. Thornton and Company began to hatch their plots. These gentlemen had different ends to serve; one was anxious to add to his political power by increasing his patronage; another was plotting to secure feeders for his university; while the third was out for mischief on general principles. But they were one heart and soul in selecting the schools of our children for their common prey. The Board of Education yielded to the behest of the plotters, and A. G. Lane, who had been identified with our schools for forty years, who had done more than any other man for the upbuilding of our system of public education, and whose fairness, integrity, and manly honesty presented to every child a noble object lesson of the cardinal virtues the schools are supposed to teach--this able and faithful man was supplanted by an imported gentleman who had never been inside of a Chicago school and who had no experience whatever in the field of popular education. That such a step would lead to disaster was plain to every unbiased man or woman, and the demoralization that followed is only what was to be expected.</p>
   <p>Not satisfied with depriving the schools of Mr. Lane's ability as the directing head, Mr. Harrison decreed his retirement even as an assistant superintendent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0266.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Again the Board of Education was ready to sacrifice the welfare of the schools and the manhood of its own members upon the altar of rat-hole politics. But the people, always slow to move, were aroused at last; and cowing before their indignation the Mayor reversed his order, and we are informed that the honorable members of the Board were really glad to be stood upon their heads again.</p>
   <p>These plain facts, fresh in the minds of everybody, illustrate the condition that confronts the new members of the Board of Education, and also the character of the body to which they are now admitted. They prove that every trace of independence has been eliminated from the Board--that the Board as a body has been degraded to a position of all but incredible subserviency and weakness--to a mere tool of the politicians of the City Hall.</p>
   <p>That our schools have suffered under such conditions is self-evident. The influence upon the morals of our splendid army of 300,000 children cannot be otherwise than deplorable. In the classrooms they are taught that trickery <pb facs="5423969_2_0267.jpg" n="4"/>and wrongdoing are punished; that honesty is its own reward; and it is instilled into their hearts and minds that above all they must be faithful, truthful, and honest. But those who manage this vast system of moral and intellectual education, the Mayor and the School Board, have taught our children a practical lesson of a radically different character. Their lesson disproves, with all the force of a demonstration, all that has been taught in the classrooms. It teaches the children that good work, faithfulness, ability, honesty, and a high sense of honor are not rewardable, but punished, and on the other hand, that reward is reserved for trickery, underhanded work, inefficiency, and rank injustice. Our school children can draw no other conclusions from the recent school scandals. That they are keen observers and good logicians anyone who cares may ascertain for himself.</p>
   <p>The new members of the School Board have a great task before them. If they cannot accomplish anything of importance at present they can at least line up on the right side. That would not be much, but it would be something. The <pb facs="5423969_2_0268.jpg" n="5"/>people have learned to be modest in their expectations and will be thankful for proofs of good intentions if they can hope for nothing of a more substantial character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
