<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Nordmendenes Sangforening</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">NORDMENDENES SANGFORENING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nordmendenes Sangforening (The Norwegian Male Chorus) celebrated its forty-first anniversary on Wednesday with a private musical evening to which were invited the luminaries of Chicago's Scandinavian music lovers. Among the guests was State's Attorney Martin Bergh of Sioux Falls, South Dakota. Mr. Bergh, although born and raised in this country, reads, writes, and speaks Norwegian fluently, and is genuinely interested in Norwegian art, music, and culture, and for this reason he was elected president of the Norwegian Singers League of America at its last convention.</p>
   <p>The guests marched to the banquet tables to the music of Lawson's Orchestra. The "orchestra" was composed of two men, and the unique feature of the two-man band was the playing of a violin and a trumpet at the same time by Mr. Lawson; how he accomplishes this feat is still a mystery.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Doe, always a popular humorist, was the speaker of the evening. He <pb facs="5423969_2_1628.jpg" n="2"/>paid tribute to the faithfulness of the many veteran Chorus members and to the excellence of their singing and thanked them for their services to the Norwegian colony of Chicago. The ambition and aim of this Chorus, said Dr. Doe, was not to gain a reputation for itself but to transmit to others its own love of Norwegian music and song.</p>
   <p>Birger Osland spoke of the wonderful way in which the chorus cared for its veterans, and Mr. William Gerner recited a poem which he had written covering the history of the years of service rendered by the Chorus.</p>
   <p>B. Lindseth and A. Soitreng were named honorary members and were decorated with the golden emblem of the Chorus in recognition of their years of service, Mr. Lindseth having been a member since he was a boy of eighteen.</p>
   <p>The banquet was followed by dancing till the early morning hours, when the Chorus and its many friends departed, well pleased with the thoroughly enjoyable evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1629.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Incidentally we might mention that great interest is being shown in the proposed visit to Norway in 1914 to attend the big celebration there and to test the facilities of the new Norwegian-American line which will launch its sailing career in 1913.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
