<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1919-06-29">June 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1919-06-29">June 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following petition was sent to Congress by the Norwegian groups, asking Congress to officially recognize the fact that Leif Ericson discovered America:</p>
   <p>"A resolution memorializing Congress relative to the recognition of Leif Ericson as the discoverer of America, and requesting that this fact be brought to the attention of the American people in some appropriate manner.</p>
   <p>"To the Honorable Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of America in Congress assembled:</p>
   <p>"Your memorialist, The Scandinavian Fraternity of America, respectfully represents and petitions as follows:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The discovery, exploration, and subsequent residence by the Norsemen <pb facs="5423969_2_0746.jpg" n="2"/>on the North American Continent in and immediately following the year 1000 A. D. have been so long a matter of history that the facts need no demonstration to the careful student. Statues commemorating the event have been erected in Boston, Milwaukee, Chicago, and Philadelphia; the one in the city last mentioned being a departure from the accepted model of Leif Ericson, son of Eric the Red, and depicting the heroic figure of Thorfinn Karlsefni who, in the year 1007, departed for the New World with a colony of men and women in three ships, and whose son, Snorre, was the first white child born on American soil; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Attested Icelandic manuscripts--beautiful specimens of ancient writing, notably the Hauk's Book [1334 A. D.], University Library, Arna-Magnaean Collection, 113-a, 113-b; and the Flatey Book, 1387 A. D., Royal Library, Old Collection, Fol. No. 1005, in Copenhagen, Denmark--recount these adventures in detail, particularly describing not only the original discovery of Leif the Lucky, but incidents leading up to and following his achievement. All recent historians of note include the essential facts of these exploits in dealing with the subject <pb facs="5423969_2_0747.jpg" n="3"/>of the discovery of the New World, and it is a matter of record in a volume by Ferdinand, son of Christopher Columbus, that the latter visited Iceland, the home of these early pioneers, on his voyage from Bristol in 1477, fifteen years before he turned the prows of his three little caravels toward what he supposed would prove to be the eastern shores of India, predicting the distance substantially the same as that recorded by these Norsemen; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, It is not meant by the memorial to endeavor to disparage the achievements of the intrepid navigator, Christopher Columbus, who, while he did not set foot upon the North American continent, nevertheless unfolded the chart of the Western World under conditions whereby his followers were enabled to explore and later establish a permanent footing upon what is now known as the United States of America, taking its substantive name from his illustrious countryman, Amerigo Vespucci; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, It is the object of this memorial that Congress shall be requested to take such action as shall give the fact of Leif Ericson's discovery appropriate <pb facs="5423969_2_0748.jpg" n="4"/>governmental recognition, either by the erection of a suitable national memorial commemorating this historical event to future generations, or by other means which Congress itself might deem proper and befitting the subject, thereby enhancing the significance and importance of the several commemorating monuments already referred to (and to which should be added the memorial shaft erected at Weston, Massachusetts in 1889, by Eben H. Horsford who for sixteen years was Professor of science at Harvard University, whereon is inscribed the fact of the occupancy in that region of Leif Ericson in the year 1000, of his brother Thorvald in 1003, of Thorfinn Karlsefni in 1007, and of Bishop Eric n in 1121, as well as the fact of the residence here of the Norsemen down to the year 1347); and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The old Viking stock, from which have sprung not only the blood, but many of the institutions which have contributed so much to make this land of ours a great and prosperous country, is, we believe, entitled to this tribute from a nation that has always delighted in giving credit where credit was due; be it therefore</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0749.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Resolved, By the Scandinavian Fraternity of America in convention assembled, and in this matter acting through its executive board, descendants of the Viking race, and, we believe, justly counted as the closest relations of the English-speaking peoples, respectfully petition the Honorable Congress of the United States of America to grant to our most illustrious progenitor, Leif Ericson, the recognition herein set forth, and which we believe to be due to him.</p>
   <p>"Supreme Lodge Scandinavian Fraternity of America,</p>
   <p>"John Hanson, Supreme President,</p>
   <p>"Frithiof Burgeson, Chairman."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
