<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-04-14">Apr. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A Cleaner City</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0958</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0958.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-04-14">Apr. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A CLEANER CITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new municipal cleanliness ordinance is now in force. Mr. Doherty will distribute 300,000 posters showing the chief features of the ordinance, and the Health Department will join hands with the Police Department to secure its enforcement.</p>
   <p>No city can be kept clean unless every resident will keep his own premises in order, and the people in general will refrain from littering the streets and sidewalks with rubbish of all kinds. These homely duties are clearly defined and emphasized in the new ordinance. The law is all right, but its enforcement at this time is another question. Though it does not require anything that is not readily complied with by the people of well-ordered communities, it will be found too exacting by a large number of the residents of Chicago. It will be violated in many essential features from the very first day. A less severe ordinance that could be enforced to the letter would give better practical results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0959.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under present conditions it does not make much difference after all whether the ordinance is good or bad. There is nothing to indicate that the men of the City Hall have experienced a change of heart. For four years they have wasted the funds appropriated for street-cleaning purposes, and persistently neglected to enforce existing sanitary regulations. The people have just put their seal of approval upon this state of things: they have said, in effect: "We do not care whether the city is clean or filthy; so stick to your course."</p>
   <p>To make the outlook for a lasting improvement still gloomier, "crusaders" have broken loose again. A "street-cleaning crusade" has been inaugurated with the usual noise and blare of trumpets. This in itself would be sufficient to kill the new law. Anything that starts with a "crusade" in this city is hopelessly doomed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
