<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-02-27">Feb. 27, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Treason from the Pulpit</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0629</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0629.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-02-27">Feb. 27, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">TREASON FROM THE PULPIT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first note of treason in the present crisis has been sounded by a Catholic priest, Reverend F. Weber of St. Peter's Church. A few days ago, the pious father officiated at the funeral of a member of St. Peter's Commandery, Knights of St. John. After preaching his funeral sermon, he changed the subject and preached a sermon of politics. Referring to the probability of a war with Spain, he said that should such a war break out, it would be the duty of the members of the Commandery to take up arms against the United States. He added that it would be an excellent thing if President McKinley and his entire cabinet were blown up. This was probably intended as a helpful suggestion to the audience.</p>
   <p>This sounds well-nigh incredible; but the priest meant what he said and spoke from conviction. When asked why he had preached such a sermon he replied:</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0630.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I preached a Catholic sermon to Catholics. It is no one's business what I said. I simply told Catholics what their duty was in case the United States fought with Spain."</p>
   <p>It is reported that these treasonable teachings aroused the anger of the audience, and that the members of the Commandery have declared to a man that in the event of a war with Spain they will be found fighting under the starry banner. This may well be believed; the loyalty of an overwhelming majority of American Catholics is not to be doubted. But the seditious sermon of Reverend F. Weber will cast suspicion upon the church in the eyes of many people and, moreover, create distrust and uneasiness in many quarters, besides adding to the popular excitement at a time when calm counsels should prevail. For this reason, it would be well if the sermon were shorn of its power for evil by a clear declaration of Catholic loyalty made by some church dignitary whose authority to speak for the church must and would be recognized by the nation. It is needless to state that but for the foul mouthings of this Catholic priest, it neither would nor could have <pb facs="5423969_2_0631.jpg" n="3"/>occurred to anybody to regard such action as either necessary or expedient. But since he has spoken as he did, and since he, upon reflection, has emphasized that what he preached was "a Catholic sermon to Catholics", it would seem that the nation had a right to insist upon an unequivocal and emphatic disavowal of this bold incitement to treason, made in the name of the church, either by a suspension of the offender from the ministry or by a clear declaration of loyalty enunciated by some one among his superiors in the government of the church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
