<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Our Banking System]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H </item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-11-02">Nov. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[OUR BANKING SYSTEM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of all the assemblies former Congressman Robert W. Bonynge has addressed during his country wide lecture tour, we doubt if any has so surprised him as did the one in Cedric Hall, Chicago, on Monday of this week. Mr. Bonynge is paid to travel in the interest of the "Aldrich Banking Law" and, due to his prominent position in national politics he has been able to interest vast audiences.</p>
   <p>Mr. Aldrich pointed out the weakness of our present banking system and stated that under this system we could only expect a series of panics. The only remedy, he said, was the Aldrich Banking Law or one similar to it and altho he pointed out all the good points he let the faults of the law conscientiously alone. However, his audience was posted in these matters far better than he realized and during the discussion period he was cornered to such a degree that he was forced to resort to the old, old subterfuge of "time is up; must leave." Dr. Sandberg opened the discussion by revealing the glaring faults of the proposed law, as well as of the present system, and urged those in attendance to put forth every effort in dealing a double blow to the system; defeat the Aldrich or any similar law, and vote for Socialistic candidates for Congress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0645.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These men, said Dr. Sandberg, would be the only ones who understand and will work for safe and sane banking laws that will protect all our citizens instead of playing into the hands of our present banking hogs. He advocated the amputation of private banks from the system letting the federal government be the nation's banker as in this manner alone would money be stable and eliminate bank panics. Had the Panama Canal been financed with national currency instead of banker's currency it could have been built at half the cost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
