<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-04-09">Apr. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The "Concert" of the Powers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SKANDINAVEN (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-04-09">Apr. 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE "CONCERT" OF THE POWERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The presentation of the joint memorandum of the powers to President McKinley on Thursday was in many respects an historic event, though the scene probably was more picturesque than momentous. Never before in the history of this land have the representatives of the great powers of Europe appeared in a body before the President of the American Republic as bearers of a joint message from the powers urging a definite line of action upon our government in its dealings with a foreign country. The scene was showy and pompous, but in reality it was merely a pretty piece of diplomatic theatricals. This particular "concert" of the great powers had even less significance than the many similar performances that have been given by them in recent years in various parts of the world. Their memorandum addressed to Spain meant something; addressed to this country it meant nothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If it had contained anything beyond a set of pretty general phrases, Great Britain, Russia, and perhaps other powers also would have withheld their cooperation. But there was no reason why they should not join in a message that must be regarded as an empty formality so far as this country is concerned, inasmuch as they might hope that their simultaneous joint demonstration in Madrid would give the Spanish government a much needed excuse for surrender.</p>
   <p>But if this "diplomatic action" is to be regarded merely as "diplomatic play" from the point of view of the powers, there was nothing perfunctory about the address of President McKinley. In reply to their "pressing appeal" to the feelings of humanity and moderation of the President and the American people, the President directed their attention to the condition in Cuba, which is "shocking the sentiment of the American nation". While appreciating "the humanitarian and disinterested character" of their communication, he expressed confidence that "equal appreciation will be shown for the earnest and unselfish endeavors of our government to fulfill a duty to humanity".</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0613.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Their delicate suggestion and "earnest hope that further negotiations will lead to an agreement" is met by the President with the statement that the situation in Cuba "has become insufferable".</p>
   <p>The President's answer was firm and dignified and as emphatic as diplomatic etiquette would permit. He told the powers in plain language that considerations of humanity demand not inaction but action in Cuba, that this country proposes to fulfill its duty to humanity, and that Europe must keep her hands off the Cuban question.</p>
   <p>This demonstration of the powers was probably welcomed by our government, as it emphasized the fact that the "resources of diplomacy are exhausted", so far as this country is concerned, and also afforded our government an opportunity to place our policy with its motives and unalterable purpose before the world and beyond the power of further Spanish misrepresentations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0614.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>President McKinley's firm stand on this occasion will go far towards restoring his prestige with those who have been impatient under his policy of apparently endless delay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
