<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-09">Sept. 9, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Brief Outline of the Traction Matter in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-09">Sept. 9, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">BRIEF OUTLINE OF THE TRACTION MATTER IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It started as a muddle and has continued as such to the present day.</p>
   <p>The following are the main happenings in outline of the history of streetcar development in our city:</p>
   <p>1859. The City passed an ordinance giving Frank Parmelee and Company, permission to run horse-drawn cars for 25 years on State and Madison Streets and on Cottage Grove Avenue to 31st Street, the then city limits. The laying of tracks was prevented, however, by a court injunction on the basis that the right to give the type of concessions here concerned was not vested in the City government. Parmelee and Company then applied to the State legislature for a charter.</p>
   <p>1859. The Chicago City Railway and the North Chicago City Railway Companies were incorporated by law passed by the legislature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0773.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1861. Chicago West Division Railway incorporated.</p>
   <p>1859-1865. Chicago City Council adopts various ordinances giving the companies rights in the busiest streets in the city. Chicago at the time had for its limits, Fullerton Avenue, Western Avenue, and 39th Street.</p>
   <p>1865. On application from the three companies, the legislature adopted a law altering the charters of the companies and extended them to 99 years. This was the notorious 99 year law.</p>
   <p>1883. The City Council adopted an ordinance extending the companies' franchises 20 years.</p>
   <p>1902. The companies, for the first time, presented their 99 year demands in an injunction case entered against the City by the Wideret-Elkins Syndicate. The U. S. District Court rejected the case <pb facs="5423969_2_0774.jpg" n="3"/>on the basis of not having jurisdiction.</p>
   <p>1903. The receiver for the Union Traction Company instituted suit against the City to show that the claim of the City that the franchise of the Company had expired was not well founded. The franchises granted in 1883 had expired in July.</p>
   <p>1905. The application of the 99 year law to all franchises in city or town, granted before the 99 year law was enacted, was sustained by Judge Peter S. Grosscup, April 15.</p>
   <p>1906. Judge Grosscup's decision voided by U. S. Supreme Court, March 12. The fight between the Union Traction Company and the original companies starts in earnest, March 19, when the stockholders of the latter companies demand that all leases to the Union Traction Company be voided. Chicago Railways Company gains new lease of life and reorganizes for <pb facs="5423969_2_0775.jpg" n="4"/>complete union between the original companies and Union Traction Company, June 6, 1906.</p>
   <p>The Historic Year, 1907.</p>
   <p>Feb. 1. The City Council adopted ordinances giving concessions to Chicago City Railways Company and Chicago Railways Company. The ordinance was vetoed by Mayor Dunne, but passed over his veto by the City Council one week later. Several aldermen, who, during the election campaign had promised to vote against the ordinance, broke their promises.</p>
   <p>April 2. The ordinances accepted by the electorate at the City election.</p>
   <p>July 13. Judge Peter S. Grosscup makes public his reorganization plan in regard to the properties of the Union Traction Company.</p>
   <p>Sept. 7. Justice Brewer, in the U. S. Court of Appeals,voids Judge Grosscup's plan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
