<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-02-13">Feb. 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Naturalized Citizens and Lincoln</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0824</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0824.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-02-13">Feb. 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">NATURALIZED CITIZENS AND LINCOLN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Naturalized citizens vie with those to the manor born in paying tribute, from loving hearts, to the hallowed memory of the great martyred President. The fearful struggle for freedom and human rights in this country a generation ago made a lasting impression upon the youth of Europe. The historic drama enacted on this side of the Atlantic was a baptism of liberty to millions of boys and girls on the other side [of the Atlantic]. They could not grasp the constitutional points involved in the struggle, but they knew that the North fought to free the black slave. And when Lincoln's melancholy features looked into theirs from their little papers, their youthful hearts went out to him, and their enthusiasm centered around the towering hero of emancipation. And when he fell, pierced by an assassin's bullet, his memory remained in the loving hearts of all the youth of the Old World.</p>
   <p>Hosts of these boys and girls have since come to this land and are now counted among its prosperous citizens. Among the scant treasures they <pb facs="5423969_2_0825.jpg" n="2"/>carried with them, the most precious of all was the image of Lincoln graven in their hearts. They have guarded it with tender care. Time cannot efface it, nor dim the radiance of its ennobling features. The hero of their youth is the ideal of their manhood--the greatest of all Americans and the grandest and noblest of all men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
