<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-24">Aug. 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Modern Chivalry?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0844</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0844.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-24">Aug. 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">MODERN CHIVALRY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another Cook County jury has acquitted a woman who murdered her husband. In accordance with our principle of not reporting details of murders, divorces, and other morality scandals, we will not review any phase of the case in question. We will simply recall that within a comparatively short time, eight women have been tried for murder of husband or fiance; of the eight one was found guilty, six were acquitted, and in the eighth case the jury disagreed and a new trial has been set.</p>
   <p>In not one of these cases could there be a shadow of a doubt as to the guilt of the woman accused, but the killers were acquitted on a plea of self-defense, cruelty, etc., for the victims could, of course, not speak in their own defense. In other words some sort of chivalry was the ruling power in each case, well <pb facs="5423969_2_0845.jpg" n="2"/>acted injured innocence winning out. This so-called brand of chivalry is bringing disastrous results in that we are beset with a regular epidemic of women killers who play their parts like trained actors.</p>
   <p>Histrionic talent combined with a pretty face and a comely form seems to be all that is needed in Chicago to make judge and jury alike forget that it is their duty to protect lives and families in our community and that no matter how attractive or appealing a woman may be, if she takes the life of another under any pretext, she is as much a murderer as a man committing the same act, and according to the law should be dealt with just as severely as in the case of a man.</p>
   <p>What are we coming to? Let us make just one little comparison. A young man grows up in poor surroundings and possibly, while befuddled with drink made accessible to him by our own votes, kills a fellow man. He is tried, sentenced, and executed, while our young refined female, reared probably in the lap of <pb facs="5423969_2_0846.jpg" n="3"/>luxury, without a need that is not supplied and whose every desire must be gratified regardless of all else, -this ornamental piece of humanity in a fit of selfish temper kills a husband or sweetheart and her sex appeal (called chivalry on the part of the male population) sets her free to further enjoy her ego and possibly bring more misery, if not death, to other humans. Is the skirted murderer any more to be pitied than the drunken product of our own rotten social system?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
