<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 223-24
<title level="a">[Ole A. Thorp Dead]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 223-24
<title level="a">[OLE A. THORP DEAD]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ole A. Thorp, founder of the firm, O. A. Thorp Co., and for twenty years its head, died Jan. 25, w at St. Marys Nazarene Hospital. Mr. Thorp was born at Eidsberg, near Christiania, Norway, in 1856. He came to Chicago in 1880 and started in the provisions importing and exporting trade. For twenty-five years he was closely associated with the business life of Chicago and was a member of various public bodies. Early in his career he conceived the idea of direct shipping of cargoes of merchandise between Europe and Chicago. Finally, in 1892, he succeeded in bringing the Wergeland from Norway with a cargo of fish, which was landed at Chicago and the ship returned loaded with provisions. Since then the Xenia and the Craig have sailed from Europe through the St. Lawrence River and the Great Lakes and landed at Chicago. On account of having first demonstrated the feasibility of making Chicago a port for Atlantic vessels,Mr. Thorp was made a member of the Deep Waterways Commission. King Oscar of Sweden and <pb facs="5423969_2_1140.jpg" n="2"/>Norway made him one on the commissioners to the world's Columbian Ecposition at Chicago in 1893, and decorated him with the Order of St. Olaf in 1899. For three years he was a member of the Chicago Board of Education and the chairman of the Buildings and Grounds Committees and was responsible for many important acts on that body. He was a member of the Board of Trade and served on its arbitration committee for several years. Mr. Thorp interested himself in charitable projects and contributed to all charities in a quiet way. He paid particular attention to the welfare of his countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
