<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-04-12">Apr. 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">An Election Sermon</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-04-12">Apr. 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">AN ELECTION SERMON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The defeat of the "gang" has taught the people of Chicago a double lesson, the full meaning of which they should be quick to grasp and slow to forget.</p>
   <p>Many well-meaning citizens had come to look upon the fortress of boodle as well-nigh impregnable. The rout of the ringsters proves, to the satisfaction of the most pessimistic citizen, that no stronghold of corruption can stand before a determined attack made by a thoroughly aroused people. This is the first lesson taught by the victory at Tuesday's election, and may timid citizens never forget it!</p>
   <p>The second lesson, written in the returns from every precinct, says, as plainly as may be, that the people themselves are primarily responsible <pb facs="5423969_2_0349.jpg" n="2"/>for the corruption of the city government. If they can break up the gang, and with comparative ease at that, whenever they make up their minds to do so, it is as clear as daylight that the gang exists only because they do not break it up. In other words, the people are robbed because they elect boodlers to rob them. They get precisely such servants as they elect; honest men if they want honest men, and boodlers if it is boodlers they want.</p>
   <p>Once in a great while a passing wave of civic reform will sweep over the city. The people will wake up from their sleep, and elect better men--for a change. When that is done, the people, i.e. you and I and all the others, will strike a victorious attitude, fawn upon ourselves, prate about the people's keen sense of justice, assure each other of our supreme faith in the people, etc., etc.--all this with more or less of a display of high-sounding rhetoric and hollow eloquence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0350.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us drop this farce of self-adulation. For it is rank humbug and nothing else. Let us admit that the people, i.e. you and I and all the others, are fools six days in the week--indifferent to our own welfare, and inclined to shirk our duties as citizens. Let us own that our sense of right and justice, in reference to politics, is apt to be very dull--at least on weekdays--and that unless aroused by corrupt practices of uncommon audacity, it will sleep and will let well enough alone.</p>
   <p>If the gang had shown some discretion in its boodling operations, the thrifty statesmen of the City Council would probably have obtained the endorsement of a triumphant election. Such is our standard of political morality. The offence of the gang was that its boodling was altogether too brutal--if such an expression may be used. Its performances were of such character as to make it impossible for the sovereign people, i.e. you and I and all the others, to shut our eyes; hence our uprising.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0351.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Now, let us look at these things as they are. Let us give our thanks to the gang for its great and remarkable frankness in robbing us; for, if it had been reasonably modest in its graft, we, the sovereign people, should probably have left it alone. Let us thank George E. Cole, W.T. Baker and their co-workers of the Municipal Voters' League for what they did, but let us tell them that they did no better than they should have done. Their work told on election day; yet they are only "unprofitable servants" to the voters--which, by the way, is very high praise.</p>
   <p>Let us confess that we, the people, did a great deal less than our full duty. A large number of us did not take the trouble to vote, while another large body of voters gave their support to the gang candidates. Let us admit frankly that this is a very poor showing and very little to brag about. If we look at ourselves in the light of naked truth, <pb facs="5423969_2_0352.jpg" n="5"/>we may hope to do better next time. Otherwise the last election will turn out to be only one of these passing spasms of civic virtue which serve mainly to emphasize our gross neglect of and indifference to corruption and other forms of crime in our municipal government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
