<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-12-09">Dec. 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The War on Vice in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-09">Dec. 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE WAR ON VICE IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the war on vice in Chicago is to result in anything but a spasmodic outburst of public wrath to be followed by general exhaustion after the wave of indignation shall have spent its force, the crusade must be directed in a sensible manner and along practical lines. A war on vice in general is most commendable, but considered as a means of relief from the present evils it would be but little better than a useless waste of energy, leaving everything substantially as before, except that good people would be still more disgusted and discouraged, while the audacity of the vicious elements would be increased. We cannot eradicate vice and crime in a great city such as Chicago; but we can repress vice and keep it within bounds; we can catch and punish the thieves and thugs; and we can make the city a very unhealthy place for the tramp.</p>
   <p>Our laws are not enforced -- that is the sum and substance of our trouble.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What is more, the present city authorities are evidently not disposed to enforce the laws. Nor do they dare, because the support of the vicious and criminal classes is one of the main pillars of their power. The thieves steal and the thugs slug and rob because they know that they can do it with impunity.</p>
   <p>To direct the war against the administration is, likewise, a mere waste of effort. When they re-elected Mayor Harrison, the people knew what he stood for; and he may justly hold that he has done exactly what he was licensed and empowered to do. He may trim his sails to a temporary squall of public indignation; with a view to the coming election he may be playing for the votes of those who never learn, though they frequently forget. But that will not alter his course. He may close a dive today, but the dive knows that "it is all O. K. with Carter Harrison and the bunch at the City Hall," and that "the joint will be out of business for a few days only".</p>
   <p>What with thuggery and other forms of lawlessness -- vice, filth, fund- <pb facs="5423969_2_0217.jpg" n="3"/>looting, and a bankrupt treasury -- the conditions in Chicago are terrible. But the fault is not primarily with Carter Harrison, nor with his master, "Bobby" Burke. The fault is with the people, the voters, including some of the knights of the cloth engaged in the present crusade against vice. The people chose, with their eyes wide open, the very kind of government they now have. If they do not like it let them blame not Carter Harrison, but themselves. Upon them rests the responsibility, as the remedy is in their hands. If the people want a cleaner city, physically and morally; if they want vice repressed and thugs punished; if they want the public money spent for public improvement instead of for private use; if they want solvency instead of bankruptcy in the city treasury and funds -- they will elect a mayor who will do these things or at least try to do his best. Unless the people are aroused to a sense of their duty and responsibilities we shall accomplish nothing of a lasting character. The voter alone can undo the harm he has wrought by his indifference and criminal carelessness. Let this be the one text of our crusaders' sermons and philippics, and they will not preach or work in vain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
