<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-01-13">Jan. 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Another Pardon Scandal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-01-13">Jan. 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER PARDON SCANDAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Tanner has seen fit to close his administration by acts of mercy which the people of the state cannot but look upon as gross and flagrant abuses of the pardoning power. The pardon extended to ex-banker Magill a couple of weeks ago came as a most unexpected surprise, but still more astonishing is the prospective release of Theodore Schnitz who, thanks to Governor Tanner, will be restored to liberty and full citizenship on the first of March.</p>
   <p>The Governor assigns as reasons for his grace that Mr. Schnitz has been permanently disbarred from the practise of law in this state and that longer confinement cannot subserve the public good. This argument is disgracefully weak. The disbarment was not an essential part of the punishment and hence cannot properly be adduced as a leading argument for clemency; and the public good is certainly not subserved by permitting cunning scoundrels, who have made poor people their prey, to escape with merely a nominal punishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Experience shows that it is difficult enough to land big thieves in the penitentiary in these parts. If those whom society succeeds in convicting at last, no sooner don the prison garb than they are permitted to doff it, what becomes of justice and the terror and majesty of the law? Where are honest people to look for protection?</p>
   <p>Abuse of pardoning power is growing dangerously common in retiring governors. A few weeks ago Governor Pingree of Michigan opened the doors of the state prison to two "gentlemen" criminals who had abused their public trust and lined their pockets with public money. The unanimous and fierce popular indignation aroused on this occasion did not prevent Governor Tanner from following in the footsteps of Pingree by extending executive clemency to notorious robbers of poor people, with some murderers thrown in as a guard of honor to the banker-thieves returning to society.</p>
   <p>Governor Mount of Indiana, who recently delivered a long harangue upon the evils and remedies of lynching, has furnished a practical illustration of his <pb facs="5423969_2_0206.jpg" n="3"/>doctrines by giving full pardon to a convict serving a life sentence for murder.</p>
   <p>And yet there are people who are astonished and shocked because mobs occasionally take the law into their own hands to make sure that justice shall not fail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
