<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago, Ill., 1905, John Anderson Publishing Co., p. 251.
<title level="a">Lee Advertising Company</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago, Ill., 1905, John Anderson Publishing Co., p. 251.
<title level="a">LEE ADVERTISING COMPANY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is the only Norwegian advertising concern in this country doing a general advertising business. The business was started by L. J. Lee and his three sons in 1895. The first year they occupied offices in the Times Building but since 1896 their offices have been in the Unity Building 79-81 Dearborn Street. The business was first confined to the Scandinavian papers published in this country, but the other foreign language papers were soon added to the list and gradually the newspapers and magazines published in the English language in United States and Canada were added. The Lee Advertising Company annually published a directory of newspapers and magazines in the foreign language and another directory of newspapers and magazines in the English language. A monthly list with current rates and circulating ratings of the leading newspapers and magazines of the U.S.A. and Canada is also published. Their foreign language newspaper directory is the only one of its kind published in this <pb facs="5423969_2_1142.jpg" n="2"/>country and is recognized by advertisers as the standard directory for this class of papers. The advertising business of this country has been growing very fast during the last sixteen years and the Lee Advertising Company has been growing with it. They are now placing advertising for a large number of advertisers from various parts of the country. They also frequently receive advertising offers from Europe, especially from Scandinavian countries, and they also place advertising in papers in the European countries. Their offices occupy the north wing on the eighth floor of the Unity Building and they employ a large force in their offices. The three sons have each charge of a separate department in the office, for which their father L. J. Lee up to the time of his death in December, 1906, was general manager. Among their staff are several well known Norwegians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
