<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-08-21">Aug. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Ancient Weapons</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-21">Aug. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">ANCIENT WEAPONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Republic or Empire" is one of the campaign expressions used most often in the present election struggle. Mr. Bryan uses it frequently, and his adherents still more frequently. People are informed that if Mr. McKinley be re-elected, then the Republic will cease to exist; in its stead we will get the type of government which the Bryanites call "Empire". Mr. McKinley is a dictator now, but if re-elected he will become far more dictatorial. "Imperialism," "militarism," and everything else that is bad will crush the country and the people and there will be no escape. Now all these scarecrow statements do not even have the virtue of being new; they are worn-out things from past generations. Mr. W. J. Bryan frequently refers to sayings by Lincoln, and he employs these sayings in a manner to make the people believe that Mr. Bryan is continuing Lincoln's fight, that he is really Abraham Lincoln the second. But he forgets to inform his listeners that Mr. Bryan's party in attacking Lincoln used the same kind of weapons which Mr. Bryan is
   <pb n="2"/> now using against Mr. McKinley and his government. Even the expressions and the synonyms are similar. It would seem as if the Democrats are now simply repeating their own election campaign of 1864. Here we bring a sample of the latter, an editorial appearing in the Indianapolis Sentinel a few days before the presidential election in 1864.</p>
   <p>"Do not the people get proofs every day that Abraham Lincoln is grabbing for himself powers, dictatorial powers, which will enable him to pay his debt and fill his coffers which now are empty due to his gluttony and his ambitious fight for power?</p>
   <p>"Eighteen hundred years ago or more the Roman republic was near its fall; it was then governed by three men, one of whom was Julius Caesar....We, too, have our trio, Lincoln, Stanton, and Halleck, none of them of great families. The result in Rome was that the state got an emperor capable of playing his fiddle while Rome was burning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0792.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We, too, have our emperor, Lincoln, quite capable of telling stale jokes while the country is being drenched with the blood of brothers arrayed against brothers. Were Lincoln to be re-elected, the revolution in America would become complete. Our commonwealth no longer would remain a republic of United States, but a consolidated empire. Every guarantee (for liberty) will disappear sooner or later. The restraint of the executive will no longer be found in the Constitution but only in the will of the President. We plead with patriotic men to stop and consider these matters before casting their votes on the coming Tuesday. Unless our people step forth to save our invaluable Constitution and Union, they are lost forever."</p>
   <p>As we notice, the same rallying cry in 1864 as now. The "anti-imperialists" of those days went somewhat farther in personalities; nobody today will claim that McKinley is an imperialist in order to pay his debt or to fill his coffers. Aside from this, however, the accusations are similar, and even the language is the same. Mr. Bryan and his followers are copying the very worst copperheads <pb facs="5423969_2_0793.jpg" n="4"/>from 1864. But the people crushingly defeated this traffic in accusations in 1864, and its sentence this year will be no less decisive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
