<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-11">Nov. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Enjoyable Concert at Music Hall]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-11">Nov. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[ENJOYABLE CONCERT AT MUSIC HALL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, November 3, we had the pleasure of attending a concert that was exceptionally enjoyable. The concert was given by Mme. Aalrud Tillisch (contralto) at Music Hall, and was so far above what is usually offered that one could feel that one was listening to an exceptional artist.</p>
   <p>We cannot feel in harmony with American critics who are prone to judge a singer by the mechanical perfection he or she possesses; we would put more stress on other attributes that, to us, are more important and create a more satisfied feeling for the listener.</p>
   <p>Mme. Aalrud Tillisch has a voice of exceptional beauty, pure, mellow, and appealing; she is tone-perfect and her enunciation so distinct that every syllable is clearly heard. She possesses the art of singing to the heart <pb facs="5423969_2_1265.jpg" n="2"/>of her listener (not only to the ear), and with little or none of the usual dramatic posturing and gesticulation she puts her very soul into the song until she seems to be a living and component part of the song itself. From beginning to end her every note struck responsive chords in the audience, and her concert cannot but linger long in the memory of all who heard her. We have heard many singers, even the most famous, but none have impressed us more, or sung them-selves so thoroughly into our hearts. The entire program can be likened to a beautiful string of perfect pearls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
