<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand, <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>. Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 348-349.
<title level="a">[Dr. Ludvig Hektoen]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand, <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>. Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 348-349.
<title level="a">[DR. LUDVIG HEKTOEN]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Ludvig Hektoen is a native of Wisconsin born July 2, 1863. His parents were born in Norway. Hr graduated from the University of Wisconsin. In 1887 he graduated from the College of Physicians and Surgeons in Chicago, and six months later he was assistant physician at the Insane Asylum of Kankakee, Illinois. In 1889 he returned to Chicago as interne at the Cook-County Hospital. In 1890 he was appointed coroner's physician until 1893. In 1900 he was honored with the appointment as head of the Department of Pathology and Bacteriology at the University of Chicago, a mark of esteem of which any physician might feel proud. A teacher and investigator in pathology. Dr. Hektoen exerts a strong and wide-spread influence on the minds and careers of the students who come under his charge. In January, 1902, Dr. Hektoen was appointed director of the Memorial Institute for infections and diseases in Chicago, and was elected president of the Chicago Pathological Society serving four years as such. The members of the <pb facs="5423969_2_1030.jpg" n="2"/>profession are the best judge of a physicians real worth, whether in the line of research or practice and such high honors are not bestowed without merit.Dr. Hektoen is one of the editors of Journal Infectious Diseases. He is also a frequent contributor to current medical literature, especially along the line of original investigations in the field of infectious diseases. He frequently serves committees and special commissions charged with the study of matters concerning public health. A record like that of Dr. Hektoen speaks for itself, especially in the circles where the value of attainment is well enough known to be correctly estimated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
