<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-05-03">May 3, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[Urgent Need for Reform]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-05-03">May 3, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[URGENT NEED FOR REFORM]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The justice shop system is to be reformed--at least so his honor says. No reform is more timely or more urgently needed. As now managed, our courts of justice are a travesty upon justice and an outrage upon the people. The "judges" are, as a rule, shysters and pettifoggers of the cheapest type--political ward heelers who receive their appointments as a reward of faithful service to bosses and rings, and hence dispense justice in the interest of the particular gangs to which they may belong. Of course, there are exceptions. Some of the justices of the peace in Chicago are competent and honest men. But the great majority are entirely unfit for the duties of any judicial office.</p>
   <p>It is well to remember that the justice shop is the court of the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0347.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is the arbiter of a myriad of small controversies among our citizens. It grants relief from wrongs inflicted upon poor men and women, or rights denied them, and metes out punishment to countless transgressors of the law. Its duties may seem insignificant to some, but its decrees are as important to the parties involved as are the decisions of the Supreme Court to our millionaire or corporation litigants. As a matter of fact, it is the root of the judicial system. If presided over by proper men, it can do more than any other tribunal to create confidence among the common people in the administration of justice and strengthen popular respect for the law. But in the hands of such men as now constitute the majority of our justices of the peace, the court fosters contempt for the laws, creates distrust in its administration and begets a spirit of lawlessness and anarchy in general.</p>
   <p>Other judicial reforms demand attention, but the most imperatively needed reform along these lines is a radical reconstruction of our system of popular justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
