<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1890-07-13">July 13, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Death of Andrew Johnson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1890-07-13">July 13, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">DEATH OF ANDREW JOHNSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Andrew Johnson, one of the Norwegian colony's beloved veterans, died at his home, 151 North Halsted Street, last Friday.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson was one of Chicago's oldest pioneers, and the oldest member of the Old Settlers Society here in Chicago. He remembers Chicago when it was but a small village, when cattle grazed on the lots that are now occupied by some of the city's largest buildings. He remembers the Prairie Schooners that sailed through Chicago to the frontiers beyond, and the Indians that roamed the prairies about the city.</p>
   <p>His name is found engraved on a stone tablet in the old Courthouse. He grew with the city, step by step, when the population was but a handful. Today, there are 1,100,000 inhabitants.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson was born in Voss, Norway, in 1824. He came to Chicago in 1837.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0100.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He lived for many years with Major Kinzie, also an old pioneer. He worked for the Butler and Norton Lumber Company at Lake Street and the River. A little later, he started a Lumber Yard for himself on Canal Street.</p>
   <p>From 1860-66, he was a member of the old Board of Supervisors, later called County Commissioners, then president of the County Board, and at the same time president of the County School Commission.</p>
   <p>The great fire of 1871 was a calamity for him. He sustained a loss of $60,000, but he began again, and now at his death, he was one of the city's wealthiest men.</p>
   <p>He used to tell interesting episodes of his life. He told over and over again the story of the only two Norwegian families living here when he came, and there were but few others. He tells of the old ferry which sailed across the Chicago river, of the first bridge, the muddy streets, churned daily by the wheels of long caravans of Prairie Schooners, of the fights with the Indians and the tough element, the gamblers, the prostitutes, and the highwaymen. All this was doubly interesting because it was told by an eyewitness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
