<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-11-26">Nov. 26, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Fit of Nervousness</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-11-26">Nov. 26, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A FIT OF NERVOUSNESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One phase of the Dewey gift-house episode deserves more than passing attention: the extreme sensitiveness of the public mind that has been revealed by this tragicomic incident.</p>
   <p>We have been wont to speak rather disdainfully about the mercurial temper of France as compared with our Anglo-Saxon staidness; but it is doubtful whether France ever witnessed such lightning changes of popular moods as have ruffled the serene surface of public opinion in this country within a few brief weeks.</p>
   <p>Our elections in recent years have disclosed a fitful disposition of the public sentiment. All these landslides and counter-landslides indicate an unstableness of popular thought that contrasts strangely with the good common sense and high intelligence of the American people. If our national and state governments had <pb facs="5423969_2_0549.jpg" n="2"/>been framed in accordance with the parliamentary system, the country would have been distracted by a series of dangerous national and local upheavals and a bewildering confusion compared with which the political development of France would have presented a picture of serene stability.</p>
   <p>We are at a loss to account for these sudden revulsions of public thought, but we cannot close our eyes to the stubborn fact. The doctors agree that nervousness is on the increase; perhaps we have contracted some sort of nervousness of the public mind as one of the penalties of our breathless development. If so, the excitement produced by the war and its many unlooked-for events could not but aggravate the disease.</p>
   <p>Admiral Dewey has been the beneficiary and the victim of this nervous capriciousness of popular sentiment. The hero worship and enthusiasm had reached a pitch that invited a reaction. Extremes meet. Just because the people two months ago were killing him with kindness, their unreasoning wrath descended upon him now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0550.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When the hero of Manila shall review his recent troubles in a calm spirit he will understand that the censure really was prompted by the love and admiration of a generous but extremely sensitive people.</p>
   <p>And with this the Dewey incident will close, leaving no heartburns behind. The people will not be robbed of nor is it likely that the hero will part with his country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
