<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title> Chicago, Ill., John Anderson Publishing Co., 1905.
<title level="a">[Biography of Captain William Johnson]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Ill.</title> Chicago, Ill., John Anderson Publishing Co., 1905.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF CAPTAIN WILLIAM JOHNSON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Few if any of the pioneer lake captains and ship owners have had a wider or more extended experience on the Great Lakes than Captain Johnson. From the age of fourteen he has been a sailor. Captain William Johnson was born near Arendal, Norway, in 1836. In 1855 he came to Chicago and at once entered the employ of Geroge Steele, who owned a number of vessels. So attached did Mr. Steele become to the young sailor, that Johnson made his home with his employer during seven successive winters and was regarded as one of his family. From the time that he entered the employ of Steele in 1855, Captain Johnson's career on the lakes was a successful one. He first sailed on the schooner, St. Lawrence, on which he remained two seasons. He then became a ship owner, by the purchase of the schooner, Fish-Hawk, which he sailed from Chicago, and which was engaged in the coasting trade. Two years later he bought the schooners, Traveler and Richard Mott, and engaged in the grain trade. During the same season he sold the Mott and purchased the schooner D. O. Dickenson. This vessel he sold in 1860 <pb facs="5423969_2_1123.jpg" n="2"/>and the same season bought the schooners, Paulina, Magnolia, and Rosa Bell. To this fleet he afterwards added the schooners, Cecillia and Ida. He was mainly engaged in the grain trade besides carrying lumber. In 1870 he built the schooners Olga, Alice, and William O. Goodman. In those early days, freight-rates on the lakes were much higher than now. He once took to Buffalo, in the Magnolia, 9000 bushels of corn in one cargo and received twenty-seven cents per bushel for carrying it. It was a large cargo for that time. At the time of his death in 1902 he was considered the wealthiest Norwegian in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
