<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-01">Apr. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Improper Campaigning</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-01">Apr. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">IMPROPER CAMPAIGNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Boer War was made a prominent issue at the Democratic primaries for the city election in several wards. Alderman Herrmann of the Twenty-first Ward was defeated for the Democratic nomination mainly upon that issue. He voted against the motion to suspend the rules in connection with Alderman Coughlin's pro-Boer resolution, and this fact, dressed up to suit the purposes of a discredited clique, was impressed upon the Democratic voters as evidence of his unfitness to represent the Ward in the City Council.</p>
   <p>The same argument is used to prevent his election. The voters are informed that Alderman Herrmann's vote would have carried the Coughlin resolution and that he must be defeated because he was not in favor of suspending the rules on this occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Similar tactics are employed in other wards also. Ward Fifteen is being flooded with cards which on one side contain a copy of the Coughlin resolution with the information that Alderman Raymer voted "Nay" upon this question, and that "his vote in favor would have carried the resolution"; while the other side says: "A vote for H. Olaf Hansen for alderman of Ward Fifteen is a vote of sympathy for the Boers of the Transvaal, for liberty, and against oppression."</p>
   <p>Such tactics will be condemned by all honest people, and especially by the sincere friends of the Boers. To drag their noble cause into the mire of ward politics is a burning disgrace. It is not the business of the City Council to pass resolutions upon the relations of foreign countries. The Coughlin resolution ought to have been voted down even if it had been an honest and disinterested expression of sympathy with the Boers. But it was nothing of the kind. Its aim was to serve partisan purposes; to hood- <pb facs="5423969_2_0251.jpg" n="3"/>wink the people by injecting an irrelevant issue into the local contest and thus distracting the attention from the rotten record of the corrupt Democratic machine and its doings.</p>
   <p>But it is not supposed that the intelligent voters of Chicago will be trapped by such cheap and dishonest tricks. They will regard with just suspicion any candidate who relies upon such tactics for his election--suspicion alike of his judgment, motives, and sense of propriety.</p>
   <p>As for Mr. Hansen, his best friends regret that his supporters should have resorted to methods that cannot but weaken his candidacy before the people of Ward Fifteen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
