<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-01-26">Jan. 26, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Let the People Speak</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-01-26">Jan. 26, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">LET THE PEOPLE SPEAK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The obstructionists in Washington have been unmasked. Their frothy declamations about the Declaration of Independence, their concern for the Constitution, their solicitude for the liberties of the Filipinos, their dreary wailings and evil prophecies, are only varying shades of a cloak of stupendous hypocrisy.</p>
   <p>How long is this farce to go on? Is the honor of the nation to be sacrificed in order to cover up the desperate condition of a bankrupt party? Is the United States of America to be held up by a low, cunning politician? Are buffoons and renegades to control the destinies of this country?</p>
   <p>In all the long-winded speeches that have been made against the peace treaty in the Senate, not one syllable can be found that has any bearing whatever upon the ratification of the treaty. That is a question, not of expansion <pb facs="5423969_2_0567.jpg" n="2"/>or anti-expansion, but of national honor or dishonor, of peace or war.</p>
   <p>We are still at war with Spain, and every day that ratification of the treaty is delayed by obstruction postpones, unnecessarily, the restoration of peace. The fortunes of war and the treaty have imposed upon us certain duties to Spain, the Filipinos, and other countries--duties which we are in honor bound to fulfill. But sacred obligations and the honor of the country are ruthlessly cast to the winds by Gorman and his followers. The difficulties that have arisen in the Philippines are the legitimate fruits of their responsible obstruction; but they are proud of their achievements, proud of their success in tarnishing our matchless victories, and of exposing the country to perils and the American name to ridicule and contempt.</p>
   <p>The American people are proverbially long-suffering; but there is a limit to their patience. The limit has been reached, and they should speak in tones that will drive the bushwhackers into their holes. Legislatures that have not spoken should forthwith demand the instant ratification of the treaty, <pb facs="5423969_2_0568.jpg" n="3"/>and constituents of Senators who glory in their shame should flood them with dispatches and letters commanding them to abandon their irrelevant obstruction and vote for the treaty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
