<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-02-20">Feb. 20, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Let War Come</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-02-20">Feb. 20, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">LET WAR COME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every heart in the land is veiled in gloom and draped in sorrow for the brave boys who went down with the "Maine." Among our adopted citizens, grief is no less heartfelt and sincere than among those to the manor born. Our nation is made up of many nationalities that all blend into one under the magic power of the starry banner. Nearly all of them were represented on the "Maine." The officers were native-born Americans, while about one-half of the men were adopted citizens, born in the various countries of northern Europe. First among the foreign-born in numerical strength came the Scandinavians. The published roster shows forty-two Scandinavians, twenty-six Irishmen, fifteen Germans, etc. Less than twenty-five per cent of the Scandinavians were saved.</p>
   <p>Our adopted citizens mourn for the precious lives thus wantonly lost. But they do not shrink from the call of duty; on the contrary, they are ready <pb facs="5423969_2_0633.jpg" n="2"/>for any sacrifice demanded by the honor of the flag and the welfare of our common country. This, it is believed, is true of our adopted citizens in general. The Skandinaven knows that it is true of all citizens of Scandinavian birth. They are a peaceful, law-abiding people; but if war must be waged for the sake of justice, liberty, and the honor of the flag, they know their duty and are eager to march at the first call of the bugle. They are not comforted by the assurance that "the people of the United States may possess their souls in peace--there will be no war with Spain." They regard such sentiments expressed at the present juncture as cowardly, not to say seditious. The majority of the Scandinavians of the United States think that a war with Spain ought to have been fought and finished long ago. In their judgment, it is the duty of this great republic to put a stop to Spanish injustice, cruelty, and barbarism in Cuba, to set the island free and to punish Spain's insults and treachery and crimes against our land and people. Any further delay of this act of justice adds to their impatience and weakens their faith in the Administration. While they recognize the grave responsibilities of President McKinley and respect his prudence, they feel that the patience and forbearance of this country have been exhausted <pb facs="5423969_2_0634.jpg" n="3"/>and that the hour for final and decisive action is at hand. They are not anxious to "possess their souls" in a dishonorable peace. They are eager to assume their full share of the sacrifices of a just and honorable war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
