<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-11-22">Nov. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Straight for the Goal</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-11-22">Nov. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">STRAIGHT FOR THE GOAL</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The latest events in Europe have silenced for the present all talk of peace, except in Russia. The extreme Russian radicals who have replaced Kerensky and his government have adopted as one of the most important planks in their platform, immediate peace. If they succeed in securing their position, which hardly seems probable, Russia, most likely will not play an important role in the future as a factor in this war. This, however, is the only call for peace that is heard at present.</p>
   <p>Germany and Austria are not presenting new proposals; on the contrary, as was to be expected, their victories in Italy have strengthened their war sentiment and have intensified the desire of the Pan-Germans for further gains.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0422.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Italian people are more united than ever in their decision to defend their country. The heroic French will fight till its soil is free of enemies, and England and America are firmly resolved to carry on the war to a victorious conclusion.</p>
   <p>The attitude of the British was expressed worthily by the Secretary of Foreign Affairs Baldwin in a speech in the House of Commons the other day: "The objectives of Great Britain in entering the war were neither imperialistic nor tinged with lust for revenge, but concern the two-fold need of rendering Europe free and of giving to it lasting peace. Great have been our sacrifices, but we are ready to go on until we have attained the great, the just, the unselfish goal which is ours."</p>
   <p>The American people do not take a back seat in regard to vision, power, courage, endurance. Always the Americans found in adversity a spur to new <pb facs="5423969_2_0423.jpg" n="3"/>exertions. The Americans of today will show that they are worthy sons of great fathers. To safeguard the liberty won by the fathers, the national unity which the fathers save, to win full and lasting liberty for all nations - such is the lofty goal for the attainment of which the American people are carrying on the war. Let the task be heavy and the fight hard, the American people will fight and work until the goal has been reached.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
