<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-08-06">Aug. 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">An Ineffectual Indictment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-08-06">Aug. 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">AN INEFFECTUAL INDICTMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The indictment returned against the Harrison administration by the grand jury for July is unusually severe. In the language of the report, "assignation houses, panel houses, disreputable resorts, massage parlors where disgraceful practices are indulged in, and other places of like character, seem to be all too prevalent and carry on their traffic with little or no restraint from the constituted authorities. Not only robbery and murder are committed, but death-dealing, foul, loathsome diseases lurk in every nook and corner, and it is impossible to estimate the amount of irreparable injury done to many of the rising generation by some of these unrestrained dens of iniquity. Unless stern, heroic, and immediate steps be taken for the effacement, regulation, or inspection of these evils, some unusual and horrible crime will be committed which will awaken the authorities and the people to the existing conditions."</p>
   <p>Every word of this is true. But why should not the authorities and the people <pb facs="5423969_2_0262.jpg" n="2"/>awaken to the existing conditions before some unusual and horrible crime is committed? Is not every phase of the existing conditions known already to the authorities and the people as well?</p>
   <p>That the charge preferred by the grand jury is a true bill cannot be denied. But Mayor Harrison may claim that he, in permitting all these iniquities, is only doing what the people have authorized and charged him to do. His second administration is not a whit worse than was his first. He has continued as he began. Every evil enumerated by the grand jury, the whole panorama of lawlessness, vice, and iniquity uncovered for our inspection, was known to the people when Mr. Harrison presented himself for re-election. His triumphant victory was a most emphatic endorsement of the man and his methods. The people, who knew what he had been doing, in returning him to power with increased prestige, told him that he had done well and commanded him to go ahead. That is what Mr. Harrison's re-election meant if elections are supposed to mean anything at all.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harrison will be justified in taking this view and hence may regard the <pb facs="5423969_2_0263.jpg" n="3"/>criticism of his administration as something that does not concern him in the least. But the evils complained of do exist and do threaten the morals, peace, and welfare of the community. That they exist in open defiance of the letter and the spirit of the law is a matter of public knowledge. The people, including the members of the grand jury, are politically and morally responsible for the disgraceful condition; hence the general indictment found by the grand jury should have been directed against the people, including every member of the honorable body, and if the charge is true, as it unquestionably is, the law has been violated in such a manner as to warrant specific indictments of Mr. Harrison and his lieutenants for criminal acts of commission or omission. It is a question whether the grand jury itself did not shirk duty in refraining from taking any definite action along this line. General arraignments that lead to nothing amount to nothing. They are merely blows in the air that hit nobody and correct no abuses, but leave everything as before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
