<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-01-10">Jan. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Queen of the West</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Danish)</item>
     <item>II A 1 (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1914-01-10">Jan. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUEEN OF THE WEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, a fairy-tale city, where our Norwegian peasant and our youth of the working class have made good! Listen to a few tales, some of them strange, but [all] true.</p>
   <p>In 1858 a youngster, Helge A. Haugan, came to America with his parents, where he almost immediately became an apprentice in the fine art of laying tile. But Helge had other plans; he founded a bank, small, very small to begin with, but today it has assests of more than $30,000,000. After Helge's death his brother, Hauman G. Haugan, took over the bank, and Helge's son, Oscar Haugan, became Norwegian Consul in Chicago. This position is neither a pleasure nor a source of profit, for Oscar has to pay his secretary, his office rent, yes, even the cost of paper and ink out of his own pocket.</p>
   <p>Or let us take Anders P. Johnson, who came to Chicago as a youth, took a job as <pb facs="5423969_2_1070.jpg" n="2"/>carpenter's apprentice, and later founded a chair factory that today is the largest in the world of its kind. Or take Christian Jevne, who came to Chicago without a cent in his pocket and started a retail grocery store that today is one of the largest in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Yes, we find Norwegian names in every walk of life. For instance, Jens I. M. Hansen, librarian at the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>P. A. Thorp was the first man to charter a steamer, load it with Norwegian goods from Norway, and have this ship unload its freight in the Chicago river.</p>
   <p>Or let us stop in "Scandinavia," on North Avenue between Western and California Avenues. Over the store windows we see such names as Henriksen [Dane], Petersen [Dane], Ulvestad [Norwegian], Fossum [Norwegian], Baker Hansen [Dane], Bookdealer Lund [Norwegian], Revyen (The [Danish] Review), and any number of Scandinavian doctors in their second-floor offices, outstanding among them all--</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
