<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-01-21">Jan. 21, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavians</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-01-21">Jan. 21, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Awake from your long political sleep and be up and doing!</p>
   <p>An appeal to Scandinavians is in perfect order. They ought to be represented in the leading county as well as State offices. I believe the Scandinavians are the chief supporters of the Republican party of the State, but thus far, they have been satisfied with voting the ticket, leaving it to others to manage the party and hold public offices. This shows a certain lack of public spirit and a deplorable absence of proper political ambition.</p>
   <p>Last fall, an effort was made to establish a Scandinavian Republican league. An organization was perfected, officers elected, and a set of bylaws adopted and published. The membership was largely Swedish, few Norwegians and no Danes being represented. This was regrettable, since the opportunity to join was open to all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0049.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There seems to be a lack of interest among our Norwegian people. One of the causes may be found in the fact that interest in education among the Norwegians has been somewhat slack. The older and wealthy settlers have invested their time and money in commercial enterprises and in farms, have accumulated wealth, and have started their children in some business instead of sending them to school. This is, of course, all right, if other duties are not neglected. A few that have been fortunate enough to climb the ladder of political honor have become so thoroughly Americanized that they have forgotten their own nationality, instead of becoming leaders and centers of political activity and interest among their people.</p>
   <p>But we can do something if we try. We now have a Scandinavian organization. Let the Norwegians of the State turn out. We will have a good time, and we will also do something for ourselves and our fellowmen. Let us hear from all of you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
