<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-16">Dec. 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Gibbons Shows the Way</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-16">Dec. 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">GIBBONS SHOWS THE WAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Gibbons, in his charge to the grand jury, has, at some length, emphasized the right attitude and pointed to the effective means for the correction of the regrettable conditions which have existed in Chicago for such a long period. The Judge places special emphasis on the fact that the laws are being violated and that such violation takes place, in part, because the officers of the law are allied with the criminals. The fact that leading citizens in a community are thus violating their official duties is in itself a grave crime, and it is this condition which the grand jury has been called upon to investigate. According to the Constitution [of the State of Illinois], the grand jury is to supervise the officials, investigate their conduct in office, and institute prosecution against them in case they are found to have acted at variance with the prescribed rules of duty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0208.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Judge states that in view of the present conditions in Chicago, it is necessary that the grand jury first of all undertake this task. It must be carried on in a thorough manner, and at whatever expense is required. Not only is the good name of the city at stake, but its moral and material health and welfare as well.</p>
   <p>The Judge then goes on to list a number of the evils and misdoings which are prevalent: the alliance of the administration with vice and criminals; the association between police officials in high position and usurers; dishonesty in the special assessment bureau; the night cafes of the city, etc.</p>
   <p>All of these conditions are to be looked into carefully by the grand jury. But the Judge repeatedly emphasizes that the chief task of the grand jury is to strike at the officials who have violated their duty. Conditions will not improve until the laws are enforced, and the laws cannot be <pb facs="5423969_2_0209.jpg" n="3"/>enforced, as long as those officials, whose duty it is to see the laws maintained, permit the laws to remain a dead letter.</p>
   <p>After all the loud clamor for "reform" which has been heard of late, it is refreshing to find a man whose position clothes him with authority pointing directly at the root of the evil and at the only effective means of correction.</p>
   <p>The attitude of Mayor Harrison toward the matter is most peculiar, however. Mr. Harrison is the highest official of the city, the man in whose hands is placed, in a specific manner, the responsibility for upholding the law in the city; in other words, he more than anybody else is responsible if his subordinates do not fulfill their duties. One would expect him to greet with pleasure the assistance of the grand jury in furnishing proof of neglect of duty by public servants. Instead, however, of offering the grand jury all the information at his command, he attacks Judge Gibbons, comparing <pb facs="5423969_2_0210.jpg" n="4"/>him to "a dog barking at the moon". Evidently Mr. Harrison feels that the shoe fits him. Yet it seems quite incredible that a mayor of this great city should so forget his position as to speak disparagingly of a judge who is only doing his plain duty by instructing the grand jury as to its duties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
