<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-04-25">Apr. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Kipley's Ax</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_2_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-03-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_2_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-04-25">Apr. 25, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">KIPLEY'S AX</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Inspector Schaack and Captain Christian Larsen are slated for dismissal. Their names adorn the black list of Chief Kipley, and they will have their official heads chopped off tomorrow, or as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kipley knows that these officials have been very useful public servants and rank with the very best men on the force. Mr. Schaack has filled his responsible position with conspicuous ability, and has performed his duties faithfully and fearlessly. As much may be said of Mr. Larsen, the popular and efficient captain of the West Chicago Avenue Station. His district has been one of the best managed in the whole city and he is justly regarded as one of the very best men who wears a police captain's star.</p>
   <p>The city cannot afford to lose the services of such men, and there is not the <pb facs="5423969_2_0320.jpg" n="2"/>hollowest pretense of a valid reason why either of them should be dropped from the force. Their dismissal simply proves that the police department is again to be converted into a political engine for the benefit of the ruling party.</p>
   <p>Yet, the people cannot consistently complain. They voted to have the old spoils system reinstated and must take their medicine, even if they get it in larger doses than was expected.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavian voters will be careful at the next election. We are sure that the honest voters have learned a lesson, one they will not soon forget. The policy of this paper has always been to lead the Scandinavian voters along the right path, and the paper will continue to do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
