<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svijet (The World)</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 9408,
<date when="1937-05-07">May 7, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">What Situation Will the New Serbian Bishop Find in America?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svijet (The World)</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 9408,
<date when="1937-05-07">May 7, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT SITUATION WILL THE NEW SERBIAN BISHOP FIND IN AMERICA?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Press news indicate that Bishop Gjorgjevic arrived in America to visit the Serbian bishopric which was given to his care. The question arises of whether or not the new bishop will grasp the situation with open eyes. More important is whether the new bishop will remain silent as his predecessor did when he sees everything.</p>
   <p>It is only natural that the new bishop will listen to the mercenaries of Belgrade, who will try to picture the Serbian diocese as a paradise and themselves as angels in it.</p>
   <p>Reports of that sort are made at Belgrade, but these reports were paid from the state's treasury. The aim of these reports was to show that the mercenaries who sent them are the chief factors in keeping the Serbian immigration patriotic and (preserving) faith in the Serbian government, and enthusiasm for the church and religion of their forefathers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In testimony of all this, they will show to the bishop articles of the Am. Srboran, the official organ of the Serbian National Union, and laudatory statements of its board members, with whom they are connected.</p>
   <p>To make matters more convincing they will accuse a few of the Serbian priests and make them responsible for anything that is unholy. These priests will be called traitors, devils, absconders from God and religion, from the people and from the national shrines. Such things the new bishop will hear. But he must get information from the other side, too; from people who have a good word for Belgrade, even if they are not paid for their opinion. Some of them claim that Belgrade contributed $100,000 for the Serbian bishopric and nobody knows what became of it.</p>
   <p>Belgrade invested heavily in the monastery at Libertyville. The bishop has to visit that monastery to come to the conclusion as to where the money went. There is a cemetery there. Close to it are huts for dancing and drinking.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0140.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Never in that monastery has there lived one monk, and yet the place was announced by diplomats and mercenaries as a national shrine, a religious shrine, a new Jerusalem. Whoever does not believe in that is considered a traitor, a Judas and absconder.</p>
   <p>The new bishop will find out that the constitution of his diocese does not function. It exists just on paper. All wrongdoings are covered up by the newspaper Am. Srbobran, which is controlled by the priest Sundic and the Serbian diplomacy.</p>
   <p>The new bishop has the power to disentangle the common-law marriages of his priests, which are creating rebellion in the Serbian church in America. If the bishop will neglect to do it for whatever reason, this situation will continue.</p>
   <p>All above was said from best intentions.</p>
   <p>A Member of the Eparchy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
