<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>From Memorial Book, "Serbian Singing Society, Karageorge."</title><date when="1934-12-09">Dec. 9, 1934</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>From Memorial Book, "Serbian Singing Society, Karageorge."</title><date when="1934-12-09">Dec. 9, 1934</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If there were a nation of which it can be said that it sings morning, noon, and night, undoubtedly that would be the Serbian nation. Ever since migrating down to the Balkan Peninsula, the ancestors of the Serbian people of to-day started their very life with singing. Whether it was while offering a sacrifice to the deity of that time, or from joy at the birth of an heir to the family, or any other significant event in their lives, they sang always! Even during the period of five centuries of life in slavery under the Turkish yoke, the song never left the lips of those brave southern Slavs, who, even in moments of tragedy, found singing their only consolation. And therein lies the answer to the world-famous, limitless treasure of Serbian national folklore, of which so highly spoke the great Goethe, the famous Grimm Brothers, and many other noted writers of the world.</p>
   <p>Guslar, with his one string instrument gusle, sang the songs of heroism, of bravery, of sublime sacrifices undergone by his forefathers and even by his contemporaries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0038.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And even at the present time when symphonies and choirs of the world delight and awe highly polished audiences, the old bard, Guslar, can still move the hearts of the Serbian people to tears, listening to the sad, heart-rendering tales of bravery and sacrifices on Kosovo Polje.</p>
   <p>Being among the latest immigrants to this country, the Serbians found other Slavs already settled here, engaged in their livelihood. And what little they carried with them, Serbians brought also their songs, their undying desire to sing.</p>
   <p>And Karageorge is one of the early pioneers in the field of national music.</p>
   <p>What intention the early members had, it has always remained as the prime goal, that is, to spread the Serbian songs in every corner where ever a Serbian soul can be found.</p>
   <p>Twenty-one years ago, while the brave soldiers of little Serbia, under the glorious guidance of the late King Peter Karageorgevich and his equally famous and illustrious son, the late King Alexander Karageorgevich, were led from <pb facs="5423966_0039.jpg" n="3"/>victory to victory, a few Serbians who were among the early settlers met together and the Karageorge Society was born. All these Serbians were from the territory under the political reign of Austro-Hungary, and seeing the famous dynasty of Karageorgevich slowly liberating the enslaved Serbians in the South from under Turkish yoke, they wanted their society to be named Karageorge, in honor of the dynasty which they knew was going to free them, too, from another yoke - that of Austro-Hungary.</p>
   <p>To-day when their fatherland is free, when the famous dynasty of Karageorge is guiding the destinies of their families left behind in Europe, Karageorge members are continuing their singing and their cultural work for the betterment of human education among their own people, and they are continuing to be ambassadors of good will and interpreters of the soul of a new, united nation, Jugoslavia. While in this friendly country, Karageorge members will strive to keep high the ideal that some day all Slavs can come together and fulfil the dreams of poets and the prophecies of many, many centuries.</p>
   <p>In twenty-one years of its existance Karageorge has presented many concerts and many plays with musical background, never with mercenary purposes in mind.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0040.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Due to the length of time and changes, the society has had several teachers. It has had its officials - president, and secretary - changed almost annually.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
