<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Memorial Book Srpsko Jedinstvo</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 12.
<title level="a">Srpsko Jedinstvo and the Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Memorial Book Srpsko Jedinstvo</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 12.
<title level="a">SRPSKO JEDINSTVO AND THE FEDERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the beginning of the 20th century, when the first Serbian organization was established, an idea was born that all existing societies must unite into a federation. So, in 1903, on the initiative of the two societies, Ujedinjeni Srbi and Srpsko Jedinstvo, the foundation was laid for the first Serbian Brotherhood Benevolent Federation, with headquarters in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In 1905 this Chicago federation started to publish its organ, Ujedinjeno Srpsko, and the first editor appointed was Mr. George Chokorilo.</p>
   <p>In 1907 this federation was liquidated.</p>
   <p>On the same day that Chicago organized its federation, the Serbian societies from the East organized another federation, Srbobran, with headquarters in Pittsburg, Pa. In 1906 this federation started to publish its organ, Amerikanski Srbobran, which still exists today.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the same time the Serbian and Montenegrin organized their own federation in Montana, which they named Serbian and Montenegro Federation, and began publishing their organ, Balkan, in 1908.</p>
   <p>So in 1908 we found three federations existing and printing three separate newspapers.</p>
   <p>Because all three federations had the same purpose, naturally the idea of merging was under way and became so strong that in 1909 delegates from all three federations held their convention in Cleveland, and on this occasion there was organized a powerful federation named "Sloga," with headquarters in New York City, and as (its) first president, Michael Pupin, famous scientist (was appointed).</p>
   <p>The federation Sloga was liquidated on Feb. 28, 1921. Since that time the Serbian society Srpsko Jedinstvo decided to work as an independent organization, as it is today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
