<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Memorial Book Srpsko Jedinstvo</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 12.
<title level="a">55th Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.B.2"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Memorial Book of the Serbian Society Srpsko Jedinstvo</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 12.
<title level="a">55th ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Serbian-Montenegrin Benevolent Society, which was organized in Chicago in the year <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, during its convention held on Oct. 17, 1894, decided to change the name as follows: Srpsko Jedinstvo (Serbian Unity), and since that time its activities are known under the same name.</p>
   <p>In 1903 Srpsko Jedinstvo was acting as a branch of the First Serbian Brotherhood Benevolent Federation of America. In 1900 it became part of the federation Sloga, which had been liquidated on February 28, 1921. Since 1921 the society Srpsko Jedinstvo was working as an independent organization. The purpose of this society is to give financial help to their members in case of sickness, accident, surgical aid and death; also to spread propaganda on national culture and unity. Its aim is also to help educate their members in American citizenship.</p>
   <p>The society accepts as members any Serbian or Slav, man or woman, from <pb facs="5423966_0110.jpg" n="2"/>18 to 40 years of age, who are healthy and of a sound mind.</p>
   <p>The youth organization Jedinstvo accepts any child from 2 to 18 years of age, and whose parents are of Serbian, Croatian or Slovenian extraction.</p>
   <p>Since 1894 the society has delivered honorary membership to the following distinguished personalities; (1) Alexandar I Obrenovich, former king of Serbia; (2) Nicholas I, Prince of Montenogro; (3) Queen Natarie, Serbia; (4) Nikola Tesla, inventor; and many others whose cultural or philanthropic activities have made them eligible for such an honorary title.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ivan Vuchetich, first organizer of this society and a member for 55 years, was elected as permanent honorary president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
