<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Popovich, D. <title>"The Immigrants' Troubles," Scrapbook of D. Popovich</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Popovich, D. <title>"The Immigrants' Troubles," Scrapbook of D. Popovich</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The life of our people in America is full of trouble. The immigrants' only refuge from grief is his songs, but he cannot be singing all the time. He has not yet decided what he wants to do, whether to return to the old country or to stay here. If he goes back,- not so good. If he stays here, - not so good either. Our people's eyes are always turned in the direction where the old country lies. That country was the immigrants birth-place, and it reared him. No power exists which can make him forget the old country. On the other hand this country, America, gives him his bread and butter and offers him an opportunity to become independent. So though his feet are on American soil, his heart and his soul are still over there.</p>
   <p>Most of our people are very generous. They have sacrificed much for the old <pb facs="5423966_0149.jpg" n="2"/>country. They have lent a helping hand to their poor friends and relatives over there. They went back to serve as volunteers in the war and contributed money for war-time necessities. They donate large sums of money for everything that is Serbian.</p>
   <p>Our compatriots are known as hard workers and savers. They try their best to save something from their meager pay-checks and send part of it across the Atlantic to their old country banks where it is probably lost. Then some unscrupulous rascals come here and swindle them out of the rest of their savings. And now the depression has come, with lack of work and no more savings. All this has made the Serbian hard-boiled and selfish. Our people have contributed to causes of all sorts, to the church, to education, to benevolent enterprises, until they have nothing left. They have scattered money right and left by handfuls and by sackfuls. Our people have contributed huge sums for conventions <pb facs="5423966_0150.jpg" n="3"/>and annual meetings and have received nothing in return. And right now we have another instance to report. Just a few days ago we received an invitation to be present at a church convention, where, as we heard, our church leaders intend to solicit from ten to twenty thousand for a new bell and building repairs. We should like to know who is responsible for this situation.</p>
   <p>Dushan Popovich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
