<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>United Serbians</title>,
<date when="1934-03-20">March 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of Church Banner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>United Serbians</title>,
<date when="1934-03-20">March 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF CHURCH BANNER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a very seldom practiced custom for our colonies to dedicate church banners.</p>
   <p>In the early part of our colonial life this custom was observed, but later it became a rarity. Church banners are emblems of Serbian religious unity. But nowadays you hardly can see those banners carried out of the church.</p>
   <p>Banner-carriers usually were selected from the ranks of highly respectable members in the colony, and it was considered as a sign of high respect and honor to be a banner-carrier.</p>
   <p>Serbians in Chicago, through many efforts and sacrifices, became the proud owners of the most beautiful church in America, and on Sunday, March 11th, with joy and happiness had a pompous ceremony, the dedication of the new church banner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0050.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This banner was donated by Mrs. Helen Schysler, who is of German descent but through her marriage has become a devoted member of our church. This banner has been made from very expensive material and represents a beautiful piece of artistic work.</p>
   <p>The dedication took place in a particularly pompous church ceremony, with hundreds of Serbs present.</p>
   <p>Rev. Styachich made a very interesting speech, explaining the meaning of this banner and ceremony.</p>
   <p>A banquet held in the church hall followed the dedication ceremony. Members of the church showed great enthusiasm about the restoration of this almost forgotten custom, still dear to their hearts. Chairman of this banquet was Simo Shakota, president of the church organization.</p>
   <p>The Serbian banner is the emblem of the people's struggle, bloody fights and suffering. Through centuries the Serbs have been fighting for their <pb facs="5423966_0051.jpg" n="3"/>liberty and national unity, always carrying around the banners which they collected from rebellious fighters. Now when their ideal is fulfilled, the banners are stored in churches, and stay as the memory of a very sad past, a silent monument to national heroism.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Simo Shakota.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
