<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Yugoslav Song Festival</title>,
<date when="1937-04">April 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[Yugoslav Song Festival]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Yugoslav Song Festival</title>,
<date when="1937-04">April 1937</date>.
<title level="a">[YUGOSLAV SONG FESTIVAL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>His Excellency Dr. Konstantin Fotich, Yugoslav Minister in Washington, has conferred a high honor on the special committee of the Yugoslav Song Festival by accepting their request, namely, that this musical event shall be under his distinguished patronage.</p>
   <p>The announcement of the forthcoming musical production has created vivid interest among the leading American experts in music and drama to such an extent, that a number of the high officials are expected to attend the performance.</p>
   <p>They will represent the University of Chicago, Northwestern University, the Board of Education, leading Conservatories of Music in Chicago, actors, painters, sculptors, playrights, composers, conductors, etc. The complete list of their names will be published shortly.</p>
   <p>Yugoslav music lovers and leaders of our colony will be present and many out of town folks will especially come here for that occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The participating soloists from the Chicago Civic Opera and Savine's Vocal Ensemble are rehearsing daily under the personal direction of our famous composer Alexander Savine. The variety of the program, as well as the quality of the production, promises to be of the highest order.</p>
   <p>Yugoslav Song Festival will be held on April 18, 1937, at 5 P.M. at the Auditorium of the Serbian Church, 1905 W. Fowler St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Samuel G. Milnovich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
