<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Calumet</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook of Adam Popovich.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Twenty Thousand Jugo-Slavs Attend Festivities Sunday at Century of Progress Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423966_0079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423966_0079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Calumet</title>,
<date when="1933">1933</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook of Adam Popovich.</title><title level="a" type="sub">TWENTY THOUSAND JUGO-SLAVS ATTEND FESTIVITIES SUNDAY AT CENTURY OF PROGRESS EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than 20,000 Jugo-Slavs filled the west stands of Soldier Field at the Jugo-Slav Day festivities yesterday.</p>
   <p>Prior to the program a parade half a mile long marched to the monument created by Dr. Meshtrovich, which stands, at Congress street and Michigan avenue, and the statue was unveiled.</p>
   <p>Adam Popovich, a young man of South Deering, directed the hundred-piece tamburica orchestra. Folk-songs were rendered by the United Jugo-Slav Society. Choral societies from Detroit, St. Louis, and Cleveland also sang.</p>
   <p>The national folk-costume was everywhere in evidence. Only four Croatian girls of this district attended in folk-costume.</p>
   <p>Joseph W. Bazdavich, physical director of the Jugo-Slav Sokol Federation, <pb facs="5423966_0080.jpg" n="2"/>supervised the gymnastic exercises.</p>
   <p>John Tilkovich, prominent Jugo-Slav composer and director of Detroit, directed the choral music, and Vaclav Husa led the band.</p>
   <p>American Legion Band 175 of the Woodlawn Post, Peoples Gas Company American Legion Post 310, Commonwealth Edison American Legion Post (champions of Illinois), and Semsley American Legion Post thrilled the vast crowd with army formations and musical numbers.</p>
   <p>The Jugo-Slav Children's Sokol and the Ladies' Auxiliary were reviewed on parade, followed by the Serbian Sisters.</p>
   <p>The Slovenian Ladies, headed by girls and youths, paraded in folk-costumes.</p>
   <p>The South Chicago Eagles were much in evidence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423966_0081.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Radmila Govedarica was declared Jugo-Slav World's Fair queen. She will receive a trip to Jugo-Slavia.</p>
   <p>Concluding the extensive program, Mrs. Brayak led the assembly in singing "My Country." Several thousand Jugo-Slav Day guests then visited the Century of Progress exposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
