<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. III, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-27">December 27, 1899</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. III, No. 52,
<date when="1899-12-27">December 27, 1899</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>God did not give any explicit commandment to the parents to love their children but he implanted that love, so it seems, in the blood of the mother, or rather, wrote it in their hearts. The voice of nature speaks plainly and forcibly to the hearts of mothers to love her children.</p>
   <p>That natural love and attachment of the parents for their children is evident not only in human beings. The virtue of paternal love is manifested also among animals, who sometimes lose their lives protecting their young ones.</p>
   <p>The love of father and mother for their children should be equal. It happens often that some parents do not love all the children equally. Father favors one child while mother favors another. Father loves sons better - mother, daughters.</p>
   <p>Faulty rearing of children sometimes causes terrible consequences. All your children have an equal right to your love and care - sons and daughters they are all yours. All of them should be loved equally, regardless of looks, behavior, smartness, or dullness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0697.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Usually some parents show less affection toward defective children. Is that right? If the parents are not responsible for their children's defects, are the children to blame? They are already unfortunate. The child is usually touchy and sensitive and very often a better observer than the grown up. It will notice your injustice and indifference quicker than you do; will consider you unjust and shall doubt you. "And I wanted to do the right thing but my father or mother are always against me; they are not satisfied with me and I can never suit them." Those are the words of the hated child. What are the consequences? Remember oh! father or mother! that unfortunate children shall be sadder and sadder; will lose ambition; will become degraded and finally perish.</p>
   <p>Such a child, realizing that it is loved less, will not love you, will not have confidence in you, will not consult you in his or her troubles for it knows that you will not sympathize with him or her. Such a child will avoid your company and finally will leave you because it did not find due affection. Parents should show their affection for their children in every respect. Should there arise any other feeling in their hearts, they should overcome it and do what is right. Fortunately, very few mothers reject <pb facs="5423968_2_0698.jpg" n="3"/>their children. There are however some very sad cases among step-parents and step-children. But who is to blame if not the father who did not instruct his children to love their new mother? In other cases the fault is with the step-mother who does not try to gain her step-children's confidence, who, instead of opening her heart and accepting them as her own, repulses them by cold indifference. She favors her own children by feeding and clothing them better; by supplying them with dainties (tid-bits).</p>
   <p>She blames her step-children for all wrong things in the family. Gives them the worst kind of work. This causes complaint, discord, and disagreement. How many tears are shed by such unhappy children, how many sad memories arise! What a longing for the dead mother, resting in the grave. You can read it in their sad eyes. Receiving hate, hate they return. In every case the stem-mother should try to win her step-children by sweetness, love, and tenderness, and the children will reciprocate by being grateful. Choose, oh mother, between evil, and the children. Reject the first, love the latter. Then you shall reform the child. No one observes your actions and words as carefully as you children and no one is a more important judge than your child.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
