<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-15">Feb. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Callows</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-15">Feb. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CALLOWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reporters, physicians, and a group of curious people witnessed on Saturday a scene that took place in a grim square, the walls of which denote not progress, as some would suppose, but retrogression. On Saturday, a medieval hanging scene was accurately reproduced, and the hangman did his best to make the occasion an impressive one. Roswell C. T. Smith was hanged for the murder of the four-year-old Weinstein girl.</p>
   <p>A mother and father lost their son, a wife became a widow, but the law satisfied Mrs. Weinstein, and for a life, it took a life.</p>
   <p>For about eight minutes, the spectators watched the last spasmodic kicking of the condemned man. Whether it occurred to anyone of them that to Smith's mother, he, the murderer, the condemned man, was just as beloved as his little victim, Hazel, was to Mrs. Weinstein, we do not know.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0653.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The condemned man, contrary to the expectations of the warden of the prison, the physician, and the hangman, went to the scaffold bravely. He realized fully what was going on around him, and he knew that the moment had arrived in which the law would exact its due. Roswell conducted himself in such a way that even the hangman, who had already hanged so many, could say nothing but: "Everything proceeding in the proper order".</p>
   <p>Today, only his parents, newspapermen, and a few physicians who were present at the execution remember Roswell. But our (Polish) parents would do well to ponder the gallows itself; the heart-rending scene of a mother parting with her son, the last spasmodic kicking of Smith should be described to parents who, by their...neglect of parental duty, make possible this grim, medieval square in which stands the gallows--so incongruous with the progress and culture of the twentieth century.</p>
   <p>Why do we speak of this today? Because it is too late to say it to fathers and mothers on the eve of losing their sons, because the journey to that grim square begins much earlier than is commonly supposed--it begins with the <pb facs="5423968_2_0654.jpg" n="3"/>moment that the parents begin to look upon their son's transgressions with indifference. And the law, which alone has the privilege of violating the commandment, "Thou shalt not kill," does not stop to consider that the condemned man is a mother's beloved son, but takes him away and sends him to the gallows. It is then that the mother and father reproach themselves for their responsibility in setting their son upon the short but terrible journey to the place of execution.</p>
   <p>Such were our reflections, among others, as we watched Roswell die on the gallows. While the others were taking in the "beauties" of the scene (for that is why they had come), these thoughts that we share with our readers today came to our mind. Bitter thoughts, thoughts that chill the marrow in our bones, thoughts on the subject of raising our youth for the gallows.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
