<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-18">Oct. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Destructive Critics]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-18">Oct. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[DESTRUCTIVE CRITICS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Strange and, at the same time, comical are some of our supposedly "great men" who have landed recently in America. They have not come here with the intention of working diligently and sincerely on social and organizational work, on an equal basis with other upright immigrant Poles. They began immediately to foment destructive criticisms to bring to naught all the former constructive work accomplished by our people. These gentlemen seem to think themselves to be the Alpha and Omega of all knowledge. As prophets they have not come here to work but.... thoughtlessly to criticize. No one had ever heard of them previously. They made no contribution to our immigration movement to place it upon the level upon which we now find ourselves to be. No counsel was ever received from them when we needed advice, nor did they contribute financially in any form in order to increase the institutions that the Poles possess here. They do not <pb facs="5423968_2_1022.jpg" n="2"/>belong to any Polish organization; they lack the slightest conception of our conditions and are completely ignorant as to the amount of work and the efforts that had to be made to create a new national life among the conglomeration of other nationalities. They do not know how difficult it was for the Poles in America to maintain their national spirit in the face of the continuous opposition with which our people were confronted by our enemies. It would seem that their sole purpose in coming to America was to criticize and ridicule everything that we have built here....without their assistance and counsel.</p>
   <p>During recent times we find that America has been flooded by people of such egotistical nature. The first activity of such "gentlemen" is to search for a prepared field where they can further their own personal interests. When their expectations are slow in being filled, or when their ambitions are thwarted, their criticisms directed against right-thinking people seem to acquire uncontrollable proportions. Articles containing unheard-of falsehoods are sent to European newspapers to present everything and everyone in a <pb facs="5423968_2_1023.jpg" n="3"/>false light. After all, what could these "gentlemen" write about us, when they have not been here long enough to become adequately informed of our conditions? They have not delved into the needs of our people nor have they fully understood the difficulties our people have had to combat to maintain our national individuality. Despite their lack of knowledge of these facts, these entirely unacquainted new arrivals attempt to appear in the role of mentors and severe critics. They pose as saviors of our immigrants; yet they dispense not words of friendly counsel, but often insults, abuses, and distorted "facts". They became the enemies of our people at the very beginning, and, although they are so close to us, they are so distant.</p>
   <p>Our Poles in America have had the opportunity of meeting many of such "great men". Unfortunately the conditions in our motherland seem to cast such unsavory individuals upon our American shores in ever increasing numbers. They do not come here with the intention of helping us erect a fourth Polish section; they come only to disturb us in our work. We were getting along <pb facs="5423968_2_1024.jpg" n="4"/>well without them, and....it would be better if we did not have them among us now. These self-centered people are not sincere social workers; they are not great of mind or spirit, but most often are nothing more than underminers and arrogant men. They have been laughed out of Europe, ridiculed because of their improper behavior, not recognized by any part of Polish society, and often expelled from the circle of those who are actually occupied with national and social work. These outcasts have come to America in search of thrills and impressions. They play the role of great men of state and expecting all Polish immigrants to pay them unlimited homage and to surrender themselves to these posers unconditionally, so that they may become their leaders and teachers. But our Poles in America are not so naive. Moreover, our people have learned by experience and, hence, are careful not to accept such "men of fate". We demand action from individuals, not vain empty words, if we are to trust them and accept them for our leaders. This is the thing that especially irritates them. Instead of endeavoring to prove by deeds that they really do desire the welfare of our Polish immigrants, that they are capable of serving this cause, and that they <pb facs="5423968_2_1025.jpg" n="5"/>are able leaders, they criticize venomously what has been built by others who have dedicated their work and money unstintingly. A person is at times inclined to laugh at some of the elaborate articles in the European newspapers, forwarded by these self-styled "great men", on the Polish conditions in foreign lands. If these writings do not betray the ill will of their authors, then they portray complete ignorance and grave lack of knowledge of things they make unsuccessful efforts to describe.</p>
   <p>These uncalled-for and unreasonable critics most often touch upon the Polish National Alliance. They touch upon it when, upon their arrival in America, they immediately endeavor to obtain some position in the organization. They depend on its officials when they need some type of..." a loan" or other assistance, and, when disappointed in one or the other, they then begin to bombard the organization and its officials. Unheard-of allegations are written by these "gentlemen," and, giving vent to their ire, they fill the columns of European newspapers with evil slander, in order to take dishonorable vengeance. We are amazed that some of our Polish news-<pb facs="5423968_2_1026.jpg" n="6"/>papers in Europe allow themselves to be taken in by such purveyors of "truth". The strange part of it all is that these European newspapers know the authors of such slanderous articles for what they really are. (They are probably quite satisfied that such disturbing elements have left their circle). The Polish people in America will gladly welcome any willing worker in the social field, but they will not tolerate a liar, a wastrel, or anyone desiring to destroy the good work accomplished thus far. Our people are willing to pay heed to the reasonable and sound counsel of an honest, sincere person. They will entrust him with the work for which he is qualified. But individuals whose intentions are evil--political and social upstarts, uninvited lying critics, and people who are basically perverted--are entirely unnecessary here; already there are too many outcasts of that type in this country. The organizations were built here by wise and sincere people who were not interested in disruptive criticism and did not occupy their time with writing insignificant articles for European publications. These true Poles have sincerely taken upon themselves the task of educating our people and congregating them in one fold. They have directed their knowledge and abilities so that they could <pb facs="5423968_2_1027.jpg" n="7"/>really bring benefits to our people. They have neither judged things in a shallow, careless manner nor played the role of thoughtless mentors, but have been true teachers and friends of our Poles in America. We need educated, righteous, and willing social workers, but we can do without the destructively critical and evil individuals. It is sincerely hoped that these words of chastisement will be accepted by those who have come here not to work for our common good but for some personal ambitions, those who thoughtlessly criticize everything that the Poles have created and built without their assistance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
