<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 27,
<date when="1904-07-06">July 6, 1904</date><title level="a">About Dances</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII, No. 27,
<date when="1904-07-06">July 6, 1904</date><title level="a">ABOUT DANCES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A working man, who earns his daily bread by the sweat of his brow, desires and needs some sort of diversion on holidays. The harder and more toilsome his work the greater his desire and eagerness to find amusement.</p>
   <p>In the presence of this, there are amusements not only pleasant but also useful, nevertheless there are instances where amusements are harmful.</p>
   <p>An amusement becomes harmful when it goes beyond the limits of decency and reason, which happens very often, especially in dancing.</p>
   <p>The dance constitutes the favorite amusement of the youth, although it is not in the least restful.</p>
   <p>On the contrary the motion of the dance is often a tiresome exertion, quite often dangerous to health. This applies especially to young girls <pb facs="5423968_2_0542.jpg" n="2"/>who, desiring to look their best, squeeze themselves tightly with a corset, while during a dance the blood becomes overheated, the heart beats faster and the lungs expand. This is the cause of common fainting spells and even of sudden death of tightly-laced dancers.</p>
   <p>Equally harmful during a dance is the partaking of cold drinks or the sudden change from warm to cold. Persons heated by dancing cool themselves off with cold drinks, go outdoors, or stand near an open window, which, without fail, results in a heavy cold and many times in a fatal illness.</p>
   <p>The fondness of dancing makes young girls subject to excessive spending. Their clothes wear out quickly and soil easily, so more often the thoughtless girl buys dresses, ribbons and other adornments, instead of saving her hard earned cash.</p>
   <p>The dance, particularly becomes harmful because it lasts ordinarily through the night. Returning home about morning the dancers are very tired out and barely falling into a sound sleep have to get up to go to <pb facs="5423968_2_0543.jpg" n="3"/>work. Therefore, their Sunday's pleasure has used up their strength much more than a whole week's work.</p>
   <p>Rightfully then, careful parents and conscientious employers do not permit the youth to attend public dances very often.</p>
   <p>St. Francis Salezy, a man of great virtues and deep wisdom, said as follows: "About a dance you can say the same as about mushrooms: most of them are poisonous and the best of them are of very little value" - and again he warns Christian maidens to avoid pleasures of dancing.</p>
   <p>The dance arouses passions and like a powerful intoxicant deadens the senses.</p>
   <p>The dance, more so without parental protection, was the cause and the source of many a girl's downfall. The acquaintances made on such occasions frequently do not lead to marriage, but end in disgrace and amguish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0544.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A respectful and decent young man does not seek a wife at a revelry, but amidst work and wholesome enjoyment, under the protection of elders, because he is not interested in a graceful dancer but in a faithful and loving life's companion.</p>
   <p>The young lady then on the other hand, if she is truly religious and instinctively modest is afraid of such balls, where any person has a right to ask her for a dance.</p>
   <p>How many times has a girl gone to a dance nice and fresh, healthy and innocent and came back infected with a terrible disease or with the unfortunate passion in her heart, which led her on to the evil path?</p>
   <p>Therefore we express our wish that our youth both male and female would rather gather in sodalities and there find the necessary recreation <pb facs="5423968_2_0545.jpg" n="5"/>which justly belongs to them - such, which strengthens their body, refreshes their mind and incites goodness.</p>
   <p>There are a superfluous number of dances, in each instance they should take place only under the immediate supervision of the parents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
