<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Society News</title>, Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1923-09">Sept. 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Arousing Race Hatreds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0840</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0840.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Society News</title>, Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1923-09">Sept. 1923</date>.
<title level="a">AROUSING RACE HATREDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our attention has been called to the fact that during the week of August 26, the Palace Theatre of this city presented for the approval of its patrons a number by the Klein Brothers, called "Jest Moments."</p>
   <p>Their reference to the "Pollacks" was slanderous, insulting and un-becoming to members of a race who are continually complaining of racial baiting, let's be frank - Jewbaiting. The comparison made by them in placing us in the category of the barnyard prowler known as a skunk, is not conducive to good will towards members of a race whose sole attempt and ambition seems to be to arouse animosity and hatred between the cosmopolitan elements that make up our community.</p>
   <p>While we are certain that most leaders of the Jewish element in our city do not tolerate attacks of this character, we deem it our duty <pb facs="5423968_2_0841.jpg" n="2"/>to call their attention to the fact that some of their compatriots on the stage are nullifying their good work through derogatory and disparaging remarks about a people to whom the Jews, after all is said and done, owe much. If it were not for the Polish nation in the middle ages when all Europe was moving out the Jew, giving the Jewish refugee asylum in Poland, the history of the Jew would have been much different today.</p>
   <p>We deprecate the uncalled for attack on our people and we resent the reflections upon us by the Klein Brothers and suggest that you write a letter of protest to the manager of the Palace Theatre, asking him to forward it to the management of the Orpheum Circuit. If the theatre managers cannot find a way of stopping the spark that causes race riots, we will find a remedy for people of the ilk of Klein Brothers in a legal and orderly manner. We do not advocate the use of ancient eggs or vegetables, as was the custom years ago, for we have never, and do <pb facs="5423968_2_0842.jpg" n="3"/>not now advocate violence as long as we have orderly processes which will serve our purpose in the preservation of our dignity and our rights.</p>
   <p>To the Jewish leaders we say that it is their duty to use their influence to eradicate Pole baiting among their people as they try to overcome Jewbaiting in certain sections of our country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
