<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-20">Jan. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Cleveland's Consumers' Strike Will Force Meat Prices Down]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-20">Jan. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[CLEVELAND'S CONSUMERS' STRIKE WILL FORCE MEAT PRICES DOWN]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eyes of the whole country are focused on the consumers strike in Cleveland, Ohio, where 40,000 people have decided not to eat meat until the meat trust reduces the price of its products. It is understood that meat prices have already been reduced, one or two cents per pound, but the public is not satisfied. So merrily the strike goes on, and the public is eating potatoes instead of meat.</p>
   <p>If all Americans used the strike method of forcing the meat prices down, then the trusts would either surrender to the public will, or they would be put out of business. We do not propose to completely eliminate meat from our daily diet, but we intend to reduce the amount consumed.</p>
   <p>Statistics show the consumption of meat per person and per year, throughout the principal countries of the world, to be as follows: Australia 262.6 pounds, New Zealand 212.5 pounds, United States 185.6 pounds, Cuba 124 pounds, England 121.3 pounds, Germany 115.94 pounds, France 78.9 pounds, Denmark 76 pounds, Belgium 70 pounds, Sweden 62 pounds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1453.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is plainly evident, that the healthy, strong and hard working industrial nations such as the Belgians, French and Germans, or the agricultural Denmark or Sweden, consume about half the amount of meat consumed by either the Americans or the English, both of which are more agricultural than industrial.</p>
   <p>It is not necessary to eat meat three times a day in order to maintain good health; once daily, is sufficient. A good piece of meat, cooked with greens and vegetables for soup, is enough nourishment for either the factory worker or the farmer. A great many of the greens and vegetables when cooked, seasoned and prepared properly, are as tasty and nourishing as meat; but it seems, that neither the American or English women know how to prepare them. The Polish, Russian, German, and French women, however, cook soup from a piece of meat and a large variety of greens and vegetables, and season it deliciously. This is considered a whole meal. Whereas an American or English woman serves beefsteak, half raw, and as hard as shoe leather, with half - cooked potatoes and some parsley, and calles it a meal. Six hours later she serves the same, and will probably repeat it again for breakfast.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1454.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Large quantities of meat are consumed, but the benefits of nourishment are small because the amount not digested by the stomach is wasted. Reduce by one - half the amount of meat you consume, prepare less of it, but prepare it so it will be tempting and tasty, and more easily digested. The use of greens and vegetables with meats is very desirable, and less expensive. True, vegetables are also expensive and yet, a head of cabbage costs only five cents while a pound of meat cost twenty or twenty-five cents - a very noticeable difference.</p>
   <p>By establishing co-operative stores we can reduce the cost of living, because farm produce can be obtained from farmers in and around the Chicago area; and groceries are not as yet controlled by trusts. But the establishment of new co-operative stock-yards is out of the question. Our only weapon against the meat trust is the strike. If it helps to bring down the prices of meats, - good - if not, we must resort to other methods.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
