<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-29">Feb. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The School Question at the Polish Catholic Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-29">Feb. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL QUESTION AT THE POLISH CATHOLIC CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We agree with the Reverend Gutowski that the question of our Polish schools is the most important one to be discussed at the proposed Polish Catholic Congress.</p>
   <p>But how shall we improve the teaching personnel in a practical manner?</p>
   <p>The loud demands for a teachers' seminary or a brothers' school should not belittle our own venerable sister teachers. Every priest and layman must admit that, heretofore, we have done everything we possibly could to educate our children. Masses of Polish people have arrived in America, but very few teachers have been among them.</p>
   <p>We were forced to use the talent at hand, both men and women teachers, although we confess that, in some schools, these were inadequate.</p>
   <p>We landed in a country which, from an educational standpoint, is richly endowed <pb facs="5423968_2_0183.jpg" n="2"/>with excellent schools and teaching personnel. We, because of circumstances, were forced to earn a living. The causes of certain complaints against the Polish schools should be sought in the lack of funds, rather than in the inefficiency of the faculty. And, on the other hand, the demand for male teachers in our schools, is perfectly natural.</p>
   <p>The boys, especially the young men, should be under the control of a male teacher. A sister teacher will always remain a woman and, in spite of her best efforts, will not have as much control over a spoiled boy as a male teacher might have.</p>
   <p>Two proposals have been submitted--to organize a teachers' seminary, or to import or organize a brotherhood of school teachers.</p>
   <p>What about the seminary? It is a good thing. But permit us to call attention to one inevitable result of organizing and maintaining a teachers' seminary. A student would receive, in such a seat of learning, a complete education in <pb facs="5423968_2_0184.jpg" n="3"/>Polish and English studies. Would these prospective teachers, after graduation, utilize their education in some profession other than that of teaching? The salaries of teachers will never be very high. The teacher will be tempted in a way that we all are: "Couldn't I earn more money as a clerk, agent or notary? Couldn't I continue my studies and become a lawyer or a doctor on my savings from my salary? And, anyway, my teacher's position is not permanent."</p>
   <p>That is how all teachers in the public schools in cities and villages in the United States think and act. That is the reason why, with very few exceptions, young ladies teach in the Chicago public schools," the educated young man seeks a wider field for his energies than the four walls of a schoolroom.</p>
   <p>The brotherhood of schoolteachers seems a better idea. These school brothers, having decided to sacrifice their lives for a teaching career, bound by voluntary oaths and working for a much smaller remuneration, would be far more dependable than lay teachers. It would not be more advantageous to organize a congregation, even though it would not be exclusively for Poles, which would <pb facs="5423968_2_0185.jpg" n="4"/>accept all Polish candidates, rather than a purely Polish congregation.</p>
   <p>But who will undertake this?</p>
   <p>F.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
