<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-12">July 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Blessing of a Picture</title><title level="a" type="sub">Poles in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-12">July 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE BLESSING OF A PICTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Poles in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ceremony of the blessing of the new picture of St. John the Baptist was conducted in the Church of St. Stanislaus Kostka, in Chicago, Illinois, on Sunday, July 10 of this year. The members made their appearance at Bradley Street in their uniforms and with the banner, after which the president, Josephine Dudzik, and six ladies of the Sodality of the Sacred Heart of Mary, carried the picture from the hall and arranged themselves in order, first the banner, then the officers followed by the six ladies and the president carrying the picture, and, finally, the members of this society filed into the church for vespers.</p>
   <p>After vespers, Rev. John Kasprzycki blessed the picture. In the same order the portrait was brought from the church to the hall and the Reverend Pastor, Vincent Barzynski, spoke to the members of this society in broader and more cordial terms, saying that he was greatly elated at this ceremony which this <pb facs="5423968_2_0800.jpg" n="2"/>society observes, that it is the first to set an example to the other societies. He also explained how great a saint the Society of St. John had selected for its patron, and said that he anticipates and hopes that it will continue to develop and obtain Divine blessing for this act as well as similar deeds.</p>
   <p>We extend our most cordial thanks to the young ladies for their sincere service, to Josephine Dudzik, as the president, to Mary Sajdak, Veronica Kunkel, Mary Mucha, Angeline Niwa, Agnes Zmich and Stephanie Kaliszewska. We extend thanks also to Reverend John Kasprzycki and to the pastor Reverend Vincent Barzynski, in behalf of the entire society.</p>
   <p>The Administration of St. John The Baptist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
