<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-22">Sept. 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">New World Commends St. Stanislaus Kostka School Exhibit at Hall of Commerce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-09-22">Sept. 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">NEW WORLD COMMENDS ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA SCHOOL EXHIBIT AT HALL OF COMMERCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As our readers know from notices that have appeared in Dziennik [Chicagoski] from time to time, the work of the pupils of St. Stanislaus Kostka School forms part of the Catholic Educational Exhibit at the Hall of Commerce.</p>
   <p>Having no desire to be accused of overpraising an institution so dear to us, we have purposely refrained from writing long articles about this Polish Educational exhibit, for we might well have written of it in high praise. We mentioned only the fact that the exhibit exists. At this time, however, we call attention to a disinterested and authoritative statement concerning the Polish school exhibit. This statement, in which the school exhibit is highly praised, was made by the most important Catholic weekly here, the New World, regarded as the official organ of the Church in this part of the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0245.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We feel it our duty to present verbatim a portion of the article, entitled "Our Educational Exhibit," appearing on page 5, column 6, of the latest issue of New World. The article reads:</p>
   <p>"The St. Stanislaus Kostka Parochial School occupies two buildings, of which one is a four-story fram building, 100 by 40 feet, the other, a four-story brick building, 212 by 80 feet. The latter includes a hall which, in size, is second only to the Auditorium.</p>
   <p>"These two buildings contain more than forty classrooms, accomodating about three thousand pupils of ages ranging from six to thirteen years. Boys from the ages of ten to thirteen years are placed under the care of lay teachers; all children, boys and girls, under ten years of age, are taught by thirty-two Sisters from the Notre Dame Convent of Milwaukee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The school was founded in 1875 by the Reverend Felix Zwiardowski, of the Order of Resurrection Fathers. It is now headed by the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, of the same Order. Ten other Resurrection Fathers assist him in his arduous but blessed work.</p>
   <p>"The educational exhibit of St. Stanislaus Kostka School consists of twenty volumes of work in English (from the first to eighth grades), and twenty-seven volumes of work in Polish. In all specimens, the remarkable calligraphy immediately strikes the eye; the upper class specimens are especially noted for the examples of ornamental calligraphy. One of the teachers, whom this writer met by chance at the exhibit, asserted that the beautiful decorations which adorn the title pages were executed by the pupils themselves, without any help whatsoever from their teachers. So much the more credit is due to both pupils and teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0247.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Preparation of these specimens so as to produce these results undoubtedly must have required great care and patience on the part of the teachers.</p>
   <p>"The exhibit compiled by the lay teachers of St. Stanislaus Kostka School consists of fourteen volumes of English work and eleven volumes in Polish; if these last can be judged by the English work, they must also be truly remarkable.</p>
   <p>"Great numbers of drawings made by pupils of both divisions show genuine artistic effort."</p>
   <p>These words constitute an impartial, authoritative judgment. Such a statement brings real credit to the directors of St. Stanislaus Kostka School--it is an invaluable moral reward for their noble, arduous work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
