<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-11">Feb. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Peter Kiolbassa's Daughter Weds Francis Kwasigroch</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-11">Feb. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PETER KIOLBASSA'S DAUGHTER WEDS FRANCIS KWASIGROCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, at 10 A.M., two notable young Polish people, Miss Rosalie Kiolbassa, daughter of City Treasurer Kiolbassa, and Francis Kwasigroch were married amidst pomp at St. Stanislaus Kostki's Church. The reception was held at the spacious parish school hall.</p>
   <p>The church overflowed with people, and many others crowded the entrance, to view the culmination of a romantic courtship. Andrew Kwasigroch, brother of Francis, parish choirmaster and singing teacher, and the church choir were at their best during the ceremony.</p>
   <p>Among the two hundred guests at the reception were Carter H. Harrison and his wife, Mr. Kraus, one of the outstanding lawyers of Chicago, and a <pb facs="5423968_2_0622.jpg" n="2"/>a number of relatives and close friends from many parts of the United States. During the course of the dinner many complimentary speeches, both in Polish and in English, were given. Peter Kiolbassa, with a smile and a tear, wished his daughter and son-in-law a long, happy and eventful life.</p>
   <p>The entertainment was the finest in the history of the school hall. Music, singing, duets, quartets, and solos intrigued the many guests. However, the descriptive detail is omitted in order to give the highlights of the life of the newlyweds.</p>
   <p>Francis Kwasigroch is a young man, who knew how to choose his companions and to make new friends of unquestionable character. His friends were, <pb facs="5423968_2_0623.jpg" n="3"/>young and old, Polish and English. This association and his educational activities enabled him to become Americanized sooner than the average Pole in Chicago; however, he has remained close to the hearts of his native countrymen. Those who know him or have made his acquaintance have a pleasant, lasting impression of him. Many of us realize what a struggle it is to rise above the many temptations of a large city. Mr. Kwasigroch is a typical example of one who has accomplished this.</p>
   <p>Today he has begun a new epoch of his life. As the wedding knot was tied important responsibilities were placed upon the shoulders of the young groom. The eyes of the new Polish-born generation and that of the American, as well as his parents and his wife's parents will be upon him, for he is the institutor of a new family.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0624.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There are hundreds of examples of young people who have married without having a full understanding nor a full realization of the significance of marriage. As it happens, many of these people are responsible for unhappy family ties, broken homes, etc.</p>
   <p>We do not attach any of these unpleasant experiences to the new husband. We know from his past record that his responsibilities will be faced with understanding and will be executed to the best of his ability. He will be a husband that his young and beautiful wife will be proud to speak of at any time. We are certain of this because his family life, education, social activity, and outside associations have always been of the best and finest character.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0625.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Miss Rosalie Kiolbassa is the daughter of City Treasurer Peter Kiolbassa, who is considered today one of the outstanding Poles in America. Her family has been long active in civil activities in Chicago. Educated in Chicago schools, Miss Kiolbassa has become an outstanding figure of her sex in Polish activities. The Polish people of Chicago had many opportunities to see her perform in amateur theatricals. She has not only proved to be a fine actress, but her connection with St. Stanislaus Church choir and singing instructions have made her a singer of considerable repute. She has long been active in church and neighborhood activities.</p>
   <p>Francis and Rosalie Kwasigroch are virtually the two outstanding Polish people of our new generation in Chicago. We wish them all the success and happiness that can befall any newly married couple. Let them always be the shining pearls of our people, of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
