<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Remarks on the Subject of Parochial Schools in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REMARKS ON THE SUBJECT OF PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two points of view on the subject of parochial schools, which have recently been displayed in Dziennik Zwiazkowy, have particularly attracted my attention, and I am putting down on paper the thoughts which have entered my mind, in order to show that both viewpoints on our parochial school are somewhat exaggerated, and that the truth lies somewhere in between.</p>
   <p>The clergyman from New England, in his article of October 28 in Dziennik Zwiazkowy, "Can We Condemn Parochial Schools in American", demands a little too much indulgence, from the Polish people in general, for these schools. The author states that children study Polish in these schools. This remark is, to say the least, laughable--I, for one, see no great merit or sacrifice on anyone's part. After all, it is the priests' duty as Poles to see to the teaching of the Polish language; the Polish people demand it, and support these schools for this very reason. Besides, we live in free America, not under the rule of Moscow or Prussia, under which the teaching of the Polish language is connected with a great deal of unpleasantness and sacrifice. If, therefore, Polish parents <pb facs="5423968_2_0376.jpg" n="2"/>send their children to these schools, it is primarily for the purpose of having them learn to speak Polish better than they could learn to do at home.</p>
   <p>But what do we observe among these children from parochial school? We observe that these children avoid using the Polish language in ordinary conversation, not only at home, for which the parents are mainly to blame but also at school and outside of school, for which the school as such must be held answerable at least in part. It is a sad and painful state of affairs, if a school does not know how, or does not want, to develop a sincere love and respect for the speech of one's parents--if one sees among the school children shame, repulsion, and aversion to their mother tongue. This situation, of course, does not prevail in all cases but the majority of the schools appear in this light.</p>
   <p>As for the teachers, I concede to the author the fact that today we must use those whom we have at hand until we can have at our disposal more and better material to select from. I will aslo concede that there are still Poles who <pb facs="5423968_2_0377.jpg" n="3"/>are reluctant to pay twenty-five cents a month for a school, that there are those who do not consider it their duty as Poles to contribute to Polish schools, even if their child does not attend them. I do not deny the fact that here and there the Government obstructs the teaching of Polish in these schools. After all, what government would not want a one-languaged peopled in its nation? But the author must admit that, seeing how the school children avoid Polish speech, we must wonder, in spite of ourselves, if some of our priests, submitting perhaps to pressure from above, are not, in an effort to Americanize Polish children, systematically discouraging the teaching of Polish. That the Government desires this, that the bishops here who look with disfavor on the Poles, desire this, and that more than one of the priests is a little too worried about keeping his job, no one will deny. Therefore, I ask you not to be too surprised by the various opinions that appear in some papers, nor to accept them as an absolute condemnation of parochial schools, because Polish immigrants as a whole have the right to guard against such an eventuality [as the abandonment of these schools].</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0378.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I should like to have ended here my remarks relating to the correspondence of the clergyman from New England, but the correspondent, while on the subject of schools, went out of his way to comment upon the unusual work and sacrifice of the entire Polish clergy for the benefit of the Poles here, and I see no evidence of this unusual work. I admit that every priest, before he builds a church, a school, or a rectory, has enough work, but when he has finished with this, outside of his work in the church, which consists of Mass, a sermon on Sunday, listening to the confessions of a few people each week, and conducting a few hours of religious service in the school, he does nothing for his community as a whole. There are those who work outside of the church and school, in this or that direction, for the welfare of their community, but these are rare exceptions. Most of the priests, except for making a few short speeches each year, do nothing for the immigrants to America. How differently does our clergy in the homeland appear! How much more does it do in the church, in the school, and in the social field! It works in the field of literature, in savings associations, in food co-operatives, in libraries, among agricultural groups, in societies; everywhere it makes its contribution to the life of the people, <pb facs="5423968_2_0379.jpg" n="5"/>and, after all, our countrymen in the homeland do not make half the sacrifices for their clergy that the Poles here make for theirs. The Poles in America make very modest demands, but they do insist upon a little more effort on the part of their clergy.</p>
   <p>Besides, the comparison of the Polish clergy with that of the Irish or Italian is not apt. We are in a much worse position than the Italians or the Irish. We should all, not just the people but also the clergy exert our efforts in every field, in order to catch up with other nationalities, such being the wish and the plea of our unfortunate mother country.</p>
   <p>The other point of view on the subject of parochial schools, which I read some two weeks ago in Dziennik Zwiazkowy in the following words: "Parochial schools plant the seeds of aversion to the Polish National Alliance, and form new corps for the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The Alliance should establish its own schools." As far as the school itself is concerned, I believe that I do not err in saving that the school should be a national Polish school, <pb facs="5423968_2_0380.jpg" n="6"/>not one bearing the label of this or that party. I do not believe that the priests or teachers are influencing the children against the Alliance, for the simple reason that this would not be wise, since the children are still too undeveloped intellectually. Whether a child some day joins the Alliance or the Union is unimportant, so long as it does not run loose or go astray. Our community contains some very worthy people, but it contains also many people overimpressed with modern progress, and quite a few doubters and light-minded people...</p>
   <p>Let those districts in Poland, where everyone who truly loves the mother country and her children works for their welfare, serve as our example. Let us take as our example Poznan, where peasant and master, laborer and townsman, nobleman and priest all work harmonionsly, according to their capacities, for the general welfare. If our country should some day emerge free again, it will not be the shoulder of the farmer, the nobleman, or the priest alone that will lift it, but the combined shoulders and efforts of all. Only by union can we attain the freedom of our mother country. Such a free Poland will never perish again.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Felka</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
