<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IIII, No. 5,
<date when="1930-02-02">Feb. 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mother</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Przebudzenie</title>, Vol. IIII, No. 5,
<date when="1930-02-02">Feb. 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MOTHER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most honorable position occupied in our society is that of a mother. The thrones of kings are tottering, great men are losing honors, power and high positions, but the position of a mother always remains the same with one exception, and that is the beauty and success of her position depends on her own endeavors. Some times that lofty position of a mother is degraded to the lowest rank of a step-mother arousing disgust and repugnance.</p>
   <p>Mother! The sweetest expression in our language. The very word brings smiles to our faces and lightens our countenances. The mention of a mother sometimes saves the erring soul of a child. Mother is the highest mistress, having a most profound influence upon humanity, molding its character. Mother is the fountain of all virtues on the one side and a volcano throwing out lava of bad example and depravity on the other.</p>
   <p>In her honor, the poets have written the most beautiful verses; the writers have created masterpieces and the sculptors have carved artistic altars. God <pb facs="5423968_2_0628.jpg" n="2"/>loves a women so much that through her He accomplishes the salvation of all humanity for He chose a woman to be the mother of His only son, Jesus Christ, the Savior of all humanity.</p>
   <p>Mother! What a great authority in that word. There is no greater responsibility in the world than that of a mother.</p>
   <p>Besides maternity, mother holds the three most important honors:(1) She is the nourisher. Up to the age of 10 the child sees only a nourisher and protector in mother. The mother, though considered as only a nourisher by the child, should know that the church entrusted her with an angel. Therefore, the child does not live by breast or bread alone; there an is a soul in a child which is as sensitive to every action and word of its mother as a negative photographic film. Care should be taken that the child develops physically, look nice and have a nice shape; its soul should also be kept healthy by spiritual nourishment in the form of a prayer. Whoever bends the knees of the child before the cross, leads its soul to God. Whoever <pb facs="5423968_2_0629.jpg" n="3"/>devotes time praying with the child, saves the child from much suffering in the future. (2) The second honor that the mother holds is the honor of a teacher. When the child grows, it asks all kinds of questions, depending on mother for an answer, having a great confidence in her. The child is sure that it will not be deceived or misled by her. The child goes to its mother for advice in a great confidence. What will a mother do if her mentality is lower than that of 10 years old children? The respect that a child has for its mother will suddenly disappear like a shadow. The child will begin to doubt some of the statements and judgments made by mother. It loses not only its confidence in her but also its respect for her, taking for granted that anything that mother said was based only on supposition and is not reliable. But when the mother's mentality is highly developed and she can impress her child with her knowledge, the child increases her attachment to her and sees in her not only a mother but the most important being, besides God. What a great opportunity for the mother whose child has an unlimited confidence in her, revealing to her all secrets. Its sensitive and elastic mind can be influenced and moulded according to the mother's will and design as she sees fit. She carves an angel out of its soul, her future <pb facs="5423968_2_0630.jpg" n="4"/>double. Otherwise the world shall have influence over the child and take it under its care, bringing it up for itself.</p>
   <p>Mother! The street will bring up your children not for you but for itself and itself only. Learn to know your vocation, otherwise your maternity shall bring you bitter bears and your child will be a curse to you and to the nation to which you belong.</p>
   <p>(3) Her third honor is that of a priestess. When the child reaches its full physical and mental development, it will not need your help any more and will take care of itself. It will go into the world to gain success. It will go in order to come back covered with glory and happiness. It will come to you, mother, for your blessing. How can you, mother, perform such a very important act, if you have no spark of faith in you? How can you hold a hand of a step mother over the head of your child if that hand served you for deprivation. Wouldn't you regret it?</p>
   <p>Wouldn't you be ashamed if you had not even the honor to bless your child's efforts?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0631.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Your child will grow up with the feeling that your heart is cold, without faith, and that your mind is filled with vanity of this world; it will turn away from you with tears in its eyes, and go into the unknown world to fare its unexplored future.</p>
   <p>The three most beautiful honors in the life of man are given to mother. Those honors must be obtained by hard work and most of the time by suffering. All great and sacred things of this world are begotten with difficulty for the evil spirit does not rest. That is why it is so hard to obtain sainthood, that is why it is so hard to become perfect. We should continue to go on in spite of all the difficulties for such is our duty. We must go even if the road should lead to calvary. We should not stop. Mothers, remember that your children are not wholly yours. You are only a mediator used by God for preserving and perfecting humanity. You should see that your fruit is sound and healthy in body and spirit, bring heroes, not simpletons into the world, then the whole world shall prostrate itself at your feet for the great mission accomplished for God and humanity.</p>
   <p>Father Siembida.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
