<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-19">Sept. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[A Characteristic Expression of "Influential" American Opinion]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-19">Sept. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[A CHARACTERISTIC EXPRESSION OF "INFLUENTIAL" AMERICAN OPINION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A wave of indignation has arisen against a certain Mrs. J. H. Patterson, wife of an official of the state of Illinois. This unhealthy feeling is especially shown by all the residents of foreign birth now living in the neighboring cities, in Hammond, East Chicago and Whiting. It is little wonder that waves of condemnation are expressed by various civic groups against this "distinguished lady," and rumors are heard to remove her husband from his present position. Let us consider here the cause for this feeling of indignation.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Patterson, the chairwoman of the Indiana Harbor Women's Club made a speech, to the above-mentioned club, on the subject of "Social Conditions." This "honorable lady" chose the "foreigners" as the topic upon which her speech revolved, that is, people of foreign origin. It was not, however, a serious, factual discussion of principal questions, but rather an ordinary outburst of malignant slander.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1038.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mrs. Patterson greatly bemoans the fact that distinguished (?) people--by this she meant the so-called Americans--are "forced to associate with the unsympathetic, disgusting persons of foreign extraction in the trains and inter-urban cars traveling between Chicago and the neighboring towns and villages." This foreign element was termed by Mrs. Patterson as "undesirable and reeking with filth." "It's a shame," the 'estimable' lady further stated, "that respectable people must live in such conditions."</p>
   <p>Enough of this repeating of the statements of this prejudiced woman. Her malignant allegations have greatly embittered the people of foreign birth who have a lady of such "pampered" ideas for their neighbor. Mrs. Patterson lives in Indiana Harbor. It is useless to oppose her statements, it would avail nothing--in her bitterness she says that, regardless of the indignation of half the members of her club, she is ready to repeat again what she said. There is no cure for obstinacy--especially that of a vicious woman. One can only look with contempt upon such statements for which her husband, Mr. Patterson, a state official, will have no cause for gratitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1039.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, let us merely pause here to consider this one question: who makes these statements--who insults these so-called foreigners? Is not Mrs. Patterson (please remember the name of the state official) also a daughter or granddaughter of "foreigners?" What right has she to denounce people of foreign birth when her father or grandfather, or some more distant family ancestor was at one time also a foreigner? Mrs. Patterson and her husband are certainly not of Indian origin.... Whence the feeling of superiority of Mrs. Patterson to people of other nationalities?</p>
   <p>In any event, it is of minor importance what the eventual answer of Mr. Patterson will be. We had no intention of introducing here the vain statement of a railing woman--her neighbors express their "gratitude" for that. The only reason for mentioning here, even to our people, this unsavory incident, is because the statements of Mrs. Patterson contain a characteristic expression of opinion of the "influential" group in America. They are those individuals who have become independently wealthy from these so-called "foreigners," against whom such contemptible remarks are made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
