<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-30">June 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">School Children Fete Pastor of St. Adalbert Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-30">June 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL CHILDREN FETE PASTOR OF ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, June 27, the school children of St. Adalbert's parish gave a special program in honor of the Reverend John Radziejewski, pastor, who celebrated his name day. The varied program contained more than thirty numbers. Congratulatory remarks were delivered in Polish by Leon Magir, John Fabisz, Tekla Manna, Miecislawa Wawrzynska, Mary Makowska, Frances Paluchowska, Agnes Wisniewska, Anne Zyks, and Elizabeth Gasarewicz, and in English by F. Belka, Joseph Modlinski, and Victoria Lamik. Each greeting was executed in perfect order, and each speaker offered a bouquet of flowers to the pastor.</p>
   <p>Piano solos were played by the Misses M. Wawrzynska, Mary Mielchrek, and Tekla Manna. Duets were played by the Misses Anne Zyks and Veronica Milicka, followed by a solo by Leo Megier.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0155.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Songs in Polish and in English greatly pleased the guest of honor as well as the audience. Recitations by the Misses A. Zyks, E. Gasarewicz, Teofila Lenartowicz, and Francis Belika were also given.</p>
   <p>Four short dramatic sketches were also presented, two in Polish and two in English. The first two were "Kolega" (Friend) and "Nawrocenie Wszebora z Lasotyna" (The Return of Wszebor from Lasotyna), and the others were "Military Discipline" and "Servant Wanted". All the skits were well applauded by the audience. The following participated in these plays: Leo Megier, Anne Zyks, T. Manna, John Fabisz, Paul Pelka, Frank Pelka, Joseph Modlinski, and Joseph Hoppa.</p>
   <p>The pastor was greatly pleased with the little school girls who sang a lullaby to dolls held in their arms. Other interesting numbers were the drill exercises of five-year-old and seven-year-old boys. Stanislaus Chyla sang a beautiful hymn.</p>
   <p>Every number on the program proved to be a thrill to the audience. All <pb facs="5423968_2_0156.jpg" n="3"/>amateur performers were at their best and felt amply rewarded by the generous applause for their efforts.</p>
   <p>It has been stated in the newspapers and by word of mouth that the parochial schools do not teach anything. Such writers and speakers ought to attend these exercises, and they would be convinced once and for all. But perhaps such individuals do not care to be convinced.</p>
   <p>This good news undoubtedly deters them from visiting our schools, where catechism is part of the curriculum. They would rather send their children to public schools where no opportunity for religious instruction or training in the Polish language is afforded. Despite this they still consider themselves Roman Catholics and true Poles, although their children become a total loss to the Polish people.</p>
   <p>One of the audience</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
