<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Warning to Polish Investors</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joseph Mierzynski (Announcement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A WARNING TO POLISH INVESTORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joseph Mierzynski (Announcement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over three million dollars has been lost by Polish people in America by investments in stock in Polish corporations. All this has happened in recent months only. This is an unfortunately heavy loss and one perhaps that will be an everlasting lesson to all investors.</p>
   <p>During the past few weeks the Polish people, according to facts, have not shown that they are capable of handling an interest on a large scale. All new Polish concerns that may arise in the future should give the people a bonafide protection for their investments. One of the best of these is the first mortgage.</p>
   <p>This is exactly what has been done by the Palatine Alliance. Every penny <pb facs="5423968_2_1363.jpg" n="2"/>that is taken by this organization is protected by real-estate possessions which are valued at millions of dollars. This announcement is made in every paper in order that the people may know about this.</p>
   <p>There are those that try to organize a new corporation and collect money from people to promote membership and the sale of stock. They do this in the following way:</p>
   <p>A number of people will gather to talk over plans for a new enterprise. Among this group two or three Palatine boosters are found. They know that the Palatine Alliance has great confidence in the Polish emigrants, that the membership exceeds 30,000, and that it helps to build Polish industry and trade. Realizing this, they take advantage of the fact that they have Palatine members in the new corporation, and call themselves a "Palatine Organization." They send out an appeal to all Palatine members for support, and their circulars are printed in such a fashion that one is led to believe that the new enterprise is being carried out by the Palatine Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1364.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this way the public in general is led to believe the opposite. The people form the opinion that the new organization belongs to the Palatine Alliance, and that money invested in that corporation is protected by first mortgage notes. By making use of the name "Palatine," the new company influences the public to invest money in a speculative concern. Many such companies became bankrupt within a short time.</p>
   <p>In order to clarify this situation, I am listing the four organizations that are associated with the Palatine Alliance. They are as follows: Palatine Trade Corporation, Palatine Transportation Corporation, Palatine School Corporation, and Palatine Mining Corporation. These four compose the Palatine Alliance which is protected by a twenty million dollar real-estate investment. The money which is invested in this company is protected. Beyond the investments in the four Palatine Alliance corporations the Alliance is not responsible for any other concerns.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1365.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I wish to point out once more to the investors who may want to purchase stock in some enterprise that the safest investment is one that protects their interests by first mortgage notes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
