<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 30,
<date when="1905-07-26">July 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Struggle against Drunkenness</title><title level="a" type="sub">What Whiskey Can Do</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 30,
<date when="1905-07-26">July 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUNKENNESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">What Whiskey Can Do</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a brightly lighted street on Christmas Eve, a little girl dress in shabby clothes walked hurriedly on her way home. Poor little Mary, for that was her name, had a father who was an habitual drunkard who, when intoxicated, beat up, not only his child, but also his good wife.</p>
   <p>Little Mary quickly climbed the steep stairs to the uppermost story, but not finding anyone at home, ran down the stairs hurriedly and went to the saloon, expecting to find her father.</p>
   <p>In the barroom a crowd and noisy hum beyond description held sway. Among many voices, hoarse from drinking, the little girl could distinguish the voice of her father, the sound of which was well known to her. Shortly there came a view of him personally, and beside him the pale, miserable countenance of her mother, her eyes red from crying. The crowd in the barroom were amusing themselves excellently, looking at a poor woman striving in vain to induce her <pb facs="5423968_2_0500.jpg" n="2"/>husband to leave the place, where he was drinking up his entire week's earnings. Little Mary was hurrying to her father, but before she could draw near, there came upon the street a whole throng, well under the influence of liquor, at the head of which was her drunken father, and after him his poor wife. Her gentle pleas and entreaties for him to return home brought him only into greater anger and fury; swearing, he battered her with his fists. At the sight of this Mary, forgetting about the fear with which her father filled her, embraced him about his knees and cried in despair:</p>
   <p>"Daddy! Daddy! do not beat mamma, because this is Christmas."</p>
   <p>These words fulfilled the measure of his madness, catching the child he lifted her in the air like a feather and with all his might he threw her down upon the ground.</p>
   <p>When the poor little one regained consciousness, she found herself in a beautiful clean bed, and beside her two forms: a gentleman with gold-rimmed glasses looked <pb facs="5423968_2_0501.jpg" n="3"/>upon her attentively, and a gray-haired lady with a gentle smile kept changing the bandage on her forehead. Little Mary does not know what is happening, she thinks she is, perhaps, in heaven. In pretty beds on clean bedding she sees also many other little children, and she asks very quietly, whether they also suffer like her?</p>
   <p>The gentleman in the gold-rimmed glasses is the doctor, he is telling her that she is in a children's hospital, that she has a deep wound in her head, and one leg broken, but nevertheless if she will lie quietly she will soon regain her health.</p>
   <p>When they tended to her leg, she received a large beautiful doll, about which she dreamed for so long. On the morrow before Mary's bed stands a pale woman, she is kissing her and crying.</p>
   <p>"My dear Mamma!"--calls out the sick little girl with gladness and puts her arms around her mother's neck, and afterwards ask about her father.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0502.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Oh!" she says "he did not intend to do me any harm, he did not know what he was doing, if he was here I would ask him if he would please not go to that filthy saloon!"</p>
   <p>Just there she heard a quiet weeping behind her, she turns around and there at the head of the bed stands her father who sobs quietly, wiping away his tears with his sleeve. He also bends above the child, but he does not know what to do with himself because of his great shame and sorrow.</p>
   <p>"Forgive me, my dear child," he cries with feeling, "I did not wish to do you any harm. It was that fatal whiskey that caused me all this misfortune! But from now on I will live differently; I promised that to your mother and God is my witness that not a drop of liquor will pass my lips."</p>
   <p>The child comes to its health and the father keeps his oath.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
