<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1911-05-24">May 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Unions in Chicago and Their Outrages</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1911-05-24">May 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR UNIONS IN CHICAGO AND THEIR OUTRAGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The murder of Mr. William Gentleman, an alleged professional slugger, shot day before yesterday, is a very sad affair. In Chicago, the largest industrial city in the world and the capital city of the labor unions, a civil war is going on among different labor organizations. The labor unions are not opposed by the public or the press. They are not even opposed by the industrialists. In Chicago, the labor organizations enjoy undisputed rights and it would seem that they are doing well.</p>
   <p>In spite of these favorable conditions, there is something fundamentally wrong with the labor unions of Chicago, for from the last of February until now there were eighteen acts of violence as a result of the friction among different labor organizations, some of them ending in death. The latest act of violence was not the result of a <pb facs="5423968_2_1610.jpg" n="2"/>fight with scabs, it was not even caused by a scuffle with the police, but by a quarrel between agents and members of labor organizations. In the saloon where Mr. Gentleman was killed day before yesterday, there were present, almost exclusively, many notable union men. Among the notables were: the agent and the president of the Elevator Operators Union; the agent of the Elevator Constructors Union; the president of the Iron Constructors Union, and the agent of the Plumbers Union. It is not known who started the trouble or who fired the fatal shot, for all of them were shooting. To the people on the street, it appeared as if there was a regular battle near by. Every one had a gun, which is against the law, and used it. Of those who were in the saloon, one was killed, a few were wounded, some were arrested, and the rest disappeared. The public, however, had the impression that the saloon had be attacked <pb facs="5423968_2_1611.jpg" n="3"/>by a band of professional bandits and not by a group of American gentlemen representing Chicago labor organizations.</p>
   <p>The situation is bad and the members of the unions should remedy it. This condition, according to available information, was not caused by regular union members, but by officials of these organizations. It seems that the offices of labor organizations are held by agitators, wranglers, and people of questionable character, dispossessed of any moral or mental qualifications; these people quarrel among themselves and settle their affairs with guns. Whenever one of these bloody encounters occurs in Chicago, we notice many Irish names among the protagonists, and only occasionally a German name. Polish names do not figure on the lists of trouble makers, not even as quiet officials of labor organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1612.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It seems that there is no remedy for this evil, and we doubt if the police, or even Mayo Harrison, can stop it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
