<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 104,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Capital, Labor and Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 104,
<date when="1921-12-10">Dec. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITAL, LABOR AND SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We all know that the laws are conservative most of the time, but not all of us know why.</p>
   <p>The answer is very simple. The only time any law is made is when it is necessary; when society is confronted with a situation which must be curbed by the law, in order that the proper authorities responsible for order in the country and the safety of its citizens, may control such situations for the benefit of the majority and not for the advantage of a few individuals or small groups of the nation.</p>
   <p>At present every country needs a suitable law for regulating differences between capital and labor.</p>
   <p>Why? Because the gigantic industry conducted on a large scale is still young, for only lately general strikes began to break out paralizing <pb facs="5423968_2_1702.jpg" n="2"/>the industry of the whole nation and causing great damage to the majority of society, standing at this time outside of the fight between capital and labor.</p>
   <p>Strikes as those of railroads, in steel mills, in coal mines, and in the stock yards have a tremendous influence on the life of the entire community, and on that account they affect not only the fighting groups, but the whole of society.</p>
   <p>Such strikes as we have now in the stock yards affect not only the owners of the slaughter houses and their employees, but also the entire society, because this battle is fought <gap unit="chars" extent="4" reason="illegible"/>fly at its expense.</p>
   <p>President Harding was right when he said in his speech to Congress that a controversy between, capital and labor concerns our whole nation and that this nation must enact a suitable law which would make it possible to settle these controversies by courts, giving decisions that would benefit the whole nation and not only a small part of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1703.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>President Harding proposed the enactment of a law which would safeguard the interests of the nation against abuse by either side, and which would point out very clearly whether a certain incident was a violation of the interests of the community or not.</p>
   <p>President Harding's proposition was opposed very bitterly by Mr. Samuel Gompers, president of the American Federation of Labor.</p>
   <p>He is not right, because he supports the point of view of only one class of society, disregarding the interests of the whole nation, which should be the highest duty of every law-abiding citizen.</p>
   <p>The controversy between capital and labor must be settled by the whole society through its lawful representatives, by means of suitable laws. These laws should decide which side is right and both sides must respect this decision.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of the workingman and the whole nation, we should create <pb facs="5423968_2_1704.jpg" n="4"/>such tribunals at once, for in a country having a constitutional government there should be no strikes, causing great damage just because both sides are stubborn and will not give in.</p>
   <p>If there was a law forcing the stock yards' owners and their workers to arbitrate, there would be no blood shed, no million dollar losses suffered by the whole nation in favor of the profiteers who raised the prices of meat and other products almost one hundred per cent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
